[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> GOOD EVENING, AND WELCOME TO
THE HISTORIC MILWAUKEE THEATRE,
YOU'LL HEAR FROM 12 REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES VYING TO BECOME THE
NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
I'M TRISH REGAN ALONG WITH
CO-MODERATORS SANDRA SMITH AND
PRETTY "WALL STREET JOURNAL"
GERRY SEIB.
>> FOX BUSINESS IS PARTNERING
WITH THE "WALL STREET JOURNAL"
TO BRING YOU THE FOURTH
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEEFBT
THE 2016 CAMPAIGN.
FOR THE NEXT HOUR, FOUR OF THE
CANDIDATES WILL BE HERE
ANSWERING THE QUESTIONS VOTERS
WANT ANSWERED.
>> LET'S INTRODUCE THEM.
NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR CHRIS
CHRISTIE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> FORMER ARKANSAS GOVERNOR
MIKE HUCKABEE
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> FORMER PENNSYLVANIA SENATOR
RICK SANTORUM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND LOUISIANA GOVERNOR BOBBY
JINDAL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THIS DEBATE WILL LAST ONE HOUR,
EACH CANDIDATE WILL HAVE 90
SECONDS TO ANSWER, ONE MINUTE
FOR EACH FOLLOW-UP.
WHEN TIME IS UP, YOU'LL HEAR
THIS BELL.
ALL RIGHT.
LET'S BEGIN WITH GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR
ECONOMICALLY OUR COUNTRY IS
STRUGGLING WITH SOME OF THE
MOST ANEMIC GROWTH ON RECORD.
THEY ARE NOT IN THE WORKFORCE
ALTOGETHER.
THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE WILLING,
ABLE AND WANTING TO GO TO WORK
IS AT A LEF THAT HAS FALLEN TO
A LEVEL WE HAVE NOT SEEN SINCE
THE 1970s.
FOR THOSE THAT ARE WORKING
WAGES AREN'T BUDGING.
COSTS, HOUSING REMAIN HIGH.
AS PRESIDENT, WHAT CONCRETE
STEPS WILL YOU TAKE TO GET
AMERICA BACK TO WORK?
>> WELL, FIRST I WANT TO SHARE
A STORY WITH YOU THAT RELATES
TO YOUR QUESTION.
I WAS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE LAST
WEEK, AND A WOMAN APPROACHED ME
AFTER THE TOWN HALL MEETING AND
SHE SAID TO ME, GOVERNOR, I'M
REALLY CONCERNED.
I SAID WHAT ARE YOUR CONCERNS?
SHE SAID I DON'T KNOW HOW TO
DESCRIBE IT.
SHE SAID BUT EVERY MONTH WHEN
MY BILLS COME IN, I FEEL THIS
AWFUL ANXIETY IN THE PIT OF MY
STOMACH THAT I'M NOT GOING TO
HAVE ENOUGH MONEY TO PAY THEM
THAT MONTH.
THERE ARE TENS OF MILLIONS OF
AMERICANS LIVING THAT WAY AFTER
THE WORST RECOVERY FROM AN
ECONOMIC RECESSION SINCE WORLD
WAR II.
AND LET'S BE CLEAR, IF WE DO
NOT CHANGE COURSE, IF WE FOLLOW
THE PRESIDENT'S LEAD, AND
THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT SECRETARY
CLINTON WILL DO, WE'RE GOING TO
BE IN THE SAME CIRCUMSTANCE.
WITH GOVERNMENT PICKING THE
WINNERS AND LOSERS.
LET ME BE CLEAR WHAT WE'LL DO.
FIRST MAKE THE TAX CODE FAIR,
FLATTER AND SIMPLER.
GET RID OF THE SPECIAL INTEREST
DEDUCTIONS, YOU KNOW WHY THEY
FEEL THAT WAY?
IT IS.
WE'LL GET RID OF THE SPECIAL
INTEREST DEDUCTIONS INSTEAD OF
THE CHARITABLE CONTRIBUTION
DEDUCTION, EVERYONE WILL KEEP
MORE OF THEIR OWN MONEY, FILE
TAX RETURNS IN 15 MINUTES AND
BY THE WAY THE GOOD THING, I'LL
BE ABLE TO FIRE A WHOLE BUNCH
OF IRS AGENTS ONCE WE DO THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> AND IN ADDITION, WE NEED TO
GET THE GOVERNMENT OFF OF OUR
BACKS, DODD-FRANK, ALL THE
REGULATION, 81,000 PAGES OF NEW
REGULATION BY THE
ADMINISTRATION LAST YEAR.
IT IS SUFFOCATING SMALL
BUSINESS, SUFFOCATING THE FOLKS
TRYING TO MAKE A LIVING.
I WILL DO WHAT I DID IN NEW
JERSEY.
LIFT IT OFF THEIR BACKS.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR HUCKABEE, WE'RE HERE
IN WISCONSIN, A STATE THAT HAS
SEEN THE BIGGEST DECLINE IN
MIDDLE CLASS HOUSEHOLDS OF ANY
AMERICAN STATE WITH MORE THAN
120,000 MANUFACTURING JOBS LOST
IN THE LAST 15 YEARS.
AS WE MOVE AWAY FROM A
MANUFACTURING ECONOMY TO A
SERVICES BASED, TECHNOLOGICAL
ECONOMY, HOW ARE YOU GOING TO
HELP THE MILLIONS OF AMERICANS
THAT ARE STUCK IN THE
TRANSITION?
>> FIRST OF ALL, TRISH, I DON'T
KNOW WHY WE HAVE TO MOVE AWAY
FROM MANUFACTURING.
THE ONLY REASON WE HAVE IS
BECAUSE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE HAVE A TAX CODE THAT HAS
PUNISHED MANUFACTURING.
I HEAR A LOT OF PEOPLE TALK
ABOUT THE PLANS TO SIMPLIFY THE
TAX CODE.
I'VE GOT ONE BETTER THAN THE
SIMPICATIONS, CALLED A FAIR
TAX, AND IT ELIMINATES ALL OF
THE TAXES ON PRODUCTIVITY.
HERE'S WHAT WOULD HAPPEN.
WE'D GET RID OF TAXES ON
PEOPLE'S WORK, SO WE WOULDN'T
PUNISH PEOPLE FOR WORKING
ANYMORE.
YET WE'VE LOST FIVE MILLION
MANUFACTURING JOBS JUST SINCE
THE YEAR 2000.
160 MANUFACTURING PLANTS HAVE
CLOSED.
HE'S EXACTLY RIGHT.
THEY DON'T HAVE JOBS ANYMORE.
AND REASON THEY DON'T HAVE JOBS
IS BECAUSE THEIR JOBS ARE IN
MEXICO, THEY'RE IN CHINA,
INDONESIA.
BRING THE JOBS BACK AND WITH
THE FAIR TAX, YOU DO THAT
BECAUSE YOU DON'T TAX CAPITAL
AND LABOR, AND BRING A SENSE OF
EQUITY TO THE OPPORTUNITY SO
THAT PEOPLE WILL NOT ONLY MAKE
IT EASIER TO FUNCTION, LOOK AT
MANUFACTURING JOBS BACK, AND
HERE'S THE BEST PART.
WE DON'T REDUCE THE IRS, WE GET
RID OF THE IRS.
WE COMPLETELY ELIMINATE THEM.
BECAUSE THE GOVERNMENT HAS NO
BUSINESS KNOWING HOW MUCH MONEY
WE MAKE AND HOW WE MADE IT,
IT'S NONE OF THEIR BUSINESS,
AND THAT'S WHY I BELIEVE THAT
MANUFACTURING IS CRITICAL.
IF WE CAN'T FEED OURSELVES,
FUEL OURSELVES AND FIGHT FOR
OURSELVES, WE CAN'T BE FREE,
AND BY THE WAY, FIGHTING FOR
OURSELVES MEANS MANUFACTURING
OUR OWN WEAPONS OF
SELF-DEFENSE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR
HUCKABEE.
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM YOU
ARE ALL HIGHLY CRITICAL OF
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S ECONOMIC
RECORD.
FEDERAL PAYROLLS SHOW ROLLS
HAVE EXPANDED NEW JOBS IN
OFFICE.
ALL THE JOBS WERE RECOVERED
LAST YEAR.
IN OCTOBER THE ECONOMY ADDED
JOBS AT THE FASTEST RATE SINCE
2009.
SO WHAT'S WRONG WITH THE OBAMA
JOBS RECORD?
>> THE MIDDLE OF AMERICA ALL
YOU HAVE TO DO IS LISTEN TO THE
LAST DEMOCRATIC DEBATE.
YOU WOULD THINK THERE'S A
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENT IN OFFICE,
THE WAY THEY COMPLAINED HOW BAD
THINGS ARE IN AMERICA AND HOW
THE MIDDLE OF AMERICA IS
HOLLOWING OUT.
I AGREE WITH MIKE HUCKABEE, I
SPENT THE MORNING IN FAB TECH,
A SHEET METAL FABRICATORS
CONFERENCE.
THOUSANDS DISPLAYING THE NEWEST
AND LATEST TECHNOLOGIES.
YOU KNOW WHAT I WAS TOLD?
BOOTH AFTER BOOTH, THERE ARE
250,000 WELDER JOBS OPEN IN
AMERICA.
250,000 WELDER JOBS, PAYING
ANYWHERE FROM 50,000 TO $70,000
A YEAR.
IF YOU WANT TO WELD PIPE FOR
OIL AND GAS PIPELINES CAN YOU
MAKE $100,000 A YEAR.
EVERY MANUFACTURER, I GO TO ONE
EVERY SINGLE WEEK.
I HAVE ONE IN THE CROWD.
A GENTLEMAN WHO IS A SUPPORTER
FROM ROCKWELL, TEXAS, HE RUNS
SPECIAL PRODUCTS AND HE HAS
JOBS OPEN IN EVERY SKILL HE
COULD POSSIBLY HIRE FOR IN
ROCKWELL, TEXAS, BUT CAN'T FIND
PEOPLE.
SO THE ISSUE IS YES, WE NEED A
TAX CODE, I PROPOSE A 20% FLAT
TAX, 20% ON CORPORATIONS, 20%
ON INDIVIDUALS, FULL EXPENSING
POWERFUL FOR MANUFACTURING, 0%
RATE FOR MANUFACTURERS, WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE A POWERFUL TAX
CODE.
WE'RE GOING TO DO SOMETHING
ABOUT REGULATION, WE'RE GOING
TO SUSPEND EVERY SINGLE OBAMA
REGULATION THAT COSTS OVER
$100,000 TO THE ECONOMY.
BUT WE HAVE TO START DOING
SOMETHING ABOUT TRAINING AND
EMPLOYEEING PEOPLE WHO ARE
SITTING ON THE SIDELINES
BECAUSE THEY DON'T SEE A PATH,
AND WE HAVE A BUREAUCRACY IN
WASHINGTON AND PRESIDENT IN
WASHINGTON AND AMONG
REPUBLICANS WHO THINK EVERYBODY
HAS TO GO TO COLLEGE.
PEOPLE NEED TO GO TO WORK AND
PROVIDE OPPORTUNITIES TO GO TO
WORK OUT OF HIGH SCHOOL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT, GOVERNOR
JINDAL, YOU HAVE PUSHED
LOUISIANA'S ENERGY-RICH
RESOURCES AS A MEANS TO GROW
JOBS IN YOUR STATE.
BUT AS OIL PRICES HAVE PLUNGED
IN RECENT MONTHS, SO HAS JOBS
GROWTH.
LOUISIANA NOW HAS AN
UNEMPLOYMENT RATE ABOVE THE
NATIONAL AVERAGE.
WILL YOUR ENERGY FOCUSED JOBS
PLAN FOR THE COUNTRY BE SUBJECT
TO THE SAME MARKET UPS AND
DOWNS?
>> A COUPLE OF THINGS, IN
LOUISIANA WE'RE A TOP TEN STATE
FOR JOB GROWTH.
AS WE SIT HERE TODAY, WE HAVE
MORE PEOPLE WORKING IN
LOUISIANA THAN EVER BEFORE
EARNING A HIGHER INCOME THAN
EVER BEFORE.
60 MONTHS IN A ROW OF
CONSECUTIVE JOB GROWTH IN THE
STATE.
WE HAVE DIVERSIFIED THE
ECONOMY.
I HAVE AN INTERVIEW PLAN THAT
SAYS ALL OF THE ABOVE CREATES
GOOD MANUFACTURING JOBS IN
AMERICA.
ONE OF THE FASTEST I.T. SECTORS
BY PERCENTAGE.
LET ME GET TO THE POINT THEY
THINK IS THE MOST IMPORTANT
ISSUE TONIGHT.
YOU ARE GOING TO HAVE SEVERAL
HOURS ON THE ECONOMY, AND
ENERGY PLANS AND TAX RATES,
THAT'S ALL GREAT.
THE MOST IMPORTANT THING WE
HAVE TO DO, WE HAVE A
FUNDAMENTAL CHOICE TO MAKE
FOLKS, ARE WE WILLING TO CUT
THE GOVERNMENT ECONOMY TO GROW
THE AMERICAN ECONOMY?
THAT IS THE MOST FUNDAMENTAL
QUESTION WE'VE GOT TO ANSWER.
WE'RE ON THE PATH TO SOCIALISM
RIGHT NOW.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THESE ARE MUTUALLY
EXCLUSIVE.
HOUR IS LATE BUT NOT TOO LATE
FOR AMERICA.
UNDER PRESIDENT OBAMA, YOU
ASKED ABOUT HIS ECONOMY, WE'VE
GOT RECORD DEPENDENTS, RECORD
NUMBER OF AMERICANS ON FOOD
STAMPS, RECORD LOW
PARTICIPATION RATE IN THE
WORKFORCE.
THIS IS A FUNDAMENTAL CHOICE,
SENDING A BIG REPUBLICAN
GOVERNMENT OF D.C. IS NOT
ENOUGH TO FIX THE PROBLEM.
NOT ENOUGH JUST TO BEAT HILLARY
CLINTON.
WE'VE GOT TO CHANGE THE
DIRECTION OF OUR COUNTRY.
WHAT THAT MEANS IS LET'S SHRINK
THE GOVERNMENT NOT SLOW GROWTH
RATE, BUT SHRINK THE GOVERNMENT
TO GROW THE AMERICAN ECONOMY.
THAT IS THE FUNDAMENTAL ISSUE
WE SHOULD BE DEBATING HERE
TONIGHT.
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT, GOVERNOR
JINDAL, THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, HAVE YOU
SAID THAT THE DEMOCRATS'
MESSAGE IS ONE OF, QUOTE, FREE
STUFF.
IN CONTRAST, REPUBLICANS WANT
TO REDUCE SPENDING.
HOW DO YOU WIN A NATIONAL
ELECTION WHEN THE DEMOCRATS ARE
OFFERING FREE HEALTH CARE, A
FREE OR SUBSIDIZED COLLEGE
EDUCATION, AND YOU'RE THE PARTY
SEEMINGLY OFFERING NOTHING IN
THE WAY OF IMMEDIATE TANGIBLE
BENEFITS?
>> YEAH, SURE.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> IF ANYBODY BELIEVES THE
STUFF THEY HEARD FROM THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE A FEW WEEKS
AGO, THERE'S NOTHING FOR FREE.
WHAT THEY FORGET TO TELL YOU IS
THEY'RE GOING TO RAISE YOUR TAX
RATES TO 70 OR 80% IN ORDER TO
PROVIDE THAT STUFF.
LET ME ASK THE FOLKS AT HOME
ONE SIMPLE QUESTION, DO YOU
WANT TO GIVE WASHINGTON MORE
CONTROL OVER YOUR LIFE?
DO YOU THINK THEY'RE DOING SUCH
A GREAT JOB, LET'S HAVE THEM
CONTROL WHAT CORPORATIONS PAY
EMPLOYEES?
HAVE THEM CONTROL EVERY ASPECT
OF OUR ECONOMY?
IS WASHINGTON DOING THAT GOOD A
JOB FOR YOU RIGHT NOW?
THE FACT IS IF YOU LISTEN TO
HILLARY CLINTON, SHE'S MADE IT
VERY CLEAR, SHE BELIEVES THAT
SHE CAN MAKE DECISIONS FOR YOU
BETTER THAN YOU CAN MAKE THEM
FOR YOURSELF.
SHE BELIEVES THAT WASHINGTON,
D.C. SHOULD PICK THE WINNERS
AND LOSERS IN OUR ECONOMY, AND
IN OUR LIFE.
AND HERE'S WHAT I BELIEVE AS A
REPUBLICAN, I BELIEVE THE
GREATNESS OF AMERICA IS NOT IN
ITS GOVERNMENT.
THE GREATNESS OF AMERICA IS IN
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
WE NEED TO GET THE GOVERNMENT
THE HELL OUT OF THE WAY AND LET
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WIN ONCE
AGAIN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM, A
SINGLE MOM WITH NO JOB AND TWO
KIDS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, HOME OF
THE FIRST IN THE NATION PRIMARY
IS ELIGIBLE FOR MORE THAN
$30,000 A YEAR IN BENEFITS.
EVEN IF SHE COULD FIND A JOB,
SHE WOULD NEED TO FIND CHILD
CARE AND IN MANY CASES MAY
CONCLUDE IT'S BETTER FOR HER TO
LIVE OFF GOVERNMENT BENEFITS.
SENATOR, HOW DO YOU HELP AND
INCENTIVIZE HER TO GO TO WORK?
IF YOU'RE THE ONE WHO'S GOING
TO CUT HER BENEFITS, WHY SHOULD
SHE VOTE FOR YOU?
>> THE ANSWER IS FIRST WE NEED
TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT A TAX
CODE THAT DOES PENALIZE.
ONE THING I'M EXCITED ABOUT OUR
TAX CODE, PROPOSED CHANGES IS
IT'S VERY PRO FAMILY.
YOU HAVE $2700 TAX CREDIT
PERIOD FOR EVERY PERSON IN THE
FAMILY, SO THAT FAMILY WOULD
HAVE $8,000 TAX CREDIT, WHICH
WOULD BE REFUNDABLE.
SO EVERY DOLLAR SHE WORKS,
SHE'S ONLY LOSING 20 CENTS.
THE PROBLEM WITH THE TAX CODE
TODAY BECAUSE OF THE DIFFERENT
PROVISIONS, YOU'RE RIGHT, YOU
GO BACK TO WORK, YOU LOSE
WELFARE BENEFITS, YOU'RE LOSING
MONEY.
THROW ON TOP OF THAT THE EVEN A
BIGGER PROBLEM, OVER 50% OF
CHILDREN BEING RAISED IN A HOME
TODAY OF A SINGLE MOM ARE
RAISED IN A HOME WHERE THE
FATHER IS LIVING AT THE TIME
THE CHILD IS BORN.
NOW WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?
THAT MEANS WE HAVE INCENTIVIZED
PEOPLE NOT TO MARRY.
WE'VE INCENTIVIZED PEOPLE TO CO
HABITATE NOT MARRY, WHY?
MOM WILL LOSE BENEFITS IF HE
MARRIES FATHER.
NOT JUST MOM GOING TO WORK BUT
MOM AND FATHER MARRYING TO FORM
A STABLE FAMILY TO BE FORMED IN
A TWO-PARENT FAMILY.
WE'VE GOT ALL SORTS OF CORRUPT
INCENTIVES THAT WERE PUT IN
PLACE, WELL MEANING BY THE
LEFT.
BUT WE NEED TO REMOVE THE
INCENTIVES, ADOPT A TAX CODE
THAT SAYS WE'RE GOING TO BE
PRO-FAMILY AND PRO-WORK.
THAT'S WHAT WE'LL DO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR.
GOVERNOR HUCKABEE, YOU HAVE
CHARACTERIZED ENTITLEMENT
REFORM AS BOTH POLITICAL AND
ECONOMIC SUICIDE.
TAXPAYERS CURRENTLY SPEND MORE
THAN 600 BILLION DOLLARS PER
YEAR ON SOCIAL WELFARE
PROGRAMS, WITH THE INTENDED
GOAL OF GETTING PEOPLE BACK ON
THEIR FEET AND WORKING AGAIN.
TODAY A RECORD NUMBER OF
AMERICANS AREN'T EVEN LOOK FOR
WORK.
ARE OUR SOCIAL WELFARE
PROGRAMS, WHILE WELL INTENDED,
CREATING A CULTURE OF
DEPENDENCY?
IF SO, HOW WILL YOU FIX IT?
>> SANDRA, LET ME MENTION THE
FACT THERE'S A BIG DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN WELFARE PROGRAMS AND
WHAT SOME PEOPLE CALL
ENTITLEMENTS.
NAMELY, SOCIAL SECURITY AND
MEDICARE.
I JUST WANT TO REMIND EVERYBODY
OUT THERE WHOSE EVER HAD A
PAYCHECK.
THE GOVERNMENT DIDN'T ASK YOU
IF YOU WANTED THEM TO TAKE
MONEY OUT OF YOUR CHECK FOR
SOCIAL SECURITY AND MEDICARE.
THEY DID THAT INVOLUNTARILY.
THOSE ARE NOT ENTITLEMENTS AND
THAT'S NOT WELFARE.
THAT'S AN EARNED BENEFIT, AND
BY GOSH, YOU PAID FOR IT, AND
IF THE GOVERNMENT SCREWED IT
UP, YOU SHOULDN'T HAVE TO PAY
THE PENALTY BECAUSE OF AN
INCOMPETENT GOVERNMENT.
THAT'S DIFFERENT THAN THE
SOCIAL PROGRAMS THAT WE'VE
SPENT $2 TRILLION ON SINCE THE
WAR ON POVERTY BEGAN EXACTLY 50
YEARS AGO THIS YEAR.
NOW THE REASON WE STILL HAVE SO
MUCH POVERTY IS IT WAS NEVER
DESIGNED TO GET PEOPLE OUT OF
POVERTY.
IT WAS DESIGNED TO MAKE SURE
THERE WAS AN INDUSTRY OF
POVERTY SO THE PEOPLE IN THE
POVERTY INDUSTRY WOULD HAVE A
LOT OF JOBS.
BUT THE PEOPLE WHO ARE POOR
HAVEN'T BENEFITTED.
HAVING GROWN UP POOR, I KNOW A
LITTLE SOMETHING ABOUT IT.
NOBODY WHO IS POOR WANTS TO BE.
THAT'S A NONSENSE STATEMENT.
AND I HEAR IT ALL THE TIME.
POOR PEOPLE OUGHT TO WORK
HARDER.
THEY'RE WORKING AS HARD AS THEY
CAN FOR GOSH SAKE.
THE SYSTEM KEEPS PUSHING THEM
DOWN BECAUSE IF THEY WORK THEY
GET PUNISHED.
THEY LOSE ALL THE BENEFITS.
WHEN WE DID WELFARE REFORM OF
THE '90s, WE SAID YOU'RE NOT
GOING TO LOSE EVERYTHING AT
ONCE, THERE'S NOT AN ARBITRARY
THRESHOLD, SO AS YOU MOVE UP
THE LADDER FROM WORK AND
TRAINING, YOU WILL ACTUALLY
ALWAYS BE BETTER OFF THAN YOU
WERE BEFORE.
THAT'S THE AMERICAN WAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> GOVERNOR JINDAL, REPUBLICANS
HAVE WON 32 OF THE NATION'S 50
GOVERNOR SEATS.
YOU KEEP FALLING SHORT
NATIONALLY.
YOU LOST THE POPULAR VOTE IN
FIVE OF THE LAST SIX
PRESIDENTIAL ELECTIONSES.
ARE DEMOCRATS PUTTING FORWARD A
BETTER NATIONAL ECONOMIC
MESSAGE THAN THE ONE
REPUBLICANS ARE OFFERING?
WHAT SHOULD REPUBLICANS DO
ABOUT IT?
>> THE REASON WE KEEP LOSING
NATIONALLY IS WE KEEP TRYING TO
BE CHEAPER VERSIONS OF THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WHAT IF REPUBLICANS EMBRACED
OUR OWN PRINCIPLES SO I EARLIER
SAID IF YOU WANT BIGGER
PAYCHECKS, MORE JOBS, LESS
GOVERNMENT DEPENDENCE, YOU'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO CUT GOVERNMENT
SPENDING.
HERE'S THE DIRTY LITTLE SECRET.
YOU'RE GOING TO HEAR A LOT OF
REPUBLICANS TONIGHT TALK ABOUT
CUTTING GOVERNMENT SPENDING.
IT'S GOING TO SOUND GREAT.
ONLY ONE OF US THAT'S CUT
GOVERNMENT SPENDING.
NOT TWO.
THERE'S ONE.
YOU'RE LOOKING AT HIM.
WE'VE GOT FOUR SENATORS
RUNNING, THEY HAVE NEVER CUT
ANYTHING IN D.C.
THEY GIVE THE LONG SPEECHES
CALLED FILIBUSTERS, PAT
THEMSELVES ON THE BACK, WHEN
THEY GO TO RELIEF THEMSELVES
THE CAUSE IN THE TOILETS GET
FLUSHED AT THE SAME TIME AND
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE LOSE.
WE HAVE SEVEN CURRENT AND
FORMER GOVERNORS RUNNING, I'M
THE ONLY ONE WHO CUT GOVERNMENT
SPENDING, IF THEY HAVEN'T DONE
IT IN THE STATE CAPITALS, WHAT
MAKES US THINK THEY'LL DO IT IF
THEY ARE SENT TO D.C.
WHEN POLITICIANS TALK, IT'S A
BUNCH OF HOT AIR.
WE CUT OUR BUDGET 26%.
RECORD NUMBER OF LOUISIANANS
WORKING.
IF REPUBLICANS WANT TO WIN
NATIONAL ELECTIONS, LET'S BE
CONSERVATIVES, REPUBLICANS,
LET'S NOT BE A SECOND VERSION
OF THE LIBERAL PARTY, CUT
GOVERNMENT SPENDING AND GROW
THE AMERICAN ECONOMY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
MODERATOR: YOU HAVE SOMETHING
TO ADD, GOVERNOR?
>> WITH ALL DUE RESPECT TO THE
GOVERNOR TO THE STATE JUST
SOUTH OF ME, A LOT OF US HAVE
CUT THINGS, AND DURING THE
RECESSION OF 2001-2003, WHEN
91% OF OUR STATE BUDGET WAS
BASICALLY THREE THINGS,
EDUCATE, MEDICATE AND
INCARCERATE, WE ENDED UP
CUTTING 11% OUT OF THE STATE
BUDGET THROUGH THAT RECESSION
SO WE DIDN'T HAVE TO GO IN AND
RAISE A BUNCH OF TAXES AND
PEOPLE WHO THOUGHT WE SHOULD.
IT'S JUST NOT ACCURATE TO SAY
NOBODY ELSE UP HERE HAS EVER
CUT.
I BELIEVE EVERY GOVERNOR HAS
HAD TO MAKE TOUGH DECISIONS,
I'M GUESSING MY COLLEAGUE
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE HAS, AS I'M
TOSSING HIM THE BALL.
>> I WANT TO RESPOND.
HE CRITICIZED SOMETHING I SAID.
MIKE, WITH ALL DUE RESPECT, I
ADMIRE YOUR SOCIAL VIEWS, SHARE
THE VIEWS, YOUR RECORDAS
GOVERNOR TELLS A DIFFERENT
STORY.
SPENDING IN ARKANSAS WENT UP
65%.
NUMBER OF STATE WORKERS WENT UP
20%.
TAXES FOR THE AVERAGE CITIZEN
WENT UP 47%.
THAT'S NOT A RECORD OF CUTTING,
I'M SAYING WE'VE ACTUALLY CUT,
WE REDUCED THE SIZE OF OUR
BUDGET, SO WANTING TO CUT ONE
THING, ACTUALLY CUTTING IS A
DIFFERENT THING.
FACTS DON'T LIE.
MODERATOR: LET'S BRING GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE IN ON THIS.
>> SANDRA, BEFORE WE GET TOO
FAR AWAY, HE BROUGHT OUT THINGS
ABOUT THE RECORD THEY NEED TO
CORRECT.
MODERATOR: LET'S KEEP THE
CONVERSATION GOING, BRING
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE IN HERE,
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT NATIONAL
DEBT, CLIMBING TOWARDS $19
TRILLION, GOVERNOR.
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT EMPLOYEES,
NEARLY 3 MILLION WORKERS, OUR
TAX CODE IS 70,000 PAGES LONG.
IF YOU ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT,
WHAT CONCRETE STEPS WOULD YOU
TAKE TO REDUCE THE SIZE OF THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT?
>> FIRST OFF, LET ME SAY THIS
IN RESPONSE TO THE BACK AND
FORTH.
FOR THE PEOPLE OUT THERE RIGHT
NOW, I WANT TO GUARANTEE YOU
ONE THING, REALLY CLEARLY, IF
YOU THINK MIKE HUCKABEE WON'T
BE THE KIND OF PRESIDENT WHO
WILL CUT BACK SPENDING OR CHRIS
CHRISTIE OR JOHN KASICH, WAIT
UNTIL YOU SEE WHAT HILLARY
CLINTON WILL DO TO THE COUNTRY
AND HOW SHE WILL DROWN US IN
DEBT.
SHE IS THE REAL ADVERSARY AND
BETTER STAY FOCUSED ON
REPUBLICANS ON HER.
I PUT FORWARD AN ENTITLEMENT
REFORM PLAN.
WE SPENT 71 CENTS OF EVERY
DOLLAR IN AMERICA ON
ENTITLEMENTS AND DEBT SERVICE.
WILLIE SUTTON USED TO SAY WHEN
ASKED WHY ROB BANKS?
BECAUSE THAT'S WHERE THE MONEY
IS.
WHERE THE MONEY IS THE
ENTITLEMENT PROGRAMS AND DEBT
SERVICE.
WE NEED TO GET AHOLD OF THAT,
WE CANNOT CONTINUE TO GO DOWN
THE 19TRILLION IN DEBT.
SO OUR PLAN WILL SAVE OVER $1
TRILLION OVER TEN YEARS AND
MAKE SURE SOCIAL SECURITY AND
MEDICARE ARE THERE FOR THOSE
WHO TRULY NEED IT, AND ALSO
MAKE SURE WE HAVE MONEY TO
REDUCE TAXES, AND SPEND ON THE
THINGS WE NEED TO SPEND.
I WILL ALSO, ON MY FIRST DAY AS
PRESIDENT, SIGN AN EXECUTIVE
ORDER THAT SAYS NO MORE
REGULATION FOR THE NEXT 120
DAYS BY ANY GOVERNMENT AGENCY
OR DEPARTMENT.
WE ARE DROWNING IN REGULATION,
STOP.
AND WE'LL GO OUT THERE AND CUT
AND REDUCE REGULATION, YOU'LL
GROW THE ECONOMY THEN, MORE
MONEY WILL COME INTO THE
SYSTEM, AND GET MORE CLOSER TO
BALANCE.
BUT THE BOTTOM LINE IS BELIEVE
ME, HILLARY CLINTON'S COMING
FOR YOUR WALLET, EVERYBODY.
DON'T WORRY ABOUT HUCKABEE OR
JINDAL.
WORRY ABOUT HER.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRISTIE,
THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT, WE ARE JUST GETTING
STARTED.
MEDICARE, SOCIAL SECURITY AND
THE FUTURE OF OBAMACARE.
THAT IS ALL STRAIGHT AHEAD.
LIVE FROM MILWAUKEE AND THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
.
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
MILWAUKEE THEATRE AND THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
ONTO THE NEXT ROUND OF
QUESTIONS, GERRY HAS THE NEXT
QUESTION.
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM,
WE'RE IN THE UPPER MIDWEST.
THE ART OF ALLIANCE IS HOME TO
176 AUTO SUPPLIER COMPANIES.
BACK IN 2008 YOU OPPOSED THE
USE OF FEDERAL BAILOUT FUNDS AS
PROPOSED BY THE THEN-BUSH
ADMINISTRATION.
AUTOMAKERS SURVIVED.
YOU STILL THINK THAT WAS THE
RIGHT POSITION?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
I'M A CAPITALIST NOT A
CORPORATIST, I'M NOT SOMEONE
WHO BELIEVES WE SHOULD BE
BAILING OUT CORPORATIONS,
WHETHER AUTO INDUSTRIES OR
BANKS.
SIMPLY A MATTER, THE AUTO
INDUSTRY WOULD HAVE SURVIVED
THROUGH A BANKRUPTCY PROCESS
INSTEAD OF WASHINGTON PICKING A
WINNER AND LOSER.
IN THIS CASE, THE WINNERS ARE
THE BOND HOLDERS AND THE LOSERS
WERE THE UNIONS.
THAT'S FINE.
THEY DID IT.
THE UNIONS SURVIVED.
WE HAVE NOT SURVIVED AND
CONTINUED TO GROW MANUFACTURING
JOBS.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT AND ECONOMY
RIGHT NOW THAT IS KILLING,
CHOKE OUR ABILITY TO BE ABLE TO
COMPETE.
I'M ONE OF THE FEW PEOPLE UP
HERE WHO BELIEVES WE NEED A
LEVEL PLAYING FIELD WHEN IT
COMES TO MANUFACTURING.
THAT MEANS A GOOD TAX CODE,
REGULATORY ENVIRONMENT, LOW
ENERGY PRICES, BETTER
OPPORTUNITIES FOR WORKERS TO
GET TRAINING, AND ALSO, I'M A
SUPPORTER OF THE EX-IM BANK.
EVERYBODY ELSE IN THE ENTIRE
FIELD IS OPPOSED TO IT.
WHY -- HOW CAN YOU COME OUT AND
SAY I'M FOR MANUFACTURING WHEN
A MAJORITY OF REPUBLICAN
CONGRESSMEN AND SENATORS
SUPPORTED THE EX-IM BANK
BECAUSE IT MEANS JOBS FOR
AMERICAN WORKERS HERE IN
AMERICA?
THE FACT IS WE'VE SEEN ALREADY
GE LOSE JOBS HERE IN AMERICA,
AND JUST MOVE THE JOBS TO
FRANCE AND HUNGARY.
WE HAVE A RIGHT AS A COUNTRY TO
COMPETE WITH OTHER COUNTRIES
THAT HAVE EXPORT FINANCING.
EVERY MAJOR MANUFACTURER, 60
COUNTRIES COMPETES AGAINST
AMERICA, WANTS TO TAKE OUR
JOBS, AND WE HAVE EVERY
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATE.
WANT TO TALK ABOUT COMMUNICATES
TO WORKERS HERE IN WISCONSIN?
ASK THEM WHY WE'RE TYING ONE
HAND BEHIND OUR BACK AND SAYING
GO OUT AND COMPETE?
[ APPLAUSE ]
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR
SANTORUM.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE,
YOU DIFFER FROM MANY GOP
OPPONENTS ON THE STAGE OVER
ACCEPTING SYRIAN REFUGEES INTO
THIS COUNTRY.
HAVE YOU SAID WE DON'T HAVE AN
OBLIGATION TO JUST OPEN OUR
DOORS.
AS THE ISLAMIC STATE CONTINUES
TO EXPAND, SLAUGHTERING AND
CRUCIFYING CHRISTIANS INCLUDING
WOMEN AND CHILDREN, REFUGEES
CONTINUE TO FLEE THEIR LAND BY
THE THOUSANDS.
SHOULD AMERICA OPEN ITS DOORS
TO ACCEPT ANY REFUGEES IN THIS
COUNTRY.
IF SO, HOW MANY?
>> SANDRA, I'VE BEEN CONCERNED
THAT THIS ADMINISTRATION HAS
NOT DONE ANYTHING TO HELP STOP
THE SLAUGHTER OF CHRISTIANS.
WE DIDN'T HELP THE KURDS, WE
SAID WE WOULD.
THE IDEA WE'RE JUST GOING TO
OPEN OUR DOORS AND HAVE NO IDEA
WHO THE PEOPLE ARE?
WHAT WE DO KNOW IS ONE OUT OF
FIVE OF THE SO-CALLED SYRIAN
REFUGEES WHO WENT INTO EUROPE
WERE ACTUALLY SYRIAN.
MANY WE HAD NO IDEA WHO THEY
WERE.
THEY WEREN'T SYRIAN.
ARE WE GOING TO OPEN THE DOOR
SO ISIS PEOPLE COME ON IN, GIVE
THEM A PLACE TO SAY AND GOOD
SANDWICH AND MEDICAL BENEFITS?
MY GOSH, WE'RE $19 TRILLION IN
DEBT WEEK CAN'T AFFORD TO TAKE
CARE OF AMERICANS.
IF WE'RE GOING TO DO SOMETHING
FOR THE SYRIANS, FIND OUT WHO
THEY REALLY ARE AND THE ONES
REALLY IN DANGER, BUILD AN
ENCAMPMENT FOR THEM BUT CLOSER
TO WHERE THEY LIVE RATHER THAN
BRING THEM HERE, WHEN THEY
DON'T KNOW THE LANGUAGE, THE
CULTURE.
AND FRANKLY IF WE'VE GOT AS
MANY HOMELESS PEOPLE WE HAVE,
I'M NOT SURE THIS MAKES ANY
SENSE.
LET'S DO IT WHERE WE CAN BEST
HELP THEM.
SEND THEM FOOD.
LET'S ASK THE SAUDIS TO STEP
UP.
I'M TIRED OF THE AMERICANS
BEING THE ONLY ONES ASKED TO DO
ALL THE HEAVY LIFTING WHEN IT
COMES TO CHARITY, AND QUITE
FRANKLY, MY NUMBER ONE CONCERN
RIGHT NOW IS TAKE CARE OF THE
FACT THAT AMERICANS ARE TAKING
IT IN THE GUT WITHOUT JOBS,
MANY OF THEM WORK IN TWO AND
THREE PART-TIME JOBS, AND IF
AMERICA WANTS TO DO SOMETHING,
GREAT.
LET'S GET OUR ECONOMY GROWING
AGAIN.
STABILIZE THE DOLLAR, AND WE'LL
BE IN A MUCH BETTER POSITION TO
HELP PEOPLE AROUND THE WORLD.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE,
THANK YOU.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRISTIE,
CHINA IS STEALING TECHNOLOGY,
PIRATING OUR INTELLECTUAL
PROPERTY.
SPYING ON AMERICAN CORPORATIONS
AND SPYING ON CITIZENS.
CHINA SLAPS TERRORISTS ON U.S.
GOODS MAKING IT HARDER FOR US
TO SELL OUR PRODUCTS.
HOW ARE YOU GOING TO STOP IT?
>> WELL, LET'S START WITH THIS,
REMEMBER WHY WE'RE IN THE
POSITION WE'RE IN WITH CHINA.
BECAUSE AN ABSOLUTELY WEAK AND
FECKLESS FOREIGN POLICY THAT
WAS ENGINEERED BY HILLARY
CLINTON AND BARACK OBAMA.
THAT'S WHY WE'RE IN THE
POSITION WE'RE IN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> BECAUSE, TRISH, THE CHINESE
DON'T TAKE US SERIOUSLY.
WHY SHOULD THEY?
THEY HACKED INTO THE AMERICAN
GOVERNMENT'S PERSONNEL FILES
AND TOOK MILLIONS OF RECORDS
AND CYBER WARFARE AGAINST THIS
COUNTRY.
I'M ONE OF THE VICTIMS OF THAT
HACK.
THEY TOOK MY SOCIAL SECURITY
NUMBER.
MY FINGERPRINTS AS A FORMER
UNITED STATES ATTORNEY, THAT
WAS ON FILE IN THERE, AND WHAT
HAS THIS PRESIDENT DONE?
NOT ONE THING.
LET ME BE REALLY CLEAR WHAT I
WOULD DO.
IF THE CHINESE COMMIT CYBER
WARFARE AGAINST US, THEY ARE
GOING TO SEE CYBER WARFARE LIKE
THEY HAVE NEVER SEEN BEFORE.
THAT IS A CLOSED SOCIETY IN
CHINA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THEY'RE HIDING INFORMATION
FROM THEIR OWN PEOPLE.
THE INFORMATION WE TAKE, WE'LL
MAKE SURE ALL THE CHINESE
PEOPLE SEE IT.
THAT WILL HAVE FUN IN BEIJING
WHEN WE SHOW THEM HOW THEY'RE
SPENDING THEIR MONEY IN CHINA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ONE LAST THING, I WILL TELL
YOU THIS, THEY'RE BUILDING THE
ARTIFICIAL ISLANDS IN THE SOUTH
CHINA SEA, AND THE PRESIDENT
WON'T -- UP UNTIL RECENTLY
WOULDN'T SAIL A SHIP WITHIN 12
MILES OR FLY A PLANE OVER IT.
THE FIRST THING I'LL DO IS I'LL
FLY AIR FORCE ONE OVER THE
ISLANDS.
THEY'LL KNOW WE MEAN BUSINESS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR JINDAL, THERE'S A
NEW TRADE DEAL THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION COMPLETED WITH
11 OTHER PACIFIC NATIONS.
THE U.S. TRADE REPRESENTATIVES
OFFICE SAYS THAT DEAL WILL CUT
18,000 DIFFERENT TARIFFS ON
AMERICAN GOODS SENT TO THE
PACIFIC.
CUT GOODS IN YOUR STATE BY 48%.
YOU'VE BEEN A SKEPTIC ABOUT THE
DEAL.
NOW THAT THE DETAILS ARE
PUBLIC, ARE YOU FOR IT?
>> I WAS SKEPTIC OF GIVING THIS
PRESIDENT MORE POWER.
NEGOTIATED A BAD DEAL WITH
IRAN, BREAKS THE LAW ROUTINELY.
LOOK, THIS TRADE DEAL IS 6,000
PAGES LONG.
UNLIKE OBAMACARE, WE SHOULD
READ IT BEFORE WE DECIDE
WHETHER TO VOTE FOR IT OR NOT
VOTE FOR IT.
I AM FOR TRADE DEALS, BUT WANT
TO MAKE SURE THEY ARE FAIR
TRADE DEALS.
TONIGHT COME BACK TO SOMETHING
CHRIS SAID EARLIER.
I ABSOLUTELY AGREE WE'VE GOT TO
BEAT HILLARY CLINTON, SENDING
ANY REPUBLICAN IS NOT GOOD
ENOUGH.
WE'VE HAD A REPUBLICAN SENATE
AND HOUSE.
WHAT HAS CHANGED?
IF WE SEND ANOTHER DEMOCRAT TO
THE WHITE HOUSE, WE WILL NOT DO
ANYTHING TO FIX THIS COUNTRY.
UNDER YOUR LEADERSHIP IN NEW
JERSEY, YOUR BUDGET HAS GONE UP
15%.
DOWN 26% IN LOUISIANA.
IT HAS GONE UP $5 MILLION IN
NEW JERSEY.
DOWN $9 BILLION IN LOUISIANA.
IN NEW JERSEY, 9 CREDIT
DOWNGRADES, IN LOUISIANA, 8
CREDIT UPGRADES IN LOUISIANA.
IF POLITICIANS SAY THEY'RE
CONSERVATIVE, CUT SPENDING, BUT
DON'T DO IT, WHY SEND THEM TO
D.C.?
IT GETS HARDER NOT EASIER WHEN
WE SEND THEM TO D.C.
LET'S CUT GOVERNMENT SPENDING,
LET'S GROW THE AMERICAN
ECONOMY.
LET'S NOT JUST BEAT HILLARY,
LET'S ELECT A CONSERVATIVE TO
THE WHITE HOUSE.
NOT JUST ANY REPUBLICAN.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRISTIE?
>> I TELL YOU, GERRY,
INTERESTING, IF YOU GO TO NEW
JERSEY, THEY'LL CALL ME LOTS OF
DIFFERENT THINGS.
A LIBERAL IS NOT ONE OF THEM.
I WILL SAY THIS.
I HAVE GREAT RESPECT FOR
BOBBY'S RECORD IN LOUISIANA.
HE'S BEEN A WONDERFUL GOVERNOR
AND PROVIDED OUTSTANDING
LEADERSHIP FOR THAT STATE AND I
RESPECT HIM FOR WHAT HE'S DONE.
ALL OF US DESERVE THAT SAME
LEVEL OF RESPECT.
MY POINT IS THIS, THE
DIFFERENCES BETWEEN ME AND
BOBBY JINDAL, WE COULD TALK
ABOUT THOSE, OBVIOUSLY BOBBY
WANTS TO SPEND A LOT OF TIME
TALKING ABOUT THAT.
I TELL YOU WHAT I WANT TO TALK
ABOUT.
I WANT TO TALK ABOUT WHAT'S
GOING TO HAPPEN TO THIS COUNTRY
IF WE HAVE ANOTHER FOUR YEARS
OF BARACK OBAMA'S POLICIES.
BY THE WAY, IT WILL BE EVEN
WORSE BECAUSE HILLARY CLINTON
IS RUNNING SO FAR TO THE LEFT
TO TRY TO CATCH UP TO HER
SOCIALIST OPPONENT BERNIE
SANDERS, IT'S HARD TO SEE HER
ANYMORE.
THE FACT IS, THE FACT IS WE
BETTER BE FOCUSED ON IT.
I TELL YOU WHAT I'LL BRING TO
THE TABLE.
THE FACT I'VE WON IN A BLUE
STATE.
THAT I WON IN A STATE FOR
RE-ELECTION AFTER GOVERNING AS
A PRO-LIFE CONSERVATIVE AND GOT
61% OF THE VOTE.
THAT'S THE PERSON YOU WANT IN
THE STAGE PROSECUTING THE CASE
AGAINST HILLARY CLINTON.
>> BUT WAIT A MINUTE, RECORDS
MATTER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> RECORDS MATTER.
YES, WE'VE GOT TO BEAT HILLARY
CLINTON, BUT CHRIS, IT'S ALSO
TRUE YOU EXPANDED FOOD STAMPS
AT A TIME WE HAVE RECORD
NUMBERS OF AMERICANS ON FOOD
STAMPS.
YOU CAVED INTO OBAMACARE,
EXPANDED MEDICARE.
WE HAVE A CHOICE.
THIS IS AN IMPORTANT DEBATE.
NOT ABOUT COMPARING LOUISIANA
TO NEW JERSEY OR BOBBY TO
CHRIS.
THIS SAN IMPORTANT DEBATE FOR
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
LET'S HAVE A DEBATE.
WE WANT TO GROW GOVERNMENT OR
GROW THE AMERICAN ECONOMY?
DO WE WANT TO GROW DEPENDENCE
ON GOVERNMENT, OR GROW GOOD
PAYING JOBS IN THE PRIVATE
SECTOR?
YOU DON'T PUT MORE PEOPLE ON
FOOD STAMPS AND MEDICAID.
YOU CUT GOVERNMENT, CUTTING
SPENDING, THAT'S WHAT WE'VE
DONE IN LOUISIANA, YOU HAVEN'T
DONE THAT IN NEW JERSEY.
WE NEED A CONSERVATIVE, NOT A
BIG GOVERNMENT REPUBLICAN IN
D.C.
>> LET ME JUST SAY, THIS
INTERESTING, I COMPLIMENTED
BOBBY.
IMAGINE HOW MUCH TIME HE'D WANT
IF I CRITICIZED HIM?
[ LAUGHTER ].
>> THE FACT IS HE'S DONE A NICE
JOB IN LOUISIANA, I DON'T HAVE
A PROBLEM WITH THE JOB HE'S
DONE.
I CUT SPENDING TWO BILLION
DOLLARS EXCEPT FOR PENSION AND
HEALTH CARE IN NEW JERSEY
DRIVEN PREDOMINANTLY BY
OBAMACARE.
REDUCED THE NUMBER OF STATE
EMPLOYEES ON THE PAYROLL BY
15%.
THE PEOPLE DON'T CARE ABOUT ANY
OF.
THAT THEY CARE ABOUT WHO'S
GOING TO BE ABLE TO BEAT
HILLARY CLINTON AND KEEP THEIR
EYE ON THE BALL.
I'M GOING TO KEEP MY EYE ON THE
BALL.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, BOTH
GOVERNORS.
NEXT QUESTION.
>> THIS IS NOT ABOUT BETWEEN ME
AND CHRIS --
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR JINDAL,
GOVERNOR JINDAL, THE NEXT
QUESTION IS TO YOU ON
OBAMACARE.
IT IS STILL UNPOPULAR WITH THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
YOU'VE SEEN THE POLLS, THEY
SHOW NEARLY HALF THE COUNTRY
STILL OPPOSES THIS LAW.
YOU HAVE BEEN CRITICAL OF YOUR
GOP OPPONENTS, SOME OF THEM
STANDING ON THE STAGE TONIGHT.
OTHERS LATER.
NOTABLY TED CRUZ, FOR NOT
HAVING COMPREHENSIVE PLANS.
YOU SAY YOU DO.
WHAT SPECIFICALLY MAKES YOUR
PLAN TO REPLACE OBAMACARE
BETTER THAN THE OPPONENTS, SOME
OF THEM STANDING NEXT TO YOU?
>> LOOK, ONLY ONE OTHER
CANDIDATE HAS A PLAN.
THAT'S JEB BUSH, HE CREATES A
NEW ENTITLEMENT PROGRAM.
MY PLAN GETS RID OF ALL OF
OBAMACARE.
IT'S GREAT THAT SENATOR CRUZ
WILL SHUT DOWN THE GOVERNMENT
OVER OBAMACARE BUT HASN'T GIVEN
US A PLAN TO GET RID OF IT.
GREAT OTHER REPUBLICANS TALK
ABOUT GETTING RID OF IT.
WHEN YOU GO TO A TOWN HALL IN
IOWA OR NEW HAMPSHIRE, ASK THEM
HOW THEY GET RID OF IT?
MY PLAN HAS BEEN ONLINE FOR
OVER A YEAR, REDUCES COSTS,
PUTS AMERICANS, THEIR PATIENTS
AND DOCTORS BACK TO CONTROL,
AND HELPS THOSE WHO NEED THIS
HELP.
BUT THIS IS ONE OF THE MOST
CRITICAL ISSUES WE FACE
DOMESTICALLY.
I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE RUNNING
THAT REFUSED TO EXPAND
MEDICAID.
I AM THE ONLY ONE THAT DID WHAT
WE COULD TO FIGHT OBAMACARE.
THIS IS AN IMPORTANT POINT.
I APPRECIATE CHRIS' POINTS TO
ME.
I LOVE MARY PAT.
THIS IS ABOUT THE MOST
IMPORTANT ELECTION IN OUR
LIFETIMES.
FOLKS, A COUPLE YEARS AGO, GIVE
US THE REPUBLICAN MAJORITIES IN
THE HOUSE AND THE SENATE,
THEY'D STOP OBAMACARE AND
AMNESTY AND THE BAD IRAN DEAL.
NOTHING CHANGED.
IF THEY FOOLED US ONCE, SHAME
ON US, IF THEY FOOLED US TWICE,
SHAME ON US.
I GIVE YOU PARTICIPATION AND A
JUICE BOX, IT'S ABOUT ACTUALLY
CUTTING GOVERNMENT SPENDING,
NOT TALKING ABOUT CUTTING
GOVERNMENT SPENDING.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR JINDAL,
THANK YOU.
>> WE STOPPED OBAMACARE IN NEW
JERSEY, BUT HERE'S THE BIGGER
ISSUE, WHAT DO YOU THINK IS
GOING TO HAPPEN WHEN HILLARY
CLINTON IS ELECTED PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES?
THE WOMAN WHO TRIED TO IMPOSE
HEALTH CARE ON THIS COUNTRY
OVER 20 YEARS AGO?
AND SHE WAS STOPPED THEN BY A
STRONG GROUP OF REPUBLICANS AND
AMERICAN PUBLIC THAT SAID NO,
THANK YOU.
WHAT SHE WILL DO, WHAT SHE WILL
DO IS MOVE US TOWARDS A SINGLE
PAYER SYSTEM.
SHE WILL COMPLETELY NATIONALIZE
THE FEDERAL HEALTH CARE SYSTEM,
THAT'S WHAT SHE WANTED TO DO 20
YEARS AGO AND I GUARANTEE
THAT'S WHAT SHE'LL DO IF YOU
GIVE HER THE KEYS TO THE WHITE
HOUSE ONE MORE TIME.
THE FACT IS WE NEED SOMEONE WHO
KNOWS HOW TO BEAT DEMOCRATS,
KNOWS HOW TO BEAT DEMOCRATS IN
A DEMOCRATIC AREA.
I'VE DONE IT TWICE AS GOVERNOR
OF NEW JERSEY, AND HILLARY
CLINTON DOESN'T WANT ONE MINUTE
ON THAT STAGE WITH ME NEXT
SEPTEMBER WHEN I'M DEBATING AND
PROSECUTES HER FOR HER VISION
OF AMERICA.
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM, I
HAVE A QUESTION FOR YOU.
JUST ABOUT EVERYBODY AGREES
THAT THE NATION'S
INFRASTRUCTURE IS IN BAD SHAPE,
URBAN HIGHWAY CONGESTION COST
THE ECONOMY, NEARLY ONE IN FOUR
BRIDGES IN THE NATIONAL HIGHWAY
SYSTEM IS OBSOLETE.
CONGRESS IS WORKING ON A SIX
YEAR HIGHWAY BILL, FUND IT FOR
THREE YEARS.
SHOULD AMERICANS BE ASKED TO
PAY MORE IN FEDERAL GAS TAXES
TO PAY FOR THIS?
>> I'M GOING TO ANSWER THAT IN
A SECOND.
THIS IS A LEGITIMATE DEBATE
BETWEEN CHRIS AND BOBBY BETWEEN
SOMEONE WHO SAYS HE CAN WIN IN
A BLUE STATE AND SOMEONE WHO
SAYS HE IS A PRINCIPLED
CONSERVATIVE.
92% CONSERVATIVE VOTING RECORD
UNLIKE THE OTHER CONSERVATIVE
REPUBLICANS, I WAS THE AUTHOR
OF WELFARE REFORM, THE ONLY
TIME WE'VE SEEN A FEDERAL
ENTITLEMENT CUT.
WE CUT IT, DID EXACTLY WHAT
EVERY CONSERVATIVE SAYS THEY
WANT TO DO.
WE TOOK THE PROGRAM, WE
ELIMINATED THE FEDERAL
ENTITLEMENT.
WE BLOCK GRANTED THE STATE.
CUT IT BY 10% AND PUT TWO
REQUIREMENTS, WORK AND TIME
LIMITS.
WE NEEDED TO DO THAT WITH THE
REST OF THE MEANS TESTED
FEDERAL ENTITLEMENTS.
I'VE DONE IT, AND DID IT WITH A
BIPARTISAN SUPPORT IN THE HOUSE
AND SENATE, AND AFTER FIGHTING
TWO PRESIDENTIAL VETOES BY BILL
CLINTON, SO I HAD A DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENT WE HAD TO GET THIS
THROUGH.
NO RECORD OF ACCOMPLISHMENT.
I AGREE WITH THE FOLKS FROM THE
CONGRESS IN THIS RACE.
I HAVE A RECORD OF
ACCOMPLISHMENT OF BEING A
CONSERVATIVE ON EVERYTHING.
NATIONAL SECURITY, ON MORAL AND
CULTURAL ISSUES, ON THE
ECONOMY, AND TWICE WON A BLUE
STATE.
THE FIRST TIME I BEAT THE
AUTHOR OF HILLARY CARE.
I HAD BILL AND HILLARY IN MY
STATE, JAMES CARVILLE MANAGED
THE STATE AGAINST ME, I RAN ON
HEALTH SAVINGS ACCOUNTS,
PRIVATE SECTOR HEALTH CARE, AS
A CONSERVATIVE, PRO-LIFE,
PRO-FAMILY, AND I WON, AND IN
2000, I WAS THE ONLY SENATOR TO
WIN A STATE AS A CONSERVATIVE
THAT GEORGE BUSH LOST.
YOU WANT SOMEONE THAT CAN WIN
WISCONSIN, MINNESOTA, MICHIGAN,
PENNSYLVANIA, OHIO, WITH A
CONSERVATIVE MESSAGE, I'M YOUR
GUY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, I DON'T THINK WE
GOT THE INFRASTRUCTURE, BUT I
UNDERSTAND.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> I'LL BE HAPPY TO ANSWER THAT
IF YOU GIVE ME THE TIME.
MODERATOR: TO DO THE THINGS
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT, THAT
YOU'RE ALL TALKING ABOUT,
GETTING THINGS DONE IN
WASHINGTON, YOU HAVE TO WORK
WITH THE OTHER SIDE.
A QUESTION, WHO IN CONGRESS DO
YOU MOST ADMIRE ON THE
DEMOCRATIC SIDE?
I NEED ONE NAME FROM EACH OF
YOU.
LET'S START WITH GOVERNOR
JINDAL.
>> WE CAN WASTE OUR TIME.
THIS IS WHY PEOPLE ARE SO
FRUSTRATED WITH THE LAST DEBATE
WITH THESE KINDS OF SILLY
QUESTIONS.
WE'VE ONLY GOT A CERTAIN AMOUNT
OF TIME TO TALK ABOUT THE
ECONOMY.
LET ME USE MY TIME TO SAY THIS.
I WANT TO FIRE EVERYBODY IN
D.C.
TERM LIMITS, MAKE THEM LIVE
UNDER THE SAME RULES BY PASSING
THE REST OF IT.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE?
>> SINCE WE'RE NOT GOING TO
ANSWER THE QUESTION.
LET ME REMIND EVERYBODY,
TOMORROW IS VETERANS DAY.
HERE'S WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO
REMIND EVERYBODY.
THE VA HAS BEEN A DISASTER IN
LARGE PART BECAUSE THE PEOPLE
IN CONGRESS HAVE NEVER BOTHERED
TO FIX IT, AND THIS PRESIDENT
-- LET ME FINISH, PLEASE.
I'M GOING TO ASK YOU THIS, WHAT
WOULD HAPPEN IF THE CONGRESS
AND THE PRESIDENT HAD TO GET
THEIR HEALTH CARE FROM THE VA?
WE WOULD FIX THE PROBLEM AND WE
WOULD FIX CONGRESS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE?
>> I'LL CONTINUE IN THE PATTERN
AND JUST SAY --
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> AND JUST SAY THIS TO
EVERYBODY SINCE IT SEEMS TO BE
AN OPEN QUESTION.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> I'LL TELL YOU THE THING THAT
DISTURBS ME THE MOST WHAT'S
GOING ON WITH THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY IN WASHINGTON.
THEY'RE NOT STANDING BEHIND OUR
POLICE OFFICERS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
THEY'RE ALLOWING LAWLESSNESS TO
REIGN IN THIS COUNTRY.
I SPENT SEVEN YEARS OF MY LIFE
IN LAW ENFORCEMENT, 700,000
SHOULD NOTE TONIGHT.
WHEN PRESIDENT CHRISTIE IS IN
THE OVAL OFFICE, I'LL HAVE YOUR
BACK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANTORUM?
>> I'M GOING TO ANSWER TWO
QUESTIONS FOR THE PRICE OF ONE.
INFRASTRUCTURE QUESTION --
THE ANSWER IS, WE NEED TO GET
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT OUT OF
THE INFRASTRUCTURE BUSINESS,
OTHER THAN VITAL ECONOMIC
HIGHWAYS.
IT'S BEEN SAID THAT IF WE CUT
THE GAS TAX TO 3 TO 5 CENTS AND
SEND THE REST BACK TO THE
STATES AND TAKE CARE OF THE
FEDERAL INFRASTRUCTURE VITAL
FOR OUR ECONOMY, LET THE -- WE
DON'T NEED THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT AND THE ROAD
BUSINESS THAT IT IS TODAY.
NUMBER ONE.
YOU KNOW WHO I RESPECT IN THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY?
YOU KNOW WHY I RESPECT THEM?
BECAUSE THEY FIGHT!
THEY'RE NOT WILLING TO BACK
DOWN, AND THEY'RE WILLING TO
STAND UP AND FIGHT AND WIN.
I RESPECT THEM BECAUSE THEY ARE
WILLING TO TAKE IT TO US.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR
SANTORUM.
>> RONALD REAGAN DID WORK WITH
TIP O'NEILL.
COMING UP, ONE OF THE TOP
ISSUES FOR VOTERS, HOW MUCH
YOU'RE PAYING IN TAXES.
WE'RE LIVE FROM MILWAUKEE WITH
THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE.
SEE YOU RIGHT BACK HERE.
.
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
WE ARE LIVE FROM MILWAUKEE.
A TOP ISSUE ON THE CAMPAIGN
TRAIL, TAXES, AND HOW MUCH YOU
PAY.
I'VE GOT A QUESTION FOR ALL OF
YOU HERE.
WHEN LOOKING AT FEDERAL INCOME
TAX, STATE INCOME TAX AND LOCAL
TAX, SOME CASES COMBINED, SOME
AMERICANS ARE PAYING OVER 50%
OF THEIR PAYCHECK TO THE
GOVERNMENT.
WHAT IS THE HIGHEST PERCENTAGE,
ALL-IN, IN THE WAY OF TAXES
THAT ANY AMERICAN SHOULD HAVE
TO PAY, AND WHAT IS THE LOWEST?
I'D LIKE TO AGAIN HEAR FROM
EACH OF YOU, AND I WANT THOSE
TWO ALL-IN NUMBERS.
I'M GOING TO START WITH YOU,
SENATOR SANTORUM?
>> I TELL YOU, I HAVE A 20%
FLAT TAX THAT'S ON ALL INCOMES.
CAPITAL GAINS, CORPORATIONS,
INDIVIDUALS, 20%.
I THINK THAT'S A FAIR NUMBER.
ONE OUT OF FIVE, TO BE ABLE TO
HELP SUPPORT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT.
BY THE WAY, APPROXIMATE, IF YOU
TAKE OUT DEDUCTIONS,
APPROXIMATE HOW MUCH THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT HAS SPENT OF
GDP, WHICH IS ABOUT 18-19% OF
GDP.
IT ACTUALLY FITS WITH SHRINKING
THE SIZE OF GOVERNMENT DOWN TO
MORE LIKE POST WORLD WAR II
LEVELS.
I DON'T ALLOW FOR DEDUCTIBILITY
FOR STATE AND LOCAL TAXES WHICH
WILL REQUIRE THEM TO GO DOWN IN
ORDER TO BE TREATED FAIRLY.
SO THE ANSWER IS, 20% AND
PROBABLY 33% OVERALL.
MODERATOR: ALL-IN, OKAY,
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE?
>> YES, OUR TAX PLAN PUTS THE
HIGHEST RATE OF 28% FOR THOSE
DOING THE MOST AND MAKING THE
MOST IN THIS COUNTRY AND 8% ON
THE LOW END.
I AGREE WITH SENATOR SANTORUM,
WE GET RID OF ALL OF THE
DEDUCTIONS AND LOOPHOLES EXCEPT
FOR THE HOME MORTGAGE INTEREST
DEDUCTION AND THE CHARITABLE
CONTRIBUTION DEDUCTION, THAT
WILL PUT MORE PRESSURE ON
GOVERNORS AND ON LOCAL
OFFICIALS NOT TO KEEP RAISING
THOSE TAXES SAYING WELL, YOU
CAN DEDUCT THEM.
28 ON THE HIGH END, 8 ON THE
LOW END.
AMERICANS FOR TAX REFORM CAME
OUT WITH A REPORT AND SAID I'VE
VETOED MORE TAX INCREASES THAN
ANY GOVERNOR IN HISTORY.
I WILL DO EXACTLY THE SAME
THING AS PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
MODERATOR: BACK TO YOU,
GOVERNOR JINDAL.
>> THE TOP RATE IS 25%, 10%,
2%.
THE 2% IS MOST IMPORTANT.
I THINK EVERYBODY SHOULD PAY
SOMETHING.
EVERYBODY SHOULD HAVE SKIN IN
THE GAME.
WE SHOULD CREATE ONE GROUP OF
AMERICANS DEPENDENT ON AMERICA.
CHRIS SAID WE ALL AGREE HILLARY
CLINTON IS BAD.
WE AGREE WE NEED TO BEAT HER,
LET'S NOT PRETEND THAT
OUT-OF-CONTROL GOVERNMENT
SPENDING IS A DEMOCRATIC ISSUE.
JUST SENDING ANOTHER REPUBLICAN
TO D.C. IS NOT GOOD ENOUGH.
WE NEED TO CUT GOVERNMENT
SPENDING, AND NOT GOING TO DO
IT SENDING ANY REPUBLICAN.
I'M GLAD HE'S VETOES TAXES.
NEW JERSEY IS THE 50TH WORST
BUSINESS CLIMATE DUE TO THE
HIGH TAXES IN NEW JERSEY.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE.
>> IF WE GOT RID OF THE TAXES
ON OUR WORK, GOT RID OF TAXES
ON SAVINGS, INVESTMENTS,
CAPITAL GAINS AND INHERITANCE
AND MADE A ZERO TAX, WE'D PAY
AT POINT OF CONSUMPTION.
WHY SHOULD WE PUNISH PEOPLE FOR
PRODUCTIVITY?
AND THE FAIR TAX DOESN'T PUNISH
PEOPLE FOR DOING WELL AND
BUILDING THE ECONOMY.
THERE'S $31 TRILLION PARKED
OFFSHORE.
WHAT HAPPENS IF THAT MONEY
COMES BACK TO AMERICA?
YOU THINK IT GOOSED THE
ECONOMY?
I GUARANTEE YOU IT WOULD.
THAT'S WHY THE FAIR TAX IS THE
BEST SOLUTION WE HAVE FOR
ECONOMIC GROWTH IN THIS
COUNTRY.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE,
AMERICANS UNDER YOUR PLAN,
WOULD PAY A TAX ON EVERY SINGLE
THING THAT THEY PURCHASE.
GIVEN THE CONSUMER SPENDING,
ACCOUNTS FOR TWO-THIRDS OF GDP.
SOME ECONOMISTS WORRY YOUR TAX
PLAN WOULD DISCOURAGE SPENDING,
THERE BY SLOWING OUR ECONOMY.
HOW DO YOU RESPOND?
>> FIRST OF ALL, DO YOU KNOW AN
AMERICAN THAT WILL STOP
SPENDING?
I DON'T.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> SNOW.
THAT'S NOT GOING TO BE THE
PROBLEM.
LOOK, AMERICANS WILL GO TO THE
MARKETPLACE WITH MORE MONEY
THEY'VE HAD.
FOR THE FIRST TIME THEY'LL HAVE
THEIR WHOLE PAY CHECK.
WHEN YOU BUY SOMETHING MADE IN
AMERICA, 22% OF THE COST OF IT
IS THE EMBEDDED TAX THEY NEVER
KNEW THEY PAID.
WHY CHINA HAS BEATEN THE
DAYLIGHTS OUT OF US, THEY CAN
BUILD STUFF WE CAN'T BECAUSE
THEY'RE NOT TAXING IT.
WHEN THEY DON'T TAX CAPITAL AND
LABOR AND WE DO.
THEY BRING SOMETHING OVER HERE,
IT'S AUTOMATICALLY CHEAPER
WITHOUT THE REGULATORY
ENVIRONMENT BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT
EMBEDDING THE TAXES, WE ARE.
TAKE THE EMBEDDED TAXES OUT.
GIVE A PERSON HIS WHOLE
PAYCHECK BECAUSE EVERY AMERICAN
WOULD NO LONGER HAVE A PAYROLL
TAX TAKEN OUT.
THEY'D SEE THEIR REAL PAYCHECK
FOR THE FIRST TIME.
WHEN THEY SPEND THE MONEY,
THEY'LL HAVE IT.
AND ONLY PAY TAXES ON THE STUFF
THAT'S NEW.
SO A LOT OF AMERICANS BUY USED
STUFF.
AMERICANS ARE NOT GOING TO QUIT
SHOPPING.
BUYING, BUT IT WOULD BE NICE IF
AMERICANS COULD CONTROL HOW
MUCH THEY PAID IN TAX, RATHER
THAN HAVING THE GOVERNMENT
REACH INTO THEIR POCKETS AND
TAKE IT OUT BEFORE THEY HAD A
CHANCE TO SEE IT, MUCH LESS
SPEND IT.
AND THAT'S WHY THE FAIR TAX
MAKES A HECK OF A LOT MORE
SENSE THAN PUNISHING
PRODUCTIVITY AND REWARDING
IRRESPONSIBILITY.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, GOVERNOR
HUCKABEE.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR JINDAL, YOU
PROPOSED SOMETHING DIFFERENT,
ELIMINATING THE FEDERAL
CORPORATE INCOME TAX ENTIRELY.
WHY WOULD HAVE YOU WAGE EARNERS
AND INVESTORS PAY A INCOME TAX
AND NOT A CORPORATION.
>> WE KNOW BIG COMPANIES DON'T
PAY THE TAXES.
THEY HIRE LOBBYISTS AND
ACCOUNTANTS AND LAWYERS SO THE
SMALL BUSINESSES GET HIT.
I WANT TO GET RID OF THE
CORPORATE TAX, BRING JOBS AND
INVESTMENT BACK TO AMERICA.
MAKE THE CEOs PAY THE SAME
ARRAIGNMENTS AS EVERYBODY ELSE.
GET RID OF THE CORPORATE
WELFARE AS WELL.
AND MAKE EVERYBODY PAY
SOMETHING, EARNED SUCCESS IS SO
MUCH BETTER THAN UNEARNED
SUCCESS.
WE CAN TALK ALL NIGHT ABOUT TAX
PLANS, ENERGY PLANS, YOU WILL
FIND A LOT OF AGREEMENT AMONG
ALL REPUBLICANS, GET RID OF THE
DEATH TAX, MARRIAGE TAX, TAKE
AWAY POWER FROM THE IRS.
WHAT WE NEED TO BE TALKING
ABOUT IS THIS, THE LAST SEVEN
YEARS, WE'VE HAD MORE
GOVERNMENT SPENDING AND
DEPENDENCE, POVERTY HAS GONE
UP, INEQUALITY GONE UP.
TOP 10% SEEN MEDIAN INCOMES GO
UP.
WE HAVE MORE INEQUALITY THANKS
TO WHAT WE'VE SEEN, THE LARGEST
MOST EXPENSIVE EXPERIMENT IN
PROGRESSIVE GOVERNMENT.
WE CAN'T KEEP SPENDING MONEY WE
DON'T HAVE.
AND THE REALITY IS, THE LAST
COUPLE OF YEARS IT HASN'T
MATTERED WHETHER REPUBLICANS OR
DEMOCRATS WERE IN CONTROL.
WE KEEP STEALING FROM OUR
CHILDREN.
THAT IS IMMORAL, IT IS WRONG
AND WE'RE CREATING MORE
GOVERNMENT DEPENDENCE IF WE
WANT TO GROW THE ECONOMY, YOU
NEED A RATIONAL ENERGY PLAN,
AND YOU GOT TO REPEAL OBAMACARE
AND CUT TAXES.
NONE OF THAT WILL BE ENOUGH IF
WE'RE NOT SERIOUS ABOUT CUTTING
GOVERNMENT SPENDING.
WE CANNOT AFFORD TO ELECT A
BIG-GOVERNMENT REPUBLICAN.
WE NEED SOMEBODY.
THIS IS THE MOST IMPORTANT
ELECTION.
HILLARY CLINTON IS GIFT
WRAPPING THIS ELECTION TO US.
LET'S NOT WASTE THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO APPLY
CONSERVATIVE PRINCIPLES AND CUT
THE SIZE OF GOVERNMENT.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR JINDAL,
THANK YOU.
WE ARE NOT FINISHED YET.
MORE FROM THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE IN
MILWAUKEE NEXT.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
LIVE FROM MILWAUKEE'S HISTORIC
THEATER.
LET'S GET BACK TO THE QUESTIONS.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, BY KEEPING
INTEREST RATES SO LOW FOR SO
LONG, IS THE FED CREATING A NEW
FINANCIAL BUBBLE IN REAL ESTATE
OR STOCK PRICES THAT WILL BURST
AND CREATE PROBLEMS DOWN THE
ROAD, OR, HAS IT BEEN RIGHT TO
ERR ON THE SIDE OF TRYING TO
HELP THE RECOVERY THROUGH LOW
RATES?
>> NOW WHEN THEY CUT INTEREST
RATES DURING THE ECONOMIC
RECESSION AND CRISIS THAT WAS
THE RIGHT THING TO DO, BUT THEY
HAVE KEPT THOSE INTEREINCOME INE
INCOME INEQUALITY IN THIS
ADMINISTRATION THAN ANY PREVIOUS
ADMINISTRATION.
THE MIDDLE CLASS IS DOING WORSE
THAN IT HAS EVER DONE BEFORE AND
INVESTOR CLASS THE WEALTHY ARE
DOING BETTER BECAUSE OF CHEAP
MONEY FROM THE FED.
THIS IS THE WORST PART.
WE HAD 1 1/2% GDP GROWTH IN THE
FIRST QUARTER.
IF WE SLIDE BACK TO RECESSION
YOU CAN'T SLIDE INTEREST RATES
BELOW ZERO.
WHERE DO WE GO IF THE ECONOMY
SLIDES BACK INTO RECESSION?
WITH THIS GOVERNMENT CONTROLLED
ECONOMY BARACK OBAMA HAS WE'RE
MOVING RIGHT BEFORE IT.
THE FED SHOULD BE AUDITED AND
THE FED SHOULD STOP PLAYING
POLITICS WITH OUR MONEY SUPPLY.
THAT IS WHAT THEY HAVE DONE.
IT HAS BEEN THE WRONG THING TO
DO.
IT IS HURTING THE AMERICAN
ECONOMY.
[APPLAUSE]
AND LET ME, ADD ONE OTHER THING
ON THIS, BE VERY AWARE NOW.
WHAT HILLARY CLINTON IS TALKING
ABOUT DOING, IF SHE IS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES IS TO MAKE
SURE THAT THE GOVERNMENT GETS
EVEN MORE INVOLVED IN THE
ECONOMY, EVEN MORE INVOLVED IN
MAKING CHOICES FOR EVERYBODY.
YOU DO NOT WANT THAT TO HAPPEN.
YOU NEED SOMEONE WHO WILL STAND
UP ON THE STAGE AND PROSECUTE
THE CASE AGAINST HER AND
PROSECUTE IT STRONG.
THAT'S WHAT I'LL DO.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM, DO
YOU AGREE WITH GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE.
YOU ALSO SAID THAT THE FED
SHOULD BE AUDITED BUT MANY WORRY
THAT GIVEN THE CONGRESSIONAL
CHALLENGES THAT THEY FACE, BY
HAVING CONGRESSIONAL OVERSIGHT
OF THE FED, WHICH HAS BEEN
HISTORICALLY AN INDEPENDENT
BODY, YOU WOULD BE MAKING THE
FED MUCH MORE POLITICAL.
HOW WOULD YOU NAVIGATE THAT
RISK?
>> I AGREE WITH GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE.
I DON'T THINK YOU CAN MAKE IT
ANYMORE POLITICAL THAN IT'S
BEEN.
THEY ARE PROTECHING A PRESIDENT
THAT IS OVERTAXING AND
OVERREGULATING, SHUTTING DOWN
THIS ECONOMY AND THEY'RE KEEPING
IT UP LIKE ATLAS TRYING TO HOLD
UP THE EARTH BY THESE
RIDICULOUSLY LOW INTEREST RATES
AND IT'S HURTING AMERICAN
SENIORS WHO ARE SEEING NO
SOCIAL SECURITY INCREASES,
SEEING NO SAVINGS.
THEY'RE PUTTING THEIR MONEY
ASIDE.
THEY'RE GETTING NOTHING IN THEIR
DEPOSIT ACCOUNTS.
THIS IS HURTING PEOPLE WHO ACTED
RESPONSIBLY ALL IN FAVOR OF
THOSE WHO, YOU KNOW, ARE
SPECULATORS AND THOSE ON
WALL STREET.
IT IS NOT A GOOD DEAL FOR THE
VAST MAJORITY OF RESPONSIBLE
AMERICANS.
THE OTHER THING WE HAVE WITH THE
FED THEY HAVE BEEN GIVEN WAY TOO
MUCH AUTHORITY.
UNDER DODD-FRANK THEY HAVE BEEN
GIVEN THIS ENORMOUS NEW
AUTHORITY.
THEY HAVE BECOME ALMOST THE MOST
POWERFUL ENTITY IN WASHINGTON,
D.C. WE NEED TO REPEAL
DODD-FRANK, TAKE AWAY AUTHORITY
FROM THE FED AND PUT THEM UNDER
MORE SCRUTINY.
THAT IS ONLY PART OF THE
PROBLEM.
I UNDERSTAND FED IS INTERESTING
FOR BUSINESS CHANNEL BUT FOR
MOST AMERICANS THE MOST
IMPORTANT BUSINESS IS THE FAMILY
AND WE HAVEN'T REALLY TALKED
MUCH ABOUT THE IMPORTANCE OF THE
FAMILY TO THE ECONOMY AND LADIES
AND GENTLEMENS, AND EVERY SINGLE
BOOK FROM LEFT TO RIGHT WRITTEN
LAST COUPLE YEARS HAS SAID THE
BIGGEST PROBLEM IN AMERICA IS
HOLLOWING OUT OF THE AMERICA IS
BREAK DOWN OF FAMILY OF MIDDLE
AMERICA.
WE SHOULD TALK ABOUT THE ISSUE,
TO STRENGTHEN MARRIAGE AND
RETURN DADS INTO HOMES IN ALL
COMMUNITIES.
YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT THE
COMMUNITIES HURTING THE MOST,
THE ONES YOU SEE PROTEST IN,
THERE ARE NO DADS.
WE NEED TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT
IT.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE,
BOTH SENATOR SANTORUM AND
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE ARE CRITICAL
OF THE FEDERAL RESERVE.
ALSO MANY QUESTION WHETHER JANET
YELLEN IS THE RIGHT PERSON TO BE
RUNNING THE FED.
IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU
KEEP JANET YELLEN?
>> WELL, MY WIFE'S NAME IS
JANET.
AND WHEN YOU SAY JANET YELLING,
I'M VERY FAMILIAR WITH WHAT YOU
MEAN.
[APPLAUSE]
BUT, LOOK, I THINK THE FED'S IN
A BIG TROUBLE BECAUSE THEY
HAVEN'T ADDRESSED THE NUMBER ONE
ISSUE HURTING AMERICANS AND
THAT'S THE FACT THAT WAGES FOR
THE BOTTOM 90% OF THE ECONOMY
HAVE BEEN STAGNANT FOR 40 YEARS.
IN 25 YEARS AFTER WORLD WAR II
UP TO 1971 WAGES GREW BY 85% IN
THIS COUNTRY.
PEOPLE WERE MOVING UP IN THE
MIDDLE CLASS.
THERE WAS A MIDDLE CLASS.
THAT IS NOT HAPPENING ANYMORE
AND IN LARGE MEASURE THE FED HAS
MANIPULATED THE DOLLAR SO IT
DOESN'T HAVE A STANDARD.
TIE THE DOLLAR TO SOMETHING
FIXED.
IF IT WILL NOT BE GOLD MAKE IT A
COMMODITY BASKET.
HERE IS WHAT WE HAVE TO DO.
WE HAVE TO GET IT WHERE PEOPLE
WHO GO OUT THERE AND WORK GET
SOMETHING IN RETURN.
IF THE DOLLAR KEEPS FLUCTUATING,
AND THIS IS, AS CRAZY AS, IS THE
PRICE OF BREAD, WELL THE FACT
IS, PEOPLE CAN'T GET AHEAD.
MODERATOR: WOULD YOU CHANGE
LEADERSHIP AT THE FED?
>> ABSOLUTELY, ABSOLUTELY
BECAUSE WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS
MAKE SURE THEY TIE THE MONETARY
STANDARD TO SOMETHING THAT MAKES
SENSE RATHER THAN TO THEIR OWN
WHIMS.
BECAUSE WHO IS GETTING GUT
PUNCHED?
IT AIN'T THE PEOPLE ON
WALL STREET.
IT'S THE FOLKS ON MAIN STREET.
THEY'RE THE ONE WHOSE WAGES HAVE
BEEN STAGNANT FOR 40 YEARS AND
THE AVERAGE AMERICAN TODAY HAS A
TOTAL SAVINGS OF A THOUSAND
BUCKS.
ONE ROOT CANAL AND THEY'RE IN
TROUBLE.
AND IF THEIR CAR BREAKS DOWN,
THE SAME WEEK, THEY'RE OUT OF
BUSINESS.
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT.
GOVERNOR HUCKABEE, THANK YOU.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT.
SENATOR SANTORUM, BY THE WAY,
TODAY IS THE 240th BIRTHDAY
OF THE UNITED STATES MARINE
CORPS.
[APPLAUSE]
>> SEMPER FI.
MODERATOR: TOMORROW IS VETERANS
DAY.
WE HONOR AND RECOGNIZE ALL THOSE
WHO HAVE FOUGHT FOR AND SERVED
THIS GREAT NATION, SENATOR.
THE U.S. DEPARTMENT OF VETERANS
AFFAIRS MEANWHILE WHICH PROVIDES
PATIENT CARE AND FEDERAL
BENEFITS TO THOSE VETERANS AS
WELL AS THEIR FAMILIES IS BESET
BY SCANDAL.
WHAT NEW IDEAS DO YOU HAVE TO
FIX THE BROKEN VA HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM?
>> THAT IS VERY PERSONAL TO ME.
I GREW UP ON VA GROUNDS.
I LIVED IN APARTMENTS ON VA
GROUND MY ENTIRE CHILDHOOD.
BOTH MY MOM AND DAD AFTER
WORLD WAR II, MET AT A VA,
MARRIED AND THAT'S WHERE I
LIVED.
KITCHEN TABLE DISCUSSIONS WAS
PARTICULARLY WHEN I WAS GROWING
UP IN THE '60s AND '70s WAS
DECLINE OF THE VA.
WHEN THEY JOINED IN THE EARLY
'50s WAS THE TOP, THE BEST AND
BRIGHTEST COMING IN AFTER THE
WAR.
WE BELIEVED IN THE CAUSE THAT WE
FOUGHT AND WE INVESTED IN OUR
HOSPITALS TO MAKE SURE OUR
VETERANS WHO LEFT WORLD WAR II
WERE TAKEN CARE OF.
BUT AFTER VIETNAM AND DURING
VIETNAM THAT BEGAN TO CHANGE,
AND IT REALLY HASN'T RECOVERED
SINCE.
THE BOTTOM LINE THE VA IS
ANTIQUATED.
THERE IS NO NEED FOR A VA HEALTH
CARE SYSTEM AS IT EXISTED AFTER
WORLD -- WHY?
BECAUSE WE HAVE THE BEST PRIVATE
HEALTH CARE SYSTEM IN THE WORLD.
WE NEEDED IT IN 1950S, HOSPITALS
WERE NOT PARTICULARLY ADVANCED
SO WE BUILT THE BEST.
WE DIDN'T MAINTAIN THE BEST.
GOVERNMENT DIDN'T KEEP ITS
PROMISES TO ITS VETERANS.
WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS TWO
THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, TO ALLOW VETERANS TO
GO TO PRIVATE SECTOR HOSPITALS
FOR ROUTINE AND ORDINARY CARE TO
GET THE BEST CARE IN THEIR
COMMUNITY POSSIBLE.
[APPLAUSE]
AND THERE IS A PLACE FOR THE
VETERANS ADMINISTRATION.
THERE ARE INJURIES AND THINGS
LIKE PTSD OR PROSTHETICS,
UNIQUELY PROBLEMS WITHIN THE
VETERANS COMMUNITY WHERE WE CAN
DEVELOP CENTERS OF EXCELLENCE
WITHIN THE, AND REPLACE THE VA
WITH A GROUP OF CENTERS OF
EXCELLENCE THAT CAN HELP OUR
FOLKS WHO COME BACK.
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM,
THANK YOU.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: I HAVE A QUESTION FOR
ALL OF YOU.
AMERICA'S CONNECTION TO THE
MILITARY HAS BEEN INCREASINGLY
FADING.
AS A SOCIETY HOW DO WE RESTORE
THAT SENSE OF DUTY, THAT SENSE
OF PRIDE THAT WAS THE HALLMARK
OF THE GREATEST GENERATION?
AGAIN I WOULD LIKE TO ASK EACH
OF YOU, 30 SECONDS EACH,
BEGINNING WITH GOVERNOR JINDAL.
>> A COUPLE OF THINGS.
FIRST I WANT TO ECHO WHAT OTHERS
SAID AND THANK THE VETERANS THAT
RUN TOWARDS DANGER, NOT AWAY
FROM IT, SO WE LIVE IN THE
GREATEST COUNTRY IN THE HISTORY
OF THE WORLD.
EVERY VETERAN SHOULD GET CAR
CARD AND GET THE HEALTH CARE
WHEREVER THEY WANT IN THE
PRIVATE SECTOR OR PUBLIC SECTOR.
I THINK WE NEED TO FIRE SOME OF
THESE VA BUREAUCRATS.
SOMEONE SHOULD GO TO JAIL OVER
THESE SCANDALS AND IT IS CRIME
THAT HAS NOT HAPPENED.
[APPLAUSE]
WHEN IT COMES TO UNITING THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE ONE OF THE
THINGS WE'VE DONE TO HONOR OUR
VETERANS IN LOUISIANA, WE HAVE
GIVEN THOUSANDS, I HAND
DELIVERED THESE, MEDALS TO
VETERANS TO THANK THEM FOR THEIR
SERVICE.
I GIVE YOU ONE QUICK EXAMPLE.
MY TIME IS UP.
VIETNAM WAR VETERANS WITH TEARS
IN THEIR EYES NOBODY EVERY
THANKED THEM BEFORE.
WORLD WAR II VETERANS, NEVER
HEARD OF STORIES OF THEIR
PARENTS HEROIC SACK CRIES.
WHATEVER CONFLICT, WHENEVER THEY
SERVED TEACH OUR CHILDREN THEY
LIVE IN THE GREATEST COUNTRY IN
THE HISTORY OF THE WORLD.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO DOESN'T
BELIEVE IN AMERICAN
EXCEPTIONALISM.
WE STILL DO AND BECAUSE OF THOSE
MEN AND WOMEN IN UNIFORM.
WE SHOULD THANK THEM EVERY DAY,
NOT JUST VETERANS DAY.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE.
>> WELL I THINK THANKING OUR
VETERANS IS A WONDERFUL THING TO
DO BUT THEY WOULD SURE
APPRECIATE A BETTER PAYCHECK.
THEY WOULD APPRECIATE THE FACT
WE KEPT OUR PROMISES TO THEM.
THE MEN AND WOMEN IN UNIFORM PUT
ON UNIFORM OF OUR NATION, WENT
HALFWAY AROUND THE WORLD.
THEY FACED DANGERS ON OUR
BEHALF.
AND WE PROMISED THEM IF THEY DID
THAT, WHEN THEY CAME HOME, WE
WOULD TAKE CARE OF THEIR MEDICAL
CARE, WE WOULD MAKE IT POSSIBLE
FOR THEIR KIDS TO GO TO COLLEGE
AND THEY'D BE ABLE TO BUY INTO A
HOME.
THEY KEPT THEIR PROMISES TO US.
WE HAVE NOT KEPT THEIR PROMISES
TO THEM AND TODAY LESS THAN 1%
OF AMERICANS BO TO THE MILITARY
FOR SERVICE.
WE'RE FIGHTING WARS WITH OTHER
PEOPLE'S KIDS IN LARGE MEASURE.
BECAUSE WE HAVE NOT TAKEN
SERIOUSLY THE MORAL, NOT THE
MONETARY, THE MORAL OBLIGATION
TO TAKE CARE OF THE VETERANS AND
TO KEEP AMERICA'S PROMISE TO THE
ONES WHO KEPT THEIR PROMISE TO
AMERICA.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> THE WAY TO RECONNECT
AMERICANS TO THE MEN AND WOMEN
IN UNIFORM IS TO FIRST AND
FOREMOST GIVE THEM A
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF WHO RESPECTS
MILITARY AND RESPECTS EVERYONE
WHO WEAR AS UNIFORM.
[APPLAUSE]
STARTS AT THE TOP.
SECRETARY CLINTON SAYS, THERE IS
NO CRISIS AT THE VA, THAT SENDS
A LONG AND HARD MESSAGE TO OUR
VETERANS THAT SHE DOESN'T GET IT
AND SHE DOESN'T RESPECT THEIR
SERVICE.
WHEN THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES DOESN'T BACK UP LAW
ENFORCEMENT OFFICERS IN UNIFORM,
HE LOSES THE MORAL AUTHORITY TO
LEAD ANY MAN OR WOMAN WHO IS IN
UNIFORM.
I SPENT SEVEN YEARS IN LAW
ENFORCEMENT.
I RESPECT THESE FOLKS.
I WILL DO SO AS
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF OF THE
MILITARY.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM.
>> SHOULD COME AS NO SURPRISE TO
CHRIS OR ANYBODY ELSE THAT
BARACK OBAMA HASN'T STOOD BEHIND
OUR MEN AND WOMEN IN UNIFORM
HERE AT HOME BECAUSE HE HASN'T
STOOD BEHIND THEM OVERSEAS.
THE RULES OF ENGAGEMENT WE
ALLOWED OUR SOLDIERS TO GO FIGHT
AGAINST PUT THEM IN HARM'S WAY
FOR POLITICAL PURPOSES.
THIS HAS BEEN THE MOST
POLITICIZED WARS WE'VE EVER SEEN
UNDER THIS ADMINISTRATION.
HE GETS IN AND GETS OUT BASED ON
WHAT POLLS ARE SAYING, WHAT
PRESSURE HE GETTING FROM GROUPS.
TALK ABOUT COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF,
WE NEED A COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF WHO
HAS A VISION AND PLAN HOW WE
WILL EXECUTE THE NATIONAL
SECURITY OF OUR COUNTRY.
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF IS NOT ENTRY
LEVEL POSITION.
EXPERIENCE MATTERS THAT IS WHY I
WOULD ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT AS A
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF BECAUSE I
HAVE THE EXPERIENCE AGAINST THE
ENEMY THAT WE CONFRONT TO DO THE
JOB.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: CANDIDATES, IT IS
TIME FOR CLOSING STATEMENTS.
30 SECONDS.
GOVERNOR JINDAL, START WITH YOU.
>> I HAVE SPENT A LOT OF TIME
TONIGHT TALKING ABOUT THE NEED
TO CUT THE SIZE OF GOVERNMENT.
THE REASON I'M DOING THAT NOT
JUST ABOUT BALANCING THE BUDGET
WITH A BUNCH OF NUMBERS.
IT IS BECAUSE I BELIEVE IN THE
AMERICAN DREAM.
I THINK PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS DONE
A LOT OF DAMAGE TO OUR COUNTRY.
I THINK ONE OF THE WORST THINGS
HE HAS DONE TO TRY TO CHANGE THE
IDEA OF AMERICA TO BE ONE OF
DEPEP DENSE.
A LOT OF POLITICIANS TALK ABOUT
GOVERNMENT SPENDING.
I'M ONLY ONE THAT ACTUALLY HAS
DONE IT RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
THE REST OF THEM IT IS A LOT OF
HOT AIR.
IF YOU WANT YOUR PAYCHECKS GOING
UP, GOOD PAYING JOBS, WANT THE
GOVERNMENT OUT OF YOUR LIVES WE
HAVE TO CUT THE SIZE OF
GOVERNMENT.
NOT ENOUGH TO ELECT ANY
REPUBLICAN.
WE'VE SEEN THAT WE HAVE TO ELECT
A REPUBLICAN THAT WILL TAKE ON
ESTABLISHMENT IN BOTH PARTIES.
I'M ASKING FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
THANK YOU.
MODERATOR: SENATOR SANTORUM.
>> ANNOUNCED FROM FACTORY FLOOR
IN WESTERN PENNSYLVANIA.
THIS CAMPAIGN HAS BEEN ABOUT TWO
WORDS FOR ME, WORKING FAMILIES.
WORKING, GETTING PEOPLE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO SEE THOSE WAGES
RISE.
TO BE ON THE SIDE OF THE
AMERICAN WORKER SO THEY CAN GET
GOOD-PAYING JOBS.
THAT MEANS WE HAVE TO START
MAKING THINGS IN AMERICA BEN.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO WILL NOT
JUST PUT POLICIES IN PLACE BUT
WILL STAND UP WITH THE BULLY
PULPIT TALK ABOUT THE DIGNITY OF
BEING A WELDER, THE DIGNITY OF
BEING A CARPENTER, ABOUT GOING
TO WORK AND EARNING SUCCESS AND
IMPORTANCE OF FAMILIES.
THE IMPORTANCE OF FAMILIES AND
FATHERS AND MOTHERS RAISING
THEIR CHILDREN AND COMMITTING TO
THAT SO THEY CAN GIVE CHILDREN
AND OUR COUNTRY BEST OPPORTUNITY
FOR SUCCESS.
WORKING FAMILIES IS THE KEY FOR
TO US WIN THIS ELECTION.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR HUCKABEE.
>> IN MANY WAYS I HAVE I FEEL
LIKE I'M THE LUCKIEST GUY ON
EARTH, I REALLY DO.
IT'S A LONG WAY FROM A LITTLE
BRICK RENT HOUSE ON SECOND
STREET IN HOPE, ARKANSAS, TO
THIS STAGE WHERE I'M RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
IT IS NOT ABOUT ME, NOT ABOUT
THESE GUYS.
OUGHT TO BE ABOUT YOU.
AND I HAVE NEVER BEEN THE
FAVORITE OF THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE
THE MOST MONEY.
BUT I WANT TO BE THE FAVORITE OF
PEOPLE WHO STILL WANT TO BELIEVE
THE AMERICAN DREAM CAN WORK FOR
THEM.
TODAY IN OUR OFFICE I GOT A
LETTER FROM A THIRD-GRADER IN
NORTH DAKOTA.
HER NAME IS REESE.
SHE SENT $6 FROM HER ALLOWANCE.
SAID I WANT TO HELP YOU BE
PRESIDENT.
YOU KNOW I'M GOING TO KEEP
STANDING ON THIS STAGE TO KEEP
FIGHTING FOR ONE REASON.
BECAUSE SOMEWHERE OUT THERE IN
NORTH DAKOTA AND ALL OVER
AMERICA THERE ARE KIDS LIKE
REESE WHO NEED A PRESIDENT WHO
WILL NEVER FORGET WHERE THEY
CAME PROBLEM.
I PROMISE I WON'T.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> I WANT TO HE WILL IT AMERICAN
PEOPLE THAT WATCH TONIGHT THE
TRUTH.
I SAW THE MOST DESGRACEFUL I'VE
SEEN THIS ENTIRE CAMPAIGN A FEW
WEEKS AGO.
HILLARY CLINTON WAS ASKED, THE
ENEMY SHE IS MOST PROUD OF AND
SHE SAID REPUBLICANS.
IN A WORLD WHERE WE HAVE
AL QAEDA AND ISIS, THE MULLAHS
IN IRAN AND VLADMIR PUTIN, THE
WOMAN WHO ASKS TO ONE AND
REPRESENT ALL OF UNITED STATES
SAYS THAT HER GREATEST ENEMIES
ARE PEOPLE LIKE YOU IN THIS
AUDIENCE AND US HERE.
I WILL TELL YOU ONE THING AND
WRITE THIS DOWN.
WHEN YOU ELECT ME PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES, I WILL GO GO
TO WASHINGTON NOT ONLY TO FIGHT
FIGHTS THAT NEED FIGHTING NOT
ONLY SAY WHAT I MEAN AND MEAN
WHAT I SAY BUT TO BRING THIS
ENTIRE COUNTRY TOGETHER FOR
BETTER FUTURE FOR OUR CHILDREN
AND GRANDCHILDREN.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, GENTLEMEN.
THAT DOES IT, EVERYONE FOR THE
FIRST DEBATE HERE IN MILWAUKEE.
JUST ABOUT ONE HOUR FROM NOW, AT
9:00 P.M. EASTERN, EIGHT MORE
CANDIDATES WILL BE TAKING TO THE
STAGE.
RIGHT NOW, SPECIAL COVERAGE OF
THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE, LIVE FROM MILWAUKEE
CONTINUES RIGHT HERE ON FOX
BUSINESS.
[APPLAUSE]