>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
GOOD EVENING, EVERYONE.
WHAT A NIGHT HERE IN THE
NATION'S FIRST PRESIDENTIAL
PRIMARY STATE, ONE TOWN HALL
FORUM, THE TWO REMAINING
DEMOCRATS, AND THE QUESTION
VOTERS WANT ANSWERED BEFORE
MAKING THEIR CHOICE.
>>> TONIGHT, THE PRESIDENTIAL
RACE IS MORE COMPETITIVE THAN
EVER, AND THE DEMOCRATS ARE
HERE, IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, TO FACE
THE VOTERS AGAIN.
>> I AM SO THRILLED THAT I'M
COMING TO NEW HAMPSHIRE AFTER
WINNING IOWA!
>> I BELIEVE WE HAVE A PATH
TOWARD VICTORY.
>> IT'S DOWN TO HILLARY CLINTON
AND BERNIE SANDERS.
JUST TWO CANDIDATES ON ONE
STAGE, TAKING QUESTIONS FROM THE
PEOPLE OF THIS BATTLEGROUND
STATE, ON ISSUES THAT HIT CLOSE
TO HOME.
>> I AM EXCITED ABOUT REALLY
GETTING INTO THE DEBATE WITH
SENATOR SANDERS!
>> THEIR DIFFERENCES ARE REAL
AND THE STAKES ARE SOARING, JUST
DAYS BEFORE THE SECOND CRUCIAL
CONTEST OF 2016.
>> MILLIONS OF PEOPLE COME
TOGETHER AND SAY LOUDLY AND
CLEARLY, ENOUGH IS ENOUGH!
>> THIS IS A CNN DEMOCRATIC TOWN
HALL EVENT.
A CHANCE FOR VOTERS TO DRIVE THE
DEBATE WITH DECISION DAY AROUND
THE CORNER.
>> DEMOCRACY IS NOT A SPECTATOR
SPORT.
>> NEW HAMPSHIRE, THE EYES OF
THE WORLD ARE GOING TO BE ON YOU
AGAIN.
>> NEW HAMPSHIRE IS CHOOSING.
THE DEMOCRATS ARE IN THE
SPOTLIGHT.
AND THEY'RE MAKING THEIR PITCHES
TO VOTERS RIGHT NOW.
>>> AND GOOD EVENING FROM THE
HISTORIC DERRY OPERAHOUSE IN
DOWNTOWN DERRY, NEW HAMPSHIRE.
WELCOME.
WE ARE HERE TONIGHT WITH JUST
SIX DAYS TO GO UNTIL PRIMARY
DAY.
JUST SIX DAYS LEFT TO DECIDE,
YET MANY VOTERS REMAIN
UNDECIDED.
SO TONIGHT, SECRETARY CLINTON
AND SENATOR SANDERS ARE HERE
WITH THE PEOPLE OF THE STATE AND
THE COUNTRY FOR A CONVERSATION.
I WANT TO WELCOME OUR VIEWERS IN
THE UNITED STATES, IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, AROUND THE WORLD.
WE'RE BEING SEEN ON CNN, CNN IN
ESPANOL, CNN INTERNATIONAL.
I ALSO WANT TO EXTEND A WARM
WELCOME FOR OUR SERVICE MEN AND
WOMEN WHO ARE WATCHING ON THE
AMERICAN FORCES NETWORK.
AND TO THOSE WHO ARE LISTENING
ON THE WESTWOOD ONE RADIO
NETWORK AND ON CNN CHANNEL 116
ON SIRIUS XM.
IN THE AUDIENCE, HERE IN DERRY,
NEW HAMPSHIRE, PEOPLE WHO TELL
US THEY WILL BE PARTICIPATING IN
TUESDAY'S DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY,
WHICH MEANS REGISTERED DEMOCRATS
OR INDEPENDENTS.
SOME HAVE ALREADY MADE UP THEIR
MINDS.
OTHERS STILL TRYING TO DECIDE
WHOM TO VOTE FOR.
THE CLOCK IS TICKING, GUYS.
WE ASKED AUDIENCE MEMBERS TO
COME UP WITH THEIR OWN
QUESTIONS, WHICH WE'VE REVIEWED
TO MAKE SURE THEY DON'T OVERLAP.
I'LL ASK SOME QUESTIONS, AS
WELL.
BUT TONIGHT IS REALLY ABOUT THE
VOTERS GETTING TO KNOW THE
CANDIDATES.
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
UP FIRST TONIGHT, VERMONT
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HAVE A SEAT.
WELCOME.
>> IT'S GOOD TO BE WITH YOU.
>> SO, YOU HAVE HAD, OBVIOUSLY,
QUITE A FEW DAYS -- IT'S BEEN
QUITE A WHIRLWIND FOR YOU.
I UNDERSTAND YOUR CAMPAIGN SAYS
YOU'VE RAISED AT LEAST $3
MILLION SINCE IOWA.
I'M WONDERING, OUT THERE, IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE TODAY, WHAT ARE YOU
FEELING?
WHAT SORT OF MOMENTUM ARE YOU
FEELING THE BERN?
>> WE'RE FEELING GREAT.
YES, I AM, NOW THAT YOU ASK.
WE'RE FEELING REALLY GREAT.
I THINK THE MESSAGE THAT WE ARE
BRINGING FORTH IS RESONATING
WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
AND YOU TALKED ABOUT MONEY.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT HAS
HAPPENED WITH OUR CAMPAIGN,
ANDERSON, WHICH HAS BLOWN ME
AWAY, IT REALLY HAS, IS THAT WE
HAVE RECEIVED 3.5 MILLION
INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS, THAT
IS MORE THAN ANY CANDIDATE IN
THE HISTORY OF THE UNITED
STATES, AND YOU KNOW WHAT THE
AVERAGE CONTRIBUTION IS?
>> $27.
>> HEY, YOU HEARD!
AND IN A DAY OF SUPER PACs,
WHERE PEOPLE ARE RAISING HUGE
AMOUNTS OF MONEY FROM WALL
STREET AND THE DRUG COMPANIES,
THE FACT THAT MILLIONS OF
INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS FROM
WORKING PEOPLE AND THE MIDDLE
CLASS WHO WANT US TO GO FORWARD,
AND TO TRANSFORM THIS COUNTRY IN
VERY SIGNIFICANT WAYS IS VERY
MOVING TO ME.
>> I'M JUST GOING TO ASK A
COUPLE OF QUESTIONS, AND THEN
WE'LL REALLY GET IT OVER TO THE
AUDIENCE.
THERE IS AN EXPECTATIONS GAME
BEING PLAYED.
AND WE'VE BEEN SEEING THIS FROM
BOTH CAMPAIGNS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
HILLARY CLINTON'S CAMPAIGN KEEPS
POINTING TO THE FACT THAT YOU'RE
FROM A NEIGHBORING STATE, THAT
YOU'RE WAY UP IN THE POLLS.
ARE YOU STILL AN UNDERDOG?
>> OF COURSE WE'RE AN UNDERDOG.
WE ARE TAKING ON THE MOST
POWERFUL POLITICAL ORGANIZATION
IN THE COUNTRY.
AND THAT'S, YOU KNOW, THE
CLINTON ORGANIZATION.
SECRETARY CLINTON, OBVIOUSLY,
RAN HERE IN 2008 AND SHE WON.
HER HUSBAND RAN HERE SEVERAL
TIMES BEFORE THAT.
SO THIS IS HER FOURTH CAMPAIGN
IN THAT FAMILY HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
IT IS CLEAR THAT MANY PEOPLE IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE DO KNOW ME,
BECAUSE I COME FROM A
NEIGHBORING STATE.
AND I THINK WE HAVE SUPPORT,
BECAUSE PEOPLE OVER THE YEARS
HAVE SEEN THE WORK THAT I AM
DOING IN STANDING UP FOR WORKING
FAMILIES AND THE MIDDLE CLASS.
BUT IN GENERAL, WE STARTED THIS
CAMPAIGN NATIONALLY, AS YOU WELL
KNOW, 40, 50 POINTS BEHIND
SECRETARY CLINTON.
WE HAD NO MONEY, WE HAD NO
ORGANIZATION, AND WE HAD
RELATIVELY LITTLE NAME
RECOGNITION.
I THINK IT'S FAIR TO SAY, WE
HAVE COME A PRETTY LONG WAY IN
THE LAST NINE MONTHS.
>> YOU ARE -- I MEAN, ACCORDING
TO THE LATEST CNN POLL, YOU'RE
UP SOME 23 POINTS, SOME PEOPLE
SAY OR BELIEVE HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
OBVIOUSLY, WE KNOW POLLS CAN GET
IT WRONG.
HOW DO YOU NOT UNDERPERFORM
HERE?
BECAUSE THERE IS AN
EXPECTATION --
>> BECAUSE THAT'S THE MEDIA
GAME!
THAT'S WHAT MEDIA TALKS ABOUT.
WHO CARES?
THE POINT IS, UNDERPERFORM --
THE POINT IS, WE'RE GOING TO
WORK AS HARD AS WE CAN TO WIN.
AND AFTER WE DO HOPEFULLY WELL
HERE, WE'RE GOING TO GO ON TO
NEVADA AND THEN SOUTH CAROLINA
AND DO AS WELL AS WE CAN ALL
OVER THIS COUNTRY.
I GOT TO SAY, WITH ALL DUE
RESPECT, THAT'S MEDIA STUFF.
OVER, YOU KNOW, I THINK SOME OF
THESE POLLS --
>> YOU DON'T LOOK AT POLLS, YOUR
CAMPAIGN?
>> SURE WE DO, BUT SOME OF THESE
POLLS ARE OFF THE CHARTS.
I THINK THIS IS GOING TO BE A
VERY CLOSE ELECTION HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
>> THERE'S BEEN SOME BACK AND
FORTH ON THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL
TODAY ABOUT, IS HILLARY CLINTON
A PROGRESSIVE?
WE'RE GOING TO GET TO THAT LATER
ON, BECAUSE WE'VE GOT SOME
QUESTIONS FROM THE AUDIENCE
ABOUT THAT AND SOME OTHER
QUESTIONS.
BUT SENATOR BARBARA BOXER, A
SUPPORTER OF CLINTON, CAME BACK,
FIRED BACK BASICALLY AT YOUR
CAMPAIGN TODAY, AT YOU, SAYING,
OF COURSE HILLARY CLINTON IS A
PROGRESSIVE, AND ASKED, YOU
KNOW, IS -- THAT BERNIE SANDERS
IS A DEMOCRAT ON SOME DAYS.
YOU HAD SAID THAT HILLARY
CLINTON IS A PROGRESSIVE ON SOME
DAYS.
IS THAT FAIR?
BECAUSE THERE ARE SOME DEMOCRATS
WHO -- I MEAN, IN YOUR HEART,
ARE YOU A DEMOCRAT?
>> SURE.
I HAVE MADE A DECISION TO RUN
FOR THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINATION TO
BE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
I WAS, FOR 16 YEARS, IN THE
HOUSE DEMOCRATIC CAUCUS, FOR 9
YEARS IN THE SENATE DEMOCRATIC
CAUCUS.
RIGHT NOW, I AM THE RANKING
MEMBER OF THE BUDGET COMMITTEE,
APPOINTED BY THE DEMOCRATIC
LEADERSHIP AND MEMBERSHIP.
A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO, I WAS
VERY PROUDLY THE CHAIRMAN OF THE
SENATE VETERANS COMMITTEE.
SO, OF COURSE I AM A DEMOCRAT.
AND RUNNING FOR THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINATION.
IN TERMS OF SECRETARY CLINTON,
AND I KNOW THE MEDIA IS KIND OF
MAKING A BIG DEAL ABOUT THIS,
ALL THAT I SAID, WHICH IS SIMPLY
TRUE, IS, I THINK IT WAS IN
NOVEMBER IN OHIO, YOU MAY RECALL
THIS --
>> YES.
>> I DON'T KNOW THE CONTEXT OF
IT, BUT SECRETARY CLINTON SAID,
SOME PEOPLE CALL ME A -- I'M
PARAPHRASING.
SOME PEOPLE CALL ME A MODERATE,
AND I PROUDLY, YOU KNOW, SAY
THAT I AM A MODERATE.
THAT'S WHAT SHE SAID.
SO WHAT ALL I SAID IS, YOU CAN'T
SAY YOU'RE A MODERATE ON ONE DAY
AND BE A PROGRESSIVE ON ANOTHER
DAY.
SOME OF MY BEST FRIENDS ARE
MODERATES.
I LOVE MODERATES, BUT YOU CAN
BN
BNTN'T BE A MODERATE AND A
PROGRESSIVE.
THEY ARE DIFFERENT.
>> WE'LL TALK MORE ABOUT THAT,
BUT I WANT TO GO TO OUR FIRST
GUEST.
CHRIS SAYS HE'S LEANING TOWARDS
SUPPORTING YOU, BUT HE'S GOT
SOME QUESTIONS ABOUT YOUR TAX
POLICIES.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THE FIRST
THING I HEAR ABOUT YOU IS THAT
YOU'RE GOING TO RAISE TAXES ON
THE MIDDLE CLASS.
I SUPPORT MY FAMILY ON A SALARY
OF $41,000 A YEAR.
I'M WONDERING IF YOU RAISE MY
TAXES, HOW DOES THAT HELP ME?
>> CAN I STAND UP?
>> YOU CAN DO WHATEVER YOU WANT.
>> OKAY.
CHRIS, THANKS VERY MUCH FOR THAT
GOOD QUESTION.
THIS IS WHAT WE ARE GOING TO DO.
THE UNITED STATES IS THE ONLY
MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH THAT
DOESN'T GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO
ALL PEOPLE AND WE END UP
SPENDING FAR, FAR MORE PER
CAPITA ON HEALTH CARE, AS DO THE
PEOPLE OF ANY OTHER COUNTRY,
CANADA, UK, FRANCE, WHATEVER.
WHAT WE ARE GOING TO FIGHT FOR
IS A MEDICARE FOR ALL
SINGLE-PAYER PROGRAM.
WHICH WOULD PROVIDE
COMPREHENSIVE HEALTH CARE TO
YOUR FAMILY AND EVERY FAMILY IN
AMERICA.
SO, LET ME TELL YOU WHAT WE DO.
WE RAISE YOUR TAXES IF YOU'RE
SOMEWHERE IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
ECONOMY, ABOUT 500 BUCKS, BUT
YOU KNOW WHAT WE'RE GOING TO DO?
FOR HEALTH CARE, WE'RE GOING TO
REDUCE YOUR HEALTH CARE COSTS BY
$5,000.
SO YOU'RE GOING TO PAY A LITTLE
BIT MORE IN TAXES, BUT YOU'RE NO
LONGER GOING TO HAVE TO PAY
PRIVATE HEALTH INSURANCE
PREMIUMS.
NOW, I'VE BEEN CRITICIZED FOR
THIS.
BUT I BELIEVE THAT HEALTH CARE
IS A RIGHT OF ALL PEOPLE, THAT
WE SHOULD NOT HAVE THESE
DEDUCTIBLES AND CO-PAYMENTS.
WE SHOULD NOT BE PAYING THE
HIGHEST PRICES IN THE WORLD FOR
PRESCRIPTION DRUGS, AND OUR
MEDICARE-FOR-ALL PROGRAM WILL
GUARANTEE COMPREHENSIVE CARE TO
ALL PEOPLE AND SAVE MIDDLE CLASS
FAMILIES SOME THOUSANDS OF
DOLLARS A YEAR.
>> CHRIS, LET ME JUST ASK YOU,
DOES THAT MATH WORK FOR YOU?
>> I MEAN, IF IT SAVES ME ON
HEALTH INSURANCE PREMIUMS, I
WILL GLADLY PAY MORE TAXES.
>> SEE, AND CHRIS, WHAT HAPPENS
IN POLITICS -- I DON'T WANT TO
SHOCK ANYBODY IN THE OFFICE --
SOMETIMES PEOPLE DISTORT THINGS.
I'VE HAD 30-SECOND ADS RUN
AGAINST ME YEARS AGO -- BERNIE
IS GOING TO RAISE YOUR TAXES!
BUT THEY FORGET TO SAY, WE'RE
GOING TO DO AWAY WITH YOUR
PRIVATE INSURANCE PREMIUMS.
BOTTOM LINE HERE IS, WE SPEND
ALMOST THREE TIMES MORE PER
PERSON THAN THE BRITISH, 50%
MORE THAN THE FRENCH.
WE CAN SAVE SUBSTANTIAL SUMS OF
MONEY AND MY MEDICARE FOR ALL
SYSTEM IS FUNDED IN A VERY
PROGRESSIVE WAY.
YES, YOU'LL PAY A LITTLE BIT
MORE, BUT YOUR HEALTH PREMIUMS
WILL DISAPPEAR.
>> THAT'S ASSUMING YOU CAN GET
THAT THROUGH, THOUGH.
>> WELL, THAT'S -- YOU KNOW,
THAT'S TRUE.
BUT ALL OF WHAT I AM TRYING TO
DO ASSUMES SOMETHING.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT MAKING PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION FREE, AND DOING THAT,
AND PAYING FOR THROUGH A TAX ON
WALL STREET'S SPECULATION, WHEN
I TALK ABOUT REBUILDING OUR
CRUMBLING INFRASTRUCTURE, WHICH,
AS YOU KNOW, IS IN DISREPAIR ALL
OVER THIS COUNTRY, AND TALK
ABOUT DOING AWAY WITH HUGE
LOOPHOLES THAT MAJOR
CORPORATIONS NOW ENJOY, SO THAT
IN A GIVEN YEAR, YOU HAVE THESE
LARGE CORPORATIONS MAKING
BILLIONS, NOT PAYING A NICKEL
THE TAXES, BECAUSE THEY'RE
PUTTING THEIR MONEY IN THE
CAYMAN ISLANDS.
NOW, HOW DO WE GET THESE THINGS
THROUGH?
WHAT THIS CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT IS
NOT JUST ELECTING A PRESIDENT,
IT IS CREATING A POLITICAL
REVOLUTION, WHERE MILLIONS OF
PEOPLE, MANY OF WHOM HAVE NOT
BEEN INVOLVED IN THE POLITICAL
PROCESS, STAND UP AND DEMAND A
GOVERNMENT WHICH REPRESENTS ALL
OF US, NOT JUST WEALTHY CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTORS.
THAT'S HOW WE MAKE CHANGE.
>> LET ME ASK YOU --
[ APPLAUSE ]
WHEN YOU USE THE TERM
"REVOLUTION," IT MAKES SOME
PEOPLE NERVOUS.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH EVOLUTION?
>> WELL, I THINK WE HAD --
REMEMBER THE REAGAN REVOLUTION
AND THE GINGRICH REVOLUTION?
WELL, MY REVOLUTION IS A LITTLE
BIT DIFFERENT.
BUT IT IS A PROCESS.
LOOK, LET'S BE CLEAR.
WE HAVE ONE OF THE LOWEST VOTER
TURNOUTS OF ANY MAJOR COUNTRY ON
EARTH.
IN THE LAST ELECTION, WHERE?
S WON A HUGE VICTORY, 63% OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE DIDN'T VOTE.
80% OF YOUNG PEOPLE DIDN'T VOTE.
NOW, WHEN PEOPLE DON'T VOTE,
THERE'S A POLITICAL VACUUM
THAT'S CREATED AND I WILL TELL
YOU HOW IT'S FILLED.
IT'S FILLED BY LOBBYITS AND
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTORS WHO COULD
CARE LESS ABOUT THE MIDDLE CLASS
WHO ARE THERE TO PROTECT THE
WEALTHIEST PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY.
SO WHAT WE ARE TRYING TO DO, AND
I WOULD TELL YOU, ANDERSON, WITH
SOME SUCCESS, IS BRING WORKING
PEOPLE AND YOUNG PEOPLE AND
LOWER INCOME PEOPLE INTO THE
POLITICAL PROCESS AND WHEN THAT
HAPPENS, YOU KNOW WHAT?
WE WILL RAISE THE MINIMUM WAGE,
WE WILL HAVE HEALTH CARE FOR ALL
PEOPLE, WE WILL MAKE PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION-FREE.
>> I WANT TO -- I WANT YOU TO
MEET JASON TULURSKI.
HE'S IN I.T. MANAGEMENT.
HE SAYS YOU ARE HIS DREAM
CANDIDATE, BUT, HE DOES HAVE
SOME CONCERNS.
>> OH, BUTS ALWAYS MAKE ME
NERVOUS.
OKAY, JASON, FIRE AWAY.
>> YOU ARE MY DREAM CANDIDATE IN
A LOT OF WAYS.
THE MESSAGE OF YOUR CAMPAIGN
REALLY SPEAKS TO ME AND ON SOME
ISSUES, I FEEL YOU ACTUALLY
SPEAK FOR ME.
BUT I ALSO KNOW THAT MOST PEOPLE
DON'T HAVE THE SAME CLASS-BASED
VIEW OF THE WORLD THAT I DO AND
I THINK YOU DO AS WELL.
I'VE SEEN ALL OF YOUR DEBATES
AND I JUST DON'T SEE YOU
CONNECTING WITH PEOPLE THAT VIEW
THE WORLD THROUGH A RELIGIOUS OR
RACIAL LENS.
PEOPLE THAT SEE THOSE AS THE
POWERFUL FORCES IN OUR SOCIETY.
I'M WONDERING WHAT YOU CAN DO TO
BETTER ENGAGE WITH THE BROADER
ELECTORATE, TO UNDERSTAND THEIR
POINTS OF VIEW, DEMONSTRATE THAT
YOU CAN BE AN EFFECTIVE LEADER
FOR THEM.
>> VERY GOOD QUESTION AND THANK
YOU FOR IT.
WE ARE REACHING OUT AS STRONGLY
AS WE CAN, FOR EXAMPLE, TO THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY AND
TO THE LATINO COMMUNITY.
AND I THINK WE ARE GAINING MORE
AND MORE SUPPORT IN THOSE
COMMUNITIES.
NUMBER ONE, IN THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY, IT'S
NOT ANIMAL AN ECONOMIC ISSUE,
RAISING THE MINIMUM WAGE AND
PROVIDING JOBS, YOUTH
UNEMPLOYMENT FOR
AFRICAN-AMERICAN KIDS NOW IS
51%.
SO THOSE ARE IMPORTANT ISSUES.
BUT I'LL TELL YOU WHAT ELSE IS
AN IMPORTANT ISSUE.
AND THAT IS, THE CRIMINAL
JUSTICE ISSUE.
THE FACT THAT WE HAVE MORE
PEOPLE IN JAIL IN AMERICA THAN
ANY OTHER COUNTRY
DISPROPORTIONATELY
AFRICAN-AMERICAN, AND LATINO.
THE FACT THAT BLACKS AND WHITES
DO MARIJUANA AT ABOUT AN EQUAL
LEVEL, AND YET FOUR TIMES MORE
BLACKS GET ARRESTED.
THE FACT THAT BLACKS ARE MORE
LIKELY TO BE STOPPED BY POLICE
IN A VEHICLE AND GET ARRESTED
THAN WHITES.
THOSE ARE HUGE ISSUES.
AND WHAT I HAVE SAID AND REPEAT,
I'LL SAY THIS ALL OVER THE CUP,
THERE WILL BE NO PRESIDENT WHO
WILL FIGHT HARDER TO END
INSTITUTIONAL RACISM THAN I
WILL.
AND WE HAVE GOT TO REFORM A
VERY, VERY BROKEN CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM.
IT BREAKS MY HEART, AND I KNOW
THAT IT BREAKS THE HEARTS OF
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY, TO SEE VIDEOS ON
TELEVISION OF UNARMED PEOPLE,
OFTEN AFRICAN-AMERICANS, SHOT BY
POLICE.
THAT HAS GOT TO END.
AND THESE ARE ISSUES THAT I TAKE
VERY SERIOUSLY, JASON.
>> YOU KNOW, I WANT TO FOLLOW
UP, BECAUSE JASON ALSO MENTIONED
FAITH, WHICH IS SOMETHING YOU'VE
SPOKEN A LITTLE BIT ABOUT.
YOU'RE JEWISH, BUT YOU'VE SAID
THAT YOU'RE NOT ACTIVELY
INVOLVED WITH ORGANIZED
RELIGION.
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO A VOTER OUT
THERE WHO SAYS -- AND WHO SEES
FAITH AS A GUIDING PRINCIPLE IN
THEIR LIVES, AND WANTS IT TO BE
A GUIDING PRINCIPLE FOR --
>> IT'S A GUIDING PRINCIPLE IN
MY LIFE, ABSOLUTELY, IT IS.
YOU KNOW, EVERYBODY PRACTICES
RELIGION IN A DIFFERENT WAY.
TO ME, I WOULD NOT BE HERE
TONIGHT, I WOULD NOT BE RUNNING
FOR PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES IF I DID NOT HAVE VERY
STRONG RELIGIOUS AND SPIRITUAL
FEELINGS.
I BELIEVE THAT, AS A HUMAN
BEING, THE PAIN THAT ONE PERSON
FEELS, IF WE HAVE CHILDREN WHO
ARE HUNGRY IN AMERICA, IF WE
HAVE ELDERLY PEOPLE WHO CAN'T
AFFORD THEIR PRESCRIPTION DRUGS,
YOU KNOW WHAT, THAT IMPACTS YOU,
THAT IMPACTS ME.
AND I WORRY VERY MUCH ABOUT A
SOCIETY WHERE SOME PEOPLE
SPIRITUALLY SAY, IT DOESN'T
MATTER TO ME.
I GOT IT, I DON'T CARE ABOUT
OTHER PEOPLE.
SO MY SPIRITUALITY IS THAT WE
ARE ALL IN THIS TOGETHER AND
THAT WHEN CHILDREN GO HUNGRY,
WHEN VETERANS SLEEP OUT ON THE
STREET, IT IMPACTS ME.
THAT'S MY VERY STRONG SPIRITUAL
FEELINGS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, I WANT YOU TO MEET
DENISE BERNARD, SHE WAS WOUNDED
IN THE BOSTON MARATHON BOMBING.
SHE SAYS SHE'S UNDECIDED.
SHE HAS A QUESTION ABOUT
TERRORISM.
>> YES, I AM A FORTUNATE
SURVIVOR FROM THE BOSTON BOMBING
AND IT HAS CHANGED MY LIFE.
AND ONE OF THE BIGGEST THINGS IS
PARTICIPATING IN EVENTS, LARGE
EVENTS, AND I'M RUNNING THE
MARATHON AGAIN --
>> GOOD FOR YOU.
>> -- THIS YEAR WITH MY HUSBAND.
BUT MY KIDS ARE GOING --
[ APPLAUSE ]
THANK YOU.
SO, MY KIDS ARE GOING TO BE OUT
THERE SPECTATING.
AND I CAN ONLY THINK ABOUT THEIR
SAFETY WHILE THEY'RE OUT THERE.
SO MY QUESTION TO YOU IS, WHAT
ARE YOUR PLANS, FOR KEEPING US
SAFE FROM TERRORISM?
>> OKAY.
FOR A START, IN MY VIEW, WE HAVE
GOT TO CRUSH ISIS, FOR A START.
AND AS SOMEBODY WHO VOTED
AGAINST THE WAR IN IRAQ, WHAT I
BELIEVE IS WE'VE GOT TO LEARN
THE LESSONS OF THAT WAR.
SO WE HAVE TO DESTROY ISIS, BUT
WE HAVE TO BE NOT JUST TOUGH, WE
HAVE TO BE SMART.
AND THAT MEANS, WE WORK WITH A
LARGE COALITION, LED BY ON THE
GROUND MUSLIM TROOPS.
KING ABDULLAH OF JORDAN MADE THE
POINT, IT WILL BE MUSLIM TROOPS
WHO WILL DESTROY ISIS, BECAUSE
ISIS HAS HIJACKED THEIR
RELIGION.
THE UNITED STATES, THE UK,
FRANCE, GERMANY, RUSSIA PROVIDE
SUPPORT, IN MY VIEW, TO THE
TROOPS ON THE GROUND.
SO WE'VE GOT TO CRUSH THEM.
INTERNALLY, WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO
DO IS SIGNIFICANTLY IMPROVE
INTELLIGENCE.
AND I THINK WE ARE NOT AS STRONG
AS WE CAN BE IN COMMUNICATING
WITH INTELLIGENCE AGENCIES ALL
OVER THIS COUNTRY.
IF PEOPLE COME INTO THIS
COUNTRY, SAY, I'VE GOT TO BE
SCREENED -- I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE
THAT WE SHOULD ACCEPT REFUGEES
FROM THE MIDDLE EAST, FROM SYRIA
AND AFGHANISTAN.
BUT I ALSO APPRECIATE THE
CONCERN THAT OTHERS HAVE, THAT
WE HAVE GOT TO SCREEN THOSE
PEOPLE, ABSOLUTELY, THOROUGHLY.
THERE NEEDS TO BE BETTER
COORDINATION BETWEEN FEDERAL,
STATE, AND LOCAL POLICE.
WE HAVE TO WORK, WHICH IS VERY
HARD, MAKING SURE THAT WE ARE
TRACKING INTERNET TRANSMISSION
OF INFORMATION, WHERE ISIS HAS
BEEN SUCCESSFUL IN GETTING
INFORMATION OUT OF RECRUITING
PEOPLE.
BUT YOUR CONCERNS -- AND AGAIN,
THANK YOU, YOU'RE A SYMBOL OF
COURAGE, THAT YOU WENT THROUGH
THAT HORROR IN BOSTON AND YOU'RE
GOING BACK AND RUNNING AGAIN.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR COURAGE.
>> I WANTED TO JUST FOLLOW UP,
JUST BRIEFLY ON THAT.
THERE IS A DISCONNECT.
DEMOCRATS IN IOWA WHO SAID THAT
TERRORISM WAS THE MOST IMPORTANT
ISSUE FOR THEM, THEY BACK
SECRETARY CLINTON OVER YOU BY 37
POINTS.
WHY DO YOU THINK THAT IS?
WHY DO YOU THINK THEY SEE HER AS
MORE READY TO HANDLE THAT?
WELL, I THINK BECAUSE SHE HAS A
GREAT DEAL OF EXPERIENCE.
SHE WAS SECRETARY OF STATE OF
OUR COUNTRY FOR FOUR YEARS.
BUT I WOULD SAY, ANDERSON, THAT
THE KEY FOREIGN POLICY VOTE IN
MODERN AMERICAN HISTORY WAS
WHETHER OR NOT WE SHOULD GO INTO
IRAQ.
AND SECRETARY CLINTON WAS IN THE
SENATE THEN, I WAS IN THE HOUSE
THEN.
WE BOTH LISTENED TO THE SAME
EVIDENCE.
I MADE THE DECISION, WHICH I
THINK HISTORY WILL CONCLUDE WAS
THE RIGHT DECISION, NOT TO GO TO
WAR.
AND IF PEOPLE WANT TO GO TO MY
WEBSITE, BERNIESANDERS.COM,
CHECK OUT WHAT I SAID IN 2002.
AND IT GIVES ME NO JOY AT ALL TO
SAY THAT MUCH OF WHAT I FEARED
WOULD HAPPEN DID, IN FACT,
HAPPEN IN TERMS OF THE
DESTABILIZATION OF THE REGION.
SO I THINK IN TERMS OF FOREIGN
POLICY, I HAVE THE JUDGMENT.
WE'VE BEEN ALL OVER THIS WORLD,
MET WITH FOREIGN POLICY LEADERS
AND I AM CONFIDENT THAT WE CAN
ASSEMBLE A TEAM THAT WOULD DO A
GREAT JOB.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET GABRIELLE
GRAVES, A STUDENT HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, SHE'S AN INDEPENDENT
VOTER, BUT SHE'S SUPPORTING YOU.
>> HI.
SO I'M FROM BROOKLYN, NEW YORK,
LIKE YOU ARE, AND MY QUESTION IS
THAT I'VE EXPERIENCED AND I'VE
WITNESSED A LOT OF POLICE
BRUTALITY AND RACIAL UNJUSTICE.
AND I WANT TO KNOW, LIKE, I
THINK AND I DO BELIEVE THAT IT
IS NEIGHBORHOODS PRIMARILY OF
PEOPLE OF COLOR, LOW-INCOME
NEIGHBORHOODS THAT ARE
DISPROPORTIONATELY AFFECTED BY
UNJUST POLICING.
AND I WANT TO KNOW IF YOU ARE TO
BE ELECTED AS PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, WHAT WOULD YOU DO
TO ENACT CHANGE AND COMBAT THIS
RACIAL INJUSTICE?
>> GABRIELLE, YOU HAVE ASKED AN
IMPORTANT QUESTION THAT IS ON
THE MINDS OF MILLIONS OF PEOPLE,
NOT JUST AFRICAN-AMERICANS, BUT
ALL PEOPLE.
HERE'S WHAT I WOULD DO.
FOR A START.
AND I SPEAK AS A FORMER MAYOR.
I WAS MAYOR OF BURLINGTON,
VERMONT, A MANY KNOW, WHO WORKED
VERY CLOSELY WITH OUR POLICE
DEPARTMENT, AND BELIEVE THAT THE
VAST MAJORITY OF POLICE OFFICERS
IN THIS COUNTRY ARE
HARD-WORKING, ARE HONEST, AND
ARE TRYING TO DO THEIR BEST
DOING VERY, VERY DIFFICULT WORK.
BUT IF A POLICE OFFICER BREAKS
THE LAW, LIKE ANY OTHER PUBLIC
OFFICIAL, THAT POLICE OFFICER
MUST BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE.
THAT'S NUMBER ONE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NUMBER TWO, YOU HAVE SEEN ON
TELEVISION, AS I HAVE, LOCAL
POLICE DEPARTMENTS THAT LOOK
LIKE OCCUPYING ARMIES.
WE HAVE GOT TO DEMILITARIZE
LOCAL POLICE DEPARTMENTS, MAKE
THEM PART OF THE COMMUNITY, NOT
INVADING ARMIES.
THIRD --
[ APPLAUSE ]
THIRD, AND VERY IMPORTANTLY, WE
HAVE GOT TO MAKE POLICE
DEPARTMENTS LOOK LIKE THE
COMMUNITIES THAT THEY SERVE.
SO IF THERE'S A DIVERSE
COMMUNITY, THE POLICE DEPARTMENT
SHOULD REFLECT THAT DIVERSITY.
FOURTHLY, IN TERMS OF POLICE
ACTION -- POLICE DEPARTMENTS ARE
RUN BY LOCAL GOVERNMENTS, BUT
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CAN PLAY
AN IMPORTANT ROLE IN HELPING TO
FUND MODEL TYPE PROGRAMS -- FOR
EXAMPLE, I THINK WE HAVE TO
RETHINK THE USE OF LETHAL FORCE.
I THINK, TOO OFTEN, LETHAL FORCE
GOES FIRST RATHER THAN LAST.
OBVIOUSLY, THERE ARE TIMES WHEN
POLICEMAN MUST USE THEIR GUNS
AND USE THEM AS QUICKLY AS
POSSIBLE.
BUT I THINK WHAT WE NEED TO DO
IS FIGURE OUT WAYS TO TRAIN
POLICE DEPARTMENTS, POLICE
OFF
OFFICERS, SO THAT LETHAL FORCE
IS THE LAST RESORT, NOT THE
FIRST RESORT.
THOSE ARE SOME OF THE THINGS I
WOULD DO.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU, BECAUSE I
THINK PEOPLE DON'T KNOW MUCH
ABOUT YOUR BACKGROUND ON THIS
SUBJECT.
IT'S INTERESTING, 54 YEARS AGO,
YOU WERE ON THE FRONT LINES OF
TRYING TO DESEGREGATE SCHOOL
HOUSING AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
CHICAGO.
YOU WERE EVEN ARRESTED -- DON'T
TELL ANYBODY THAT.
>> WHAT WAS IT THAT MOTIVATED A
20-YEAR-OLD WHITE KID FROM
BROOKLYN TO DO THAT?
>> IT'S HARD TO SAY WHAT
MOTIVATES ANYBODY.
I THINK, AS A KID, MY PARENTS
WEREN'T POLITICAL.
MY BROTHER WAS A LITTLE BIT, I
MANY PARENTS WERE NOT.
BUT, YOU KNOW, LIKE IN ANY
SCHOOL, YOU SEE BIG KIDS PICKING
ON LITTLE KIDS, YOU KNOW?
AND I RESENTED THAT.
I ALWAYS DID.
AND, YOU KNOW, INJUSTICE
BOTHERED ME VERY, VERY MUCH.
AND WHEN I WENT TO THE
UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, I HAD THE
OPPORTUNITY TO -- I WASN'T A
GREAT STUDENT, I HAVE TO -- I
HAVE TO ADMIT IT.
IN FACT, I LEARNED MORE
OFF-CAMPUS -- I SHOULDN'T SAY
THIS TO OTHER STUDENTS,
THOUGH -- DO YOUR HOMEWORK,
STUDY --
>> GOT A LOT OF TEACHERS IN THIS
ROOM.
>> BUT I LEARNED A LOT OFF OF
CAMPUS.
I GOT INVOLVED IN A GROUP SOME
MAY KNOW, SOME MAY NOT, CALLED
THE CONVERSE OF RACIAL EQUALITY.
WE GOT INVOLVED IN A GROUP
TRYING TO DESEGREGATE HOUSING.
WE ALSO GOT INVOLVED IN EFFORTS
TO DESEGREGATE THE SCHOOL SYSTEM
THERE AND I GOT ARRESTED.
BUT I THINK, YOU KNOW, AS FAR
BACK AS I CAN REMEMBER, AND
ANDERSON, I CAN'T TELL YOU WHY,
BUT INJUSTICE IS SOMETHING THAT
I HAVE ALWAYS FOUGHT THROUGHOUT
MY LIFE.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET KEITH
HOWARD.
HE WAS A VETERAN, HE WAS
HOMELESS AFTER SERVING IN THE
ARMY.
HE'S NOW THE EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR
OF LIBERTY HOUSE, WHICH IS NOW A
TRANSITIONAL FACILITY FOR FORMER
HOMELESS VETS.
HE SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED.
KEITH, WELCOME.
>> YEAH, SENATOR SANDERS,
THROUGHOUT THIS ELECTION CYCLE,
WE AT LIBERTY HOUSE HAVE BEEN
CONTACTED BY A NUMBER OF
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES.
TO DATE, WE'VE NOT HEARD FROM
ANY DEMOCRATS.
HAVE YOU CEDED THE SUPPORT OF
VETERANS TO THE REPUBLICANS?
AND IF YOUR ANSWER IS NO, WHAT
IS YOUR EVIDENCE?
>> WHAT IS MY EVIDENCE?
MY EVIDENCE IS THAT I'M THE
FORMER CHAIRMAN OF THE U.S.
SENATE COMMITTEE ON VETERANS'
AFFAIRS.
THAT I INTRODUCED ALONG WITH THE
SUPPORT OF THE AMERICAN LEGION,
THE VFW, THE DAV, THE VIETNAM
VETS OF VIRTUALLY EVERY MAJOR
VETERANS ORGANIZATION THE MOST
COMPREHENSIVE VETERANS HEALTH
CARE LEGISLATION IN THE MODERN
HISTORY OF THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
AND SADLY ENOUGH, YOU KNOW, IT'S
ONE THING FOR REPUBLICANS TO
TALK ABOUT HOW MUCH THEY LOVE
VETERANS.
I GOT TWO REPUBLICAN VOTES ON A
COMPREHENSIVE BILL SUPPORTED BY
VIRTUALLY THE ENTIRE VETERANS
COMMITTEE.
BUT I DIDN'T GIVE UP.
WHAT I DID THEN IS WORK WITH
PEOPLE LIKE JOHN McCAIN, JEFF
MILLER OVER IN THE HOUSE, AND WE
PASSED -- WASN'T MY IDEAL BILL,
I COMPROMISED -- BUT IT WAS THE
MOST SIGNIFICANT PIECE OF
VETERANS HEALTH CARE LEGISLATION
PASSED IN MODERN HISTORY.
WE PUT SOME $16 BILLION INTO
VETERANS' HEALTH CARE, AS WELL
AS IN TAKING CARE OF VETERANS IN
A NUMBER OF OTHER AREAS.
SO IT'S EASY FOR POLITICIANS TO
GIVE SPEECHES.
BUT WHAT MY WORK IN THE SENATE
HAS BEEN INVOLVED IS MAKING SURE
THAT VETERANS IN THIS COUNTRY
GET THE BEST-QUALITY HEALTH CARE
POSSIBLE, GET THEIR BENEFITS
WHEN THEY NEED THEM, NOT WAIT
YEARS AND YEARS.
AND WE'VE MADE SOME PROGRESS ON
THAT.
DO OUR BEST TO END VETERANS'
HOMELESSNESS AND PRESIDENT OBAMA
PUT A LOT OF MONEY INTO THAT,
AND WE HAVE HAD SOME SUCCESS.
STILL HAVE A WAY TO GO.
SO I THINK IF YOU CHECK MY
RECORD, IT WILL TELL YOU THAT I
RECEIVED THE AWARDS, THE HIGHEST
AWARD, FROM THE AMERICAN LEGION
AND THE VFW FOR MY WORK ON
VETERANS ISSUES.
SO I'M PROUD OF THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> LET ME FOLLOW UP ON THAT.
YOU WERE ON THE VETERANS AFFAIRS
COMMITTEE FOR EIGHT YEARS.
YOU HEADED IT FOR TWO YEARS.
THERE WERE 18 INSPECTORS
GENERALS REPORTS TALKING ABOUT
PROBLEMS PLAGUING THE V.A. WHY
DID IT TAKE SO LONG?
AND DID IT TAKE YOU TOO LONG TO
ACT?
>> FAIR QUESTION.
AND I THINK THE ANSWER IS THAT
WE HAVE WORKED ON MANY, MANY
ISSUES, ANDERSON.
AND YOUR POINT IS FAIR, THAT WE
SHOULD HAVE ACTED SCHOONER.
WE SHOULD HAVE KNOWN WHAT WAS
GOING ON IN PHOENIX.
THOSE LONG WAITING LINES AND THE
LIES THAT SOME ADMINISTRATORS
WERE TELLING US.
ON THE OTHER HAND, WHAT WE ALSO
DID, THOUGH, IS MAKE SIGNIFICANT
PROGRESS IN TERMS OF DEALING
WITH HOMELESSNESS.
WE'VE PASSED A POST-9/11 GI
BILL, WHICH PROVIDES COLLEGE
EDUCATION FOR THE MEN AND WOMEN
WHO SERVED IN IRAQ AND
AFGHANISTAN.
WE PASSED A CAREGIVERS' ACT,
WHICH FOR THE FIRST TIME WILL
PROVIDE SUPPORT FOR THOSE FOLKS,
MOSTLY WOMEN, WHO ARE STAYING
HOME WITH DISABLED VETS.
SO I THINK IN RECENT YEARS, WE
HAVE MADE SOME PROGRESS.
YOUR POINT IS A GOOD ONE.
WE SHOULD HAVE DONE BETTER.
>> ALL RIGHT.
I WANT YOU TO MEET MARGERIE
SMITH.
SHE SERVED NINE TERMS IN THE
STATEHOUSE HERE.
SHE SAYS SHE'S CURRENTLY
UNDECIDED.
WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
SENATOR, YOU AND I HAVE A LOT IN
COMMON.
I WAS BORN IN BROOKLYN IN 1941.
>> THERE WE GO!
>> SO --
>> YOU LOOK YOUNGER THAN I DO.
WHY IS THAT?
>> THAT'S VERY KIND OF YOU TO
SAY.
BUT I'M NOT RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT.
SENATOR, MANY OF US SEE HOW
DEEPLY HELD YOUR PHILOSOPHY, AND
THAT MATTERS TATTA LOT TO US.
WE SHARE THOSE GOALS.
AT THE SAME TIME, YOU HAVE
WORKED FOR MANY YEARS TO SAY,
IT'S MY WAY OR THE HIGHWAY.
YOU TALKED TONIGHT ABOUT WANTING
TO HAVE A REVOLUTION IN THE
HOUSE AND SENATE IN ORDER TO GET
PEOPLE THERE WHO SHARE YOUR
VIEWS.
THERE MIGHT BE SOME NEW MEMBERS
OF THE HOUSE AND SENATE, BUT
THEY'RE NOT GOING TO BE ALL THAT
MANY.
HOW ARE YOU GOING TO BE ABLE TO
WORK WITH A CONGRESS THAT MIGHT
NOT SHARE OUR DEEPLY-HELD GOALS
IN ORDER TO ACHIEVE A MORE
PERFECT UNION?
>> WELL, MARGERIE, THANK YOU FOR
YOUR QUESTION.
IT IS JUST NOT ACCURATE TO
SAY -- I KNOW SOMETIMES PEOPLE
MAY PORTRAY ME IN THIS RESPECT,
IT IS NOT ACCURATE TO SAY THAT
IT'S MY WAY OR THE HIGHWAY.
BECAUSE LET ME GIVE YOU SOME
EXAMPLES.
I JUST MENTIONED THAT I
COMPROMISED SIGNIFICANTLY WITH
PEOPLE LIKE JOHN McCAIN AND
REPUBLICANS IN THE HOUSE TO PASS
WHAT IS REGARDED AS THE MOST
SIGNIFICANT PIECE OF VETERANS
LEGISLATION PASSED IN MANY,
YEARS.
SECOND OF ALL, WHEN I WAS IN THE
HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES, THERE
WERE YEARS, MARGERIE, WHEN I
RECEIVED MORE VOTES -- I WON
MORE AMENDMENTS THAN ANY OTHER
MEMBER OF THE HOUSE OF
REPRESENTATIVES, BECAUSE I
REACHED OUT WHERE THERE WAS
COMMON GROUND WITH REPUBLICANS
SO I THINK I HAVE A HISTORY OF
BEING ABLE TO WORK WITH
REPUBLICANS WHEN THERE IS COMMON
GROUND.
BUT HERE IS THE MAJOR POINT THAT
I WANT TO MAKE.
AND I WILL CONTINUE TO DO THAT.
BUT HERE IS THE TRUTH, AND IT'S
AN UNPLEASANT TRUTH, AND I KNOW
THAT NOT EVERYBODY HERE WILL
AGREE WITH ME.
IN MY VIEW, WE HAVE A CONGRESS
TODAY THAT IS MUCH MORE
INTERESTED IN DOING THE BIDDING
OF THE WEALTHY AND THE POWERFUL
WALL STREET AND THE DRUG
COMPANIES AND THE FOSSIL FUEL
INDUSTRIES, RATHER THAN THE
NEEDS OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
AND I BELIEVE WE'RE NOT GOING TO
MAKE THE REAL CHANGES THAT WE
NEED DEALING WITH THE GROTESQUE
LEVEL OF INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY, REFORMING A CORRUPT
CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM, WHICH
ALLOWS BILLIONAIRES TO BUY
ELECTIONS, DEALING WITH CLIMATE
CHANGE, MAKING SURE WE DON'T
CONTINUE TO PAY THE HIGHEST
PRICES IN THE WORLD FOR
PRESCRIPTION DRUGS WHEN LAST
YEAR, THE THREE MAJOR DRUG
COMPANIES MADE $45 BILLION IN
PROFIT.
NOW, HOW DO WE CHANGE ALL OF
THAT?
WELL, WHERE WE CAN, WE WORK WITH
OUR REPUBLICAN FRIENDS.
BUT CHANGE, IN MY VIEW, AND WHAT
HISTORY TELLS US, HAS ALWAYS
COME FROM THE BOTTOM ON UP.
THAT'S WHAT THE CIVIL RIGHTS
MOVEMENT WAS ABOUT.
THAT'S WHAT THE WOMEN'S MOVEMENT
WAS ABOUT.
THAT'S WHAT THE GAY MOVEMENT WAS
ABOUT.
THAT'S WHAT THE ENVIRONMENTAL
MOVEMENT IS ABOUT.
AND WHAT WE NEED RIGHT NOW IS A
VERY PROFOUND AND DEEP MOVEMENT
IN THIS COUNTRY, WHERE MILLIONS
OF PEOPLE, IN FACT, GET INVOLVED
AND SAY, I'M SORRY, MY KID IS
NOT GOING TO HAVE TO GRADUATE
COLLEGE $100,000 IN DEBT.
THAT'S WRONG.
MY MOM IS ENTITLED TO DECENT
HEALTH CARE AND PRESCRIPTION
DRUGS THAT SHE CAN AFFORD.
THOSE ARE THE KINDS OF MOVEMENTS
THAT WE NEED, AND THAT'S HOW WE
WILL BRING ABOUT REAL CHANGE IN
THIS COUNTRY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET MARK
VINES.
HE'S A GRAPHIC ARTIST, A BOY
SCOUT MASTER.
HE SAYS HE DECIDED TO SUPPORT
YOU IN THE PRIMARY.
YOUR QUESTION.
>> THAT'S BECAUSE I WAS A BOY
SCOUT TOO.
>> GOOD EVENING.
FOUR OF OUR LAST FIVE SENATORS
WERE ELECTED AND SERVED TWO
TERMS.
DO YOU SEE ANY INABILITY TO
SERVE TWO TERMS?
>> YOU WOULD BE 83 AT THE END OF
YOUR SECOND TERM.
>> YOU KNOW, BUT THANK
GOODNESS -- LET'S NOT BE AGEIST!
>> I'M NOT, I'M NOT.
>> YOU KNOW, I AM, THANK GOD, IN
GOOD HEALTH.
AND ONE CAN'T PREDICT THE
FUTURE, ONE NEVER KNOWS WHAT
HAPPENS TOMORROW.
BUT WHEN I WAS A KID, I WAS A
LONG-DISTANCE RUNNER.
I WAS NOT QUITE THE MARATHON
RUNNER, BUT I WAS A
CROSS-COUNTRY RUNNER.
AND I'VE HAD GOOD ENDURANCE AND
GOOD STRENGTH MY WHOLE LIFE.
SO, YOU KNOW, IF I AM FORTUNATE
ENOUGH TO WIN THE GENERAL
ELECTION, AND WE DO WELL, YES, I
WOULD LIKE TO RUN FOR
RE-ELECTION.
>> YOU GOT A LOT MORE ENERGY
THAN I DO.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK AND WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK
WITH MORE AUDIENCE QUESTIONS FOR
SENATOR SANDERS.
YOU'RE WATCHING THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL, LIVE FROM NEW HAMPSHIRE.
I think it
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL AT THE DERRY OPERAHOUSE.
WE'RE HERE WITH SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS.
LET'S CONTINUE THE QUESTIONS.
I WANT TO PLAY FOR SENATOR
SANDERS A CLIP FROM HILLARY
CLINTON'S SPEECH MONDAY NIGHT
AFTER THE IOWA CAUCUSES.
LET'S LISTEN.
>> HERE'S WHAT I WANT YOU TO
KNOW.
IT IS RARE, IT IS RARE THAT WE
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY WE DO NOW.
TO HAVE A REAL CONTEST OF IDEAS.
TO REALLY THINK HARD ABOUT WHAT
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY STANDS FOR
AND WHAT WE WANT THE FUTURE OF
OUR COUNTRY TO LOOK LIKE IF WE
DO OUR PART TO BUILD IT.
I AM A PROGRESSIVE WHO GETS
THINGS DONE FOR PEOPLE.
>> THERE WERE A LOT OF YOUR
SUPPORTERS, WHO WHEN THEY HEARD
THAT, DIDN'T THINK, OR EXPRESSED
THEIR BELIEF THAT SHE'S NOT A
PROGRESSIVE.
WE TALKED ABOUT THIS A BIT AT
THE BEGINNING.
BUT JUST SO WE'RE CLEAR, DO YOU
THINK THAT HILLARY CLINTON IS A
PROGRESSIVE?
>> LET ME SAY THIS.
I HAVE ENORMOUS RESPECT FOR
HILLARY CLINTON.
I'VE KNOWN HER FOR 25 YEARS, AND
IT'S UNFORTUNATE IN POLITICS,
AND EVERYBODY SHOULD KNOW THIS,
WHAT MEDIA OFTEN WANT YOU TO DO,
AND I'M SURE IT'S THE SAME FOR
HILLARY CLINTON, BEAT HER UP,
ATTACK HER.
BECAUSE THAT WILL MAKE THE NEWS.
I HAVE TRIED MY BEST NOT TO DO
THAT.
YOU'RE LOOKING AT A GUY WHO HAS
BEEN IN POLITICS A LONG TIME,
AND I HAVE NEVER RUN A NEGATIVE
AD IN MY LIFE.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO NEVER
RUNNING A NEGATIVE AD IN MY
LIFE, OKAY?
I DON'T THINK PEOPLE DESERVE
THAT.
WE HAVE TO -- SECRETARY CLINTON
JUST SAID, THAT'S WHAT POLITICS
IS ABOUT.
IT'S A DEBATE ON THE ISSUES.
SECRETARY CLINTON HAS A LONG AND
DISTINGUISHED PUBLIC CAREER.
SHE HAS WORKED WITH CHILDREN,
WHEN SHE BEGAN, AND GOD ONLY
KNOWS THAT WE NEED A LOT OF
WORK, GIVEN THE FACT THAT WE
HAVE THE HIGHEST RATE OF
CHILDHOOD POVERTY OF ANY COUNTRY
ON EARTH.
SO I RESPECT HER, I THOUGHT SHE
DID A GOOD JOB AS SECRETARY OF
STATE.
I SERVED WITH HER IN THE SENATE.
WE WORKED TOGETHER ON SOME
ISSUES.
BUT THERE ARE OTHER ISSUES,
ANDERSON, WHERE I THINK SHE IS
JUST NOT PROGRESSIVE.
I DO NOT KNOW ANY PROGRESSIVE
WHO HAS A SUPER PAC AND TAKES
$15 MILLION FROM WALL STREET.
THAT'S JUST NOT PROGRESSIVE.
AS I MENTIONED EARLIER, THE KEY
FOREIGN POLICY VOTE OF MODERN
AMERICAN HISTORY WAS THE WAR IN
IRAQ.
THE PROGRESSIVE COMMUNITY WAS
PRETTY UNITED IN SAYING, DON'T
LISTEN TO BUSH.
DON'T GO TO WAR.
SECRETARY CLINTON VOTED TO GO TO
WAR.
VIRTUALLY ALL OF THE TRADE
UNIONS AND MILLIONS OF WORKING
PEOPLE UNDERSTAND THAT OUR TRADE
POLICIES, NAFTA, CAFTA,
PERMANENT TRADE RELATIONS WITH
CHINA, ET CETERA, HAVE BEEN
WRITTEN BY CORPORATE AMERICA AND
THE GOAL OF IT IS TO BE ABLE TO
THROW AMERICAN WORKERS OUT ON
THE STREET, MOVE TO CHINA AND
OTHER LOW-WAGE COUNTRIES, AND
BRING THEIR PRODUCTS BACK INTO
THIS COUNTRY.
AND THAT'S ONE OF THE REASONS
WHY THE MIDDLE CLASS OF THIS
COUNTRY AND THE WORKING CLASS IS
STRUGGLING SO HARD.
SECRETARY CLINTON HAS BEEN A
SUPPORTER IN THE PAST OF VARIOUS
TRADE POLICIES, NAFTA AND PMTR
WITH CHINA.
RELUCTANTLY AND AFTER A LOT OF
PRESSURE ON HER, SHE CAME OUT
AGAINST THE TPP AND I'M GLAD
THAT SHE DID.
EVERY SENSIBLE PERSON
UNDERSTANDS THAT CLIMATE CHANGE
IS REAL, IT IS CAUSED BY HUMAN
ACTIVITY, AND WE HAVE GOT TO
TRANSFORM OUR ENERGY SYSTEM AWAY
FROM FOSSIL FUEL.
FOR A LONG TIME, SECRETARY
CLINTON WAS TALKING ABOUT THE
BENEFITS OF THE KEYSTONE
PIPELINE.
WELL, THERE ARE NO BENEFITS TO
EXCAVATING AND TRANSPORTING SOME
OF THE DIRTIEST FOSSIL FUEL IN
THE WORLD.
I WAS IN THE LEAD IN OPPOSITION
TO THE KEYSTONE PIPELINE.
I'M IN OPPOSITION TO THE
PIPELINE RIGHT HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE AND THE PIPELINE IN
VERMONT.
I THINK WE HAVE GOT TO MOVE
AGGRESSIVELY AWAY FROM FOSSIL
FUEL IF WE'RE GOING TO LEAVE
THIS PLANET IN A WAY THAT'S
HEALTHY AND HABITABLE FOR OUR
KIDS.
SO THOSE ARE JUST SOME OF THE
AREAS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> JUST ONE QUICK FOLLOW-UP TO
THAT.
THERE'S A NEW BOOK CALLED
"BUYER'S REMORSE: HOW OBAMA LED
PROGRESSIVES DOWN," YOU GAVE IT
A RINGING ENDORSEMENT --
>> I DIDN'T GIVE IT AN
ENDORSEMENT.
>> TELL ME WHAT YOU DID.
>> I WROTE A BLURB FOR IT, YOU
MAY HAVE THE BLURB THERE, AND
WHAT I SAID IS THAT THE NEXT
PRESIDENT SHOULD BE VERY
AGGRESSIVE IN BRINGING PEOPLE
INTO THE POLITICAL PROCESS.
AND THAT, I BELIEVE, FROM THE
BOTTOM OF MY HEART, AND IF
ELECTED PRESIDENT, THAT WILL BE
A TOP PRIORITY OF MINE.
>> DID PRESIDENT OBAMA LET
PROGRESSIVES DOWN?
>> I THINK IN SOME AREAS,
PROGRESSIVE -- FOR EXAMPLE, IN
THE TRADE AREA.
RIGHT NOW, I THINK THEY SIGNED
TODAY THE TPP IN NEW ZEALAND.
I THINK IT IS A CONTINUATION OF
BAD TRADE POLICIES.
THE PRESIDENT SUPPORTS IT, I
STRONGLY DISAGREE WITH IT.
ON THE OTHER HAND, LET'S BE VERY
CLEAR.
AND I GOT A LITTLE BIT UPSET
THAT OUR REPUBLICANS FRIENDS
SUFFER FROM A VERY SERIOUS
ILLNESS CALLED ANESTMNESIA.
THEY FORGOT WHAT THE ECONOMY OF
THIS COUNTRY WAS LIKE SEVEN
YEARS AGO WHEN WE WERE LOSING
700,000 JOBS A MONTH, WHEN WE
WERE RUNNING UP A $1.4 TRILLION
DEFICIT, AND BY THE WAY, THE
WORLD'S FINANCIAL SYSTEM WAS ON
THE VERGE OF COLLAPSE.
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND VICE
PRESIDENT BIDEN HAVE TAKEN US A
VERY, VERY LONG WAY FROM THOSE
DISMAL DAYS.
ARE WE WHERE WE WANT TO BE
TODAY?
NO.
BUT WE HAVE COME A LONG WAY AND
PRESIDENT OBAMA DESERVES AN
ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF CREDIT FOR
THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, AS YOU KNOW, IN A
RECENT POLL, I'M SURE, 88% OF
ADULTS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE SAID
HEROIN ABUSE IS A VERY SERIOUS
PROBLEM IN THE STATE.
I WANT YOU TO MEET DAVID COTY, A
RECOVERY COACH WHO'S IN
LONG-TERM RECOVERY HIMSELF.
HE SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED, LEANING
TOWARDS YOU.
DAVID, THANKS FOR BEING HERE.
WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION?
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, SENATOR, FOR HEARING
ME.
I COME TO YOU TONIGHT AS THE
FATHER OF A TEENAGER.
I HAVE A YOUNG TEENAGE DAUGHTER.
AND MY BIGGEST CONCERN THESE
DAYS IS THE AVAILABILITY OF
OPIATES AND OTHER DRUGS,
SUBSTANCES ON THE STREET.
AND THE EFFECTS THAT THEY HAVE
ON OUR YOUTH AND ON OUR
CITIZENS.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS, WE'RE
LOSING 129 PEOPLE A DAY IN THIS
COUNTRY.
IN THE CITY OF MANCHESTER, WE'RE
LOSING ONE PERSON A WEEK AT --
>> UNBELIEVABLE.
>> YOU KNOW, MINIMALLY.
AND MY QUESTION TO YOU IS, IF --
WHAT WOULD YOU DO IN ORDER TO
SECURE RECOVERY SERVICES FOR
THOSE THAT HAVE SLIPPED THROUGH
THE CRACKS OF PREVENTION AND
MOVED ON TO TREATMENT?
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR
QUESTION.
IT IS A CRISIS HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
AND BY THE WAY, THERE'S A CRISIS
IN VERMONT.
YOU MAY RECALL OUR GOVERNOR GAVE
HIS STATE OF THE UNION SPEECH A
YEAR AGO ON THIS ISSUE.
BECAUSE PEOPLE THINK, WELL, NEW
HAMPSHIRE AND VERMONT, THESE ARE
RURAL STATES, NOT A PROBLEM.
YOU'RE RIGHT, IT IS A TERRIBLE
PROBLEM.
WHAT DO WE DO?
FOR A START, WE UNDERSTAND THAT
SUBSTANCE ABUSE AND ADDICTION IS
A HEALTH ISSUE, NOT A CRIMINAL
ISSUE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND WHEN I TALK ABOUT MOVING
TOWARD UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE,
WHAT I UNDERSTAND THAT TO BE,
AND IT IS ABSOLUTELY IMPERATIVE
THAT IT BE, IS UNDERSTANDING
THAT MENTAL HEALTH AND ADDICTION
IS PART OF HEALTH CARE.
AND WHAT THAT MEANS IS WHEN
PEOPLE NEED TREATMENT, THEY
SHOULDN'T HAVE TO WAIT THREE
MONTHS.
WHEN THEY NEED IT, THEY SHOULD
BE ABLE TO GET IT.
SO THAT MEANS WE NEED A
REVOLUTION IN THIS COUNTRY IN
MENTAL HEALTHCARE TO ADDRESS THE
CAUSES OF ADDICTION AND PROVIDE
TREATMENT.
AND I WAS TO A TREATMENT CENTER
IN MANCHESTER, WHICH IS KIND OF
PEER-ORIENTED.
FORMER PEOPLE WHO HAD ADDICTION
WORK WITH OTHER PEOPLE.
THAT'S ONE APPROACH.
THERE ARE MANY OTHER APPROACHES.
BUT THE BOTTOM LINE IS, WE HAVE
A VERY, VERY SERIOUS CRISIS IN
THIS COUNTRY, AND WE HAVE GOT TO
MAKE SURE THAT WHEN PEOPLE NEED
THE HELP, THEY GET THE HELP.
AND THE OTHER QUESTION WE HAVE
TO ASK IS, AND IT'S A TOUGH
QUESTION, NOBODY I KNOWS THE
ANSWER.
WHY IS IT?
ONE OF THE REASONS, BY THE WAY,
IS I THINK THAT DOCTORS ARE
PRESCRIBING OPIATES IN A WAY
THAT THEY HAVE GOT TO CUT BACK A
LITTLE BIT ON.
THEY'RE GIVING OUT A WHOLE LOT
OF PILLS.
A FRIEND OF MINE GOT A MOLE
REMOVED.
HE GOT 50 VERY STRONG
PAIN-KILLING DRUGS.
THESE DRUGS ARE RAMPANT, KIDS
ARE USING THEM, GETTING ADDICTED
AND THEN GETTING INTO HEROIN.
I THINK WE'VE GOT TO TALK TO THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY ABOUT
WHAT THEY'RE PRODUCING, DOCTORS
WHAT THEY'RE PRESCRIBING, AND WE
HAVE TO MAKE TREATMENT AVAILABLE
TO PEOPLE WHEN THEY NEED IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET RAUL.
>> WHILE I'M INSPIRED BY YOUR
PASSION ON THE ISSUES, I WANT
ONE OF THE CONCERNS I HAVE IS
YOUR ELECTABILITY IN A GENERAL
ELECTION, WHEN THERE'S LESS
OPPORTUNITY TO REALLY CONNECT
WITH VOTERS.
>> GOOD.
>> AND, YOU KNOW, CAN YOU WIN IN
OTHER PARTS OF THE COUNTRY?
>> EXCELLENT QUESTION.
LOOK, IN THE REAL WORLD, THERE
ARE PEOPLE -- I HESITATE TO SAY
THIS IN THIS ROOM, BUT THERE ARE
PEOPLE WHO LIKE DONALD TRUMP.
I KNOW.
THERE ARE -- NOT IN THIS ROOM!
BUT THERE ARE.
AND, YOU KNOW, THAT'S THE WORLD.
WE ARE A DIVERSE POLITICAL
NATION.
AND THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO LIKE
AND RESPECT HILLARY CLINTON, AND
PEOPLE WHO LIKE ME AND SO FORTH
AND SO ON.
AND I DON'T OBJECT.
SOMEBODY WILL STAND UP AND SAY,
I SUPPORT HILLARY CLINTON.
THAT'S FINE, YOU KNOW.
BUT WHAT I DON'T -- WHAT I
OBJECT TO IS WHEN PEOPLE SAY,
BERNIE, I REALLY LIKE YOU, I
LIKE YOUR IDEAS, I LIKE YOUR
RECORD, BUT I'M NOT GOING TO
VOTE FOR YOU BECAUSE YOU CAN'T
WIN, OKAY?
SO LET ME ADDRESS THAT ISSUE.
I'M NOT A GREAT FAN OF POLLS.
NOT EVEN CNN POLLS.
BUT CNN HAD A POLL, AS I RECALL,
AND WHAT THAT POLL SAID IS THAT
BERNIE SANDERS RAN SIGNIFICANTLY
BETTER AGAINST DONALD TRUMP THAN
DID HILLARY CLINTON, OKAY?
THERE WAS ANOTHER POLL THAT SAID
THE SAME THING.
BECAUSE AMONG OTHER THINGS, I DO
VERY WELL WITH INDEPENDENTS.
AND THAT'S ONE OF THE REASONS
WHY WE ARE DOING WELL AGAINST
REPUBLICANS.
SO, NUMBER ONE, SOME OF THESE
POLLS HAVE ME WAY, WAY AHEAD OF
DONALD TRUMP.
FURTHER SO THAN HILLARY CLINTON.
NUMBER TWO, LOOK AT BATTLEGROUND
STATES, LIKE NEW HAMPSHIRE.
THE LAST POLL THAT I SAW IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE HAD ME 19 POINTS AHEAD
OF TRUMP, SECRETARY CLINTON, ONE
POINT, OKAY?
SIMILAR RESULTS NOT QUITE SO
STRONG IN IOWA AND WISCONSIN,
OKAY.
POLLS -- FORGET POLLS.
THEY GO UP AND DOWN.
WHAT ELSE?
DEMOCRATS WIN ELECTIONS WHEN
THERE IS A LARGE VOTER TURNOUT.
THAT'S WHAT OBAMA DID IN 2008.
REPUBLICANS WIN ELECTIONS WHEN
PEOPLE ARE DEMORALIZED AND GIVE
UP ON THE POLITICAL PROCESS.
I BELIEVE, AND I THINK AN
OBJECTIVE ASSESSMENT OF MY
CAMPAIGN AND SECRETARY CLINTON'S
CAMPAIGN.
AND SHE'S RUN A GOOD CAMPAIGN.
BUT I THINK AN OBJECTIVE
ASSESSMENT WOULD SAY THAT THERE
IS MORE EXCITEMENT AND ENERGY IN
OUR CAMPAIGN.
WE ARE BRINGING OUT WORKING
CLASS PEOPLE WHO HAVE PREVIOUSLY
GIVEN UP ON POLITICS.
WE ARE BRINGING OUT LARGE
NUMBERS OF YOUNG PEOPLE.
SO IF YOU WANT TO WIN IN
NOVEMBER, AND I WANT US TO
DEFEAT REPUBLICANS, SECRETARY
CLINTON WANTS US TO DEFEAT
REPUBLICANS, EVERYBODY IN THIS
ROOM UNDERSTANDS THAT WE DON'T
WANT SOME RIGHT-WING REPUBLICAN
IN THE OVAL OFFICE.
BUT I BELIEVE, QUITE HONESTLY,
THAT I AM THE STRONGEST
CANDIDATE TO DO THAT.
BECAUSE I THINK I CAN DRIVE A
LARGE VOTER TURNOUT, BRINGING IN
NEW ENERGY INTO THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY.
>> LET ME ASK YOU, BECAUSE, AS
YOU KNOW -- AS YOU KNOW, IN THIS
STATE, AN INDEPENDENT, AND THERE
ARE A LOT OF INDEPENDENTS IN
THIS STATE, THEY CAN VOTE IN THE
REPUBLICAN PRIMARY, THEY CAN
VOTE IN THE DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY.
SO THERE ARE SOME VOTERSS OUT
THERE, INDEPENDENT VOTERS, WHO
ARE TRYING TO DECIDE BETWEEN YOU
AND DONALD TRUMP.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO THEM?
>> THIS IS WHAT I WOULD SAY.
I WOULD SAY THAT EXAMINE TRUMP'S
RECORD CAREFULLY.
AND IT IS NOT ONLY HIS BIGOTED
REMARKS AGAINST LATINOS,
SUGGESTING THAT MEXICANS COMING
INTO THIS COUNTRY ARE RAPISTS OR
CRIMINALS, OR DRUG DEALERS, OR
HIS ABSURD REMARK THAT WE SHOULD
NOT ALLOW MUSLIMS INTO THIS
COUNTRY, EVEN ABOVE AND BEYOND
THOSE OUTRAGEOUS, BIGOTED
STATEMENTS, TAKE A LOOK AT WHAT
HE STANDS FOR ECONOMICALLY.
THIS COUNTRY HAS MILLIONS OF
PEOPLE STRUGGLING ECONOMICALLY.
I BELIEVE WE SHOULD RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO 15 BUCKS AN HOUR
OVER THE NEXT COUPLE OF YEARS.
TRUMP SAYS, NO, $7.25 AN HOUR,
WE SHOULD NOT RAISE THE MINIMUM
WAGE.
MOST WORKERS DON'T AGREE WITH
THAT.
TRUMP IN A REPUBLICAN DEBATE
SAID WAGES ARE TOO HIGH IN
AMERICA!
REALLY?
TOO HIGH IN AMERICA?
THAT'S WHAT HE SAID IN A
REPUBLICAN DEBATE.
AND HERE'S THE OTHER ONE THAT
KIND OF BLOWS ME AWAY.
TRUMP IS, AS YOU KNOW, A
WELL-KNOWN SCIENTIST.
BRILLIANT SCIENTIST.
AND HE HAS CONCLUDED AFTER YEARS
OF STUDYING THE ISSUE THAT
CLIMATE CHANGE IS A HOAX.
BROUGHT TO US BY THE CHINESE.
NOW, THAT SHOCKED ME, ANDERSON,
BECAUSE I THOUGHT THAT HE WOULD
HAVE THOUGHT IT WAS A HOAX
BROUGHT TO US BY THE MEXICANS OR
THE MUSLIMS.
THE CHINESE, I DIDN'T QUITE GET.
BUT THE POINT IS, IF YOU EXAMINE
HIS AGENDA, IT IS NOT AN AGENDA
FOR WORKING AMERICANS.
HE WANTS TO GIVE HUNDREDS OF
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN TAX
BREAKS TO THE TOP 0.2%.
SO I THINK AND I WOULD LOVE THE
OPPORTUNITY, FRANKLY, I'M
PREJUDICED, I WANT TRUMP TO WIN
THE REPUBLICAN NOMINATION.
AND I WOULD LOVE THE OPPORTUNITY
TO RUN AGAINST HIM.
I THINK WE WOULD WIN BY A LOT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE JUST HAVE A FEW MORE,
ACTUALLY.
IF YOU'LL TAKE A SEAT.
SO WE JUST HAVE TIME FOR A FEW
MORE QUESTIONS.
WE'VE COVERED A LOT OF IMPORTANT
POLICY ISSUES.
THERE'S A LOT OF FOLKS OUT THERE
WHO REALLY DON'T KNOW MUCH ABOUT
YOU, SO I THOUGHT WE WOULD ASK A
COUPLE OF LIGHTER QUESTIONS, TO
GET TO KNOW YOU.
I READ ONE OF YOUR DAUGHTERS
SAY, THAT IF YOU HAD A CAR OR IF
THEY SOLD
>> DO YOU DO A LARRY DAVID
IMITATION?
>> ANDERSON, I'M GOING TO BE --
I KNOW YOU'VE BEEN IN JOURNALISM
FOR A LONG TIME --
>> ARE YOU DOING LARRY DAVID
RIGHT NOW?
>> I AM LARRY DAVID.
AND YOU DIDN'T GET IT!
>> WHAT'S YOUR PROUDEST MOMENT?
EITHER PROFESSIONALLY OR
PERSONALLY?
>> I THINK MY PROUDEST GENERAL
MOMENT IS BEING MARRIED FOR 27
YEARS, HAVING FOUR GREAT KIDS,
SOME OF THEM ARE HERE TONIGHT,
AND SEVEN VERY BEAUTIFUL
GRANDCHILDREN.
THAT'S MY PROUDEST MOMENT.
>> IF WE ASK -- YOUR WIFE, JANE,
IS HERE.
IF WE ASKED HER TO DESCRIBE YOU
IN ONE WORD, WHAT WORD DO YOU
THINK SHE'D USE?
>> TELL 'EM, JANE.
>> ANTI?
>> INTEGRITY.
>> I THOUGHT YOU SAID
ANTI-GREED, OKAY.
INTEGRITY.
ALL .
>> I WANT TO GIVE YOU 30 SECONDS
TO MAKE A CLOSING ARGUMENT IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE.
>> THANK YOU.
I ENJOYED IT.
THIS IS CALLED DEMOCRACY AND I
LOVED IT.
OUR COUNTRY FACES ENORMOUS
PROBLEMS.
IF I BELIEVE THAT ESTABLISHMENT
POLITICS AND ESTABLISHMENT
ECONOMICS COULD SOLVE THE
PROBLEMS, I WOULD NOT BE RUNNING
FOR PRESIDENT.
THE SAD TRUTH IS THAT WE HAVE A
RIGGED ECONOMIC SYSTEM, PEOPLE
ARE WORKING LONGER HOURS FOR LOW
WAGES, ALMOST ALL NEW WEALTH AND
INCOME IS GOING TO THE TOP 1%.
WE HAVE A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM, WHICH IS
UNDERMINING DEMOCRACY AND
ALLOWING BILLIONAIRES TO BUY
ELECTIONS.
IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, I WILL DO
MY BEST, WORKING WITH THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE AS WE REVITALIZE
OUR DEMOCRACY TO TAKE THOSE
ISSUES ON TO REBUILD THE
AMERICAN MIDDLE CLASS AND BECOME
THE COUNTRY THAT ALL OF US KNOW
THAT WE HAVE THE POTENTIAL TO
BE.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
WHEN WE COME BACK, HILLARY
CLINTON TAKES THE STAGE, TAKING
QUESTIONS FROM THE AUDIENCE.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC TOWN HALL.
WE HEARD FROM DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATE BERNIE SANDERS.
PLEASE WELCOME SECRETARY OF
STATE HILLARY CLINTON.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> HELLO.
>> WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> YOU'VE OBVIOUSLY HAD A PRETTY
INCREDIBLE PAST SEVERAL DAYS.
NEW HAMPSHIRE HAS ALWAYS BEEN
GOOD TO THE CLINTONS.
HOW DOES IT FEEL OUT THERE?
>> IT FEELS GREAT.
I'VE HAD JUST AN AMAZING TIME.
WE LANDED IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
NIGHT FROM IOWA STILL PRETTY
PUMPED UP ABOUT WINNING THERE
AND THEN GOT TO WORK THE NEXT
DAY AND I'M SEEING A LOT OF OLD
FRIENDS, MEETING A LOT OF NEW
PEOPLE.
I HAVE AN UPHILL CLIMB AND I'M
GOING TO CLIMB AS HIGH AND HARD
AS I CAN BECAUSE I WANT TO MAKE
MY CASE FOR THE PEOPLE OF NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
AS YOU SAID, THEY'RE PEOPLE THAT
I FEEL VERY CLOSE TO.
THEY'VE BEEN GOOD TO MY HUSBAND,
TO ME, MY FAMILY.
BUT WHAT'S MOST IMPORTANT IS THE
FIRST IN THE NATION PRIMARY.
IT TRULY IS A GREAT OPPORTUNITY
TO GET OUT THERE, EXPLAIN WHAT
YOU WANT TO DO AS PRESIDENT,
PRESENT YOUR IDEAS AND GET
VETTED BY THE PEOPLE OF NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
>> BERNIE SANDERS JUST A SHORT
TIME AGO SAID HE IS THE UNDERDOG
HERE.
YOUR CAMPAIGN HAS SAID HE COMES
FROM NEIGHBORING VERMONT, YOU
GUYS ARE DOWN IN THE POLLS.
DO YOU FEEL YOU DO BETTER WHEN
YOU'RE FIGHTING FROM BEHIND?
>> YOU KNOW, I DON'T KNOW.
I --
>> DOES IT BRING OUT SOMETHING
IN YOU?
>> WELL, THE INTENSITY OF THE
EXPERIENCE AND THE IMPORTANCE OF
TRYING TO CONVEY WHAT'S AT STAKE
IN THIS ELECTION BECAUSE TO ME
OBVIOUSLY TUESDAY'S A REALLY BIG
DEAL WITH THE PRIMARY, BUT THE
GOAL HAS TO BE TO PREVENT THE
REPUBLICANS FROM GETTING BACK
INTO THE WHITE HOUSE AND UNDOING
ALL THE PROGRESS THAT HAS BEEN
MADE UNDER PRESIDENT OBAMA.
AND SO I -- I'M VERY PROUD OF
THE CAMPAIGN THAT SENATOR
SANDERS AND I ARE RUNNING.
I MEAN, WE REALLY HAVE FOCUSED
ON ISSUES.
WE SHARE A LOT OF THE SAME BIG
PROGRESSIVE GOALS, BUT WE HAVE
DIFFERENT WAYS OF GOING ABOUT
THEM, WE BRING DIFFERENT
EXPERIENCES, BUT WE ARE
CONTRASTING ON ISSUES, COMPARED
TO THE REPUBLICANS WHO I THINK
ARE CONTRASTING ON INSULTS.
AND I THINK IT'S A BETTER
CONTEST WHERE WE CAN TAKE OUR
IDEAS TO GROUPS LIKE THIS
THROUGHOUT NEW HAMPSHIRE, GET
QUESTIONS, HAVE PEOPLE VET THEM
AND THEN LET THE VOTERS MAKE UP
THEIR MINDS.
>> YOU TALK ABOUT PROGRESSIVE
VALUES.
EARLIER IN THE DAY SENATOR
SANDERS WAS ASKED IF YOU WERE
PROGRESSIVE.
HE SAID SOME DAYS.
ARE YOU REALLY PROGRESSIVE?
IN THE PAST YOU SAID YOU PLEAD
GUILTY TO BEING A MODERATE.
>> YOU ASKED ME THIS QUESTION IN
THE FIRST DEBATE, RIGHT?
>> I DID.
IT'S COMING UP AGAIN TODAY.
>> I SAID I'M A PROGRESSIVE WHO
LIKES TO GET THINGS DONE.
I WAS SOMEWHAT AMAZED TODAY THAT
SENATOR SANDERS SET HIMSELF UP
TO BE THE GATEKEEPER ON WHO IS
THE PROGRESSIVE BECAUSE UNDER
THE DEFINITION FLYING AROUND ON
TWITTER AND STATEMENTS BY THE
CAMPAIGN, BARACK OBAMA WOULD NOT
BE A PROGRESSIVE, JOE BIDEN
WOULD NOT BE A PROGRESSIVE,
JEANNE SHAHEEN WOULD NOT BE A
PROGRESSIVE.
EVEN THE LATE, GREAT SENATOR
PAUL WELLSTONE WOULD NOT BE A
PROGRESSIVE.
SO I'M NOT GOING TO LET THAT
BOTHER ME.
I KNOW WHERE I STAND.
I KNOW WHO STANDS WITH ME.
I KNOW WHAT I'VE DONE.
BUT I DON'T THINK IT HELPS FOR
THE SENATOR TO BE MAKING THOSE
KINDS OF COMPARISONS BECAUSE
CLEARLY WE ALL SHARE A LOT OF
THE SAME HOPES AND ASPIRATIONS
FOR OUR COUNTRY THAT WE WANT TO
SEE ACHIEVED, AND I DON'T THINK
IT'S APPROPRIATE THAT IF PLANNED
PARENTHOOD ENDORSES ME OR THE
HUMAN RIGHTS CAMPAIGN ENDORSES
ME, YOU KNOW, THEY'RE THROWN OUT
OF THE PROGRESSIVE WING AND PUT
INTO THE ESTABLISHMENT.
THAT'S JUST NOT ANYTHING WE NEED
TO DO.
LET'S HAVE A GOOD CONTEST OF
IDEAS, LET'S CONTRAST WHERE WE
STAND AND THAT'S WHAT I INTEND
TO DO FOR THE NEXT COUPLE OF
DAYS.
>> IT WOULD OBVIOUSLY BE
HISTORIC IF YOU WERE ELECTED
PRESIDENT.
>> YOU THINK SO?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I'VE STUDIED A LITTLE BIT OF
HISTORY.
BUT IT SEEMS LIKE YOUNG WOMEN
AREN'T RALLYING TO THIS
POTENTIALLY HISTORIC HOME.
I SAY THIS IN IOWA.
AMONG WOMEN UNDER 30, SENATOR
SANDERS BEAT YOU BY 70 POINTS.
THAT'S AMAZING.
LOOK, YOU KNOW, I WAS VERY
FORTUNATE TO HAVE A GREAT TEAM
OF YOUNG PEOPLE, MEN AND WOMEN,
SUPPORTING ME.
BUT I ACCEPT THE FACT THAT I
HAVE WORK TO DO TO CONVEY WHAT I
STAND FOR, WHAT I'VE
ACCOMPLISHED, WHAT WANT TO DO
FOR YOUNG PEOPLE IN OUR COUNTRY.
>> WHY DO YOU THINK IT IS?
>> I DON'T REALLY KNOW,
ANDERSON.
HERE'S WHAT I WANT YOUNG PEOPLE
TO KNOW.
THEY DON'T HAVE TO BE FOR ME,
I'M GOING TO BE FOR THEM.
IT DOESN'T REALLY MATTER.
IF THEY ARE NOT SUPPORTING ME, I
WILL BE THEIR PRESIDENT, I WILL
DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO GIVE THEM
THE OPPORTUNITIES THEY DESERVE.
AS I SPEAK WITH YOUNG PEOPLE
ACROSS THE COUNTRY IN IOWA, NEW
HAMPSHIRE AND ELSEWHERE, I DO
SENSE THIS REAL FEELING OF BEING
SOMEHOW DISADVANTAGED, PUT ON
THE WRONG SIDE OF AMERICAN
OPPORTUNITY, AND I UNDERSTAND
THAT.
I MEAN, THE STUDENT DEBT
PROBLEMS, THE FEELING THAT THE
JOBS THAT ARE OUT THERE ARE NOT
PRODUCING THE KIND OF INCOME OR
OPPORTUNITY THAT YOUNG PEOPLE
BELIEVE THEY SHOULD BE ABLE TO
GET, BUT AT THE SAME TIME I'M SO
IMPRESSED BY THE LEVEL, THE
INTENSITY OF COMMITMENT OF THIS
GENERATION TO REALLY GOING AFTER
DISCRIMINATION, GOING AFTER
RACISM AND SEXISM AND THE KIND
OF ABUSES THAT LGBT COMMUNITY
MEMBERS HAVE, LOOKING FOR WAYS
TO BRING MORE JUSTICE IN THE
ECONOMY AND THE ENVIRONMENT,
FIGHTING CLIMATE CHANGE.
SO I'M IMPRESSED WITH THEM AND
I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING I CAN
TO REACH OUT AND TO EXPLAIN WHY
GOOD IDEAS ON PAPER ARE
IMPORTANT BUT YOU'VE GOT TO BE
ABLE TO TRANSLATE THEM INTO
ACTION TO GET RESULTS FOR
PEOPLE.
I HAVE A LOT OF EXPERIENCE DOING
THAT.
I THINK I CAN DELIVER POSITIVE
CHANGE FOR YOUNG PEOPLE IN OUR
COUNTRY, AND I HOPE TO HAVE THE
CHANCE TO WIN THEIR SUPPORT.
>> WHAT'S WRONG WITH A
REVOLUTION?
>> WELL, THAT'S FOR SENATOR
SANDERS TO EXPLAIN BECAUSE THAT
CERTAINLY IS THE CORE OF HIS
MESSAGE TO YOUNG PEOPLE.
I HAVE A DIFFERENT TAKE ON IT.
I THINK THE PROGRESS THAT WE
HAVE MADE AND PARTICULARLY THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY HAS MADE HAS
BEEN HARD FOUGHT FOR, HARD WON
AND MUST BE DEFENDED.
SO I WANT TO DEFEND THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
IT IS ONE OF THE GREAT
ACCOMPLISHMENTS, NOT ONLY OF
THIS PRESIDENT BUT OF THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY GOING BACK TO
HARRY TRUMAN.
THE REPUBLICANS ARE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU KNOW, THE REPUBLICANS ARE
DETERMINED TO REPEAL IT AND THEY
TRIED 62 TIMES JUST TO TURN IT
BACK TO THE INSURANCE COMPANIES.
SENATOR SANDERS AND I SHARE THE
SAME GOAL.
WE WANT TO GET TO UNIVERSAL
HEALTH CARE COVERAGE.
BEFORE IT WAS CALLED OBAMA CARE
IT WAS CALLED HILLARY CARE, AS
YOU REMEMBER.
>> I REMEMBER.
>> I FOUGHT REALLY HARD, THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES AND DRUG
COMPANIES SPENT MILLIONS AGAINST
ME.
I KNOW WHAT IT'S LIKE TO GO UP
AGAINST THE STATUS QUO AND
SPECIAL INTERESTS.
SO WHEN PRESIDENT OBAMA
SUCCEEDED, I WAS THRILLED.
I DON'T AGREE WITH SENATOR
SANDERS THAT WE SHOULD START
OVER, THAT WE SHOULD THROW OUR
COUNTRY INTO A CONTENTIOUS
NATIONAL DEBATE ABOUT HEALTH
CARE AGAIN.
WE'RE AT 90% COVERAGE.
I'M GOING TO FIX WHAT NEEDS TO
BE FIXED, WE'RE GOING TO MOVE
FROM 90 TO 100, WHICH IS A LOT
EASIER TO GET TO THAN STARTING
AT ZERO TO GET TO 100.
SO WE HAVE A DIFFERENCE.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET SOME OF
THE FOLKS IN OUR AUDIENCE.
>> SURE, SURE.
>> THIS IS DAVE SCANNEL, A HIGH
SCHOOL ENGLISH TEACHER FROM
MANCHESTER.
HE SAID HE'S UNDECIDED.
>> HI.
>> THE NEXT PRESIDENT WILL HAVE
AS MANY AS THREE SUPREME COURT
APPOINTMENTS TO MAKE.
I'M WONDERING BEYOND ABORTION
ARE THERE ANY ISSUES UPON WHICH
YOU WOULD IMPOSE OR ASSERT A
LITMUS TEST?
IF YOUR ANSWER IS NO, AREN'T
ISSUES LIKE MARRIAGE EQUALITY,
CAMPAIGN FINANCE SO VITAL TO WE
AS DEMOCRATS THAT YOU WOULD HAVE
TO KNOW THE AS TO HOW THESE
JUSTICES WOULD RULE BEFORE YOU
MAKE THE NOMINATION?
>> I DO HAVE A LITMUS TEST,
DAVE.
I HAVE A BUNCH OF LITMUS TESTS
BECAUSE I AGREE WITH YOU.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT COULD GET AS
MANY AS THREE APPOINTMENT.
ONE OF THE MANY REASONS WE CAN'T
TURN THE WHITE HOUSE OVER TO THE
REPUBLICANS AGAIN IS BECAUSE OF
THE SPORT.
I'M LOOKING FOR PEOPLE WHO
UNDERSTAND HOW THE WORLD WORKS,
WHO DOESN'T HAVE A KNEE-JERK
REACTION TO SUPPORT BUSINESS, TO
SUPPORT THE IDEA THAT MONEY IS
SPEECH, THAT GUTTED THE VOTING
RIGHTS ACT.
I VOTED FOR THE REAUTHORIZATION
OF THE VOTING RIGHTS ACT WHEN I
WAS IN THE SENATE.
IT PASSED 98-0 BASED ON A VERY
EXTENSIVE SET OF HEARINGS AND
RESEARCH.
SUPREME COURT COMES ALONG, THEY
SUBSTITUTE THEIR JUDGMENT FOR
THE CONGRESS, SIGNED BY GEORGE
W. BUSH.
THAT IS ONE OF OUR PROBLEMS.
THEY HAVE A VIEW THAT I JUST
FUNDAMENTALLY DISAGREE WITH
ABOUT WHAT THE WAY WE HAVE TO
KEEP THE BALANCE OF POWER IN OUR
SOCIETY IS.
SO THEY HAVE GIVEN WAY TOO MUCH
POWER TO CORPORATIONS, THEY HAVE
GIVEN CITIZENS UNITED THE
BIGGEST GIFT TO THE KOCH
BROTHERS, KARL ROVE AND ALL OF
THOSE FOLKS WHOSE VALUES I DON'T
SHARE AND WHO ARE DOING
EVERYTHING THEY CAN TO TRY TO
TURN THE CLOCK BACK.
WE HAVE TO PRESERVE MARRIAGE
EK
EQUALITY, WE HAVE TO GO FURTHER
TO END DISCRIMINATION AGAINST
THE LBGT COMMUNITY, WE HAVE TO
PRESERVE ROE V. WADE, NOT LET IT
BE NIBBLED AWAY OR REPEALED.
WE'VE GOT WORK TO DO.
AND HERE'S HOW I THINK ABOUT IT.
WHEN I WAS A SENATOR, I HAD TO
VOTE ON SUPREME COURT JUSTICES.
I'M LOOKING FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE
ROOTED IN THE REAL WORLD, WHO
KNOW THAT PART OF THE GENIUS OF
OUR SYSTEM, BOTH ECONOMIC AND
GOVERNMENT, IS THIS BALANCE OF
POWER.
IF IT GETS TOO FAR OUT OF WHACK
SO THAT BUSINESS HAS TOO MUCH
POWER, ANY BRANCH OF THE
GOVERNMENT HAS TOO MUCH POWER,
THE DELICATE BALANCE THAT MAKES
UP OUR POLITICAL SYSTEM AND THE
BROAD BASE PROSPERITY WE SHOULD
BE WORKING FOR IN OUR ECONOMY IS
THE WORSE OFF FOR IT.
SO HAVE I VERY STRONG FEELINGS
ABOUT WHAT I AM LOOKING FOR IF I
AM GIVEN THE HONOR OF APPOINTING
SOMEBODY TO THE SUPREME COURT.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET JIM
McKINNON, A DEMOCRAT SAID HE'S
SUPPORTING YOU.
>> MADAM SECRETARY, I'M PLEASED
TO SEE YOU.
THIS MAY COME A LITTLE BIT FROM
RIGHT FIELD BUT IT'S VERY
PERSONAL TO ME AND RESONATES TO
MANY OTHER PEOPLE WHO ARE
ELDERLY DEALING WITH HEALTH
ISSUES.
THE QUESTION IS COMING FROM ME
AS A PERSON WHO IS WALKING WITH
COLON CANCER.
AND I'M WALKING WITH COLON
CANCER WITH THE WORD TERMINAL
VERY MUCH IN MY VOCABULARY,
COMFORTABLY AND SPIRITUALLY.
BUT I WONDER WHAT LEADERSHIP YOU
COULD OFFER WITHIN AN EXECUTIVE
ROLE THAT MIGHT HELP ADVANCE THE
RESPECTFUL CONVERSATION THAT IS
NEEDED AROUND THIS PERSONAL
CHOICE THAT PEOPLE MAY MAKE AS
WE AGE AND DEAL WITH HEALTH
ISSUES OR BE THE CARE GIVERS OF
THOSE PEOPLE TO HELP ENHANCE
THEIR END OF LIFE WITH DIGNITY?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU FOR
BEING HERE, THANK YOU SO MUCH
FOR BEING PART OF THIS GREAT NEW
HAMPSHIRE PRIMARY PROCESS AND
THANK YOU FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
AND I REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR
ASKING THE QUESTION.
I HAVE TO TELL YOU THIS IS THE
FIRST TIME I'VE BEEN ASKED THAT
QUESTION.
>> I FIGURED THAT.
>> YES.
I REALLY --
>> ANY CANDIDATE.
>> AND I THANK YOU FOR IT
BECAUSE WE NEED TO HAVE A
CONVERSATION IN OUR COUNTRY.
THERE ARE STATES, AS YOU KNOW,
THAT ARE MOVING TO OPEN UP THE
OPPORTUNITY WITHOUT CRIMINAL
LIABILITY FOR PEOPLE TO MAKE
THIS DECISION IN CONSULTATION BY
THEIR FAMILIES, EVEN IN SOME
CASES WITH MEDICAL
PROFESSIONALS, BUT THE ISSUE IS
WHETHER THE MEDICAL
PROFESSIONALS WANT TO BE
INVOLVED OR JUST BE COUNSELORS.
SO IT IS A CRUCIAL ISSUE THAT
PEOPLE DESERVE TO UNDERSTAND
FROM THEIR OWN ETHICAL,
RELIGIOUS FAITH-BASED
PERSPECTIVE.
HERE'S HOW I THINK ABOUT IT.
I WANT AS PRESIDENT TO TRY TO
C
CATALYZE THAT DEBATE.
I BELIEVE YOU'RE RIGHT.
THIS IS GOING TO BECOME AN ISSUE
MORE AND MORE OFTEN.
WE ARE ON THE GOOD SIDE HAVING
PEOPLE LIVE LONGER BUT OFTEN
THEN WITH VERY SERIOUS ILLNESSES
THAT THEY CAN BE SUSTAINED ON
BUT AT SOME POINT DON'T WANT TO
CONTINUE WITH THE CHALLENGES
THAT POSES.
SO I DON'T HAVE ANY EASY OR GLIB
ANSWER FOR YOU.
I THINK WOULD I WANT TO REALLY
IMMERSE MYSELF IN THE ETHICAL
WRITINGS, THE HEALTH WRITING,
THE SCIENTIFIC WRITINGS, THE
RELIGIOUS WRITINGS.
I KNOW SOME OTHER COUNTRY, THE
NETHERLANDS AND OTHERS, HAVE A
QUITE OPEN APPROACH.
I'D LIKE TO KNOW WHAT THEIR
EXPERIENCE HAS BEEN BECAUSE WE
HAVE TO BE SURE THAT NOBODY IS
COERCED, NOBODY'S UNDER DURESS
AND THAT IS A DIFFICULT LINE TO
DRAW.
SO I THANK YOU, I THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR RAISING THIS REALLY
IMPORTANT, ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL
QUESTION THAT WE'RE ALL GOING TO
HAVE TO DO SOME THINKING ABOUT.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
>>.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> THIS IS MICHAEL FIELD.
HE'S A MARRIED FATHER OF ONE,
SAID HE'S UNDECIDED, HE'S
LEANING TOWARD SENATOR SANDERS.
>> HI, MICHAEL.
>> HI, SECRETARY CLINTON.
YOU HAVE A HISTORY OF
INTERVENTIONIST FOREIGN POLICY
THAT IS TROUBLING TO MANY
DEMOCRATIC VOTERS INCLUDING
MYSELF.
AS A VOTER OPPOSED TO THE UNITED
STATES BEING THE WORLD'S
POLICEMEN, CAN YOU ASSURE ME YOU
WOULD NOT EXPAND OUR MILITARY
INVOLVEMENT ABROAD?
>> NO, I CAN'T, MICHAEL.
I'D LIKE TO BE ABLE TO SAY THAT
I COULD BUT HERE'S WHAT I CAN
SAY -- I HAVE LEARNED AND I HAVE
BEEN REALLY IN THE CRUCIBLE OF
MAKING A LOT OF HARD DECISIONS
OVER THE LAST YEARS AND MILITARY
FORCE MUST ALWAYS BE A LAST
RESORT, NOT A FIRST CHOICE.
THAT IS ONE OF THE BIGGEST
DIFFERENCES BETWEEN ME AND THE
REPUBLICANS.
I WORKED VERY HARD AS SECRETARY
OF STATE TO DO WHAT I COULD
DIPLOMATICALLY TO AVOID
CONFLICT.
THAT'S WHY I WORKED TO GET THE
COALITION TOGETHER TO IMPOSE
SANCTIONS ON IRAN SO THAT WE
COULD GET THEM TO THE
NEGOTIATING TABLE IN ORDER TO
TEST WHETHER WE COULD GET AN
AGREEMENT TO PUT A NUCLEAR
WEAPONS AGREEMENT IN PLACE.
I DID THAT IN LARGE MEASURE
MOTIVATED BY MY DEEP CONCERN
THAT THE ABSENCE OF EFFECTIVE
DIPLOMACY MIGHT VERY WELL HAVE
SPARKED AN ARMS RACE AMONG SOME
VERY UNSTABLE NATIONS IN THE
REGION AND MAYBE EVEN LED TO
CONFLICT.
I WILL DO EVERYTHING I POSSIBLY
CAN TO AVOID SENDING AMERICAN
TROOPS ABROAD, GETTING US
INVOLVED IN MILITARY CONFLICTS,
BUT I CAN'T IN GOOD CONSCIENCE
STAND HERE AND TELL YOU THAT
THERE WOULD NEVER BE ANY
CIRCUMSTANCES IN THE TIME THAT I
SERVED AS PRESIDENT WHERE IT
VERY WELL MIGHT BE IN AMERICA'S
BEST VITAL NATIONAL SECURITY
INTEREST.
SO I WANT TO BE HONEST WITH YOU.
I WILL DO WHAT I CAN, I WILL
STAND AGAINST ADVENTURISM,
ILL-THOUGHT OUT MISSIONS.
I WILL NOT SEND AMERICAN COMBAT
TROOPS TO IRAQ OR SYRIA, THAT IS
OFF THE TABLE THAT, WILL BE A
TABLE MISTAKE.
WE WILL CONTINUE TO USE SPECIAL
FORCES AND WE HAVE TO BECAUSE OF
THE KINDS OF THREATS WE FACE,
YOU KNOW, THE NETWORK OF
TERRORIST ORGANIZATIONS, NOT
JUST ISIS BUT OTHERS WHO ARE
PART OF THIS UNFORTUNATE NETWORK
THAT STRETCHES FROM NORTH AFRICA
TO SOUTH ASIA, POSE SERIOUS
THREATS TO FRIENDS, ALLIES AND
PARTNERS AS WELL AS TO
OURSELVES.
AND WE'VE GOT TO KEEP OUR
COUNTRY SAFE AND WE HAVE TO WORK
WITH THE REST OF THE WORLD TO
TRY TO DEFEAT ISIS, TO END THAT
TERRORIST THREAT.
SO I WILL BE A VERY CAREFUL,
DELIBERATE DECISION-MAKER WHEN
FACING HARD CHOICES BECAUSE I
KNOW WHAT'S AT STAKE.
AND I KNOW YOU CAN UNDERSTAND
WHY THERE CAN'T BE FROM ME
ANYWAY A BLANKET STATEMENT BUT I
WANT TO ASSURE YOU I WILL BE
TRANSPARENT, I WILL BE OPEN AND
I WILL EXPLAIN TO THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE IF ANY OCCASION ARISES
WHERE WE DO HAVE TO TAKE
MILITARY ACTION TO PROTECT
OURSELVES OR OUR CLOSE FRIENDS
AND PARTNERS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT TO FOLLOW UP.
YESTERDAY ON CAPITOL HILL THE
SENATE ARMED SERVICES COMMITTEE,
THE COMMANDER OF THE MARINE
CORPS SAID "ALL ELIGIBLE
QUALIFIED MEN AND WOMEN SHOULD
REGISTER FOR THE DRAFT," TALKING
ABOUT SELECTIVE SERVICE.
DO YOU HAVE THINK WOMEN SHOULD
ALSO HAVE TO REGISTER FOR
SELECTIVE SERVICE LIKE MEN.
>> YOU KNOW, THE FIRST TIME I
HEARD THAT YESTERDAY AND HERE'S
THE REASONING AS BEST I
UNDERSTAND FROM LISTENING TO THE
TESTIMONY EXCERPTS, THAT IF
WE'RE GOING TO OPEN COMBAT
POSITIONS TO QUALIFIED WOMEN SO
THAT THEY CAN COMPETE TO BE ARMY
RANGERS, THEY CAN COMPETE TO BE
NAVY SEALS, THEY CAN COMPETE TO
BE INFANTRY OFFICERS IN THE MAN
REI
-- MARINES, WE HAVE EXPANDED
THE DEFINITION.
I THINK IT'S NECESSARY TO GO AS
FAR AS OUR MILITARY OFFICERS ARE
RECOMMENDING.
FROM MY PERSPECTIVE, THE ALL
VOLUNTEER MILITARY HAS WORKED
AND WE SHOULD NOT DO ANYTHING
THAT UNDERMINES IT BECAUSE IT
HAS PROVIDED A SOLID CORE OF
PEOPLE WHO ARE WILLING TO SERVE
OUR COUNTRY.
THE IDEA OF HAVING EVERYBODY
REGISTER CONCERNS ME A LITTLE
BIT,S UNLESS WE HAVE A BETTER
IDEA WHERE IT'S GOING TO COME
OUT.
WHERE I WANT PEOPLE TO REGISTER,
I WANT EVERY PERSON TO REGISTER
AT THE AGE OF 18 TO BE ABLE TO
VOTE AUTOMATICALLY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I THINK IF WE HAD, YOU KNOW,
IF WE HAD A SYSTEM LIKE THAT, I
WOULD BE VERY PLEASED ABOUT IT.
I HAVE A HARD TIME IMAGINING THE
KIND OF NATIONAL EMERGENCY THAT
WOULD REQUIRE THE USE OF THE
SELECTIVE SERVICE SYSTEM.
SO I JUST HAVE TO BE BETTER
INFORMED ABOUT WHY THEY'RE
MAKING THIS RECOMMENDATION.
>> I WANT TO YOU MEET REBECCA
HU
HUTCHINSON, A FORMER STATE
REPRESENTATIVE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
SHE SAID SHE'S UNDECIDED AND HAS
A QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> I FEEL I HAVE A FOLLOW-UP TO
THE PREVIOUS QUESTION.
YOU CLEARLY HAVE VERY IMPRESSIVE
FOREIGN POLICY EXPERIENCE, AND
I'VE HEARD YOU POINT OUT TO US
THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA CHOSE YOU
AND TRUSTED YOU TO BE HIS
SECRETARY OF STATE, BUT I GET
STUCK WHEN I THINK ABOUT YOU
VOTED FOR THE IRAQ WAR, WHICH
YOU NOW SAY WAS A MISTAKE.
WHAT HAVE YOU LEARNED SINCE THAT
VOTE THAT COULD GIVE ME
CONFIDENCE THAT YOU WOULDN'T
MAKE A MISTAKE OF THAT MAGNITUDE
AGAIN?
>> OH, I THINK THAT'S A VERY
FAIR QUESTION.
YOU KNOW, I DID MAKE A MISTAKE
AND I ADMITTED THAT I MADE A
MISTAKE AND IN LARGE MEASURE
THAT MISTAKE REALLY AROSE FROM
THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION'S
APPROACH TO WHAT THEY THOUGHT
THEY COULD ACCOMPLISH IN IRAQ.
THE VERY EXPLICIT APPEAL THAT
PRESIDENT BUSH MADE BEFORE
ANNOUNCING THE INVASION THAT
GETTING THAT VOTE WOULD BE A
STRONG PIECE OF LEVERAGE IN
ORDER TO FINISH THE INSPECTIONS.
AND HE MADE THAT COMMENT.
AND THE U.N. INSPECTOR SAID GIVE
US THE TIME, WE WILL FIND OUT,
GIVE US THE HAMMER OVER THEIR
HEAD, NAMELY THE VOTE, AND WE
WILL BE ABLE TO FIND OUT WHAT
THEY STILL HAVE IN TERMS OF WMD.
AND THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION
DIDN'T GIVE THEM THE TIME.
AND THAT WAS A BREACH OF FAITH
IN MY VIEW.
BUT, YOU KNOW, I GAVE THEM THE
VOTE IN LARGE MEASURE BECAUSE I
THOUGHT THAT WOULD GIVE US THE
TIME AND WE WOULD FIND OUT SHORT
OF INVASION.
TURNED OUT NOT TO BE AND I
REALLY REGRET THAT THAT'S THE
WAY PRESIDENT BUSH PROCEEDED.
THAT WOULD NOT BE SOMETHING YOU
WOULD HAVE TO BE WORRY ABOUT
WITH ME.
IF I TELL YOU WE'RE GOING TO DO
DIPLOMACY, WE'RE GOING TO HANG
TOUGH, WE'RE GOING TO GET
ANSWERS, THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT WE
WILL DO.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET SHAWN
BURKE, A DEMOCRAT FROM DAERRY,
HE'S A SUPPORTER YOURS.
>> ONCE YOU GET ELECTED, HOW ARE
YOU GOING TO DEFEND YOURSELF
AGAINST RIGHT-WING ATTACKS?
>> WELL, SHAWN, I'VE HAD A LOT
OF PRACTICE.
YOU KNOW, I CAN LAUGH UP HERE
BUT IT'S NOT EASY.
IT IS A BRUTAL EXPERIENCE.
WHEN IT FIRST STARTED HAPPENING
TO ME BACK IN THE EARLY 90s WHEN
I WAS WORKING ON HEALTH CARE
AND, YOU KNOW, I WAS JUST
UNRECOGNIZABLE TO MYSELF WHAT
TALK RADIO WAS SAYING, WHAT
REPUBLICAN MEMBERS OF CONGRESS
AND THEIR ALLIES WERE SAYING.
I WAS JUST STUNNED.
I COULD NOT UNDERSTAND HOW THEY
GOT AWAY WITH IT.
AND I HAVE HAD TO LEARN TO TAKE
CRITICISM SERIOUSLY BUT NOT
PERSONALLY.
AND BY THAT I MEAN THIS -- THE
VERY FAIR QUESTION FROM REBECCA.
PEOPLE ASK YOU QUESTIONS OR
CRITICIZE YOU, THINK ABOUT IT
SERIOUSLY.
THERE ARE LESSONS TO BE LEARNED
OFTEN FROM PEOPLE WHO DON'T
AGREE WITH YOU, BUT DON'T TAKE
IT PERSONALLY SO THAT IT JUST
PARALYZES YOU, LITERALLY STOPS
YOU IN YOUR TRACKS.
SO NOW THAT I'VE BEEN THROUGH
THIS FOR SO MANY YEARS, SHAWN,
MY UNDERSTANDING OF THE
POLITICAL TACTICS THAT THE OTHER
SIDE USES IS PRETTY WELL VERSED.
THEY PLAY TO KEEP.
THEY PLAY TO DESTROY.
THEY ARE CONSTANTLY DOING
WHATEVER THEY CAN TO WIN.
AND THEY HAVE A HISTORY NOW
GOING BACK, YOU KNOW, 35, 36
YEARS OF GOING AFTER PEOPLE WHO
THEY BELIEVE THEY CAN'T
OTHERWISE STOP UNLESS THEY
ENGAGE IN NEGATIVE ATTACKS.
SO RIGHT NOW, FOR EXAMPLE, A
COUPLE OF HEDGE FUND
BILLIONAIRES HAVE STARTED A
SUPER PAC TO RUN ADS AGAINST ME.
CALL ROVE HAS SLOLICITED MONEY O
RUN ADS AGAINST ME.
CLEARLY THEY KNOW THEY MEAN WHAT
I SAY AND I WILL DO WHAT I SAY
AND I WILL STAND IN THEIR WAY
AND STOP THEM FROM PERPETUATING
A AN AGENDA ON AMERICA THAT IS
BAD FOR OUR DEMOCRACY, BAD FOUR
OUR ECONOMY, BAD FOR OUR
SOCIETY.
SO MUCH I KNOW I HAVE TO KEEP
DEFENDING AGAINST THEM BUT I'M
THE ONE WHO HAS THE EXPERIENCE
TO DO THAT.
IT'S UNLIKE ANYTHING YOU'VE EVER
GONE THROUGH TO BE THE SUBJECT
OF TENS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
OF UNTRUE, TERRIBLE ATTACKS.
AND NOW THE KOCH BROTHERS SAY
THEY'RE GOING TO SPEND $750
MILLION TO DEFEAT THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINEE.
I'M STILL STANDING AND I WILL BE
STANDING SO DON'T WORRY ABOUT
THAT.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> LET ME JUST QUICKLY FOLLOW
UP.
YOU MENTIONED A TAX ON THE EARLY
90s.
DO YOU STILL BELIEVE THERE'S A
VAST RIGHT-WING CONSPIRACY.
>> DON'T YOU?
>> I'M ASKING YOU.
>> YEAH.
IT'S GOTTEN EVEN BETTER FUNDED.
YOU KNOW, THEY BROUGHT IN SOME
NEW MULTI-BILLIONAIRES TO PUMP
THE MONEY IN.
LOOK, THESE GUYS PLAY FOR KEEPS.
THEY WANT TO CONTROL OUR
COUNTRY.
SENATOR SANDERS AND I AGREE ON
THAT COMPLETELY.
THEY WANT TO RIG THE ECONOMY SO
THEY CONTINUE TO GET RICHER AND
RICHER, THEY COULD CARE LESS
ABOUT INCOME INEQUALITY.
THEY SOLVE THEIR CONSCIENCES BY
GIVING BIG MONEY TO
PHILANTHROPY, GETTING BIG
PICTURES OF THEM STANDING IN
FRONT OF WHATEVER CHARITY THEY
DONATED TO BUT MAKE NO MISTAKE,
THEY WANT TO DESTROY UNIONS,
THEY WANT TO GO AFTER ANY
ECONOMIC INTERESTS THAT THEY
DON'T BELIEVE THEY CAN CONTROL.
THEY WANT TO DESTROY OUR BALANCE
OF POWER.
THEY WANT TO GO AFTER OUR
POLITICAL SYSTEM AND FILL IT
WITH PEOPLE WHO WILL DO THEIR
BIDDING.
I SAID TODAY IN DOVER, YOU KNOW,
I DON'T THINK ALL OF THE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES ARE SO ILL
INFORMED ABOUT CLIMATE CHANGE
THAT THEY SAY THEY DON'T KNOW
BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT SCIENTISTS.
THEY'RE JUST DOING THE BIDDING
OF THE KOCH BROTHERS.
THEY'RE TOLD DON'T YOU DARE SAY
CLIMATE CHANGE IS REAL BECAUSE
WE'RE IN THE FOSSIL FUEL
BUSINESS.
SO THIS IS EXACTLY WHAT THEY ARE
UP TOP.
AND, YES, IT IS PROBABLY --
LOOK, AT THIS POINT IT'S
PROBABLY NOT CORRECT TO SAY IT'S
A CONSPIRACY BECAUSE IT'S OUT IN
THE OPEN.
THERE IS NO DOUBT ABOUT WHAT
THEY'RE DOING AND WHO THE
PLAYERS ARE AND WHAT THEY'RE
TRYING TO ACHIEVE AND THEY'RE
SHOPPING AMONG THE REPUBLICANS
CANDIDATES TO FIGURE OUT WHO
AMONG THEM WILL MOST LIKELY DO
THEIR BIDDING.
SO JUST KNOW WHAT WE'RE UP
AGAINST BECAUSE IT'S REAL AND
WE'RE GOING TO BEAT IT.
BUT IT'S GOING TO TAKE EVERYBODY
WORKING TOGETHER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> MEET ALLISON.
SHE'S A TORN BETWEEN YOU AND
SENATOR SANDERS.
>> THANK YOU FOR ALL YOU'VE DONE
FOR OUR COUNTRY AND FOR WOMEN.
SOME OF THE FACTORS HAVE ERODED
TRUST IN YOU.
WHAT WILL YOU DO TO REGAIN THAT
TRUST, ENGENDER TRUST IN
AMERICANS AND ME.
>> THANK YOU FOR SAYING IT'S
RELATED TO WHAT I JUST SAID.
AND I ACKNOWLEDGE THIS AS
PERSONALLY PAINFUL AS IT IS.
WHEN YOU HAVE BEEN SUBJECTED TO
THE LEVEL, THE VELOCITY OF
ATTACKS THAT COME EVERY DAY,
EVEN IF THERE IS NO FACTUAL
BASIS TO IT, IT'S JUST NORMAL
FOR PEOPLE TO SAY, GOSH, THERE'S
GOT TO BE SOMETHING, WHY DO THEY
KEEP SAYING THIS AND THEN WE DO
THAT.
I TESTIFY FOR 11 HOURS, THERE'S
NOTHING TO BENGHAZI, THEY DON'T
GIVE IT UP, THEY KEEP COMING
AFTER IT.
SO I KNOW THAT I HAVE TO REALLY
DEMONSTRATE AS CLEARLY AS I CAN
WHO I AM, WHAT I STAND FOR AND
WHAT I'VE ALWAYS DONE.
I'VE ALWAYS BEEN GUIDED BY THE
SAME VALUES, I HAVE ALWAYS
LISTENED TO PEOPLE AND I'VE
ALWAYS WORKED AS HARD AS I COULD
TO PRODUCE RESULTS FOR PEOPLE.
SO WHEN I RAN FOR THE SENATE THE
FIRST TIME AND I WAS OUT THERE
AND, YOU KNOW, PEOPLE WERE
BARRAGING, I WAS RUNNING FIRST
AGAINST RUDY GIULIANI AND ALL OF
THAT, I WAS ABLE TO JUST KEEP
GOING AND TELL PEOPLE HERE'S WHO
I AM, HERE'S WHAT I DO, I WANT
TO DO THIS WITH YOU AND I WON
AND THEN SINCE YEARS LATER WHEN
I RAN, I GOT A HIGHER PERCENTAGE
AND THEN I DID HAVE, AS YOU ALL
REMEMBER, A REALLY TOUGH
CAMPAIGN AGAINST THEN SENATOR
OBAMA.
WE SAW EACH OTHER VERY UP CLOSE
AND PERSONAL.
AND HE WINS AND TURNS AND ASKS
ME TO BE HIS SECRETARY OF STATE
BECAUSE HE TRUSTS ME, HE TRUSTS
MY JUDGMENT, HE TRUSTS MY
EXPERIENCE.
SO ALL I CAN DO IS TO JUST GET
UP EVERY DAY AND WORK TO DO WHAT
I BELIEVE OUR COUNTRY NEEDS,
FIND WAYS TO HELP PEOPLE,
WHETHER IT'S ON MENTAL HEALTH OR
ADDICTION OR AUTISM OR STUDENT
LOANS, WHATEVER IT MIGHT BE.
AND I TRUST THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
I TRUST THE PEOPLE OF NEW
HAMPSHIRE TO SEE MY LIFETIME OF
WORK AND SERVICE AND TO SORT OUT
ALL OF THE STATIC AND TO KNOW
THAT I WILL WORK MY HEART OUT
FOR YOU.
AND THAT'S WHAT I HOPE YOU WILL
UNDERSTAND.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT TO WELCOME RABBI
SEVETTE, HE'S AN INDEPENDENT,
SAID HE'S UNSURE OF HIS VOTE.
>> ANOTHER RABBI TAUGHT THAT
EVERY PERSON HAS TO HAVE TWO
POCKETS AND IN EACH POCKET THEY
CARRY A DIFFERENT NOTE.
IN ONE POCKET IT SAYS THE
UNIVERSE WAS CREATED FOR ME AND
IN THE OTHER POCKET THE NOTE
SAYS I AM JUST DUST AND, ASHES.
I WANT YOU TO TAKE A MOMENT AND
TELL US WHAT YOU WOULD TELL BUS
YOUR TWO POCKETS.
HOW DO YOU CULTIVATE THE EGO
THAT WE ALL KNOW YOU MUST HAVE,
A PERSON MUST HAVE TO BE THE
LEADER OF THE FREE WORLD AND
ALSO THE HUMILITY TO RECOGNIZE
THAT YOU CAN'T BE EXPECTED TO BE
WISE ABOUT ALL THE THINGS THAT
THE PRESIDENT HAS TO BE
RESPONSIBLE FOR.
>> ANOTHER ABSOLUTELY WONDERFUL
QUESTION.
THANK YOU, RABBI.
I THINK ABOUT THIS A LOT.
I FEEL VERY FORTUNATE THAT I AM
A PERSON OF FAITH, THAT I WAS
RAISED IN MY CHURCH AND THAT I
HAVE HAD TO DEAL AND STRUGGLE
WITH A LOT OF THESE ISSUES ABOUT
AMBITION AND HUMILITY, ABOUT
SERVICE AND SELF-GRATIFICATION,
ALL OF THE HUMAN QUESTIONS THAT
ALL OF US DEAL WITH BUT WHEN YOU
PUT YOURSELF OUT INTO THE PUBLIC
ARENA, I THINK IT'S INCUMBENT
UPON YOU TO BE AS SELF-CONSCIOUS
AS POSSIBLE.
THIS IS HARD FOR ME.
YOU KNOW, I NEVER THOUGHT I'D BE
STANDING ON A STAGE HERE ASKING
FOR PEOPLE TO VOTE FOR ME OF
PRESIDENT.
I ALWAYS WANTED TO BE OF
SERVICE.
I MET MY HUSBAND WHO WAS SUCH A
NATURAL, KNEW EXACTLY WHAT HE
WANTED TO DO.
I WAS HAPPY TO SUPPORT HIM WHILE
I WORKED IN THE CHILDREN'S
DEFENSE FUND AND LEGAL SERVICES
AND TAUGHT LAW AND HAD OUR
DAUGHTER.
I NEVER THOUGHT I WOULD DO THIS.
SO I HAVE HAD TO COME TO GRIPS
WITH HOW MUCH MORE DIFFICULT IT
OFTEN IS FOR ME TO TALK ABOUT
MYSELF THAN TO TALK ABOUT WHAT I
WANT TO DO FOR OTHER PEOPLE OR
TO TELL STORIES ABOUT, YOU KNOW,
THE MAN I MET IN ROCHESTER WHOSE
AIDS MEDICINE IS NO LONGER
AFFORDABLE.
THAT CAN GRIP ME AND MAKE ME
FEEL LIKE THERE'S SOMETHING I
CAN DO ABOUT THAT.
SO I'M CONSTANTLY TRYING TO
BALANCE HOW DO I ASSUME THE
MANTLE OF A POSITION AS
ESSENTIALLY AUGUSTE AS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES AND NOT
LOSE TRACK OF WHO I AM AND WHAT
I BELIEVE IN AND DO WHAT I WANT
TO DO TO SERVE.
I HAVE THAT DIALOGUE AT LEAST
ONCE A DAY IN SOME SETTING OR
ANOTHER.
AND I DON'T KNOW THAT THERE IS
ANY EVER ABSOLUTE ANSWER.
LIKE, OKAY, UNIVERSE, HERE I AM,
WATCH ME ROAR OR, OH, MY GOSH, I
CAN'T DO IT, IT'S JUST
OVERWHELMING, I HAVE TO RETREAT.
IT'S THAT BALANCE THAT I KEEP TO
TRY TO FIND IN MY LIFE THAT I
WANT TO SEE BACK IN OUR COUNTRY
AND IT WILL BE SOMETHING THAT I
CONTINUE TO TALK ABOUT WITH A
GROUP OF FAITH ADVISERS WHO ARE
CLOSE TO ME.
I GREAT SCRIPTURE LESSON EVERY
MORNING FROM A MINISTER THAT I
HAVE A REALLY CLOSE PERSONAL
RELATIONSHIP WITH.
AND, YOU KNOW, IT JUST GETS ME
GROUNDED.
HE GETS UP REALLY EARLY, SENDS
IT TO ME SO THERE IT IS IN MY IN
BOX AT 5 A.M. I HAVE FRIENDS WHO
ARE RABBIS WHO SEND ME NOTES,
GIVE ME READINGS THAT ARE GOING
TO BE DISCUSSED IN SERVICES.
SO I REALLY APPRECIATE ALL THAT
INCOMING.
AND THE FINAL THING I WOULD SAY
BECAUSE, AGAIN, IT'S NOT
ANYTHING I'VE EVER TALKED ABOUT
THIS MUCH PUBLICLY, EVERYBODY
KNOWS I HAVE LIVED A VERY PUBLIC
LIFE FOR THE LAST 25 OR SO
YEARS.
AND SO I'VE HAD TO BE IN PUBLIC
DEALING WITH SOME VERY DIFFICULT
ISSUES AND PERSONAL ISSUES,
POLITICAL, PUBLIC ISSUES.
AND I READ A TREATMENT OF THE
PROD CALL SON BY A JESUIT POET
AND I READ THAT PARABLE AND
THERE WAS A LINE IN IT THAT
BECAME A LIFELINE FOR ME AND IT
BASICALLY IS PRACTICE THE
DISCIPLINE OF GRATITUDE.
SO REGARDLESS OF HOW HARD THE
DAYS ARE, HOW DIFFICULT OF THE
DECISIONS ARE, BE GRATEFUL, BE
GRATEFUL FOR BEING A HUMAN
BEING, BEING PART OF THE
UNIVERSE, BE GRATEFUL FOR YOUR
LIMITATIONS, KNOW THAT YOU HAVE
TO REACH OUT TO HAVE MORE PEOPLE
WITH YOU TO SUPPORT YOU, TO
ADVISE YOU, LISTEN TO YOUR
CRITICS, ANSWER THE QUESTIONS,
BUT AT THE END BE GRATEFUL,
PRACTICE THE DISCIPLINE OF
GRATITUDE AND THAT HAS HELPED ME
ENORMOUSLY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE MORE
QUESTIONS FROM THE AUDIENCE FOR
SECRETARY CLINTON WHEN WE COME
BACK.
I thin
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL AT THE DERRY OPERA HOUSE IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE.
I WANT TO PLAY A PIECE OF VIDEO
AND GET YOU TO RESPOND.
>> WE DO NOT REPRESENT THE
INTERESTS OF THE BILLIONAIRE
CLASS, WALL STREET OR CORPORATE
AMERICA.
WE DON'T WANT THEIR MONEY.
AND I AM VERY PROUD TO TELL YOU
THAT WE ARE THE ONLY CANDIDATE
ON THE DEMOCRATIC SIDE WITHOUT A
SUPER PAC.
AND THE REASON THAT WE HAVE DONE
SO WELL HERE IN IOWA, THE REASON
I BELIEVE WE'RE GOING TO DO SO
WELL IN NEW HAMPSHIRE AND IN THE
OTHER STATES THAT FOLLOW, THE
REASON IS THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
ARE SAYING NO TO A RIGGED
ECONOMY!
>> WE GOT A NUMBER OF QUESTIONS,
EVEN FROM PEOPLE WHO SUPPORT
YOUR POLICIES, WHO SAY THEY DO
BELIEVE THAT YOU REPRESENT THE
INTERESTS OF WALL STREET AND
CORPORATE AMERICA.
HOW DO YOU RESPOND?
>> LOOK, THAT'S JUST NOT THE
CASE.
AND I DID REPRESENT NEW YORK
OBVIOUSLY.
THERE WAS NO DOUBT THAT I TOOK
ON A LOT OF GOING ON DOWN ON
WALL STREET, INCLUDING CALLING
THEM OUT ON THE MORTGAGE ISSUES,
CALLING FOR A CONSUMER FINANCIAL
PROTECTION BUREAU, EVEN BEFORE
WE GOT ONE CREATED, CALLING FOR
CHANGES IN CEO PAY.
BUT I HONESTLY THINK THAT THE
BEST ANSWER TO THIS IS THE FACT
THAT EVERYBODY THAT I KNOW WHO
LOOKS AT WHAT'S HAPPENING IN
THIS CAMPAIGN SEES THE SAME
THING.
THE WALL STREET INTERESTS, THE
MONEY INTERESTS, THE REPUBLICAN
POLITICAL INTERESTS ARE SPENDING
A LOT OF MONEY TO TRY TO DEFEAT
ME.
SO I JUST FIND IT KIND OF A
STRANGE ARGUMENT.
I HAPPEN TO AGREE WITH SENATOR
SANDERS.
I'M NOT JUST GOING AFTER WALL
STREET, THOUGH.
I THINK THAT'S TOO NARROW A
TARGET.
I THINK WE NEED TO GO AFTER A
COMPANY LIKE JOHNSON CONTROLS
THAT IS TRYING TO AVOID PAYING
TAXES AFTER ALL OF US BAILED IT
OUT BY PRETENDING TO SELL ITSELF
IN A SO-CALLED INVERSION IN
EUROPE.
IT'S A PERVERSION.
IT SHOULD BE STOPPED.
I WANT TO GO AFTER THE HEDGE
FUNDS THAT HAVE BOUGHT UP DRUG
COMPANIES, VALIANT
PHARMACEUTICALS, TAKING DRUG
THAT HAVE BEEN AROUND A LONG
TIME AND UPPING THE PRICE.
I TAKE SERIOUSLY THE OBLIGATION
I WOULD HAVE AS PRESIDENT TO
ONCE AGAIN GET THE DECK
UNSTACKED, TO GET THE ODDS
FAVORING THE AVERAGE AMERICAN
AGAIN.
BUT I JUST HAVE TO -- I HAVE TO
RESPECTFULLY SAY I THINK SENATOR
SANDERS' TARGET IS TOO SMALL.
I REALLY DO.
I RESPECT HIM GOING AFTER THE
BIG BANKS.
I AGREE WITH HIM NO, BANK IS TOO
BIG TO FAIL, NO EXECUTIVE TOO
POWERFUL TO JAIL, BUT WE
ACTUALLY PASSED THE PROCESS TO
BE ABLE TO TAKE ON BANKS THAT
POSE EXCESSIVE RISK IN OUR
FINANCIAL SYSTEM IN DODD-FRANK.
SO LET'S KNOW THE NEXT PRESIDENT
HAS TO IMPLEMENT BUT DOESN'T
HAVE TO ACHIEVE THAT.
HERE'S WHAT I WANT TO DO.
I WANT TO GO AFTER ALL THE OTHER
CULPRITS.
IT WASN'T JUST THE BIG BANKS.
IT WAS THE INSURANCE COMPANY,
AIG.
IT WAS THE INVESTMENT BANK
LEHMAN BROTHERS, IT WAS
COUNTRYWIDE MORTGAGE, IT WAS
WACHOVIA.
THERE WERE A LOT OF BAD ACTORS.
IF YOU ALL YOU DO IS LOOK OVER
HERE, THEY'RE GOING TO BE OVER
THERE IN THE SHADOW BANKING
SECTOR COOKING UP ALL KINDS OF
WAYS TO ONCE AGAIN PUT OUR
ECONOMY AT RISK.
I'VE GOT NO ARGUMENT THAT WE
NEED TO TAKE ON THIS VESTED
INTEREST.
I JUST HAVE A WIDER GROUP THAT I
THINK WE NEED TO GO AFTER FROM
PHARMACEUTICALS, INSURANCE
COMPANIES, SHADOW BANKING AND
OTHER CORPORATIONS THAT I THINK
ARE UNDERMINING OUR ECONOMY AND
FRANKLY THEY UNDERMINING OUR
DEMOCRACY.
THIS JOHNSON CONTROL THING
REALLY INFURIATES ME.
WE BAILED THEM OUT.
THE REPUBLICANS WANTED THE AUTO
INDUSTRY TO JUST FAIL.
THEY DIDN'T CARE ABOUT THE
MILLIONS OF JOB.
BARACK OBAMA AND THE DEMOCRATIC
CONGRESS GAVE THEM A BAILOUT.
IT TURNED OUT TO BE A GOOD DEAL.
ALL OF US PAID FOR IT.
THEY PAID BACK THE TREASURY, WE
DIDN'T LOSE ANY MONEY AND WE
SAVED A LOT OF JOBS.
JOHNSON CONTROLS IS BEGGING FOR
A BAILOUT AND NOW THEY'RE NOT
GOING TO PAY THEIR TAXES?
WE'RE GOING TO GO RIGHT AFTER
THAT.
THAT IS ABSOLUTELY WRONG AND WE
NEED TO BE FOCUSED ON GETTING A
FIX TO THIS.
>> ONE OF THE THINGS THAT
SENATOR SANDERS POINTS TO AND A
LOT OF YOUR CRITICS POINT TO IS
YOU MADE THREE SPEECHES FOR
GOLDMAN SACHS, YOU WERE PAID
$675,000 FOR THREE SPEECHES.
WAS THAT AN ERROR IN JUDGMENT?
>> I MADE SPEECHES TO LOTS OF
GROUPS --
>> BUT DID YOU HAVE TO BE PAID
$675,000?
>> WELL, I DON'T KNOW.
THAT'S WHAT THEY OFFERED SO --
YOU KNOW, EVERY SECRETARY OF
STATE THAT I KNOW HAS DONE THAT.
>> BUT YOU MUST HAVE KNOWN.
>> TO BE HONEST, I WASN'T
COMMITTED TO RUNNING.
I DIDN'T KNOW WHETHER I WOULD OR
NOT.
>> YOU DIDN'T THINK YOU WERE
GOING TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT?
>> I DIDN'T WHEN I WAS SECRETARY
OF STATE, SEVERAL TIMES I SAID I
THINK I'M DONE.
AND, YOU KNOW, SO MANY PEOPLE
CAME TO ME, STARTED TALKING TO
ME, THE CIRCUMSTANCES, THE
CONCERNS I HAD ABOUT THE
REPUBLICANS TAKING BACK THE
WHITE HOUSE BECAUSE I THINK THEY
WRECKED WHAT WE ACHIEVED IN THE
90s WITH 23 MILLION NEW JOBS AND
INCOMES GOING UP FOR EVERYBODY,
I DID NOT WANT TO SEE THAT
HAPPEN AGAIN, I WANT TO DEFEND
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
ACCOMPLISHMENTS AND THE PROGRESS
WE'VE MADE, I WANT TO GO
FURTHER.
SO, YEAH, I WAS CONVINCED.
BUT ANYBODY WHO KNOWS ME, WHO
THINKS THAT THEY CAN INFLUENCE
ME, NAME ANYTHING THEY'VE
INFLUENCED ME ON.
JUST NAME ONE THING.
I'M OUT HERE EVERY DAY SAYING
I'M GOING TO SHUT THEM DOWN, I'M
GOING AFTER THEM, I'M GOING TO
JAIL THEM IF THEY SHOULD BE
JAILED, I'M GOING TO BREAK THEM
UP.
THEY'RE NOT GIVING ME VERY MUCH
MONEY NOW.
I CAN TELL YOU THAT MUCH.
FINE WITH ME.
I'M PROUD TO HAVE 90% OF MY
DONATIONS FROM SMALL DONORS AND
60%, THE HIGHEST EVER FROM
WOMEN, WHICH I'M REALLY, REALLY
GLAD ABOUT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> SO JUST TO BE CLEAR, THAT'S
NOT SOMETHING YOU REGRET THESE
THREE SPEECHES?
>> NO, I DON'T.
I DON'T FEEL THAT I PAID ANY
PRICE FOR IT AND I AM VERY CLEAR
ABOUT WHAT I WILL DO AND THEY'RE
ON NOTICE.
>> I WANT TO SEE IF CHRIS LOPEZ
IS HERE.
CHRIS, THERE YOU ARE.
CHRIS IS AN INDEPENDENT WITH A
QUESTION FOR SECRETARY CLINTON.
SHE SAYS SHE UNDECIDED.
>> HI, CHRIS.
>> HI.
THANKS FOR TAKING MY QUESTION.
I SEE A LOT OF HYPOCRISY IN THIS
COUNTRY WHEN I HAVE A REALLY
HARD TIME GETTING THE MEDICINE I
NEED AND YET IT'S REALLY EASY TO
GET ALCOHOL.
WHAT WILL YOU DO TO
DECRIMINALIZE MARIJUANA SO
PEOPLE -- SO I AND PEOPLE LIKE
ME CAN GET THE PAIN AND SPASM
RELIEF THAT WE NEED?
>> I WILL DO A LOT, CHRIS,
BECAUSE WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY
TO DO MUCH MORE WITH RESPECT TO
RESEARCH INTO MARIJUANA, WHAT IT
CAN DO TO HELP PEOPLE WITH THE
KINDS OF CONDITIONS YOU'VE JUST
BRIEFLY DESCRIBED.
I WANT TO MOVE IT FROM A
SCHEDULE ONE DRUG TO A SCHEDULE
TWO SO WE CAN DO MORE RESEARCH
AND I WANT YOU TO KNOW WHAT WE
KNOW FROM SCIENCE.
BUT I ALSO WANT YOU TO BE ABLE
TO USE IT WHILE WE'RE DOING THE
RESEARCH.
SO MANY STATES RN, AS YOU KNOW,
HAVE MOVED TO PROVIDE LEGAL
PROTECTION FOR THE MEDICAL USE
OF MARIJUANA.
I THINK WE SHOULD BE LEARNING
ABOUT WHAT WORKS, WHAT DOESN'T
WORK.
DIFFERENT STATES HAVE ACTUALLY
LISTED THE KIND OF ILLNESSES AND
CONDITIONS IT CAN BE USED FOR.
ARE THEY RIGHT IN I DON'T KNOW.
THAT'S WHY WE TO DO THE
RESEARCH.
I ALSO WANT YOU TO KNOW WHAT
DOSAGE IS RIGHT, WHAT INTERACTS
WITH THE OTHER MEDICATION YOU'RE
TAKING.
HA
I HAVE NO DOUBT THAT THERE ARE
REAL BENEFITS FOR PEOPLE.
WE KNOW IN CHEMOTHERAPY AND WE
KNOW FROM OTHER CONDITIONS IN
USING THE RIGHT AMOUNT OF THE
RIGHT KIND OF MARIJUANA.
I JUST WANT TO MAKE SURE IT'S
THE RIGHT AMOUNT AND THE RIGHT
KIND.
THAT'S WHY I WANT TO GET THAT
RESEARCH UP AND GOING AS QUICKLY
AS POSSIBLE.
BUT YOU SAID SOMETHING ELSE
WHICH I THINK IS REALLY
IMPORTANT.
WE CAN'T BE HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE AND NOT TALK ABOUT THE
ADDICTION PROBLEM IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
NOT TALK ABOUT THE FACT THAT
THERE HAVE BEEN MORE DEATHS BY
OVERDOSES THAN CAR CRASHES IN
THIS STATE.
NOT TALK ABOUT THE LIVES THAT
ARE BEING DESTROYED, THE PEOPLE
THAT I MEET, THE GRANDMOTHERS
RAISING THEIR GRANDCHILDREN
BECAUSE THEY LOST THEIR
CHILDREN.
I JUST LEFT A RALLY IN
MANCHESTER AND A WOMAN GRABBED
MY HAND AND SHE SAID I JUST LOST
MY SON TO AN OVERDOSE.
SO I HAVE BEEN WORKING WITH
ELECTED OFFICIALS LIKE SENATOR
SHAHEEN, LOOK GOVERNOR HASSAN,
LIKE GOVERNOR SHUM LYNN OF
VERMONT WHO SUPPORTS ME TO
FIGURE OUT HOW DO WE PUT
TOGETHER A NEW APPROACH, A NEW
LAW ENFORCEMENT APPROACH SO THAT
FIRST TIME, LOW LEVEL DRUG USERS
ARE NOT ISN'T TO JAIL BUT
INSTEAD WE HAVE MORE TREATMENT
AND RECOVERY PROGRAMS?
THERE ARE 23 MILLION PEOPLE WHO
NEED HELP IN OUR COUNTRY, BOTH
ALCOHOL AND DRUGS.
THERE ARE 10% OF THE KIND OF
SPACES THAT THEY NEED TO TAKE
CARE OF THOSE PEOPLE.
SO WE'VE GOT TO WORK ON LAW
ENFORCEMENT, WE HAVE TO WORK ON
DOCTORS TO UNDERSTAND BETTER
WHEN THEY PRESCRIBE OPIOIDS,
WHICH IS OFTEN THE FIRST STEP
TOWARDS HEROIN, HAVE EVERY
POLICE DEPARTMENT EQUIPPED WITH
THE ANTIDOTE TO REVERSE
OVERDOSE.
ALL OF THIS FITS TOGETHER.
YOU DESERVE ANSWERS ABOUT
MARIJUANA AND WE DESERVE MORE
TREATMENT FOR PEOPLE ADDICTED TO
DRUGS AND ALCOHOL FOR OTHER
KINDS OF CHALLENGES.
THAT'S WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO DO.
>> THIS IS JULIE FROM WINDHAM.
JULIE?
>> THANK YOU FOR TAKING MY
QUESTION.
I'M THE PROUD MOTHER OF FIVE
GIRLS, TWO OF MY OWN, THREE STEP
DAUGHTERS.
UNFORTUNATELY THEY ARE ALL
FEELING THE BERN.
I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW WHAT YOU
WOULD DO TO CONVINCE THEM TO
VOTE FOR YOU.
>> HOW OLD ARE THEY?
>> THEY'RE IN THEIR 21, 22 AND A
COUPLE 23s AND A 25-YEAR-OLD.
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, TELL THEM
I'M GLAD THEY'RE INTERESTED IN
POLITICS AND I REALLY MEAN THAT.
I WANT THEM TO BE INVOLVED.
I WANT THEM TO FEEL LIKE I FELT
WHEN I WAS THAT AGE, SOME YEARS
AGO, AND GETTING EXCITED AND
INTERESTED IN POLITICS FOR THE
FIRST TOO MANY.
I ALSO WANT THEM TO TAKE A LOOK
AT MY RECORD, WHAT I HAVE DONE
MY ENTIRE LIFE, STARTING AS A
YOUNG LAWYER, WORKING AS THE
CHILDREN'S DEFENSE FUND, WORKING
WITH JUVENILES, GATHER
INFORMATION TO END SEGREGATED
ACADEMIES IN THE SOUTH.
I WAS A LEGAL SERVICES LAWYER
STANDING UP FOR EQUALITY UNDER
THE LAW, DEFENDING PEOPLE'S
RIGHTS BECAUSE I BELIEVE
PASSIONATELY THAT THOSE OF US
WHO HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO
SERVE SHOULD SERVE.
AND THAT I HOPE THEY WILL LOOK
AT WHAT I HAVE ACCOMPLISHED FROM
STARTING THE CHILDREN'S HEALTH
INSURANCE PROGRAM THAT INSURES 8
MILLION KIDS, LOOKING AT WAYS TO
TRY TO BE SMART IN REFORMING OUR
ADOPTION AND FOSTER CARE SYSTEM
WITH VERY PARTISAN REPUBLICANS
WHEN I WAS FIRST LADY, GETTING
HEALTH CARE FOR OUR NATIONAL
GUARD, HELPING TO NEGOTIATE AN
IMPLEMENT A TREATY TO REDUCE
NUCLEAR WEAPONS, A LONG LIST.
THE REASON I SAY THAT IS I THINK
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT THAT AS
PEOPLE MOVE TOWARD THE PRIMARY
ON TUESDAY, WHATEVER YOUR AGE,
YOU REALLY THINK ABOUT WHAT
SOMEONE IS PROPOSING AND WHAT
THEIR RECORD IS ABOUT GETTING IT
DONE.
AND AS I'VE SAID AND I MEAN IT
ABSOLUTELY, I HAVE THE HIGHEST
RESPECT FOR SENATOR SANDERS.
BUT AS THE CONCORD MONITOR SAID
TODAY IN ITS WRITING ABOUT THIS,
YOU KNOW, IT'S VERY HARD TO SEE
HOW ANY OF HIS PROPOSALS COULD
EVER BE ACHIEVABLE.
SO I DON'T WANT TO OVERPROMISE.
WE HAD TOO MUCH OF THAT.
I WANT TO TELL PEOPLE WHAT I
WILL DO, I WANT TO BE SPECIFIC
BECAUSE I DO WANT TO GO BACK TO
THE QUESTION I WAS ASKED
EARLIER, RECREATE THE TRUST THAT
SEEMS TO HAVE BEEN SPLINTERED IN
AMERICA.
WE NEED TO SET BIG GOALS AGAIN.
I AM ALL FOR THAT, I HAVE BIG
AMBITIOUS GOALS, AFFORDABLE
COLLEGE, EARLY CHILDHOOD
EDUCATION, MAKING SURE WE'RE ON
THE PATH TO PAID FAMILY LEAVE,
ALL OF WHICH WILL HELP YOUR
DAUGHTERS.
BUT I ALSO WANT THEM TO HOLD ME
ACCOUNTABLE.
I WANT THEM TO SAY, OKAY, HOW IS
THAT ACTUALLY GOING TO HAPPEN?
WHAT DO WE HAVE TO DO TO MAKE
IT?
BELIEVE GOT TO GET 60 VOTES TO
BREAK A FILIBUSTER IN THE
SENATE.
NANCY PELOSI SAID WE'RE NOT
GOING TO REVISIT HEALTH CARE.
WE'RE GOING TO STICK WITH THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
THAT'S WHERE I AM.
I WANT TO PRODUCE A REAL
DIFFERENCE IN PEOPLE'S LIVES.
I AM A PROGRESSIVE WHO GETS
RESULTS AND I WILL BE A
PROGRESSIVE PRESIDENT WHO GETS
RESULTS.
THE FINAL THING I WOULD SAY IS
IT IT IS STILL THE CASE THAT
THERE ARE CHALLENGES AND
OBSTACLES TO YOUNG WOMEN'S
AMBITIONS, AND I'M GOING TO TRY
TO BREAK THE HIGHEST AND HARDEST
GLASS CEILING.
I HOPE IT SPLINTERS COMPLETELY.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
AND I HOPE FOR YOUR DAUGHTERS IT
OPENS DOORS THAT MIGHT NOT BE
OPEN RIGHT NOW.
REGARDLESS OF WHETHER ANY OF
THEM EVER DO ANYTHING
POLITICALLY BUT IN THEIR LIVES,
THEIR PROFESSIONS, HOW THEY'RE
TREATED, I HOPE IT DOES GIVE
THEM MORE OF A SENSE OF
EMPOWERMENT.
THAT'S WHAT I WANT FOR MY
DAUGHTER AND MY AMAZING
GRANDDAUGHTER AND THAT'S WHAT I
WANT FOR YOUR DAUGHTERS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AS WE DID WITH SENATOR
SANDERS, WE TALKED ABOUT A LOT
OF IMPORTANT POLICY ISSUES.
I WANT TO ASK A COUPLE OF
PERSONAL QUESTIONS FOR VOTERS TO
GET --
>> YOU DON'T THINK THEY KNOW
EVERYTHING?
>> WE'LL SEE ABOUT THAT.
IT'S INTERESTING TO ME.
AS YOU SAID, YOU HAVE BEEN ONE
OF THE MOST FAMOUS WOMEN OF THE
WORLD NOW FOR DECADES.
YOU HAVE NO ANONYMITY.
IF YOU COULD BE ANONYMOUS FOR
JUST ONE DAY, WHAT WOULD DO YOU?
>> I USED TO DO THIS IN THE
WHITE HOUSE.
YOU KNOW, I WOULD PUT ON A
BASEBALL CAP AND SUNGLASSES AND,
YOU NO, SWEAT PANTS AND A SWEAT
SHIRT AND PULL MY HAIR BACK AND
I WOULD GO WALK AND I WOULD TELL
THE SECRET SERVICE THEY HAD TO
WEAR CASUAL CLOTHES, TAKE THE
THING OUT OF THEIR EARS AND LOOK
LIKE TOURISTS.
I WOULD END UP ON THE MALL AND A
FALLLY WOULD COME UP AND SAY
WOULD YOU MIND TAKING OUR
PICTURE IN FRONT OF THE WHITE
HOUSE?
I'D BE HAPPY TO.
SO THERE'S NOTHING I LIKE BETTER
THAN TO BE ANONYMOUS, AS HARD AS
THAT IS TO ACHIEVE.
I WOULD SPEND THE DAY OUT IN
NATURE, TAKING A LONG WALK,
WALKING THROUGH ONE OF THE
BEAUTIFUL TOWNS HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, STOPPING IN A CAFE,
STOPPING IN A BOOK STORE, YOU
KNOW, MAYBE CALLING SOME OF MY
FRIENDS, SOME OF WHOM ARE HERE
TONIGHT AND SAY DON'T TELL
ANYBODY BUT MEET ME THERE.
THAT'S WHAT I WANT TO DO.
AND IT'S WHAT I GET THE GREAT
JOY OUT OF.
I AM SO FORTUNATE THAT I STILL
HAVE MY FRIENDS FROM GRADE
SCHOOL AND EVERY OTHER PHASE OF
MY LIFE.
THEY KEEP MY GROUNDED, THEY KEEP
MY HONEST, THEY DEFLATE MY HEAD,
THEY DEAL WITH THE UNVERSE IN
ONE POCKET AND THE DUST AND
ASHES IN THE OTHER.
SO ANY TIME I GET TO SPEND TIME
WITH THEM AND THEN OF COURSE IT
WOULD HAVE TO END WITH SEEING MY
GRANDDAUGHTER BECAUSE THAT'S THE
CREME DERESISTANCE.
>> WHAT DOES SHE CALL YOU?
>> SHE CALLS ME GRANDMA.
SHE'S WORKING REALLY HARD ON
WORDS AND IT WAS SO THRILLING,
THEY CAME TO IOWA THAT LAST
WEEKEND BECAUSE WE OBVIOUSLY
WEREN'T GOING TO LEAVE AND SO
THEY GOT IN LATE SATURDAY NIGHT
AND SUNDAY MORNING I'M GETTING
READY AND BILL AND I ARE HAVING
COFFEE AND EVERYTHING.
SO CHELSEA BRINGS HER IN AND
SHSHE
SEES ME AND SHE GOES GRANDMA!
AND THE CAUCUS COULD HAVE
HAPPENED RIGHT THERE.
>> YOU TALK ABOUT THE CIRCLE OF
FRIENDS.
IN 2011 YOUR MOM PASSED AWAY.
IN 2008 SHE WAS PART OF YOUR
CAMPAIGN.
YOU WROTE ABOUT HOW AT THE END
OF THE DAY YOU WOULD SIT AROUND
THE TABLE, KICK OFF YOUR SHOES
AND TALK ABOUT WHAT HAPPENED.
WHAT ADVICE WOULD SHE GIVE YOU
IF SHE WERE HERE?
>> MY MOTHER TRULY IS MY
INSPIRATION BECAUSE SEE HAD SUCH
A TERRIBLE, MISERABLE LIFE
BECAUSE SHE WAS ABANDONED AND
REJECTED BY HER OWN FAMILY AND
WAS OUT OF THE HOUSE WORKING AT
A HOUSE MAID AT THE AGE OF 14.
HER RESILIENCE TO HAVE HER OWN
FAMILY AND TAKE CARE OF US TO ME
WAS THE ULTIMATE OF
ACCOMPLISHMENT IN ANY LIFE.
AND SHE WOULD ALWAYS GIVE ME THE
ADVICE SHE GAVE ME AS A LITTLE
GIRL.
YOU KNOW, YOU GET KNOCKED DOWN,
EVERYBODY GETS KNOCKED DOWN.
WHAT MATTERS IS WHETHER U YOU G
UP AND WHEN YOU GET UP WHAT DO
YOU DO?
HOW DO YOU BEHAVE?
ARE YOU GOING TO BE BITTER,
ANGRY, UPSET?
ARE YOU GOING TO BE POSITIVE,
GET SOMETHING DONE, HELP
SOMEBODY ELSE?
AND I'M SURE THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT
SHE WOULD BE SAYING NOW.
SHE WOULD BE ENCOURAGING ME,
SHE'D BE VERY PROUD, A LITTLE
APPREHENSIVE BECAUSE, YOU KNOW,
IT'S A BRUTAL BUSINESS BEING IN
POLITICS AND PEOPLE SAY THINGS
ABOUT THOSE YOU LOVE, WHETHER
IT'S YOUR DAUGHTER OR SOMEONE
ELSE.
SO SHE WAS -- SHE WAS VERY
SUPPORTIVE BUT YOU COULD TELL,
YOU KNOW, HOW MUCH PAIN SHE KIND
OF ABSORBED FROM TIME TO TIME.
SO I WOULD SIT WITH HER AND I
WOULD SAY DON'T LISTEN TO THAT
STUFF, MOM.
AND SHE'D SAY, WELL, I HAVE TO
KNOW WHAT THEY'RE SAYING ABOUT
YOU.
I'D SAY, YOU KNOW, DON'T PUT
YOURSELF THROUGH THAT.
SO THAT WOULD BE WHAT SHE'D BE
DOING NOW I THINK, TOO.
>> I WANT YOU TO BE ABLE TO MAKE
A CLOSING ARGUMENT TO PEOPLE IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE.
>> OH.
WELL, THANK YOU.
FIRST OF ALL, THANKS AGAIN FOR
BEING PART OF THIS PROCESS, THIS
FIRST IN THE NATION PRIMARY.
YOU KNOW, I SAID EARLIER TODAY
SOME PEOPLE SAID, WELL, SENATOR
SANDERS IS AHEAD AND I RESPECT
THAT.
SO MAYBE I SHOULD GO ON TO THE
NEXT STATES.
AND I SAID ABSOLUTELY NOT.
NEW HAMPSHIRE HAS BEEN SO GOOD
TO ME AND MY FAMILY AND I LOVE
CAMPAIGNING IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
I LOVE THIS PROCESS.
SO YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE TO PUT
UP WITH ME.
I'M GOING TO BE GOING AROUND THE
STATE, GOING TO AS MANY EVENTS
AS I CAN, ANSWERING AS MANY
QUESTIONS, TRYING TO TALK ABOUT
WHAT I AM OFFERING.
I REALLY BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE A
CHANCE TO BUILD ON THE PROGRESS
WE'VE MADE AND TO GET RESULTS
FOR PEOPLE, TO GET THE ECONOMY
PRODUCING MORE GOOD JOBS, TO GET
INCOMES RISING AGAIN.
THAT'S MY GOAL.
I WILL NOT RAISE MIDDLE CLASS
TAXES BECAUSE THE MIDDLE CLASS
HASN'T EVEN YET RECOVERED FROM
THE GREAT RECESSION.
WE'RE GOING TO STICK WITH THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, WE'RE GOING
TO MAKE IT WORK, GET EARLY
CHILDHOOD EDUCATION, AFFORDABLE
COLLEGE AND PAY DOWN STUDENT
DEBT.
A LOT OF THE AGENDA THAT IS
IMPORTANT TO OUR COUNTRY,
PARTICULARLY TO YOUNG PEOPLE AND
WE'RE GOING TO DEFEND OUR
RIGHTS.
WE'RE GOING TO DEFEND A WOMAN'S
RIGHT TO MAKE HER OWN HEALTH
CARE DECISIONS, WE'RE GOING TO
DEFEND PLANNED PARENTHOOD, WE'RE
GOING TO DEFEND MARRIAGE
INEQUALITY AND DEFEND
DISCRIMINATION AND TAKE ON THE
GUN LOBBY BECAUSE IT'S
UNCONSCIONABLE TO HAVE 33,000
PEOPLE A YEAR DIE FROM GUN
VIOLENCE.
JOIN ME IN THIS CAMPAIGN.
I HOPE YOU WILL COME OUT AND
VOTE FOR ME ON TUESDAY AND I
WILL FIGHT FOR YOU EVERY SINGLE
DAY IN THE WHITE HOUSE.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
.
>> I WANT TO THANK BOTH
CANDIDATES FOR COMING HERE
TONIGHT AND I WANT TO THANK THE
VIEWERS FOR COMING AND ASKING
SUCH AMAZING QUESTIONS.
A REMINDER, WE'LL BE HERE WITH
IT ALL.
OUR COVERAGE CONTINUES WITH DON
LEMON RIGHT AFTER THIS.
THANKS AGAIN.
>> THANK YOU ALL!
THANK YOU, GUYS!
I WANT TO MEET THE RABBI.