[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> GOOD EVENING, EVERYONE.
IN JUST THREE DAYS, REPUBLICANS
HERE ARE GOING TO GO TO THE
POLLS.
IF HISTORY IS ANY GUIDE,
SATURDAY'S SOUTH CAROLINA
PRIMARY WILL HELP SOME CAMPAIGNS
AND BREAK OTHERS.
TONIGHT MATTERS SO MUCH.
FOR THREE CANDIDATES, ONE LAST
CHANCE FOR VOTERS TO ASK THE
QUESTIONS FACE-TO-FACE TO HELP
THEM DECIDE.
>> TONIGHT, A CONVERSATION WITH
THREE LEADING REPUBLICANS IN
SOUTH CAROLINA.
THEY ARE FACING THE VOTERS AND
FIGHTING FOR EVERY LAST VOTE.
>> IF YOU EVER WANT TO FALL IN
LOVE WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE,
RUN FOR PRESIDENT.
>> MARCO RUBIO, RISING.
TED CRUZ, TALKING TOUGH.
>> THE TIME FOR GAMES IS OVER.
>> BEN CARSON, RUNNING BEHIND,
HOPING TO RISE ABOVE THE FRAY
AND THE REST OF THE FIELD.
>> I THINK I CAN WIN SOUTH
CAROLINA.
>> THREE CONTENDERS, MEN OF
FAITH IN A STATE WHERE FAITH
RUNS DEEP AND THE FAITHFUL VOTE.
BUT SOUTH CAROLINA IS THE STATE
THAT KNOWS RAW POLITICS.
>> HE'S NOW LITERALLY JUST
MAKING THINGS UP.
>> MARCO RUBIO HITTING CRUZ.
CRUZ HITTING BACK.
>> WHENEVER ANYONE POINTS OUT
THEIR RECORD, THEY SIMPLY START
SCREAMING LIAR, LIAR, LIAR.
>> THREE CONTENDERS IN A STATE
WHERE MANNERS MATTER BUT WINNING
MATTERS MORE.
JUST DAYS BEFORE THE FIRST
SOUTHERN PRIMARY AT THE END OF A
CAMPAIGN LIKE WE AND THE VOTERS
HAVE NEVER SEEN BEFORE.
THIS SAN ANDERSON 360 CNN TOWN
HALL.
VOTERS SEEKING ANSWERS.
A CHANCE TO DRIVE THE DEBATE
BEFORE MAKING A CHOICE THAT
COULD MAKE HISTORY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> GOOD EVENING.
WELCOME TO THE OLD CIGAR
WAREHOUSE IN GREENVILLE, SOUTH
CAROLINA.
WHAT A NIGHT AHEAD.
WE'RE HERE TONIGHT WITH JUST
THREE DAYS TO GO UNTIL PRIMARY
DAY.
JUST THREE DAYS LEFT TO DECIDE,
YES A LOT OF VOTERS IN THIS
STATE REMAIN UNDECIDED.
SENATORS RUBIO, CRUZ AND DR.
CARSON ARE HERE WITH THE VOTERS
AND VIEWERS FOR A CONVERSATION.
TOMORROW NIGHT I'LL BE WITH JOHN
KASICH, JEB BUSH AND DONALD
TRUMP.
I WANT TO WELCOME OUR VIEWERS
WATCHING IN THE UNITED STATES,
WATCHING HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA
AND AROUND THE WORLD ON CNN
INTERNATIONAL.
ALSO WANT TO EXTEND A WARM
WELCOME TO ALL OUR SERVICE MEN
AND WOMEN WATCHING ON THE
AMERICAN FORCES NETWORK AND TO
THOSE LISTENING TO THE WESTWOOD
ONE RADIO NETWORK AND CHANNEL
116 ON SIRIUS XM.
IN THE AUDIENCE TONIGHT IN
GREENVILLE, PEOPLE WHO TELL US
THEY'LL BE PARTICIPATING IN
SATURDAY'S PRIMARY.
SOME DECIDED.
SOME UNDECIDED.
WE ASKED AUDIENCE MEMBERS TO
COME UP WITH THEIR OWN QUESTIONS
WHICH WE REVIEWS TO MAKE SURE
THEY DON'T OVERLAP.
I'LL ASK SOME QUESTIONS AS WELL.
WE HOPE THIS IS ABOUT SOUTH
CAROLINA VOTERS GETTING TO KNOW
THE CANDIDATES.
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
JOINING US FIRST TONIGHT IS
RETIRED NEUROSURGEON DR. BEN
CARSON.
WELCOME.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> TAKE A SEAT.
HOW IS IT GOING?
>> VERY GOOD.
>> GOOD.
I WANT TO START JUST -- YOU,
OBVIOUSLY, A RETIRED
NEUROSURGEON.
YOU'VE BEEN OUT ON THE CAMPAIGN
TRAIL FOR TEN MONTHS.
WHAT'S HARDER.
BRAIN SURGERY OR POLITICS?
>> BRAIN SURGERY IS A LOT
HARDER.
BUT, YOU KNOW, THE INTERESTING
THING THAT I'VE DISCOVERED ABOUT
POLITICS, GOOD THINGS AND BAD
THINGS, IT'S BEEN WONDERFUL
HAVING AN OPPORTUNITY TO MEET SO
MANY PEOPLE ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
AND HEAR WHAT THEIR CONCERNS
ARE.
IT HADN'T BEEN THAT GREAT, YOU
KNOW, DEALING WITH THE PRESS.
>> ARE YOU LOOKING AT ME?
>> WELL, THAT'S WHAT REALLY
TONIGHT IS ABOUT.
YOU INTERACTING WITH THE VOTERS.
I'M GOING TO ASK A COUPLE OF
QUESTIONS AND THEN WE'LL TURN IT
OVER TO THE VOTERS.
AS YOU KNOW, THE GOVERNMENT IS
TRYING TO UNLOCK THE CELL PHONE
OF ONE OF THE TERRORISTS IN SAN
BERNARDINO.
THEY'VE BEEN UNABLE TO DO THAT.
THEY'VE GOTTEN A JUDGE TO ASK
APPLE, TO TRY TO ORDER APPLE TO
CREATE NEW OPERATING SOFTWARE
THAT WOULD ALLOW THEM
ESSENTIALLY A BACK DOOR TO OPEN
UP AND GET ACCESS.
DO YOU THINK APPLE SHOULD BE
FORCES TO DO THAT?
APPLE SAYS THAT'S GOING TO
VIOLATE NOT ONLY PRIVACY RIGHTS
BUT IT'S GOING TO MAKE
EVERYBODY'S CELL PHONE
VULNERABLE POTENTIALLY TO
HACKERS.
>> YOU KNOW, THE INTERESTING
THING IS, I THINK THAT APPLE AND
PROBABLY A LOT OF OTHER PEOPLE
DON'T NECESSARILY TRUST THE
GOVERNMENT THESE DAYS.
AND THERE'S PROBABLY VERY GOOD
REASON FOR PEOPLE NOT TO TRUST
THE GOVERNMENT.
BUT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO GET
OVER THAT BECAUSE RIGHT NOW
WE'RE FACED WITH TREMENDOUS
THREATS, AND INDIVIDUALS,
RADICAL JIHADISTS WHO WANT TO
DESTROY US.
AND WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO WEIGH
THESE THINGS ONE AGAINST THE
OTHER.
I BELIEVE THAT WHAT WE NEED IS A
PUBLIC/PRIVATE PARTNERSHIP WHEN
IT COMES TO ALL OF THESE
TECHNICAL THINGS AND
CYBERSECURITY BECAUSE WE'RE ALL
AT RISK IN A VERY SIGNIFICANT
WAY.
SO IT'S GOING TO BE A MATTER OF
PEOPLE LEARNING TO TRUST EACH,
WHICH MEANS APPLE NEEDS TO SIT
DOWN WITH TRUSTWORTHY MEMBERS OF
THE GOVERNMENT.
AND THAT MAY HAVE TO WAIT UNTIL
THE NEXT ELECTION.
THEY NEED TO SIT DOWN WITH
PEOPLE THEY CAN TRUST AND HAMMER
OUT A RELATIONSHIP.
>> IF YOU WERE PRESIDENT RIGHT
NOW AND YOU JUST HAD 11 MONTHS
LEFT IN YOUR TERM, WOULD YOU
NOMINATE SOMEONE TO FILL JUSTICE
SCALIA'S SEAT?
>> I PROBABLY WOULD.
I PROBABLY WOULD TAKE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO NOMINATE SOMEONE.
DOESN'T NECESSARILY MEAN THAT
THAT PERSON IS GOING TO BE ACTED
ON OR CONFIRMED.
BUT WHY NOT DO IT?
BUT HERE'S THE REAL PROBLEM.
YOU KNOW, THE SUPREME COURT, A
VERY IMPORTANT PART OF OUR
GOVERNING SYSTEM WAS ORIGINALLY
INTENDED TO CONSIST OF JURISTS
WHO ARE PEOPLE WHO LOVE AMERICA,
PEOPLE WHO FULLY UNDERSTOOD OUR
CONSTITUTION, AND WERE THERE TO
MAKE SURE THAT AMERICA PRESERVED
ITS CONSTITUTIONAL TRADITIONS.
IT WAS NOT SUPPOSED TO BE A
PARTISAN GROUP.
IT HAS BECOME VERY PARTISAN.
SO AS A RESULT, EVERYTHING THAT
IS DONE SURROUNDING IT, THE
PICKS, THE CONFIRMATION
HEARINGS, DECIDING ON WHETHER TO
ACTUALLY MAKE THE VOTE, ALL OF
IT HAS BECOME PARTISAN AND
REACTION TO WHAT HAS HAPPENED.
DOES IT MEAN THAT WE'RE FOREVER
GONE?
NO.
I THINK IT MEANS THAT THESE ARE
THINGS THAT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE
TO START LOOKING AT.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO START
FIGURING OUT HOW IN THE WORLD DO
WE ONCE AGAIN GET BACK TO A
REASONABLE JUDICIAL SYSTEM.
WE DO NOT HAVE THAT NOW.
WE HAVE OVERREACHING.
WE HAVE A CONGRESS THAT FOR SOME
REASON HAS BECOME THE PEANUT
GALLERY AND JUST WATCHING WHAT
THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH AND THE
JUDICIARY DO.
AND NOT REALLY STEPPING UP TO
CORRECT SOME OF THE INCORRECT
DECISIONS THAT HAVE BEEN MADE BY
THE SUPREME COURT.
>> HOW WOULD A PRESIDENT CARSON
PICK JUDGES?
WOULD YOU HAVE A LITMUS TEST AS
PEOPLE OFTEN SAY?
>> YES, THE LITMUS TEST WOULD BE
THEIR LIFE.
YOU KNOW, I WOULD LOOK BACK AT
WHAT THEY HAVE DONE THROUGHOUT
THEIR LIVES, WHAT KIND OF
RULINGS THEY'VE HAD THROUGHOUT
ASSOCIATIONS THEY HAVE HAD.
YOU CAN TELL A LOT MORE ABOUT
HOW A PERSON HAS LIVED THEIR
LIFE THAN YOU CAN WITH, YOU
KNOW, A SERIES OF INTERVIEWS,
WHICH THEY HAVE BEEN PREPPED
FOR, WHICH THEY KNOW EXACTLY HOW
TO ANSWER.
WE'VE BEEN BURNED BY THOSE KINDS
OF THINGS BEFORE.
>> SO YOU WOULDN'T NECESSARILY
HAVE A LIST OF QUESTIONS ON
ABORTION, ON WHATEVER OTHER
ISSUES?
>> I THINK I COULD FIND OUT WHAT
THEIR OPINIONS ARE BY LOOKING
BACK AT THEIR LIFE.
THE BIBLE SAYS IN MATTHEW 7:20,
BY THEIR FRUIT YOU WILL KNOW
THEM.
>> I WANT TO HAVE YOU MEET A
VOTER.
JESSICA FULLER.
SHE WORKS IN ADVERTISING.
SHE'S A VOTER IN GREENVILLE.
SHE'S STILL UNDECIDED.
YOU COULD PICK UP A VOTE HERE
TONIGHT.
>> EXCELLENT.
>> WELCOME, JESSICA.
>> HI.
WELCOME TO GREENVILLE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> DR. CARSON, HOW DO YOU
RECONCILE THE DIFFERENCES
BETWEEN TRADITIONAL CHRISTIAN
VALUES, SPECIFICALLY CARRYING
FOR THE LEAST OF THESE AND GOP
STANCES ON SOCIAL ISSUES SUCH AS
WELFARE AND SUBSIDIES FOR THE
POOR?
>> WHEN YOU SEE CURRENT GOP, I
AM PART OF THE GOP AND LET ME
TELL YOU WHAT MY STANCE IS.
MY STANCE IS THAT WE THE PEOPLE
HAVE THE RESPONSIBILITY TO TAKE
CARE OF THE INDIGENT IN OUR
SOCIETY.
IT'S NOT THE GOVERNMENT'S JOB.
AND IF YOU CAN READ THE
CONSTITUTION ALL YOU WANT, IT
NEVER SAYS THAT IT IS THE
GOVERNMENT'S JOB.
AND I THINK THAT'S WHERE WE'VE
GOTTEN CONFUSED.
IN THE OLD DAYS OF AMERICA WHEN
COMMUNITIES WERE SEPARATED BY
HUNDREDS OF MILES, WHY WERE THEY
ABLE TO THRIVE?
BECAUSE IF IT WAS HARVEST TIME
AND THE FARMER WAS UP IN THE
TREE PICKING APPLES AND FELL AND
BROKE HIS LEG, EVERYBODY PITCHED
IN AND HARVESTED HIS CROPS FOR
HIM.
SOMEBODY GOT KILLED BY A BEAR,
EVERYBODY TOOK CARE OF THEIR
FAMILY.
SO WE HAVE A HISTORY OF TAKING
CARE OF EACH OTHER.
NOW FOR SOME STRANGE REASON,
STARTING SORT OF IN THE '20s,
THE GOVERNMENT STARTED GETTING
INVOLVED IN EVERYTHING.
IT KEPT GROWING, METASTASIZING.
BY THE TIME WE GOT TO THE '60s,
LBJ WAS SAYING, WE, THE
GOVERNMENT, ARE GOING TO
ELIMINATE POVERTY.
HOW DID THAT WORK OUT?
$19 TRILLION LATER, 10 TIMES
MORE PEOPLE ON FOOD STAMPS, MORE
POVERTY, MORE WELFARE, BROKEN
HOMES, OUT OF WEDLOCK BIRTHS,
CRIME, INCARCERATION.
EVERYTHING IS NOT ONLY WORSE.
IT'S MUCH WORSE.
AND THAT'S BECAUSE IT'S NOT
THEIR JOB.
IT'S OUR JOB.
I WISH THE GOVERNMENT WOULD READ
THE CONSTITUTION.
I THINK THAT WOULD PROBABLY HELP
QUITE A BIT.
AND MAYBE THEY DID READ IT AND
GOT CONFUSED WHEN THEY READ THE
PREAMBLE WHICH SAYS ONE OF THE
DUTIES IS TO PROMOTE THE GENERAL
WELFARE.
THEY PROBABLY THOUGHT THAT MEANT
PUTTING EVERYBODY ON WELFARE.
BUT I DON'T THINK IT MEANS THAT
AT ALL.
AND WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS LEVEL
THE PLAYING FIELD.
THE GOVERNMENT CAN PLAY A VERY
IMPORTANT ROLE IN FACILITATING
WHAT WE THE PEOPLE DO.
LET ME GIVE YOU ONE QUICK
EXAMPLE.
LOOK AT ALL THE OUT OF WEDLOCK
BIRTHS THAT ARE GOING ON,
PARTICULARLY IN OUR INNER
CITIES.
I HAVE BEEN SPEAKING AT A LOT OF
THE NONPROFIT ORGANIZATIONS THAT
SUPPORT ORGANIZATIONS THAT
SUPPORT THESE WOMEN SO THAT THEY
DON'T HAVE AN ABORTION, SO THAT
THEY HAVE THE BABY.
USUALLY THEIR EDUCATION STOPS
WHEN THEY HAVE THAT BABY.
NOW IF YOU NOT ONLY SUPPORT THEM
THROUGH THAT PREGNANCY, BUT NOW
PROVIDE CHILD CARE FOR THEM SO
THEY CAN GO BACK TO SCHOOL AND
GET THEIR GED OR THEIR
ASSOCIATES DEGREE OR BACHELORS
DEGREE OR MASTERS DEGREE, LEARN
HOW TO TAKE CARE OF THEMSELVES,
TEACH THEIR BABY HOW TO TAKE
CARE OF THEMSELVES SO THAT YOU
BREAK THE CYCLE OF THE
DEPENDENC
DEPENDENCY.
THAT'S THE ONLY WAY WE'LL GET
THROUGH THESE PROGRAMS.
THAT IS TRUE COMPASSION.
HAVING PEOPLE BECOME DEPENDENT
ON OTHERS IS NOT COMPASSION AT
ALL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DR. CARSON, I WANT YOU TO
MEET KATIE BUSBY.
SHE WORKS FOR THE CHAMBER OF
COMMERCE.
SHE SAYS SHE IS UNDECIDED.
>> DR. CARSON, YOU WOULD
PROBABLY AGREE ONE OF THE
BIGGEST ISSUES FACING OUR
COUNTRY IS NATIONAL SECURITY
THREAT.
WITH GROUPS LIKE ISIS AND MIDDLE
EAST BECOMING MORE AND MORE
UNSTABLE, YOU ARE RUNNING AS A
CANDIDATE THAT'S NEVER GOVERNED
BEFORE.
ARE YOU QUALIFIED TO BE
COMMANDER IN CHIEF, AND ARE YOU
QUALIFIED TO DEAL WITH THESE
NATIONAL SECURITY THREATS?
>> I, OBVIOUSLY, THINK SO OR I
WOULDN'T BE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT.
YOU KNOW, IT'S THE POLITICAL
CLASS THAT HAS TRIED TO CONVINCE
EVERYBODY THAT THEY ARE THE ONLY
ONES WHO CAN SOLVE OUR PROBLEMS.
BUT THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS
OUR SYSTEM WAS DESIGNED FOR
CITIZEN STATESMEN.
IT WAS DESIGNED FOR PEOPLE WHO
HAVE HAD REAL LIFE EXPERIENCES
AND THEN CAN TRANSFER THAT TO
GOVERNMENT WORK.
YOU KNOW, I CAN GUARANTEE YOU
THAT I'VE HAD MORE 2:00 A.M.
PHONE CALLS THAN ANYBODY ELSE,
ALL THE REST OF THEM, HAD TO
MAKE LIFE AND DEATH DECISIONS,
HAD TO DERIVE INFORMATION
FREQUENTLY FROM INTERNS OR
RESIDENTS WHO DIDN'T KNOW A LOT
BUT YOU MANAGE TO GET THE RIGHT
INFORMATION AND MAKE THE RIGHT
DECISIONS, PUT TOGETHER TEAMS,
COMPLEX TEAMS TO ACCOMPLISH
THINGS THAT HAVE NEVER BEFORE
BEEN ACCOMPLISHED BEFORE.
YOU KNOW, I THINK WHAT WE REALLY
NEED ARE PEOPLE WHO KNOW HOW TO
SOLVE PROBLEMS, NOT PEOPLE WHO
KNOW HOW TO TALK.
WE CAN ALL TALK, BUT WE CAN'T
ALL SOLVE PROBLEMS.
AND WHAT I THINK YOU NEED TO
LOOK AT IS THE COURSE OF A
PERSON'S LIFE.
GO BACK AND SEE, WHAT KINDS OF
THINGS HAVE THEY HAD TO FACE?
WHAT KINDS OF THINGS HAVE THEY
HAD TO OVERCOME?
AND, YOU KNOW, THE PEOPLE WHO
SAY, WELL, YOU'VE NEVER RUN
ANYTHING.
YOU DON'T KNOW HOW TO DO
MAYBE NONE OF THE THINGS THEY
WANT TO DO.
BUT IT DOES TAKE SKILL TO TAKE,
YOU KNOW, THE DIVISION OF
PEDIATRIC NEUROSURGERY WHEN I
BECAME CHIEF.
IT WASN'T ON THE MAP.
AND TO TAKE IT TO NUMBER ONE IN
THE COUNTRY BY 2008, THAT'S NOT
SOMETHING THAT'S DONE LIGHTLY.
TO START THE CARSON SCHOLARS
FUND.
THESE ARE THINGS OUTSIDE.
AND PEOPLE SAY YOU CAN'T START
ANOTHER SCHOLARSHIP PROGRAM.
THERE ARE TENS OF THOUSANDS OF
THEM.
BUT WE STARTED IT.
IT'S IN ALL 50 STATES.
HAS WON MAJOR NATIONAL AWARDS
THAT ARE ONLY GIVEN TO ONE
ORGANIZATION IN THE COUNTRY.
OBVIOUSLY, YOU HAVE TO KNOW HOW
TO DO THINGS.
I'VE SPENT 18 YEARS ON THE BOARD
OF KELLOGG'S.
16 YEARS ON THE BOARD OF COSTCO.
LEARNED A TREMENDOUS AMOUNT
ABOUT BUSINESS, DOMESTICALLY AND
INTERNATIONAL.
AND A LOT OF THINGS THAT PEOPLE
WHO ARE POLITICIANS WHO ARE
RUNNING HAVE NEVER DONE.
SO I THINK YOU HAVE TO REALLY
LOOK AT WHAT A PERSON
ACCOMPLISHES IN THEIR LIFE AND
NOT WHETHER THEY HAVE A SPECIFIC
PEDIGREE OF THE POLITICAL CLASS
WHO THINKS THAT THEY RULE US
WHEN, IN FACT, THIS COUNTRY IS
OF, FOR AND BY THE PEOPLE.
AND IT'S WE THE PEOPLE WHO NEED
TO ASSUME ONCE AGAIN THE
PINNACLE POSITION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DR. CARSON, THIS IS ALEXANDER
SEXTON.
HE WORKS IN THE DEFENSE SECTOR.
HE IS ALSO UNDECIDED BUT LEANING
IN YOUR FAVOR.
WELCOME.
>> DR. CARSON, THANK YOU FOR
YOUR TIME.
LIKE MANY AMERICANS, I'VE ONLY
RECENTLY FELT THE NEED TO OWN A
GUN.
AND, YOU KNOW, RIGHT NOW THE
WORLD IS IN A DANGEROUS PLACE.
SO WHAT IS YOUR PLAN TO PRESERVE
MY RIGHTS TO OWN A GUN AND ALSO
TO PROTECT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE?
>> SURE.
WELL, YOU KNOW, THE SECOND
AMENDMENT IS THERE FOR A VERY
GOOD REASON.
IT WAS SO THAT THE PEOPLE COULD
ASSIST THE GOVERNMENT IN CASE OF
AN INVASION.
MORE IMPORTANTLY IT WAS SO THAT
THE PEOPLE COULD PROTECT
THEMSELVES IN CASE THE
GOVERNMENT ITSELF EVER BECAME
TIRANICAL AND TRIED TO RULE THE
PEOPLE.
SO WE'VE HAD GUNS FOR HUNDREDS
OF YEARS.
AND WE'VE BEEN FREE FOR HUNDREDS
I THINK THERE MAY BE A
CORRELATION THERE.
AND I THINK, YOU KNOW, AFTER THE
SAN BERNARDINO ATTACKS AND THE
PARIS ATTACKS, THE CURRENT
ADMINISTRATION, THEIR IDEA OF
SOLVING THE PROBLEM WAS TO TAKE
GUNS AWAY FROM THE PEOPLE.
SOMEHOW THAT'S GOING TO SOLVE
YOUR PROBLEM BECAUSE THERE ARE
TERRORISTS TRYING TO KILL YOU.
TAKE YOUR GUNS AWAY.
IT MAKES ABSOLUTELY NO SENSE.
WHAT THEY SHOULD BE DOING IS
OFFERING FREE CLASSES IN GUN
SAFETY TO ALL THE CITIZENS WHO
WANT TO TAKE IT SO THEY CAN
PROTECT THEMSELVES.
IT IS THE FUNDAMENTAL RIGHT THAT
WE HAVE TO BE ABLE TO PROTECT
OURSELVES.
BUT WE ALSO NEED TO TAKE SAFETY
INTO ACCOUNT.
AND AS LONG AS WE DO THAT, IN A
REASONABLE WAY, I THINK YOUR
RIGHT, MY RIGHT, ALL OF OUR
RIGHTS SHOULD BE PRESERVED.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT TO FOLLOW UP.
HE WAS SAYING HE GOT A GUN FOR
THE FURST TIME IN HIS LIFE.
DO YOU OWN A GUN?
HAVE YOU EVER FELT THE NEED TO
OWN A GUN?
>> YES.
I DON'T KNOW THAT I FELT THE
NEED TO HAVE A GUN BUT I LIKE
HAVING A GUN.
I HAVE MULTIPLE MARKSMANSHIP
AWARDS FROM ROTC.
AND VERY MUCH IN FAVOR OF
PRESERVING THOSE RIGHTS.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET VICKI
BURNS, A RETIRED SMALL BUSINESS
OWNER.
SHE'S LEANING TOWARD GOVERNOR
BUSH BUT HAS NOT YET MADE UP HER
MIND.
>> HELLO, DR. CARSON.
MY QUESTION FOR YOU IS, IF YOU
ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT, WHAT
WOULD BE YOUR BIG IDEA?
IN THE PAST WE'VE HAD GREAT
PRESIDENTS THAT HAVE UNITED OUR
COUNTRY WITH PROGRAMS SUCH AS
THE SPACE PROGRAM, THE WPC, AND
WE ARE IN MUCH NEED OF A BIG
IDEA.
>> WELL, I HAVE MULTIPLE BIG
IDEAS.
BUT HERE'S ONE OF THE THINGS
THAT I REALLY WANT TO GET ACROSS
TO THE COUNTRY.
WE HAVE ONLY 330 MILLION PEOPLE.
SOUNDS LIKE A LOT OF PEOPLE.
BUT CHINA HAS 1.4 BILLION
PEOPLE.
INDIA HAS 1.1 BILLION PEOPLE.
WE HAVE TO COMPETE WITH THEM ON
THE WORLD STAGE, WHICH MEANS WE
CAN'T AFFORD TO WASTE ANY OF OUR
PEOPLE.
SO IT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE FOR US
TO HAVE 20-PLUS PERCENT OF
PEOPLE WHO ENTER HIGH SCHOOL
DROPPING OUT OF HIGH SCHOOL IN
THE TECHNOLOGICAL AGE, IN THE
INFORMATION AGE.
IT MAKES NO SENSE FOR US TO HAVE
5% OF THE WORLD'S POPULATION AND
25% OF THE INMATES.
AND WE HAVE TO REORIENT
OURSELVES IN A WAY THAT WE KEEP
THOSE THINGS FROM HAPPENING
BECAUSE FOR EVERY ONE OF THOSE
YOUNG PEOPLE, WE CAN KEEP FROM
GOING DOWN THAT PATH OF
SELF-DESTRUCTION.
THAT'S ONE MORE PERSON THAT WE
DON'T HAVE TO BE AFRAID OF OR
PROTECT OUR FAMILY FROM.
ONE MORE PERSON WE DON'T HAVE TO
PAY FOR IN THE PENAL SYSTEM OR
WELFARE SYSTEM.
ONE MORE TAXPAYING, PRODUCTIVE
MEMBER OF SOCIETY WHO MAY
DISCOVER THE CURE FOR CANCER OR
A NEW ENERGY SOURCE.
WE CAN'T AFFORD TO THROW AWAY
ANY OF OUR PEOPLE.
THAT'S THE BIG IDEA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THIS IS RICHARD LELAND, A
FAMILY PHYSICIAN HERE IN
GREENVILLE.
HE ALSO SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED.
WELCOME.
>> DR. CARSON, IN THE EVENT THAT
YOU DID NOT WIN THE PRESIDENCY
BUT ONE OF YOUR FELLOW
REPUBLICANS DID, IF THEY WERE TO
ASK YOU TO CONSIDER SERVING AS
THE SURGEON GENERAL OR HEAD OF
THE DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND
HUMAN SERVICES WITH YOUR PASSION
AND YOUR ABILITY, WOULD YOU BE
WILLING AT SOME POINT TO
CONSIDER THIS?
>> I'VE GOT TO TELL YOU, I'M NOT
LOOKING FOR A JOB.
YOU KNOW, AFTER --
>> WELL, THERE IS ONE JOB YOU'RE
LOOKING FOR.
>> AFTER 15,000 OPERATIONS AND A
VERY ARDUOUS CAREER, I'M
DEFINITELY NOT JUST LOOKING FOR
SOMETHING TO DO.
I FEEL THAT OUR COUNTRY IS ON
THE PRECIPICE AND IT'S ABOUT TO
GO OVER THE EDGE.
AND IF WE CONTINUE WITH POLITICS
AS USUAL, DEMOCRATS OR
REPUBLICANS, WE ARE GOING TO GO
OVER THAT EDGE.
AND I THINK WE HAVE TO REACH
DOWN AND RECOGNIZE THAT WE'RE --
WE CAN'T JUST TINKER AROUND THE
EDGES.
WE HAVE TO HAVE SOME REAL IDEAS
HERE.
IDEAS ARE HOW WE GET THAT
ECONOMIC ENGINE, WHICH IS THE
MOST DYNAMIC AND POWERFUL
ECONOMIC ENGINE THE WORLD HAS
EVER KNOWN ROLLING AGAIN.
I'VE GOT GOOD IDEAS ABOUT THAT.
BENCARSON.COM.
AND I CAN EXPLAIN THEM IF
ANYBODY ASKS ME THAT QUESTION.
BUT YOU ALSO, WHEN WE LOOK AT
WHAT'S HAPPENING TO OUR NATION
IN TERMS OF OUR VISION FOR WHO
WE ARE, I THINK WE'RE STARTING
TO LOSE SIGHT OF WHO WE ARE.
WE ARE SO BUSILY GIVE AWAY OUR
IDENTITY, OUR VALUES AND OUR
PRINCIPLES FOR THE SAKE OF
POLITICAL CORRECTIONS --
CORRECTNESS THAT WE DON'T KNOW
WHO WE ARE.
THE BIBLE SAYS WITHOUT A VISION,
THE PEOPLE PERISH.
SO I HAVE A VISION THAT I THINK
I SHARE WITH A LOT OF WE THE
PEOPLE.
AND THAT'S THE DIRECTION I WANT
TO GO IN.
IT WOULD BE VERY DIFFICULT FOR
ME TO SERVE IN AN ADMINISTRATION
THAT DIDN'T HAVE THAT SAME
PHILOSOPHY.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A SHORT
BREAK, DR. CARSON.
WE'LL HAVE MORE QUESTIONS WITH
DR. CARSON WHEN WE COME BACK.
YOU'RE WATCHING A REPUBLICAN
TOWN HALL FROM
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN TOWN
HALL HERE IN GREENVILLE, SOUTH
CAROLINA.
WE'RE TALKING TO DR. BEN CARSON.
OUR NEXT QUESTION FROM KATIE
ABRAMS, A CLEMSON STUDENT, AND
SHE IS UNDECIDED.
WELCOME.
>> HI, DR. CARSON.
MY NAME IS KATIE.
WHEN I WAS 18 AND JUST GRADUATED
FROM HIGH SCHOOL, I LOST ONE OF
MY DEAREST FRIENDS TO A
SENSELESS MURDER.
IT'S ONE OF THE MAIN REASONS I'M
PASSIONATE ABOUT IMPACTING
CHANGE IN THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
PEOPLE THAT GO TO PRISON SHOULD
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO
REASSIMULATE INTO SOCIETY.
IF YOU ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT,
HOW WOULD YOU WORK ALONGSIDE
POLICYMAKERS TO IMPACT POSITIVE
CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORM?
>> AS I MENTIONED A LITTLE
EARLIER, WE HAVE 5% OF THE
POPULATION OF THE WORLD AND 25%
OF THE INMATES.
AND THAT, OBVIOUSLY, MEANS
THAT'S SOMETHING IS ASKEW.
AND WE'RE PUTTING A LOT OF
PEOPLE IN PRISON WHO DON'T NEED
TO BE IN PRISON.
THEY AREN'T VIOLENT CRIMINALS,
AND ALL WE DO IS SEND THEM TO
THE UNIVERSITY WHERE THEY BECOME
VIOLENT CRIMINALS AND THEN
RELEASE THEM ON SOCIETY.
THAT MAKES ABSOLUTELY NO SENSE
WHATSOEVER.
WHEN WE SEND PEOPLE TO PRISON WE
NEED TO BE THINKING ABOUT
WHETHER THEY ARE GOING THERE FOR
LIFE OR WHETHER THEY'LL BE
REINTEGRATED INTO SOCIETY.
IF THEY ARE GOING TO BE
REINTEGRATED INTO SOCIETY, WE
NEED TO BE THINKING ABOUT HOW
ARE WE GOING TO MAKE THAT A
SUCCESSFUL REINTEGRATION?
IN MANY CASES THAT MAY MEAN WE
SHOULD BE OFFER SOMETHING
PRACTICAL TRAINING.
THERE'S NO REASON PEOPLE CAN'T
LEARN HOW TO BECOME A WELDER OR
A PLUMBER OR A WHOLE HOST OF
DIFFERENT THINGS.
PLUS, YOU KNOW, THERE ARE HIGH
LEVEL COURSES WHERE THEY CAN
LEARN MATHEMATICS AND WE OUGHT
TO BE THINKING ABOUT HOW DO WE
TAKE THESE PEOPLE AND TURN THEM
AWAY FROM A LIFE THAT'S GOING
DOWN THE WRONG PATHWAY TO ONE
WHERE THEY BECOME PART OF THE
FABRIC OF SUCCESS IN AMERICA.
>> SO DOES THAT MEAN FOR YOU
RELOOKING AT MANDATORY MINIMUM
SENTENCES FOR --
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> -- LOW LEVEL, NONVIOLENT
OFFENDERS?
>> ABSOLUTELY IT MEANS THAT.
IT MEANS WE NEED TO LOOK AT
THOSE WHO ARE MENTALLY ILL.
THERE ARE A LOT OF MENTALLY ILL
WHO ARE BEING HOUSED IN PRISONS.
WE HAVE FACILITIES ALL OVER THE
COUNTRY THAT ARE SITTING EMPTY
BECAUSE WE HAVE DECIDED THAT
IT'S TOO EXPENSIVE TO TAKE CARE
OF THE MENTALLY ILL.
SO THEY END UP ON THE STREET
WHERE FREQUENTLY THEY BECOME
VICTIMIZED BY PEOPLE AND THEN
WIND UP IN THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
AND THEN WE PUT THEM IN AMONGST
PEOPLE WHO ARE VIOLENT
CRIMINALS.
NOW YOU TAKE SOMEBODY MENTALLY
UNSTABLE AND NOW YOU ARE
TEACHING THEM TO BE A VIOLENT
CRIMINAL AND THEN RELEASING THEM
ON OUR SOCIETY.
THAT DOESN'T MAKE ANY SENSE.
SO I THINK IT WOULD BE A LOT
CHEAPER IF WE BEGIN TO TAKE CARE
OF THESE PEOPLE THE WAY THEY
SHOULD BE TAKEN CARE OF.
THERE'S GOING TO BE, QUITE
FRANKLY, PLENTY OF MONEY TO TAKE
CARE OF THE PEOPLE WHEN WE STOP
DOING ALL THE SILLY STF WE'RE
DOING WITH ALL OF THESE THINGS
WE ARE DOING.
THE MONEY WILL BE DRAWN IN
THAT'S SITTING ON THE SIDELINES
AND WE ONCE AGAIN BEGIN TO
CREATE THE CAN-DO ATTITUDE AS
OPPOSED TO THE WHAT CAN YOU DO
FOR ME ATTITUDE, AND I THINK
AMERICA WILL BE ON ITS WAY
PRETTY QUICKLY.
>> KATIE, APPRECIATE YOUR
QUESTION.
THIS IS WILL RICHTER.
HE GOES TO CLEMSON.
HE'S DECIDING BETWEEN YOU AND
SENATOR RUBIO.
>> THAT SHOULD BE AN EASY
CHOICE.
>> HI, DR. CARSON.
ACCORDING TO A 60 MINUTES
INVESTIGATION, THE JUSTICE
DEPARTMENT SAYS THAT CHINA'S
CORPORATE ESPIONAGE IS SO VAST
THAT IT CONSTITUTES A NATIONAL
SECURITY EMERGENCY COSTING
AMERICAN COMPANIES HUNDREDS OF
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS AND AMERICAN
CITIZENS OVER 2 MILLION JOBS.
IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, HOW WOULD
YOU GO ABOUT PROTECTING AMERICAN
INTELLECTUAL PROPERTY RIGHTS
ABROAD WHILE MAINTAINING
DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS?
>> A VERY IMPORTANT QUESTION.
I MEAN, WE ARE BEING HIT
THOUSANDS OF TIMES A DAY.
IF YOU GO TO INDIVIDUAL
AMERICANS, MILLIONS OF TIMES
EVERY DAY BY CYBERATTACKS FROM
CHINA AND OTHER PLACES.
AND THAT'S WHY, YOU KNOW, I HAVE
ADVOCATED FOR A COMPREHENSIVE
SOLUTION FOR CYBERSECURITY.
YOU CAN READ ABOUT THAT ON THE
WEBSITE.
BUT AGAIN, PUBLIC/PRIVATE
PARTNERSHIPS SO THAT WE CAN
CREATE THE KIND OF COMMON
MONITORING PROCESS SO THAT IF
YOU GET ATTACKED OR YOUR COMPANY
GETS ATTACKED, YOU KNOW, WE HAVE
A COMMON PLACE THAT WE CAN
REPORT THAT AND WE CAN BEGIN TO
SEE WHERE THE PIECES FIT
TOGETHER SO THAT WE UNDERSTAND
WHERE IT'S COMING FROM.
AND, QUITE FRANKLY, WE HAVE SOME
PRETTY SUBSTANTIAL OFFENSIVE
CYBER CAPABILITIES.
OUR ADMINISTRATION IS RELUCTANT
TO USE THEM.
I WOULD NOT BE RELUCTANT TO USE
THEM.
IF SOMEBODY HIT US FROM ANOTHER
COUNTRY WITH A CYBERATTACK, THEY
WOULD NOT DO IT A SECOND TIME.
BELIEVE ME.
AND PEOPLE THINK THAT I'M NICE.
AND I AM NICE, BUT I ALSO WANT
TO PROTECT OUR PEOPLE.
AND PROTECT -- IF YOU STAND UP
TO PEOPLE WHO ARE DOING THESE
THINGS, IT MAKES THEM MUCH LESS
LIKELY TO CONTINUE.
BUT AGAIN, BY HAVING A
PUBLIC/PRIVATE PARTNERSHIP,
BEING ABLE TO TAP INTO ALL OF
OUR RESOURCES, I THINK WE HAVE A
MUCH BETTER OPPORTUNITY TO
DEFEND OURSELVES AND TO PUT UP
THE KINDS OF DEFENSES THAT CAN
KEEP MORPHING SO THAT'S THEY
WILL NOT BE ABLE TO KEEP UP WITH
US.
AMERICANS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN
INCREDIBLY INNOVATIVE.
IF WE CAN RELEASE THAT
INNOVATION AND GET RID OF SOME
OF THE THINGS THAT DAMPEN THAT'S
INNOVATION, I THINK WE'LL STAY
FAR AHEAD OF THE COMPETITION.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
APPRECIATE IT.
I WANT YOU TO MEET BILLY, A
STAY-AT-HOME MOM.
SHE IS ALSO STILL UNDECIDED.
>> HELLO, DR. CARSON.
I DO APPRECIATE YOUR MILD
MANNERED NATURE AND IN THIS
CAMPAIGN.
HOWEVER, IF YOU ARE THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE, HOW DO YOU
PLAN TO NOT -- HOW DO YOU PLAN
TO GET YOUR MESSAGE OUT OVER A
BOISTEROUS DEMOCRAT?
>> WHICH BOISTEROUS DEMOCRAT
WOULD THAT BE?
NOW QUITE SIMPLY, WHAT I HAVE
DISCOVERED, AS A PEDIATRIC
NEUROSURGEON, AND AS SOMEONE WHO
DEALT WITH LOTS OF CHILDREN, I
HAD A PROGRAM AT THE HOSPITAL
WHERE I BRING IN 800 STUDENTS AT
A TIME.
FREQUENTLY ELEMENTARY STUDENTS.
AND YOU WOULD SAY, HOW ARE YOU
GOING TO BE ABLE TO SPEAK TO 800
ELEMENTARY STUDENTS AND KEEP
THEM QUIET?
YOU KNOW WHAT?
BY SPEAKING SOFTLY BECAUSE THEN
THEY WOULD THINK, OH, WHAT'S
HE'S SAYING AND THEY WOULD SHUT
UP.
IT ACTUALLY WORKED EXTREMELY
WELL.
BUT, REALLY, THE KEY IS NOT SO
MUCH THE VOLUME WITH WHICH YOU
SPEAK.
BUT IT'S THE CONTENT OF WHAT YOU
SAY.
THAT'S WHAT'S GOING TO MAKE THE
DIFFERENCE.
AND I THINK THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
ARE SMART ENOUGH TO BE ABLE TO
UNDERSTAND BLUSTER AND RHETORIC
VERSUS TRUTH.
AND WHEN IT COMES TO THE GENERAL
ELECTION, YOU KNOW, PEOPLE WHO
ARE RUNNING AROUND SAYING THINGS
LIKE, FREE COLLEGE FOR EVERYONE,
IT WILL BE VERY EASY TO COUNTER
THAT BY SIMPLY EDUCATING PEOPLE
AS TO THE ACTUAL FINANCIAL
CONDITION OF OUR NATION.
AND THAT'S NOT DONE.
I THINK MARGARET THATCHER
PROBABLY SAID IT BEST.
SHE SAID SOCIALISM IS GREAT
UNTIL YOU RUN OUT OF OTHER
PEOPLE'S MONEY.
AND THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT WOULD
HAPPEN AND WE WOULD EXPLAIN THAT
TO PEOPLE, AND I THINK THEY
WOULD UNDERSTAND.
SO I LOOK FORWARD TO SUCH A
CHALLENGE.
>> OF COURSE, IN JUST A --
[ APPLAUSE ]
IT'S NOT JUST, OBVIOUSLY, IN A
GERM ELECTION.
YOU'VE BEEN ON THE STAGE WITH
SOME BOISTEROUS FOLKS THE LAST
FEW MONTHS.
WHAT ARE YOU THINKING WHEN YOU
ARE ON A STAGE IN THOSE DEBATES?
WHAT'S IS GOING THROUGH YOUR
MIND?
>> HONESTLY, WHAT'S WAS GOING
THROUGH MY MIND IS WILL THESE
GUYS IN ANY WAY REMEMBER WHAT
HAPPENED IN2012 WHEN THEY TRIED
TO TEAR EACH OTHER APART, WHICH
WAS PROBABLY THE ONLY REASON
THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA WAS ABLE TO
WIN RE-ELECTION WITH A RECORD
THAT NO ONE COULD HAVE WON ON.
SO WE HAVE TO STOP FINDING WAYS
TO SNATCH DEFEAT FROM THE JAWS
OF VICTORY.
>> DO YOU HAVE A CANDIDATE YOU'D
PREFER TO RUN AGAINST IN A
GENERAL?
BERNIE SANDERS OR HILLARY
CLINTON?
>> I WOULD RELISH RUNNING
AGAINST EITHER ONE OF THEM.
IT WOULD NOT BE A PROBLEM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> OUR NEXT QUESTION COMES
FROM -- OH, I'M SORRY.
WE'RE GOING FOR SOME OF THE
PERSONAL QUESTIONS.
TAKE A SEAT HERE.
SO WAS IT HARD FOR YOU TO GIVE
UP SURGERY?
DO YOU TRAIN FOR THIS FOR SO
LONG.
YOU WERE AN EXCELLENT SURGEON BY
ALL ACCOUNTS.
>> SOME PEOPLE SAY I WAS JUST AN
OKAY SURGEON.
BUT, NO, I MISS VERY MUCH WHAT
MEDICINE USED TO BE.
I DO NOT MISS WHAT IT HAS
BECOME.
AND I THINK YOU WILL FIND IF YOU
TALK TO A LOT OF PEOPLE IN THE
MEDICAL PROFESSION THAT THEY'RE
NOT VERY HAPPY TODAY.
>> BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT ABLE TO
SPEND TIME WITH PATIENTS?
>> THERE ARE SO MANY NEW RULES
AND REGULATIONS.
AND, YES, THE ETHICS AND ALL THE
VARIOUS THINGS YOU HAVE.
YOU DON'T EVEN HAVE A CHANCE TO
LOOK AT THE PATIENT.
THERE'S A LOT OF INFORMATION
THAT YOU CAN GAIN FROM JUST
LOOKING AT SOMEBODY WHEN YOU ARE
TALKING TO THEM, WHICH IS AN
ESSENTIAL PART OF MEDICAL CARE
THAT'S BEING LOST.
SO I -- THAT'S THE REASON THAT I
HAVE DENOTED A DIFFERENT TYPE OF
SYSTEM THAT ACTUALLY COSTS LESS
THAN EITHER THE CURRENT
SO-CALLED AFFORDABLE CARE ACT OR
THE SYSTEM THAT WE HAVE BEFORE
THAT THAT PROVIDES EXCELLENT
CARE FOR EVERYBODY, INCLUDING
THE INDIGENT AND DOESN'T HAVE
ANY SUCCESS CLASS CITIZENS.
WE HAVE ENOUGH MONEY TO DO IT.
WE SPEND ALMOST TWICE AS MUCH
PER CAPITA ON HEALTH CARE AS
MANY OTHER NATIONS THAT HAVE
MUCH BETTER ACCESS.
AND WE HAVE SO MUCH DISRUPTION
AND INEFFICIENCY IN OUR SYSTEM
THAT CAN BE EASILY CORRECTED.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA PLAYS GOLF.
FORMER PRESIDENT GEORGE W. BUSH
PAINTS NOW.
USED TO CLEAR BRUSH OUT IN
TEXAS.
WHAT DO YOU DO TO RELAX?
>> PLAY POOL.
I LOVE TO PLAY POOL.
>> ARE YOU COMPETITIVE WHEN YOU
PLAY POOL?
>> I LIKE TO WIN.
AND I'LL TELL YOU, IT RELAXES
ME.
WHEN I WOULD COME HOME FROM A
BUSY DAY OF SURGERY, I WOULD
SHOOT POOL.
AND MY WIFE WHO DIDN'T KNOW HOW
TO PLAY POOL LEARNED HOW TO PLAY
POOL AND HAS BECOME AN EXCELLENT
PLAYER.
SHE'S GOOD COMPETITION.
IF I MISS UP, SHE WILL BEAT ME.
>> WHAT SORT OF MUSIC DO YOU
LISTEN TO?
>> I PRIMARILY LIKE CLASSICAL
MUSIC.
PARTICULARLY BAROQUE MUSIC.
>> DID YOU LISTEN TO THAT WHEN
YOU DID SURGERY?
>> YES.
ALL THE RESIDENTS KNEW THEY'D
ALSO LEARN CLASSICAL MUSIC.
I REMEMBER ONE RESIDENT, I'D
ALWAYS ASK HIM QUESTIONS.
HE'D ALWAYS SAY THAT'S THE 1812
OVERTURE.
HE SAID, I KNOW I'M GOING TO BE
RIGHT ONE TIME.
>> DR. CARSON, A PLEASURE.
DR. BEN CARSON, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WHEN WE COME BACK, SENATOR
MARCO RUBIO TAKES THE STAGE AND
TAKES YOUR QUESTIONS.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE MANAGE TO YOU FROM THE OLD
CIGAR WAREHOUSE IN GREENVILLE,
SOUTH CAROLINA.
THE FIRST OF TWO CONSECUTIVE
REPUBLICAN TOWN HALLS ON CNN.
THE NEXT ONE IS TOMORROW NIGHT
IN COLUMBIA FEATURING JOHN
KASICH, JEB BUSH AND DONALD
TRUMP.
RIGHT NOW, PLEASE WELCOME
SENATOR MARCO RUBIO OF FLORIDA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
HEY, SENATOR.
WELCOME.
HAVE A SEAT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SO WELCOME, FIRST OF ALL.
THANKS FOR BEING HERE.
>> IT'S A NICE PLACE.
>> IT'S A BEAUTIFUL BUILDING.
HOW IS IT FEELING ON THE
CAMPAIGN TRAIL AFTER A FIFTH
PLACE FINISH IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
>>> COUNTED YOU OUT.
YOU HAD A GOOD DEBATE.
MAJOR ENDORSEMENT FROM SOUTH
CAROLINA GOVERNOR NIKKI HALEY.
ARE YOU FEELING THE
MARCO-MENTUM?
>> PEOPLE ARE COMING TO OUR
RALLIES, SIGNING UP.
OBVIOUSLY, SATURDAY WE'LL FIND
OUT.
PEOPLE ARE GOING TO VOTE.
WE'RE GOING TO DO OUR BEST.
WE'VE GOT A GOOD MESSAGE.
I FEEL GOOD.
WE'LL SEE WHAT THAT TRANSLATES
TO.
>> IT'S GETTING TOUGH OUT THERE.
ACCUSATIONS GOING BACK AND
FORTH.
YOU CALLED TED CRUZ A LIAR.
HE SAID YOUR CAMPAIGN IS RELYING
ON FABRICATION.
REFUTED CLAIMS.
DO YOU STAND BY THE ACERTION
HE'S LYING?
>> IF YOU SAY SOMETHING THAT
ISN'T TRUE AND YOU KNOW THAT IT
ISN'T TRUE, THERE'S NO OTHER
WORD FOR IT.
WHEN IT'S ABOUT YOUR RECORD YOU
HAVE TO CLEAR IT UP.
IF YOU DON'T THEN PEOPLE SAY IT
MUST BE TRUE.
YOU DON'T DISPUTE IT.
WE SAW WHAT HE DID TO DR. CARSON
IN IOWA.
WE SAW YESTERDAY, TREY GOWDY,
SOMEONE CAME UP WITH A FAKE
FACEBOOK POST SAYING TREY GOWDY
WAS NO LONGER ENDORSING ME.
I'LL ADDRESS THEM.
THAT'S NOT THE CORE OF MY
CAMPAIGN.
I SPEND 99% OF MY TIME TALKING
ABOUT AMERICA'S FUTURE.
IF SOMEONE SAYS SOMETHING THAT'S
NOT TRUE AND I DON'T CLEAR IT
UP, THEN PEOPLE MAY THINK IT'S
NOT TRUE.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID
SOMETHING I WANT TO ASK YOU
ABOUT SO YOU CAN RESPOND TO IT.
HE SAID YESTERDAY YOU HAVE A
CANDIDATE WHO SPONSORED A BILL
THAT I SUPPORTED TO FINALLY
SOLVE THE IMMIGRATION PROBLEM
AND HE'S RUNNING AWAY FROM IT AS
FAST AS HE CAN.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS NO
STANDING TO TALK ABOUT
IMMIGRATION.
HIS PARTY CONTROLLED THE WHITE
HOUSE AND HOUSE AND SENATE FOR
TWO YEARS AND DID NOTHING.
AFTER BARACK OBAMA PUT IN PLACE
TWO UNCONSTITUTIONAL EXECUTIVE
ORDERS WHICH HAS MADE IT HARDER.
I BELIEVE THIS ISSUE HAS TO BE
DEALT WITH.
IF YOU ARE SERIOUS ABOUT DEALING
WITH IMMIGRATION, YOU BETTER
SECURE THE BORDER FIRST.
NOTHING ELSE IS GOING TO BE ABLE
TO HAPPEN.
NOTHING ELSE CAN HAPPEN UNTIL
YOU SECURE THE BORDER FIRST.
PEOPLE HAVE BEEN CLEAR ABOUT
THAT.
THAT'S THE KEY THAT UNLOCKS THE
DOOR TO DEALING WITH THE REST OF
THE ISSUE.
WE WON'T BE ABLE TO MAKE ANY
PROGRESS.
>> THE PRESIDENT IS SAYING, YOU
SPONSORED A BILL THAT HE'D
SUPPORT IT.
>> IT'S BEEN TRIED THREE TIMES
IN THE LAST DECADE.
IT'S FAILED EACH TIME.
NOW WE HAVE TO UNDERSTAND THAT
THE ONLY WAY FORWARD IS THROUGH
A STEP-BY-STEP APPROACH THAT
BEGINS BY FINALLY SECURING OUR
BORDER.
WE'RE A SOVEREIGN COUNTRY.
EVERY COUNTRY HAS A RIGHT TO
CONTROL WHO COMES HERE, WHEN
THEY COME HERE, HOW THEY COME
HERE.
WE'RE THE MOST GENEROUS NATION
IN THE WORLD ON IMMIGRATION.
>> DO YOU THINK IT COULD PASS?
>> I DIDN'T THINK THE SENATE
VERSION COULD PASS.
THIS BILL IS NOT STRONG ENOUGH.
I UNDERSTOOD THE DEMOCRATS
CONTROLLED THE SENATE.
THAT'S THE BEST WE COULD PRODUCE
IN A SENATE CONTROLLED BY
DEMOCRATS.
WE WANTED TO SEND IT TO THE
HOUSE.
WE'D HOPE THE HOUSE REPUBLICANS
WOULD MAKE IT BETTER.
THEY NEVER TOOK IT UP.
THERE'S NO WAY FORWARD.
I CAN JUST TELL YOU AFTER THAT
EXPERIENCE, FOR A FACT, HAVING
BEEN THROUGH THAT, NO PROGRESS
WILL BE MADE ON IMMIGRATION IN
THIS COUNTRY UNTIL WE PROVE TO
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, NOT JUST
PASS A LAW BUT PROVE TO THEM
WE'VE BUILT THE SUFFICIENT LAWS
AND FENCES ON THE BORDER THAT'S
WE HAVE MANDATORY E-VERIFY, AN
ENTRY/EXIT TRACKING SYSTEM TO
PREVENT VISA OVERSTAYS AND HIRE
ADDITIONAL BORDER SECURITY TO
SECURE THE BORDER.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU ABOUT A FEW
ITEMS MAKING HEADLINES TODAY.
IT'S A QUESTION I ASKED DR.
CARSON.
AS YOU KNOW, THE GOVERNMENT IS
TRYING TO GET APPLE TO CREATE
NEW SOFTWARE TO BASICALLY ALLOW
THEM TO UNLOCK THE PHONE USED BY
THE SAN BERNARDINO TERRORIST.
APPLE IS SAYING IF WE CREATE
THIS BACK DOOR IT'S A WHOLE NEW
SOFTWARE THING AND IT'S GOING TO
ENDANGER D99.9% OF THE GOOD
USERS.
>> IT'S ABOUT ENCRYPTION.
THERE'S ENCRYPTION OUT.
IT'S STANDARD ON THE NEW APPLE.
AND WHAT IT DOES IS IT PROTECTS
YOUR PRIVACY.
IF YOU LOSE YOUR iPAD OR iPHONE,
NO ONE CAN HACK IN AND GET THE
INFORMATION.
IF WE PASSED A LAW THAT REQUIRED
THEM TO CREATE A BACK DOOR,
CRIMINALS COULD FIGURE THAT OUT
AND USE IT AGAINST YOU.
THERE'S ALREADY ENCRYPTED
SOFTWARE THAT EXISTS AND WE'D
NOT BE ABLE TO STOP THAT.
THERE WOULD STILL BE ENCRYPTION
CAPABILITIES.
THEY JUST WOULDN'T BE AMERICAN
BUT PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY COULD
HAVE IT.
THAT'S WHY IT'S SUCH A DIFFICULT
ISSUE.
ON THE FLIP SIDE, THERE MIGHT BE
VALUABLE INFORMATION ON THAT
PHONE FROM THE SAN BERNARDINO
KILLERS THAT'S COULD LEAD US TO
PREVENTING FUTURE CRIMES OR
FUTURE TERRORIST ATTACKS.
SO I THINK WE ARE GOING TO HAVE
TO FIGURE OUT A WAY TOWARD BY
WORKING WITH SILICON VALLEY AND
THE TECH INDUSTRY.
THERE HAS TO BE A WAY THAT
CONTINUES TO PROTECT THE PRIVACY
OF AMERICANS BUT CREATES SOME
PROCESS BY WHICH LAW ENFORCEMENT
AND INTELLIGENCE AGENCIES COULD
ACCESS ENCRYPTED INFORMATION.
I DON'T HAVE A MAGIC SOLUTION.
IT'S COMPLICATED.
IT'S A NEW ISSUE THAT'S EMERGED.
BUT IT WILL TAKE A PARTNERSHIP
BETWEEN THE TECHNOLOGY INDUSTRY
AND THE GOVERNMENT TO CONFRONT
AND SOLVE THIS.
>> SO IT DOES CONCERN YOU,
BASICALLY APPLE'S CONCERNS, THE
IDEA THIS WOULD CREATE A BACK
DOOR --
>> IF YOU CREATE A BACK DOOR
THERE IS THE POSSIBILITY A
CRIMINAL GANG COULD FIGURE OUT
WHAT THE BACK DOOR IS.
THAT'S POSSIBILITY -- YOU CREATE
A BACK DOOR, YOU ARE CREATING A
VULNERABILITY.
YOU'LL NOT CHANGE THE FACT THAT
OTHER COMPANIES AROUND THE WORLD
WHO ARE NOT SUBJECT TO U.S. LAW,
THEY CAN CREATE ENCRYPTION THAT
WE'LL NEVER BE ABLE TO GET
ACCESS TO.
IT'S NOT AS SIMPLE AS PEOPLE
THINK.
APPLE IS UNDER COURT ORDER.
THEY NEED TO FOLLOW WHATEVER THE
COURT ORDER IS ULTIMATELY BUT
GOING FORWARD WE'LL HAVE TO WORK
WITH SILICON VALLEY, THE TECH
INDUSTRY TO FIGURE OUT A WAY
FORWARD ON ENCRYPTION THAT
ALLOWS US SOME CAPABILITY TO
ACCESS INFORMATION IN AN EXIGENT
CIRCUMSTANCE WHERE THERE MAY BE
INFORMATION ON THERE THAT COULD
PREVENT A TERRORIST ATTACK.
>> ANOTHER ITEM IN THE NEWS.
WE'VE JUST LEARNED PRESIDENT
OBAMA PLANS TO VISIT CUBA SOME
TIME, I THINK THIS MONTH BUT I
DON'T KNOW THE EXACT DATE.
IS THAT SOMETHING AS PRESIDENT
YOU WOULD EVER DO?
>> NOT IF IT'S NOT A FREE CUBA.
THE PROBLEM WITH THE CUBAN
GOVERNMENT.
IT'S NOT JUST A COMMUNIST
DICTATOR SHRNG IT'S AN
ANTI-AMERICAN COMMUNIST
DICTATORSHIP.
THEY HELPED NORTH KOREA EVADES
U.N. SANCTIONS.
THE CUBAN GOVERNMENT TODAY
HARBORS HUNDREDS OF FUGITIVES OF
AMERICAN JUSTICE.
PEOPLE THAT HAVE STOLEN YOUR
MONEY.
THEY COME TO THE U.S., STEAL
MONEY, MEDS CARE FRAUD, GO BACK
TO CUBA.
THE CUBAN GOVERNMENT IS
PROTECTING THEM.
THEY ARE HARBORING A KILLER FROM
NEW JERSEY WHO KILLED A STATE
TROOPER IN NEW JERSEY.
SHE ESCAPED JAIL, FLED TO CUBA.
THE CUBAN GOVERNMENT IS
PROTECTING HER.
BEYOND THAT, THEY ARE A
REPRESSIVE REGIME.
THERE'S NO ELECTION IN CUBA.
I WANT THE RELATIONSHIP TO
CHANGE BUT IT HAS TO BE
RECIPROCAL.
LOOK WHAT WE DID WITH BURMA.
TODAY THE FORMER MINORITY PARTY
IS NOW THE MAJORITY PARTY IN
THEIR LEGISLATIVE BODY BECAUSE
OUR CHANGE TOWARDS THEM WAS
CONDITIONAL ON THEIR CHANGE
TOWARDS THEIR PEOPLE.
HE DIDN'T ASK THAT OF THE CUBAN
PEOPLE.
A YEAR AND TWO MONTHS AFTER THE
OPENING OF CUBA, THE CUBAN
GOVERNMENT REMAINS AS
OPPRESSIVE.
NOW THEY HAVE ACCESS TO MILLIONS
IF NOT BILLIONS IN RESOURCES
THEY DIDN'T HAVE ACCESS TO.
>> I'M TOLD THE PRESIDENT IS
GOING NEXT MONTH.
>> PROBABLY NOT GOING TO INVITE
ME.
>> PROBABLY NOT.
>>> THIS IS MAGGIE.
A SENIOR AT FUHRMAN UNIVERSITY.
SHE'S LEANING IN YOUR FAVOR.
>> GOOD.
LET'S FINISH IT TONIGHT.
>> SHE LIKES DR. CARSON AS WELL.
>> I LIKE DR. CARSON AS WELL.
>> WELCOME TO GREENVILLE.
I'M SURE YOU'RE WELL AWARE THAT
COLLEGE AND STUDENT DEBT LOANS
ARE ON THE RISE.
AS SOMEONE WHO IS PLANNING TO
ATTEND DENTAL SCHOOL THIS
UPCOMING FALL BY ONLY IN-STATE
OPTION IS ABOUT $100,000 A YEAR
SETTING ME UP FOR ABOUT $500,000
OF DEBT BEFORE I HAVE THE CHANCE
TO MAKE A DIME OF IT BACK.
DO YOU CURRENTLY THINK THAT'S
THERE'S A PROBLEM WITH THE COST
OF EDUCATION?
>> YES.
>> AND IF SO, WHAT'S YOUR PLAN
TO MAKE IT MORE AFFORDABLE,
SPECIFICALLY, HOW DO YOU DEAL
WITH CUTTING COSTS FOR STUDENTS
BUT STILL MAINTAINING A HIGH
QUALITY OF EDUCATION?
>> I BELIEVE I'M THE ONLY
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATE THAT TALKS
ABOUT STUDENT LOAN DEBT.
ONE REASON WHY IS THREE YEARS
AGO, I STILL OWED OVER $100,000
IN STUDENT LOAN DEBT.
I WAS ONLY ABLE TO PAY OFF
BECAUSE I WROTE A BOOK CALLED
"AN AMERICAN SON" NOW AVAILABLE
IN PAPERBACK.
PEOPLE ALWAYS LAUGH.
I LOVE THAT JOKE.
IT'S NOT A JOKE.
IT IS AVAILABLE IN PAPERBACK.
I HAVE A BIPARTISAN AGENDA ON
THIS ISSUE.
FOUR MAIN THINGS.
THE FIRST IS ALTERNATIVE
CREDITING.
TODAY THERE ARE ONLY SIX
ACCREDITING BOARDS IN THE
COUNTRY.
YOU CAN ONLY AWARD A FOUR-YEAR
DEGREE IF YOU ARE ACREDITED BY
ONE OF THESE SIX INSTITUTION.
IT'S A MONOPOLY.
BECAUSE TODAY IN THE 21st
CENTURY, WE HAVE THE ABILITY TO
LEARN MULTIPLE WAYS.
YOU DON'T JUST HAVE TO SIT IN A
CLASSROOM.
THERE ARE SO MANY WAYS TO
ACQUIRE INFORMATION.
AND SO WHAT I PUSH FOR IS AN
ALTERNATIVE ACCREDITING MODLE
THAT ALLOWS ACCREDITED LEARNING.
GIVE PEOPLE CREDIT FOR WHAT
THEY'VE LEARNED THROUGH LIFE
EXPERIENCE, WORK EXPERIENCE,
MILITARY EXPERIENCE.
IF YOU HAVE MASTERED A SUBJECT,
YOU SHOULD NOT BE FORCED TO SIT
IN A CLASSROOM AND PAY TO TAKE A
COURSE ON SOMETHING YOU ALREADY
KNOW.
THIS ALTERNATIVE ACCREDITING
MODEL WOULD ALLOW US TO DO THIS.
YOU CAN'T USE FINANCIAL AID AND
THE PRIVATE SECTOR DOESN'T
RECOGNIZE IT.
I THINK WE NEED TO DO THAT.
THAT'S IMPORTANT FOR
NONTRADITIONAL STUDENTS.
LET'S SAY THERE'S A SINGLE
MOTHER.
SHE MAKES 2 -- $11 AN HOUR.
THE ONLY WAY SHE'LL MAKE MORE
MONEY IS TO GO BACK TO SCHOOL.
BUT SHE HAS TO WORK FULL TIME
DURING THE DAY AND RAISE HER
KIDS AT NIGHT.
IF THERE WAS AN ALTERNATIVE
ACCREDITING MODEL THAT ALLOWED
HER TO EARN CREDITS THROUGH WHAT
SHE LEARNED ON HER YEARS ON THE
JOB IT WOULD SHORTEN THAT TIME
IF NOT ALLOW HER TO COMPLETE
THAT DEGREE.
ALTERNATIVE ACCREDITING THAT
ALLOWS YOU TO GET THE MAXIMUM
AMOUNT OF CREDITS WITHOUT HAVING
TO PAY FOR IT IN AN INSTITUTION.
AND THE STUDENT INVESTMENT PLAN.
THIS WOULD ALLOW YOU TO GO TO A
PRIVATE INVESTMENT GROUP WHO
WOULD INVEST IN YOU THE WAY AN
INVESTMENT GROUP INVESTS IN A
BUSINESS.
THEY WOULD BELIEVE IN YOU SO
MUCH AND IN YOUR SUCCESS THAT
THEY WOULD PAY FOR YOUR COLLEGE.
IF YOU BECOME FINANCIALLY
SUCCESSFUL, THEY'LL MAKE THEIR
INVESTMENT BACK WITH A PROFIT.
IF YOU DO NOT, THEY'LL LOSE
THEIR MONEY AND MADE A BAD
INVESTMENT.
BUT ALL THE RISK IS ON THEM.
THE THIRD IS TO MAKE
INCOME-BASED REPAYMENT.
I HAVE THAT LAW RIGHT NOW THAT
I'M WORKING ON WITH MARK WARNER,
A DEMOCRAT FROM VIRGINIA.
WHY THAT IS IMPORTANT IS BECAUSE
I WOULD RATHER COLLECT $20 A
MONTH FROM A STUDENT THAN
NOTHING.
BECAUSE IF YOU ARE COLLECTING
$20, AT LEAST YOU ARE COLLECTING
$20 AND THEY AREN'T DEFAULTING
ON THE DEBT.
IF YOU DEFAULT THAT RUINS YOUR
CREDIT.
YOU CAN'T BUY A HOUSE.
IT REALLY HURTS YOU.
AND RIGHT TO KNOW BEFORE YOU GO
WHICH I'M WORKING ON WITH RON
WYDEN, THE DEMOCRAT FROM OREGON.
BEFORE YOU TAKE OUT A LOAN,
SCHOOLS HAVE TO TELL YOU HOW
MUCH PEOPLE MAKE WHEN THEY
GRADUATE FROM THAT SCHOOL WITH A
DEGREE YOU'RE SEEKING.
WHY IS THAT IMPORTANT?
IT WILL PROBABLY TEACH YOU THE
MARKET FOR ROMAN PHILOSOPHERS
HAS TIGHTENED.
SO YOU MAY NOT WANT TO BORROW
$50,000 UNLESS YOU'RE GOING TO
TEACH IT OR GO ON TO GRAD
SCHOOL.
IT'S GOING TO ALLOW YOU TO
COMPARE SCHOOLS AND LOOK AT TWO
DIFFERENT SCHOOLS AND SAY I WANT
TO MAJOR IN HISTORY.
A HISTORY MAJOR FROM THIS SCHOOL
MAKES 50 GRAND A YEAR AND IT
ONLY COST $20,000.
A HISTORY MAJOR FROM THIS SCHOOL
MAKES $50,000 A YEAR BUT IT COST
$100,000.
NOW YOU HAVE SOMETHING TO MAKE A
DECISION ON OTHER THAN THE U.S.
NEWS AND WORLD REPORT COLLEGE
RANKING.
THIS IS THE KINDS OF THINGS I'M
WORKING ON BECAUSE THIS IS
DEEPLY PERSONAL.
WHEN I GRADUATED  -- WHEN I GOT
MARRIED, MY LARGEST PAYMENT
AFTER THE RENT WAS OUR STUDENT
LOAN DEBT.
OVER $1,000 A MONTH.
I ALWAYS JOKE THAT I NEVER MET
HER BUT I PAID SALLIE MAE A LOT
OF MONEY.
AND TODAY HIGHER EDUCATION IS A
NECESSARITY.
IT'S NO LONGER A LUXURY.
THERE ARE NO GOOD PAYING JOBS
WITHOUT SOME SKILL AND/OR
EDUCATIONAL ACHIEVEMENT IN THE
DWONst
21st CENTURY.
I DO THINK IT'S A BIG ISSUE AND
I WANT US TO WORK ON IT.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I'M GOING TO THROW AWAY MY ROMAN
PHILOSOPHY QUESTION.
>> I DIDN'T DO WELL WITH ROMAN
PHILOSOPHY.
>> MEET RETIRED GENERAL McMANUS.
HE IS STILL DECIDING BETWEEN YOU
AND GOVERNOR KASICH.
GENERAL?
>> SENATOR RUBIO, MANY WOULD
ARGUE THAT'S WE'RE NOT ONLY
ELECTING A PRESIDENT THIS CYCLE
BUT OUR COMMANDER IN CHIEF TO
LEAD AMERICA IN DEALING WITH
SOME VERY DEMANDING NATIONAL
SECURITY ISSUES AHEAD.
>> YES, SIR.
>> WHAT HAS PREPARED YOU THE
MOST FOR THIS CRITICAL MISSION
AND WHAT STRENGTHS OF YOUR
FOUNDATION FOR THE TRUST AND
CONFIDENCE OUR SOLDIERS, SAILORS
AND AIRMEN AND MARINES MUST HAVE
IN YOU.
>> FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU FOR
YOUR SERVICE.
I WANT TO THANK ALL THE VETERANS
OF SOUTH CAROLINA AND ACROSS THE
COUNTRY FOR THE SERVICE THEY
PROVIDED TO OUR COUNTRY.
IT'S NOT JUST ELECTING A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
THAT'S THE MOST IMPORTANT JOB.
THE PRESIDENT DOESN'T RUN THE
ECONOMY.
THE PRIVATE SECTOR DOES.
T
NATIONAL SECURITY AND COMMANDER
IN CHIEF IS THE MOST IMPORTANT
JOB OF THE PRESIDENT.
I SAY THIS WITHOUT ANY
RESERVATION.
I HAVEN'T LIVED AS LONG AS SOME
OF THE PEOPLE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT BUT NO ONE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT, ESPECIALLY ON THE
REPUBLICAN SIDE, HAS MORE
EXPERIENCE ON NATIONAL SECURITY
OR FOREIGN POLICY THAN I DO.
AS BOTH A MEMBER OF THE
INTELLIGENCE COMMITTEE AND
FOREIGN RELATIONS COMMITTEE OVER
THE LAST FIVE YEARS I'VE BEEN
DEALING WITH EVERY SINGLE MAJOR
ISSUE THIS COUNTRY CONFRONTS.
I UNDERSTAND THESE ISSUES WELL.
I HAVE A RECORD OF GOOD JUDGMENT
ON THOSE ISSUES.
IN 2011 WHEN MOAMMAR GADHAFI WAS
FACING HIS OVERFLOW I ARGUED IF
THAT BECAME A PROTRACTED ED
CONFLUCT IT WOULD LEAVE A
VACUUM.
WHEN BASHAR ASSAD WAS BEING
OVERTHROWN.
I SAID THEY'D BE KILLED OR
EXILED N THAT VACUUM WOULD BE
FILLED BY A RADICAL JIHADIST
GROUP.
AND THAT'S WHAT HAPPENED WITH AL
NASRA AND ISIS.
WHEN ISIS EMERGED AND CROSSED
INTO IRAQ, I WARNED THAT THEY
WOULD BECOME A MAJOR THREAT IF
NOT CONFRONTED AND DEFEATED
IMMEDIATELY.
THE PRESIDENT CALLED IN THE JV
TEAM.
TODAY THEY HAVE AFFILIATES IN
OVER A DOZEN TEAMS AND THEY --
WE SAW WHAT THEY DID IN SAN
BERNARDINO, WHAT'S THEY INSPIRED
IN PARIS AS WELL.
OVER THE LAST FIVE YEARS I'VE
BEEN INVOLVED IN FOREIGN POLICY
AND NATIONAL SECURITY I'VE
PROVEN THAT I HAVE BOTH THE
JUDGMENT AND THE EXPERIENCE TO
MAKE THE RIGHT DECISIONS AND THE
RIGHT CALL ON THESE ISSUES.
THE HARDEST VOTE I'VE EVER TAKEN
WAS A VOTE TO AUTHORIZE THE USE
OF FORCE IN SYRIA.
TALKED ABOUT THIS IN THE DEBATE
THE OTHER NIGHT.
IT'S THE MOST DIFFICULT VOTE
YOU'LL EVER TAKE IN CONGRESS.
WHEN BASHAR AL ASSAD GASSED HIS
OWN PEOPLE AND POISONED THEM,
PRESIDENT OBAMA ANNOUNCED HE'D
NOT TAKE MILITARY ACTION UNLESS
WE IN CONGRESS AUTHORIZED THE
USE OF THAT FORCE.
SO I WAS ANGRY WHEN I SAW THE
IMAGES.
I'M SURE YOU SAW THE SAME
I LOOKED AT THESE PICTURES OF
LITTLE CHILDREN, CURLED UP, SOME
DEAD ALREADY BECAUSE THEIR OWN
LEADER USED POISONED GAS AND
BIOLOGICAL AGENTS AGAINST THEMG.
I WAS OUTRAGED AND WANTED US TO
EXACT REVENGE ON THEM.
THEN I LOOKED AT WHAT THE
PRESIDENT WAS PROPOSING.
SOMETHING JOHN KERRY CALL AN
ATTACK THAT WOULD BE
UNBELIEVABLY LIMITED.
THAT ATTACK THE PRESIDENT WANTED
TO CARRY OUT I CONCLUDED WOULD
BE COUNTERPRODUCTIVE.
IT ACTUALLY WOULD HAVE EMPOWERED
ASAUD.
ALL HE WAS GOING TO DO WAS A
SYMBOLIC STRIKE.
ASSAD WAS GOING TO EMERGE FROM
IT SAYING I TOOK ON THE U.S. AND
HELD ON.
IT WOULD HAVE MADE HIM STRONGER,
NOT WEAKER.
I CONCLUDED I WOULD NOT VOTE TO
AUTHORIZE THE USE OF FORCE.
IT WAS A TOUGH DECISION BECAUSE
WHAT I HAD SEEN IN THOSE IMAGES
THAT'S OUTRAGED US ALL.
I CAN LOOK AT THAT FIELD OF
CANDIDATES RUNNING TODAY AND
TELL YOU WITHOUT ANY HESITATION
THAT'S NO ONE RUNNING AS A
REPUBLICAN HAS SHOWN BETTER
JUDGMENT OR HAS MORE EXPERIENCE
ON NATIONAL SECURITY OR ON
FOREIGN POLICY THAN I DO.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, GENERAL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> JUST WANT TO FOLLOW UP WITH
THAT.
QUICK FOLLOW-UP.
GOVERNOR BUSH AGAIN CONTINUED
HIS LINE OF ATTACK ON YOU SAYING
YOU'RE INEXPERIENCED.
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO REPUBLICANS
IN SOUTH CAROLINA WHO SAY DO WE
REALLY WANT ANOTHER FIRST TERM
SENATOR IN THE WHITE HOUSE?
>> SURE.
I WOULD TELL YOU THAT I BELIEVE
BARACK OBAMA IS A FAILED
PRESIDENT NOT BECAUSE HE WAS A
ONE TERM SENATOR.
HE HAS SEVEN YEARS OF
PRESIDENTIAL EXPERIENCE.
ONLY TWO PEOPLE IN THE WORLD
WITH MORE EXPERIENCE THAN HE
DOES, GEORGE W. BUSH AND BILL
CLINTON.
TODAY SEVEN YEARS, HE IS WORSE
IN THE SEVEN th YEAR THAN IN HIS
FIRST.
CLEARLY EXPERIENCE WAS NOT THE
ISSUE.
THE REASON HE'S FAILED AS A
PRESIDENT IS BECAUSE HIS IDEAS
DON'T WORK.
HIS PHILOSOPHY, HIS IDEOLOGY IS
A FAILED ONE.
I ALSO THINK IT'S UNFAIR TO SAY
I HAVE NO EXPERIENCE.
I HAVE 15 YEARS OF EXPERIENCE OF
TURNING CONSERVATIVE IDEAS INTO
CONSERVATIVE ACTION.
I SERVED 8 1/2 YEARS IN THE
FLORIDA LEGISLATURE.
NOT AS A BACK BENCHER BUT A
LEADER.
WE'VE BEEN TALKING ABOUT
IMMINENT DOMAIN.
FLORIDA HAS SOME OF THE BEST
IMINENT DOMAIN LAWS IN THE
COUNTRY.
YOU KNOW WHO PASSED THAT LAW?
I DID.
I WAS SPEAKER OF THE FLORIDA
HOUSE.
WE BROUGHT CAREER ACADEMIES TO
OUR HOUSE.
STUDENTS AND HIGH SCHOOLS IN
FLORIDA GRADUATE NOT JUST WITH A
HIGH SCHOOL DIPLOMA BUT
CERTIFIED TO WORK AS WELDERS,
PLUMBERS, ELECTRICIANS, PIPE
FITTERS IN VOCATIONAL TRAINING
BECAUSE OF WHAT WE'VE PUT IN.
WE'VE REDUCED PROPERTY TAXES
BECAUSE I LED THE EFFORT TO DO
THAT.
WE BROUGHT THE HARLEM'S OWN
CHILDREN'S MODEL INTO FLORIDA.
WE REFORMED OUR CURRICULUM
WITHOUT COMMON CORE, WITHOUT THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
AND IN MY TIME IN THE SENATE,
THE SENATE HAS NOT BEEN THE MOST
ACTIVE PLACE IN THE LAST FIVE
YEARS BECAUSE I LED THE EFFORT
IN A BIPARTISAN WAY WE IMPOSED
SANCTIONS ON HEZBOLLAH.
GOT RID OF THE OBAMACARE
BAIL-OUT ACT.
WE LEVERAGE U.S. FOREIGN AID TO
TAKE ON THE SCOURGE OF HUMAN
TRAFFICKING AND MODERN DAY
SLAVERY AROUND THE WORLD.
WE IMPOSED SANCTIONS ON HUMAN
RIGHTS VIOLATIONERS IN
VENEZUELA.
MY CAMPAIGN IS NOT ABOUT THE
PAST.
IT'S ABOUT THE FUTURE.
ABOUT WHAT WE'RE GOING TO DO.
I CAN SAY THIS WITHOUT ANY, ANY
HESITATION WHATSOEVER, I AM AS
CONSERVATIVE AS ANYONE RUNNING
FOR PRESIDENT.
BUT I AM A 15-YEAR CONSERVATIVE
WHO HAS PROVEN TIME AND AGAIN
THE CAPABILITY AND WILLINGNESS
TO TAKE CONSERVATIVE IDEAS AND
TURN THEM INTO CONSERVATIVE
SOLUTIONS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET PATTY
STONER.
SHE'S LIVED IN GREENVILLE FOR 40
YEARS.
SHE'S DECIDING BETWEEN YOU AND
SENATOR CRUZ.
>> I HAVE A NEPHEW CURRENTLY
SERVING AND IS DEPLOYED IN THE
MIDDLE EAST AS A PERSON ON AN
ELITE TEAM.
THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF DISCUSSION
ABOUT WOMEN IN COMBAT.
AND MY CONCERN IS IF YOU PUT
WOMEN ON THE FRONT LINE, YOU
WOULD HAVE TO LESSEN STANDARDS.
AND THAT WOULD PUT MORE TROOPS
AT ARM'S LENGTH AND ENDANGER.
ALSO, DO YOU FEEL LIKE WOMEN CAN
COMPETE ON THE SAME LEVEL TO BE
ABLE TO GET A POSITION ON
SPECIAL FORCES?
>> WELL, I DO NOT BELIEVE THAT
THE MILITARY IS A PLACE WHERE WE
SHOULD BE LOWERING STANDARDS IN
ORDER TO MEET SOME SORT OF OTHER
GOAL.
I BELIEVE THAT I'M OPEN TO
PEOPLE IN BOTH GENDERS SERVING
SO LONG AS THEY CAN MEET THE
MINIMUM REQUIREMENTS.
WE CAN'T WEAKEN THOSE TO
ACCOMMODATE SOMEBODY INTO THE
JOB.
LIVES ARE ALL THE LINE.
AND NATIONAL SECURITY IS ON THE
LINE.
BY THE WAY, THERE ARE PLENTY OF
MEN WHO CAN'T MEET THOSE
STANDARDS EITHER.
WE SHOULD NOT LOWER STANDARDS
FOR ANYONE.
THIS IS NOT A GAME.
YOU ARE PUTTING PEOPLE INTO
HARM'S WAY WHERE THEY HAVE TO BE
ABLE NOT SIMPLY TO DO THE JOB IN
FRONT OF THEM BUT ALSO TO BE
ABLE TO PROTECT THE PEOPLE
WORKING ALONGSIDE THEM.
AND SO FOR ME, IT'S NOT ABOUT
THE GENDER.
IT'S ABOUT THE ABILITY TO DO THE
JOB.
AS PRESIDENT AND COMMANDER IN
CHIEF, I WILL NOT LOWER
STANDARDS IN ORDER, TOO CHIEF
SOME SORT OF SOCIETAL AIM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
THIS IS JOSHUA GOODWIN, THE VICE
CHAIR OF THE UPSTATE YOUNG
REPUBLICANS.
HE SAYS HE'S VOTING FOR YOU ON
SUNDAY.
>> GOOD.
LET'S NOT BLOW IT.
>> GOOD EVENING, SENATOR.
WELCOME BACK TO GREENVILLE.
MY QUESTION IS REGARDING THE
CHARLESTON SHOOTING.
MYSELF AND MANY SOUTH
CAROLINIANS WERE DEVASTATED BY
THE HATRED OF RACISM.
AS A LEADER, I'D LIKE TO KNOW,
HOW WOULD YOU SIMULTANEOUSLY
ADDRESS THE ISSUE OF RACISM, YET
UNIFY US AS A COUNTRY.
>> YES, SIR.
THAT'S AN IMPORTANT QUESTION.
LET ME BEGIN BY SAYING THE
ENTIRE COUNTRY WAS INSPIRED BY
THE WAY SOUTH CAROLINA AND IN
PARTICULAR THE PEOPLE IMPACTED
AT MOTHER EMMANUEL CHURCH
REACTED TO THE SHOOTING.
THE IMAGES OF THESE FAMILY
MEMBERS SAYING ON TELEVISION WE
FORGIVE THE KILLER HAD AN IMPACT
ON THE COUNTRY THAT WAS
PROFOUND.
IT SAYS A LOT ABOUT SUCCESS.
IT ALSO SAYS A LOT ABOUT THE
ROLE THAT FAITH PLAYS IN THIS
STATE.
IF YOU ASK PEOPLE ABOUT IT,
THEY'LL TELL YOU THE CHURCH WAS
AT THE CENTER OF NOT HOW SOUTH
CAROLINA RESPONDED NOT JUST TO
THAT SHOOTING BUT A PREVIOUS
POLICE SHOOTING AND TO A FLOOD
THAT WAS A 1,000-YEAR EVENT.
YOU TALK ABOUT RACE RELATIONS.
IT'S A DIFFICULT ISSUE IN THIS
COUNTRY.
I CAN TELL YOU AND A LOT OF IT
IS CENTERED AROUND LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND POLICE
DEPARTMENTS.
I KNOW FOR A FACT THAT THE
OVERWHELMING MAJORITY OF THE MEN
AND WOMEN WHO SERVE US IN LAW
ENFORCEMENT ARE INCREDIBLE
PEOPLE.
WHO EVERY SINGLE DAY PUT THEIR
LIVES POTENTIALLY ON THE LINE
FOR OUR SAFETY AND SECURITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT I ALSO KNOW -- BUT I ALSO
KNOW THAT THERE ARE COMMUNITIES
IN THIS COUNTRY WHERE MINORITY
COMMUNITIES AND THE POLICE
DEPARTMENT HAVE A TERRIBLE
RELATIONSHIP.
I PERSONALLY KNOW SOMEONE WHO
HAPPENS TO BE A POLICE OFFICER
AND A YOUNG AFRICAN-AMERICAN
MALE WHO TOLD ME THAT HE'S BEEN
PULLED OVER SEVEN, EIGHT TIMES
IN THE LAST FEW YEARS AND NEVER
GETS A TICKET.
WHAT IS HE SUPPOSED TO THINK?
HE GETS PULLED OVER, NEVER GETS
A TICKET.
NO ONE HAS ANY EXPLANATION.
WHAT IS HE SUPPOSES TO THINK?
I ALSO KNOWN IN THIS COUNTRY
FLOOS A SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF
YOUNG AFRICAN-AMERICAN MALES WHO
FEEL AS IF THEY ARE TREATED
DIFFERENTLY THAN THE REST OF
SOCIETY.
HERE'S THE BOTTOM LINE.
WHETHER YOU AGREE WITH THEM OR
NOT, I HAPPEN TO HAVE SEEN THIS
HAPPEN.
WHETHER YOU AGREE OR NOT, IF A
SIGNIFICANT PERCENTAGE OF THE
AMERICAN FAMILY BELIEVES THAT
THEY ARE BEING TREATED
DIFFERENTLY THAN EVERYONE ELSE,
WE HAVE A PROBLEM.
AND WE HAVE TO ADDRESS IT AS A
SOCIETY AND AS A COUNTRY.
I DO NOT BELIEVE WE CAN FULFILL
OUR POTENTIAL AS A NATION UNLESS
WE ADDRESS THAT.
I'M NOT SURE THERE'S A POLITICAL
SOLUTION TO THAT PROBLEM BUT
THERE ARE THINGS WE CAN DO.
ONE REASON YOU SEE EDUCATIONAL
AND ACADEMIC UNDERPERFORMANCE
NOT JUST IN THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
COMMUNITY BUT IN THE HISPANIC
COMMUNITY IS BECAUSE A
DISPROPORTIONATE NUMBER OF OUR
CHILDREN ARE GROWING UP IN
BROKEN HOMES IN DANGEROUS
NEIGHBORHOODS LEAVING IN
SUBSTANDARD HOUSING AND FORCED
BY THE GOVERNMENT TO ATTEND A
FAILING SCHOOL.
THEY'RE GOING TO STRUGGLE TO
SUCCEED UNLESS SOMETHING BREAKS
THAT PSYCHELE.
WE'VE SEEN THINGS THAT WORK.
YOU GET INVOLVED IN THE LIVES OF
CHILDREN N ADDRESS THOSE STRAKS
AGAINST THEM AND YOU CAN SEE THE
SAME RESULTS YOU'D SEE ANYWHERE
ELSE IN THE COUNTRY.
I DO BELIEVE AS A SOCIETY WE
HAVE TO CONFRONT THIS BECAUSE
ULTIMATELY, IF A SIGNIFICANT
PERCENTAGE OF THE AMERICAN
FAMILY FEELS THAT THEY ARE
LOCKED OUT OF THE PROMISE OF
AMERICA, WE WILL NEVER BE ABLE
TO FULFILL OUR DESTINY AS A
GREAT NATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> A QUICK FOLLOW-UP.
ON A PERSONAL BASIS, HAVE YOU
EVER FELT THE STING OF RACISM?
>> YOU KNOW, LET ME TELL YOU A
COUPLE OF THINGS.
MY PARENTS WERE EXTRAORDINARY
PEOPLE.
THEY RAISED ME TO BELIEVE THAT
IT DIDN'T MATTER THAT THEY CAME
FROM CUBA AND HE WAS A
BARTENDER, SHE WAS A MADE.
THERE WAS NOTHING WE COULDN'T
DO.
I REMEMBER DURING THE MARIO BOAT
LIFT GROWING UP IN LAS VEGAS,
THAT SOME OF THE NEIGHBORHOOD
KIDS, OLDER KIDS, ONE DAY WERE
TAUNTSING MY FAMILY SAYING, WHY
DON'T YOU GO BACK ON YOUR BOAT
GO BACK TO YOUR COUNTRY.
I DIDN'T KNOW WHAT THEY WERE
TALKING ABOUT?
WHAT BOAT?
MY MOM DOESN'T EVEN SWIM.
APHRAFRAID OF WATER.
AND THE MARIO BOAT LIFT IS GOING
ON.
PEOPLE ARE UPSET AND THEY ARE
HEARING THIS STUFF.
DON'T BLAME THE KIDS.
THEY MUST BE HEARING IT FROM
SOMEBODY.
THAT DISTURBED ME AS A YOUNG
CHILD.
FOR THE MOST PART IN MY LIFE, I
NEVER SAW THAT AS A REFLECTION
ON AMERICA BUT AS A REFLECTION
ON THOSE KIDS.
MY PARENTS NEVER RAISED US TO
FEEL THAT WE WERE VICTIMS.
THEY ALWAYS RAISED US TO BELIEVE
OUR DESTINY AND FUTURE, WE LIVE
IN THE ONE PLACE ON EARTH WHERE
IF YOU WORKED HARD AND
PERSEVERED YOU COULD ACHIEVE.
THAT DOESN'T MEAN I DON'T DENY
THERE ARE THOSE WHO HAVE HAD A
DIFFERENT EXPERIENCE.
AND WE HAVE TO RECOGNIZE THAT.
IF YOU LOOK BACK AT THE HISTORY
OF THIS COUNTRY, WE HAVE SOME
BLEMISHES THAT EVEN TO THIS DAY
WE'RE FIGHTING THROUGH.
WHAT'S EXTRAORDINARY ABOUT
AMERICA IS THAT WE'VE FOUGHT
THROUGH THAT.
A NATURE OF PERPETUAL
IMPROVEMENT.
IF YOU LOOK AT HOW FAR WE'VE
COME SINCE THE 1960s.
IF YOU LOOK AT WHERE SOUTH
CAROLINA IS TODAY COMPARED TO
30, 40 YEARS AGO.
IN MY CAMPAIGN FOR PRESIDENT I
GOT THE ENDORSEMENT OF A
CANDIDATE OF INDIAN DESCENT AND
TOMORROW WE'LL BE CAMPAIGNING
ALONG AN AFRICAN-AMERICAN
MEMBER.
THAT SAYS A LOT ABOUT SOUTH
CAROLINA.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET DOUGLAS
PARROT.
HE WAS LEANING TOWARD DONALD
TRUMP.
>> THE UNITED STATES ECONOMY
SEEMS TO BE CHUGGING ALONG AT AN
ANEMIC 2% GDP.
HOUSEHOLD INCOMES ARE DOWN.
WORKPLACE PARTICIPATION IS DOWN.
THE STOCK MARKET SEEMS TO BE
TRENDING DOWN.
AND THE FED HAS BEEN SYSTTIMULAG
OUR ECONOMY FOR THE PAST DECADE
AND THIS IS WHAT WE HAVE TO SHOW
FOR IT.
COULD YOU PRIORITIZE THREE
ACTIONS TO TURN THIS ECONOMIC
SHIP AROUND?
>> LET ME ADDRESS THE FED ISSUE.
THAT'S NOT THE FED'S JOB TO
STIMULATE THE ECONOMY.
THE FED IS A CENTRAL BANK NOT AN
OVERLORD OF THE ECONOMY.
NOT SOME SORT OF SPECIAL JEDI
COUNCIL.
THE FED IS A CENTRAL BANK.
THEIR JOB IS TO PROVIDE STABLE
CURRENCY.
I BELIEVE THEY SHOULD OPERATE ON
A RULES-BASED SYSTEM WHERE THEY
HAVE A VERY SIMPLE RULE THAT
DETERMINES WHEN INTEREST RATE
GOES UP AND WHEN THEY GO DOWN.
TODAY IT'S LIKE A MAGIC 8 BALL.
WE DON'T KNOW AND IT CREATES
UNCERTAINTY IN THE MARKETPLACE.
YOUR QUESTION GOES TO THE CORE
OF SOMETHING DEEPER.
WE ARE LIVING THROUGH A MASSIVE
AND RAPID ECONOMIC
TRANSFORMATION.
THIS IS NOT AN ECONOMIC DOWNTURN
TO.
A MASSIVE ECONOMIC
TRANSFORMATION.
WE'RE HAVING THE INDUSTRIAL
REVOLUTION EVERY FIVE YEARS.
YOU CAN BE ON THE KCUTTING EDGE
OF AN INDUSTRY TODAY AND IN FIVE
YEARS IT'S OBVIOUS LET'S.
I
-- OBSOLETE.
THE NEW JOBS REQUIRE SKILLS MANY
OF OUR PEOPLE MAY NOT HAVE
BECAUSE THEY HAVEN'T BEEN
TRAINED FOR IT.
WE HAVE TO MAKE OURSELVES A
FRIENDLIER PLACE.
YOU LOOK AT SOUTH CAROLINA.
WHY IS SOUTH CAROLINA ATTRACTING
MANUFACTURING?
I'LL TELL YOU WHAT IT'S DOING.
IT'S LOWERING ITS TAXES.
REDUCING THE REGULATORY BURDEN.
THESE THINGS ARE IMPORTANT.
AS PRESIDENT, I WANT TO BE AN
ACTIVE AND VIBRANT ADVOCATE FOR
SETTING AN AGENDA THAT WE'RE
GOING TO SIMPLIFY OUR TAX CODE.
THE HIGHEST COMBINED CORPORATE
TAX RATE.
I WANT TO LOW TER TO A FLAT RATE
OF 25%.
INCLUDING SMALL BUSINESSES,
ORGANIZED AS SUBCHAPTER S.
PAYING AS HIGH AS 39.5%.
I WANT BUSINESSES TO INVEST
EVERY DOLLAR INTO THEIR
BUSINESS.
I WANT TO MOVE TO A TERRITORIAL
SYSTEM OF TAXATION.
WE'RE THE LAST MAJOR INDUSTRIAL
COUNTRY THAT DOUBLE TAXES ITS
COMPANIES FROM MAKING MONEY
OVERSEAS.
YOU HAVE $2 TRILLION OF AMERICAN
CORPORATE CASH SITTING OVERSEAS.
$2 TRILLION IS EQUIVALENT TO THE
GDP OF RUSSIA.
THAT'S HOW MUCH AMERICAN
CORPORATE CASH IS NOT BEING
INVESTED HERE AND IS INSTEAD
BEING INVESTED OVERSEAS.
REGULATORY REFORM IS IMPORTANT.
A REGULATORY BUDGET THAT SAYS
WE'RE GOING TO PUT A HARD CAP ON
HOW MUCH FEDERAL REGULATIONS CAN
COST OUR ECONOMY.
N THAT WILL FORCE AGENCIES TO
REDUCE REGULATIONS AND IT WILL
SAY IF YOU'LL ADD A NEW
REGULATION YOU'LL HAVE TO CUT AN
XI
EXISTING ONE BECAUSE REGULATIONS
ARE A BURDEN.
THE THIRD THING IS THE NATIONAL
DEBT.
IT IS $19 TRILLION WITH CLOSE TO
$100 TRILLION IN UNFUNDED
LIABILITIES.
WE'LL HAVE A DEBT CRISIS IN
AMERICA SOON IF WE DO NOT
ADDRESS IT.
IN LESS THAN FIVE YEARS, 83% OF
THE FEDERAL BUDGET WILL BE
CONSUMED BY MEDICARE, MEDICAID,
SOCIAL SECURITY AND THE INTEREST
ON THE DEBT.
ONLY 17% OF OUR BUDGET LEFT FOR
EVERYTHING ELSE, INCLUDING THE
MILITARY.
THAT'S UNACCEPTABLE.
THAT'S A DEBT CRISIS.
I WANT US TO SAVE SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE.
WE CAN DO IT WITHOUT DISRUPTING
IT FOR PEOPLE THAT ARE ON IT
NOW.
MY MOTHER IS ON SOCIAL SECURITY
AND MEDICARE.
I'M AGAINST ANY CHANGES TO THOSE
PROGRAMS THAT'S BAD FOR MY
MOTHER.
BUT IT WON'T LOOK THE SAME FOR
ME.
INSTEAD OF RETIRING AT 67, I MAY
HAVE TO RETIRE AT 68.
IF I WAS IN THE SENATE, I'D BE
ONE OF THE YOUNGEST PEOPLE
THERE.
IF I MADE A LOT OF MONEY, MY
SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS MAY NOT
GROW AS FAST AS THEY DO FOR
SOMEONE WHO MADE LOTS OF MONEY.
MEDICARE COULD BE THE OPTION OF
USING MY MONEY TO BUY A PLAN I
LIKE BETTER.
THESE ARE NOT UNREASONABLE
CHANGES.
THEY AREN'T TOO MUCH TO ASK OF
ME WHO IS 25 YEARS AWAY FROM
RETIREMENT IN EXCHANGE FOR
BALANCING OUR BUDGET, BRINGING
OUR DEBT UNDER CONTROL AND
LEAVING SOCIAL SECURITY AND
MEDICARE UNDISTURBED FOR CURRENT
BENEFICIARIES.
YOU DEAL WITH OUR DEBT, SCALE
DOWN OUR TAX CODE AND YOU'LL SEE
AMERICA LEAD THE WORLD IN THE
21st CENTURY ECONOMY.
WE FAIL TO DO THAT, WE REMAIN
STAGNANT LIKE WE ARE NOW.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, WE'RE GOING TO
TAKE A QUICK BREAK.
WE'LL BE BACK IN A MOMENT WITH
MORE VOTER QUESTIONS FOR SENATOR
MARCO RUBIO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE HERE WITH SENATOR MARCO
RUBIO.
BEFORE WE GET BACK TO AUDIENCE
QUESTIONS, JUST TODAY, SANDRA
JUSTICE DAY O'CONNOR SAID THERE
SHOULD BE NO DELAY IN FILLING
THE VACANCY LEFT BY JUSTICE
SCALIA'S DEATH.
SHE SAID WE NEED SOMEBODY THERE
TO DO THE JOB.
>> I WOULD SAY A COUPLE OF
THINGS.
THERE'S AN 80-YEAR PRECEDENCE ON
THIS.
IN THE LAST YEAR, THE SENATE
DOESN'T USUALLY MOVE FORWARD.
YOU ARE APPOINTING SOMEONE TO A
LIFETIME APPOINTMENT
THEORETICALLY TO THE SUPREME
COURT.
SO THE SUPREME COURT CAN
FUNCTION WITH EIGHT JUSTICES.
AND THEN THEIR TERM WILL END AND
A NEW ONE WILL BEGIN.
THIS WILL BE AN ISSUE IN THE
CAMPAIGN.
VOTERS ARE GOING TO ASK OF THE
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES, WHAT
KIND OF JUSTICE ARE YOU GOING TO
APPOINT.
THERE'S GOING TO BE AN ELECTION
AND THE NEW PRESIDENT WILL HAVE
AN OPPORTUNITY TO NOMINATE
SOMEONE.
THAT'S THE APPROACH I SUPPORT.
>> YOU SAID THERE'S BEEN A
PRECEDENT.
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID THERE'S
NOTHING IN THE CONSTITUTION THAT
SAYS YOU CAN'T.
IF YOU WERE PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU
NOMINATE SOMEONE?
>> NO, I WOULD RESPECT THAT
PRECEDENT.
THERE'S NOTHING IN THE
CONSTITUTION THAT SAYS HE CAN'T
NOMINATE SOMEONE.
THERE'S ALSO NOT SOMETHING THAT
SAYS THE SENATE MUST IMMEDIATELY
CONFIRM THERE.
THERE WILL BE SOMEONE FILLING
THAT VACANCY, AND I THINK THE
NEW PRESIDENT SHOULD BE THE ONE
WHO FILLS THAT.
IT MAY NOT BE A REPUBLICAN.
I THINK IT'S GOING TO BE A
REPUBLICAN.
THAT'S WHAT I WANT IT TO BE.
I THINK IT'S GOING TO BE AN
ISSUE IN THIS CAMPAIGN AND THE
VOTERS WILL BE ABLE TO WEIGH IN
ON IT.
>> MEET AMBER McDONALD.
AN ELEMENTARY SCHOOLTEACHER.
SHE'S UNDECIDED.
>> GOOD EVENING.
HOW ARE YOU?
>> GOOD.
>> AS AN EDUCATOR FOR 14 YEARS,
I'VE SEEN A CHANGE IN OUR
CHILDREN.
I'M VERY PASSIONATE ABOUT WHAT I
DO, AND SO IT MAKES MY JOB
DIFFICULT WHEN THOSE CHILDREN
COME IN HAVING OTHER CONCERNS.
THEY ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THEIR
PARENTS WHO FOUGHT BEFORE THEY
CAME.
CONCERNED THEY DIDN'T HAVE FOOD
TO EAT BREAKFAST AND ALL OF THAT
COMES INTO WHAT WE DO EVERY
SINGLE DAY.
HOW CAN YOU HELP US TO MAKE THAT
EASIER TO WHERE WE CAN EDUCATE
THE PARENTS TO WHERE THOSE
THINGS ARE EASIER FOR THEM, THEN
IT HELPS OUR CHILDREN TO HAVE AN
EASIER DAY, NOT AS STRESSFUL.
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
I HAVE THREE EDUCATORS IN MY
FAMILY, ELEMENTARY SCHOOL.
I HEAR THE SAME THING.
OUR SCHOOLS ARE INHERITING
WHATEVER SOCIETY SENDS THEM IN
THE MORNING.
IF A CHILD IS BEING RAISED IN A
BROKEN HOME LIVING IN
SUBSTANDARD HOUSE, NO ACCESS TO
HEALTH CARE, AND FACING THESE
OTHER CHALLENGES, THIS CHILD
FACES SIGNIFICANT OBSTACLES THAT
NEED TO BE ADDRESSED.
THE QUESTION IS WHAT CAN
GOVERNMENT DO ABOUT IT?
THERE'S NO LAW I CAN PASS TO
MAKE PEOPLE BETTER PARENTS.
NO MATTERS HOW HARD YOU TRY AND
WANT TO HELP, THERE'S ONLY SO
MUCH YOU CAN DO ABOUT THAT AS
WELL.
WE NEED TO EMPOWER PARENTS.
IT'S ONE REASON MY TAX PLAN
INCREASES THE PER CHILD TAX
CREDIT.
I'VE BEEN CRITICIZED FOR THAT BY
"THE WALL STREET JOURNAL" AND
OTHERS.
THEY DON'T LIKE THE PER CHILD
TAX CREDIT.
WHERE DO WE LIVE IN A COUNTRY
WHERE BIG BUSINESS INVEST MONEY
IN A PIECE OF EQUIPMENT THEY GET
TO WRITE IT OFF BUT IF A WORKING
PARENT INVESTS MORE MONEY IN
THEIR CHILDREN THEY DON'T GET TO
WRITE THAT OFF THEIR TAXES.
WORKING PARENTS SHOULD BE
ALLOWED TO KEEP MORE OF THEIR
OWN MONEY TO HAVE THE RESOURCES
IT TAKES TO RAISE THEIR
CHILDREN.
IT'S EXPENSIVE TO RAISE CHILDREN
IN THE 21st CENTURY.
MY TAX PLAN RECOGNIZES THAT.
I THINK YOUR QUESTION GOES TO
THE CORE OF SOMETHING WE NEED TO
REMIND OURSELVES.
THERE'S NOT A GOVERNMENT
SOLUTION TO EVERY PROBLEM IN OUR
COUNTRY.
THAT DOES NOT MEAN OUR LEADERS
SHOULDN'T SPENLD THE TIME TO
TELL PEOPLE THAT WHAT HAPPENS IN
OUR HOUSE, WHAT HAPPENS IN YOUR
HOUSE IS OFTEN TIMES MUCH MORE
IMPORTANT THAN WHAT HAPPENS IN
THE WHITE HOUSE.
THE MOST IMPORTANT JOB I EVER
HAVE WILL NOT BE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES BUT TO BE A
FATHER TO MY FOUR CHILDREN.
I THINK THAT'S IMPORTANT FOR US
AS A SOCIETY CONTINUE TO
UNDERSTAND THAT YOU CANNOT HAVE
A STRONG COUNTRY WITHOUT STRONG
PEOPLE.
YOU CANNOT HAVE STRONG PEOPLE
WITHOUT STRONG VALUES AND YOU
CANNOT HAVE STRONG VALUES
WITHOUT STRONG FAMILIES.
NO ONE IS BORN WITH STRONG
VALUES.
THEY HAVE TO BE UNSTILLED IN YOU
IN A STRONG HOME.
GOVERNMENT CANNOT MAKE FAMILIES
STRONGER BUT IT CAN DO THINGS TO
HA
HELP FAMILIES.
AND NOT HAVING ANY LAWS, WHETHER
OUR SAFETY NET PROGRAM OR TAX
CODE THAT DISCOURAGES MARRIAGE
OR UNDERMINES PARENTING.
>> YOU ARE OBVIOUSLY VERY
ACCOMPLISHED.
DID YOU ALWAYS KNOW YOUED TO DO
PUBLIC SERVICE?
>> NO, I WANTED TO PLAY IN THE
NFL.
AND I WOULD HAVE, HAD IT NOT
BEEN FOR MY LACK OF SPEED, SIZE
AND TALENT.
BUT I ALWAYS HAD AN INTEREST IN
PUBLIC SERVICE.
MY GRANDFATHER, ONE OF THE JOBS
HE HAD AS A YOUNG MAN WAS A
READER IN THE FRONT OF A CIGAR
FACTORY IN CUBA.
THEY DIDN'T HAVE TV OR RADIO.
THEY DID BUT NOT IN THE CIGAR
FACTORY.
HE'D READ NEWSPAPERS AND NOVELS
TO THE WORKERS.
AS A RESULT BECAME A VERY
WELL-READ PERSON AND INSTILLED
THIS INTEREST IN POLITICS AND
WORLD AFFAIRS.
I THINK THAT WAS A SEED THAT
GREW OVER TIME.
NO ONE CAN PREDICT YOU'LL BE AT
A SETTING LIKE I AM TODAY.
I ALWAYS HAD SOMEWHAT OF AN
INTEREST IN IT.
I THOUGHT I'D BE AN NFL PLAYER
AND NFL COACH BEFORE I GOT TO
THIS POINT.
OBVIOUSLY FAST FORWARDED PAST
THE NFL PART.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET JASON LEE.
HE'S A MINISTER, FATHER OF FOUR
KIDS AND HE'S STILL UNDECIDED.
>> I HAD THE SAME SHORTCOMING IN
THE NFL AS WELL.
>> I THINK ALMOST EVERYONE DOES.
>> MOST GOP CANDIDATES POINT TO
RONALD REAGAN AS A MODEL
PRESIDENT.
THEY LOOK UP TO.
SO I WANT TO ASK IN TERMS OF
LOOKING AT HIM AS A MODEL FOR
IMMIGRATION AND REFUGEE
RESETTLEMENT, HE HAD THE REFUGEE
RESETTLEMENT ANNUAL CAP AS HIGH
AS 200,000 IN ONE OF HIS TERMS.
SO MY QUESTION IS, LOOKING AT
HIM AND CONSIDERING YOURSELF TO
BE A COMPASSIONATE CONSERVATIVE,
WILL YOU LET MORE VETTED,
SECURED REFUGEES INTO THIS
COUNTRY?
AND WHAT WILL YOUR PLAN BE FOR
THIS AMERICAN TRADITION OF
REFUGEE RESETTLEMENT?
>> I BELIEVE THAT AMERICA MUST
ALWAYS CONTINUE TO BE A PLACE
THAT ALLOWS PEOPLE SEEKING
REFUGE FROM POLITICAL
PERSECUTION AND VIOLENCE TO
COME.
HERE'S THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
REAGAN'S WORLD AND THE ONE WE
LIVE IN NOW.
WHEN RONALD REAGAN WAS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, THERE DID
NOT EXIST THE RADICAL JIHADIST
GROUP THAT WAS ATTEMPTING TO USE
THE IMMIGRATION LAWS OF OTHER
COUNTRIES AGAINST THOSE
COUNTRIES.
AND THAT'S THE THREAT WE NOW
FACE.
IT'S THE REASON WHY IN AMERICA
THERE WAS A TIME IN MANY
COMMUNITIES WHERE NOBODY LOCKED
THEIR DOORS.
NOW EVERYBODY LOCKS THEIR DOORS.
IT'S BECAUSE WE LOVE THE PEOPLE
INSIDE OF OUR HOME.
AND SO TODAY IN THE PROCESS BY
WHICH YOU ACCEPT PEOPLE INTO THE
UNITED STATES IS GOING TO HAVE
TO BE DIFFERENT.
WE KNOW FOR A FACT THAT ISIS,
FOR EXAMPLE, HAS CAPTURED KEY
PLACES IN SYRIA WHERE PASSPORTS
ARE PRODUCED.
YOU SEE OPEN SOURCE REPORTING
THAT ISIS HAS THE CAPABILITY OF
BASICALLY CREATING LEGITIMATE
SYRIAN PASSPORTS, EXCEPT THE
PICTURE AND NAME IS NOT EXACTLY
WHO IS SAYS IT IS.
THIS IS A REAL THREAT FOR
AMERICA.
IF WE ACCEPTED 10,000 SYRIAN
REFUGEES TOMORROW AND 9,999 OF
THEM WERE GOOD PEOPLE AND ONE
WAS AN ISIS KILLER, WE HAVE A
PROBLEM.
WE HAVE TO BE 100% RIGHT GIVEN
THE THREAT WE FACE.
IT'S NOT ABOUT A RELIGIOUS TEST
OR DISCRIMINATION.
IT'S JUST THAT WE HAVE TO BE
100% RIGHT.
THAT MEANS OUR VETTING PROCESS
MUST BE STRICTER.
IT'S ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE TO VET
PEOPLE NOW FROM THAT PART OF THE
WORLD.
WE DON'T HAVE A DATABASE TO RELY
ON.
YOU CAN'T CALL UP 1-800-SYRIA
AND ASK DO YOU KNOW WHO THEY ARE
AND WHY THEY ARE COMING?
IT'S HARDER TO VET PEOPLE FROM
CERTAIN PARTS OF THE WORLD.
WE'LL ALWAYS BE OPEN TO REFUGEES
BUT IN THE 21st CENTURY IF WE
DON'T KNOW WHO YOU ARE AND WHY
YOU ARE COMING 100% FOR SURE,
WE'LL NOT BE ABLE TO ALLOW YOU
TO COME IN BECAUSE THE THREAT IS
SO SIGNIFICANT AND SO REAL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
SENATOR RUBIO, THIS IS JEFF
PHILIPS, AN ATTORNEY.
HE LIKES YOU AND DONALD TRUMP.
STILL HAS NOT MADE UP HIS MIND.
>> DR. BEN CARSON MENTIONED
BEFORE YOU CAME OUT HERE THAT
THE GOP MAY NOT HAVE LEARNED ITS
LESSON IN 2012 REGARDING
INFIGHTING, ESPECIALLY IN THE
PRIMARY.
THIS PRIMARY HAS BEEN AS
CONTENTIOUS AS ANY I'VE SEEN IN
THE 45 YEARS I'VE BEEN WATCHING
POLITICS.
THE QUESTION IS THIS.
THERE'S GOING TO BE A LOT OF
HEALING THAT'S GOING TO HAVE TO
BE A LOT OF BRIDGE BUILDING
AFTER THIS PRIMARY, NO MATTER
WHO WINS IT.
AND I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW WHAT
YOU WOULD DO AND WHAT YOU HAVE
DONE IN THE PAST TO SHOW THAT
YOU HAVE THE ABILITY NOT ONLY TO
UNIFY THE REPUBLICAN PARTY BUT
UNIFY THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WELL
ENOUGH TO WIN THE GENERAL
ELECTION?
>> THAT'S A GREAT QUESTION.
>> WE NEED TO REMEMBER THAT IN
THIS COUNTRY WE'RE BLESSED THAT
WE HAVE IN THIS COUNTRY, WE
SOLVE THROUGH ELECTIONS WHAT'S
OTHER COUNTRIES SOLVE THROUGH
CIVIL WARS.
THE WORST THING THAT HAPPENS TO
SOMEONE IN THE POLITICAL PROCESS
IS YOU LOSE AN ELECTION.
THEY SAY NASTY THINGS ABOUT YOU
AND RUN A BAD AD ABOUT YOU.
IN OTHER COUNTRIES IF YOU LOSE
AN ELECTION, YOU GO TO JAIL OR
INTO EXILE.
WE'RE BLESSED TO BE LIVING IN A
REPUBLIC WHERE WE HAVE STRONG
DISAGREEMENTS ABOUT THE FUTURE
OF OUR COUNTRY BUT THEY ARE
SETTLED AT THE BALLOT BOX.
NOT THE TIP OF A GUN OR SPEAR.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO COME
TOGETHER.
I BELIEVE I ALREADY PROVIDE
THAT.
THERE'S A REASON WHY VIRTUALLY
EVERY CANDIDATE IN THIS FIELD
HAS ATTACKED ME.
I RUN A CAMPAIGN I BELIEVE
APPEALS TO THE PROD SECTOR OF
THE REPUBLICAN ELECTORATE.
WE BASICALLY CAMPAIGN TO EVERY
VOTER IN THE REPUBLICAN
COALITION.
MY PROMISE TO YOU IF I'M THE
NOMINEE, I'M NOT JUST GOING TO
UNIFY THE REPUBLICAN PARTY.
I'M GOING TO GROW IT.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE OUR MESSAGE
TO PEOPLE WHO HAVEN'T VOTED FOR
REPUBLICANS IN A LONG TIME.
THEY HAVEN'T VOTED FOR US
BECAUSE THE LEFT AND DEMOCRATS
HAVE SAID THE REPUBLICAN PARTY
IS THE PARTY OF THE RICH PEOPLE
AND THE DEMOCRATS ARE THE PARTY
OF THE WORKING PEOPLE.
THAT'S ONE OF THE BIGGEST LIES.
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY IS LED BY A
DEVOUT AVOWED DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALIST.
HAS BECOME A FAR LEFT PARTY.
AND THEY ARE THE PARTY OF BIG
GOVERNMENT.
BIG GOVERNMENT HURTS PEOPLE THAT
ARE TRYING TO MAKE IT.
BECAUSE THE BIGGER THE
GOVERNMENT, THE MORE THE PEOPLE
THAT INFLUENCE GOVERNMENT WIN AT
THE EXPENSE OF EVERYBODY ELSE.
LOOK AT DODD/FRANK.
THE BIG BANKS ARE BIGGER THAN
EVER.
THE REGIONAL BANKS AND COMMUNITY
BANKS ARE GETTING WIPED OUT.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE OUR MESSAGE
TO PEOPLE LIVING PAYCHECK TO
PAYCHECK.
YOU KNOW WHY I CAN TAKE THAT
MESSAGE TO THEM?
I GREW UP PAYCHECK TO PAYCHECK.
MY WIFE AND I HAVE LIVED
PAYCHECK TO PAYCHECK.
I KNOW WHAT THAT FEELS LIKE.
WE'LL TAKE OUR MESSAGE TO YOUNG
AMERICANS STRUGGLINGE ING UNDER
THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS OF STUDENT
LOAN DEBT.
WE'RE GOING TO BE THE PARTY THAT
MAKES IT EASIER FOR A SINGLE MOM
TO GO BACK TO SCHOOL AND GET A
DEGREE THAT ALLOWS HER TO FIND A
BETTER PAYING JOB.
WE'LL TAKE OUR MESSAGE TO
PARENTS RAISING CHILDREN IN THE
21st CENTURY.
WE'RE RAISING FOUR CHILDREN
RIGHT NOW AND KNOW HOW HARD IT
IS TO INSTILL THE VALUES THEY
TEACH IN OUR CHURCH INSTEAD OF
THE VALUES THE KUCULTURE TRIES
RAM DOWN OUR THROATS.
THAT DOESN'T MEAN EVERYONE IS
GOING TO AGREE WITH ME ON
EVERYTHING.
BUT I'M GOING TO BE A PRESIDENT
FOR ALL AMERICANS.
EVEN THOSE THAT DON'T VOTE FOR
ME, I'M GOING TO CUT THEIR
TAXES, TOO.
AN AMERICAN PRESIDENT HAS TO
LOVE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, EVEN
THOSE THAT DON'T LOVE YOU BACK,
AND THAT'S WHAT I INTEND TO DO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ONE OF THE THINGS THAT TED
CRUZ SAID EARLIER TODAY, HE
CALLED YOU, THAT YOU ARE
BEHAVING LIKE DONALD TRUMP WITH
A SMILE.
I WANT YOU TO BE ABLE TO
RESPOND.
>> DONALD TRUMP SMILES.
I'VE SEEN HIM SMILE.
THIS BACK AND FORTH IS SILLY.
IF SOMEONE SAYS SOMETHING ABOUT
ME THAT ISN'T TRUE, I'M GOING TO
CORRECT THE RECORD.
ULTIMATELY, IT'S NOT ABOUT ME OR
TED OR DONALD.
IT'S ABOUT WHAT IS THIS COUNTRY
GOING TO LOOK LIKE WHEN MY
15-YEAR-OLD DAUGHTER GRADUATES
FROM COLLEGE.
WHAT IS IT GOING TO LOOK LIKE
WHEN HE BUYS HER FIRST HOME OR
TRIES TO START HER FIRST
BUSINESS.
WHAT ABOUT WHEN MY 8-YEAR-OLD
SON DOES THE SAME?
2016 IS A TURNING POINT.
I BELIEVE WE ONLY HAVE TWO WAYS
FORWARD.
WE ARE EITHER GOING TO BE THE
FIRST AMERICANS THAT LEAVE THEIR
CHILDREN WORST OFF THAN
THEMSELVES OR WE'LL BE THE
AUTHORS OF A NEW AMERICAN
CENTURY, THE GREATEST ERA IN OUR
HISTORY.
THAT'S A DRA MATTIC CHOICE.
I BELIEVE 2016 ABOUT THAT.
WHEN THE STAKES ARE THAT HIGH,
THAT'S WHAT I'M GOING TO SPEND 9
9% OF MY TIME TALKING ABOUT.
>> WHEN DID YOU KNOW THAT YOUR
WIFE JEANNETTE WAS THE WOMAN FOR
YOU?
>> WELL, I'D LIKE TO THINK SHE
LIKED ME FIRST, BUT I LIKED HER.
>> HOW DID YOU MEET?
>> I WAS PLAYING SAND VOLLEYBALL
AT A PARK IN WEST MIAMI FLORIDA
AND SAW THIS REALLY CUTE GIRL
SITTING THERE.
I ASKED QUESTIONS ABOUT HER.
I DIDN'T GET TO KNOW HER UNTIL
MY COLLEGE ROOMMATE WAS DATING
HER BEST FRIEND AND INTRODUCED
US.
IT TOOK HER A LITTLE WHILE TO
CONVINCE HER I WAS THE RIGHT
PERSON.
WE WERE DATING FOR SEVEN YEARS.
GOT MARRIED IN 1998.
ONE OF THE MOST BLESSED THINGS
THAT EVER HAPPENED TO ME.
I'M BLESSED TO HAVE NOT JUST A
GODLY AND WONDERFUL WIFE AND
PARTNER IN LIFE BUT BLESSED BY
FOUR INCREDIBLE CHILDREN.
I TELL PEOPLE ALL THE TOMB
THAT'S AN EXTRAORDINARY PLEASING
THAT I HAVE SO MUCH PEACE ABOUT
NO MATTER WHAT HAPPENS.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
I'D LOVE TO BE YOUR PRESIDENT
BUT MY KIDS ARE GOING TO LOVE ME
NO MATTERS WHAT HAPPENS AND SO
IS MY WIFE.
I'M BLESSED BY THAT.
>> IF YOU ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT,
WOULD YOU STILL COACH YOUR SON
IN FOOTBALL?
>> I WOULD LIKE TO.
I'LL HAVE TO TALK TO THE SECRET
SERVICE ABOUT IT.
THE THING ABOUT SPORTS.
YES, WOULD YOU LOVE YOUR
CHILDREN TO BE SUCCESSFUL?
YES, IN WHATEVER THEY DO.
SPORTS HAS BEEN AN INCREDIBLE
TEACHER OF LIFE LESSONS.
I WAS DISAPPOINTED BY WHAT
HAPPENED IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
AND THE LESSONS I APPLIED TO
THAT DISAPPOINTMENT CAME FROM
SPORTS.
I USED TO PLAY DEFENSIVE BACK.
I GOT BEAT FROM TIME TO TIME ON
A PASS PLAY.
YOU'RE GOING TO IF YOU ARE A
CORNER BACK.
YOU HAVE TO PUT THAT BEHIND YOU
BECAUSE YOU HAVE ANOTHER PLAY
SOMETHING UP.
I LEARNED THAT LESSON FROM
ATHLETICS.
FOR ME, SPORTS HAS BEEN A WAY TO
INSTILL LIFE LESSONS IN MY
CHILDREN, PARTICULARLY HOW TO
DEAL WITH FAILURE, DISAPONTEMENT
AND HOW TO WORK ALONGSIDE OTHER
PEOPLE TO ACHIEVE A GOAL.
>> WITH ALL WE'VE LEARNED ABOUT
CONCUSSIONS, DO YOU WORRY ABOUT
YOUR CHILD?
>> WELL, WE TRY TO MAKE IT AS
SAFE AS WE POSSIBLY CAN.
FOOTBALL HAS INHERENT DANGER.
SO DOES COMPETITIVE STUNT
CHEERLEADING.
SO DOES DRIVING A CAR BACK AND
FORTH TO WORK.
I ULTIMATELY THINK FOOTBALL IS
AN INCREDIBLE SPORT.
IT TEACHES LESSONS, LIFE LESSONS
THAT I THINK ARE VALUABLE.
YOU CAN MAKE THE GAME SAFER.
YOU CAN NEVER MAKE IT ENTIRELY
SAFE.
AND SO YOU DO SPEND A LOT OF
TIME COACHING KIDS HOW TO
PROPERLY TACKLE, NOT USE YOUR
HEAD.
VERY DIFFERENT FROM WHEN I WAS
GROWING UP AND THEY TAUGHT YOU
TO USE YOUR HEAD.
AND THE DEMOCRATS SAY THAT
EXPLAINS A LOT ABOUT MARCO
RUBIO.
THAT'S NOT TRUE.
MY POINT IS IT'S A SPORT THAT
BRINGS INHERENT DANGER, BUT SO
DOES LIFE.
>> YOU MENTIONED YOU'RE COLOR
BLIND WHICH I HADN'T REALIZED.
AND YOU SHOULD HAVE SEEN YOUR
CLOTHES BEFORE YOUR WIFE STARTED
PICKING THEM OUT.
>> WE'RE STICKING WITH REDS AND
BLUES AND GRAYS AND BLUES.
I HAVE TROUBLE DISTINGUISHING.
>> IT'S A MESS.
>> DID YOU ALWAYS HAVE THAT?
>> I DIDN'T KNOW UNTIL PEOPLE
STARTED TELLING ME, THAT'S A
NICE GREEN SHIRT.
I'M LIKE, THE BLUE ONE I HAVE
ON?
IT'S GREEN.
>> YOU LIKE EDM.
>> I DO.
>> ELECTRONIC DANCE MUSIC.
>> YES.
MAYBE PEOPLE THOUGHT IT WAS
SOMETHING ELSE.
>> YOU EVER BEEN TO A RAVE?
>> NO, I'VE NEVER BEEN TO A
RAVE.
>> I DON'T KNOW.
THIS IS THE REPUBLICAN PRIMARY,
ANDERSON.
>> YOU LIKE EDM.
THAT'S WHAT THEY DO.
>> I LISTEN TO IT.
I THINK I'M A LITTLE TOO OLD TO
BE GOING TO A RAVE.
>> MAYBE BACK IN THE DAY.
>> I HAVE THE BOOTS FOR IT.
I GREW UP LISTENING TO '90s HIP
HOP STUFF.
IN THE LAST YEARS WHAT'S
HAPPENED WITH EDM, YOU HAVE
THESE ELECTRONIC -- THESE DISC
JOCKEYS, DEEJAYS OVERLAYING IT
WITH COUNTRY MUSIC AND ALL SORTS
OF THINGS.
THE LYRICS ARE CLEAN, THE BEATS
OF MUSIC ARE FUN.
>> DO YOUR KIDS LIKE IT, TOO?
>> THE WORDS ARE CLEAN.
SOMETIMES THEY HAVE NO WORDS.
IT'S PERFECT.
THEY DON'T HAVE TO WORRY ABOUT
THE LYRICS.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU FOR
YOUR TIME.
APPRECIATE IT.
THANK YOU, SENATOR RUBIO FOR
TAKING PART.
>>> COMING UP NEXT, IOWA CAUCUS
WINNER REPUBLICAN SENATOR TED
CRUZ.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>
WELCOME BACK.
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES TAKING
QUESTIONS FROM VOTERS WITH THE
PRIMARY JUST THREE DAYS AWAY.
PLEASE WELCOME IOWA CAUCUS
WINNER SENATOR TED CRUZ OF
TEXAS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WELCOME.
HOW ARE YOU?
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> THANKS.
>> SO YOU OBVIOUSLY WON IN IOWA.
YOU'VE HAD A VERY GOOD DAY
TODAY.
>> THERE'S NEW POLL OUT SAYING
ON THE NATIONAL RACE, YOU ARE
ACTUALLY NOW IN THE LEAD.
E
HOW DOES IT FEEL FOR YOU?
>> IT FEELS FANTASTIC.
ALL THE PUNDITS IN IOWA SAID WE
DIDN'T HAVE A PRAYER.
EVERYONE ON TELEVISION WAS
SAYING DONALD TRUMP WAS GOING TO
WIN AND THEN WE SAW
RECORD-SHATTERING TURNOUT SHOW
UP.
THE FOLKS THAT CAME TOGETHER, IT
WAS COALITION THAT IT'S GOING TO
TAKE TO WIN THE NOMINATION AND
ALSO WIN THE GENERAL ELECTION.
WE ENDED UP, OUR CAMPAIGN EARNED
MORE VOTES THAN ANY CAMPAIGN IN
THE HISTORY OF THE IOWA
REPUBLICAN CAUCUS.
IT REALLY WAS A TESTAMENT TO THE
GRASS ROOTS.
>> YOU GOT A CEASE AND DESIST
LETTER TODAY FROM DONALD TRUMP.
I DON'T THINK I'VE EVER HEARD OF
THAT ACTUALLY HAPPENING IN A
RACE.
ONE OF MANY FIRSTS THAT WE'VE
SEEN.
WHAT DID YOU THINK WHEN YOU
ACTUALLY GOT THE LETTER?
>> I'LL CONFESS, I LAUGHED OUT
LOUD.
THIS HAS NOT BEEN A TYPICAL RACE
BY ANY SENSE.
AND I DON'T THINK ANYONE IS
SURPRISED THAT DONALD IS
THREATENING TO SUE PEOPLE.
HE'S DONE THAT MOST OF HIS ADULT
LIFE.
BUT THIS LETTER REALLY WAS --
LOOK, I'VE PRACTICED LAW 20
YEARS, AND THIS LETTER REALLY
PRESSED THE BOUNDS OF THE MOST
FRIVOLOUS AND RIDICULOUS LETTERS
I'VE EVER SEEN.
HE WAS UPSET ABOUT AN AD THIS
WE'RE RUNNING ON TV.
THE AD TALKS ABOUT THE
VACANCY AT THE SUPREME COURT AND
THAT WE'VE GOT ISSUES SUCH AS
LIFE AND LIBERTY AND THE SECOND
AMENDMENT THAT ARE IN THE
BALANCE.
>> AND IT USES AN INTERVIEW FROM
TIM RUSSERT IN THE 1990s.
>> DONALD TRUMP SAYS HE'S
PRO-CHOICE, SUPPORTS PARTIAL
BIRTH ABORTION AND HE'S
PRO-CHOICE IN EVERY RESPECT.
HIS ARGUMENT IN THE LETTER IS
RUNNING HIS OWN WORDS WAS
DEFAMATION.
>> HE SAYS, THOUGH, YOU'RE
MISREPRESENTING HIS CURRENT
POSITION THAT HE'S EVOLVED ON
PRO-LIFE.
>> IT'S THE MOST RIDICULOUS
THEORY THAT TELLING VOTERS WHAT
HIS ACTUAL RECORD IS THAT IS
DECEITFUL AND LYING.
I INVITED MR. TRUMP, I SAID,
PLEASE, FILE THIS LAWSUIT UP.
>> WANT TO DEPOSE HIM.
>> IN ANY DEFAMATION CASE, TRUTH
IS A COMPLETE DEFENSE.
HIS SAID LAWYER -- WE DON'T SAY
HE'S PRO-CHOICE.
DONALD SAYS HE'S PRO-CHOICE IN
EVERY RESPECT.
>> THAT WAS BACK IN THE 1990s.
HE SAID HE EVOLVED.
DO YOU ACCEPT HE'S PRO-LIFE?
>> FOUR DAYS AGO ON THE
CAMPAIGN, DONALD TRUMP SMAND HOW
MANY WONDERFUL THINGS PLANNED
PARENTHOOD DOES.
THEY ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR TAKING
THE LIVES OF MILLIONS OF UNBORN
CHILDR
CHILDREN.
NOBODY WHO IS ACTUALLY PRO-LIFE
COULD STAND UP ON THE STAGE AND
SING THE PRAISES.
I DON'T THINK WE NEED TO BE
SENDING FEDERAL TAXPAYER FOUND
AN ORGANIZATION ON VIDEO HAS
BEEN IMPLICATED IN WHAT APPEARS
TO BE MULTIPLE FEDERAL FELONIES.
>> I DON'T WANT TO SOUND LIKE
I'M ARGUING HIS CASE FOR HIM,
FOR ACCURACY CASE, HE SAYS HE
DOES NOT SUPPORT ABORTION.
>> IF YOU TELL PEOPLE HIS
RECORD, IF YOU ACTUALLY SHOW
DONALD TRUMP ON NATIONAL
TELEVISION IN HIS OWN WORDS THAT
HE'S GOING TO FILE A LAW TO
REVENT YOU FROM DOING THAT, I
POINTED OUT WE'VE GOT AT LEAST
FOUR PIECES OF EVIDENCE, NUMBER
ONE, HIS OWN WORDS ON NATIONAL
TELEVISION, NUMBER TWO, WHAT HE
SAID ON THE DEBATE STAGE FOUR
DAYS AGO, SINGING THE PRAISES OF
PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
HIS SISTER WAS PUT ON THE COURT
OF APPEALS BY BILL CLINTON.
HE SAID HIS SISTER WOULD MAKE A
PHENOMENAL SUPREME COURT
JUSTICE.
HIS SISTER IS A RADICAL PRO
ABORTION JUDGE.
SHE STRUCK DOWN NEW JERSEY'S BAN
ON PARTIAL BIRTH ABORTION AS
IRRATIONAL.
THAT'S AN EXTREME POSITION.
THAT'S WHO HE SUGGESTED AS
SUPREME COURT JUSTICE LAST YEAR.
ONE OF THE THINGS I LAID OUT,
LISTEN, DONALD FOR THE LAST FOUR
DECADES HAS WRITTEN CHECKS TO
DEMOCRATS OVER AND OVER AND OVER
AGAIN FROM JIMMY CARTER TO
HILLARY CLINTON, TO JOHN KEKERR
CHUCK SCHUMER, HARRY REID.
IS THERE HE SAYS HE HAS A LOT OF
FRIENDS.
>> BUT IT'S NOT FRIENDS.
>> I KNOW.
>> DONALD AND HIS SON GAVE ABOUT
THREE TIMES AS MUCH TO THE
DEMOCRATS AS THEY DID TO THE
REPUBLICANS.
THEY HELPED FUND PUTTING NANCY
PELOSI AND HARRY REID AS SPEAKER
OF THE HOUSE AND THEY HELP SET
THE STAGE FOR OBAMA CARE AND FOR
ANYONE THAT CARES ABOUT
CONSERVATIVE JUDGE, I'LL TELL
YOU, ANDERSON, THERE IS NO
UNIVERSE IN WHICH COULD I WRITE
A CHECK TO CHUCK SCHUMER OR
HARRY REID OR HILLARY CLINTON OR
JOHN KERRY OR JOE BIDEN OR JIMMY
CARTER AND ANYONE WHO HAS DONE
THAT BY DEFINITION DOES NOT CARE
ABOUT CONSERVATIVE JUSTICES
BECAUSE THE PEOPLE HE SUPPORTED
THOUGHT TOOTH AND NAIL TO PUT
LIBERALS ON THE SUPREME COURT.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU ABOUT THE
ISSUE WITH APPLE AND THE iPHONE.
IF ANYBODY IS JUST JOINING YOU,
A JUDGE HAS ORDERED AND TO
BASICALLY DEVELOP A NEW SOFTWARE
TO CREATE BACK DOOR TO ALLOW LAW
ENFORCEMENT TO GET INTO THE
PHONE TO GET INFORMATION FROM
SAN BERNARDINO.
>> APPLE FOR THEIR PART THEY SAY
THIS CREATES A BECOME DOOR THAT
BASICALLY ENDANGERS ALL OF OUR
CELL PHONES.
>> I THINK APPLE HAS SERIOUS
ARGUMENT THAT THEY SHOULD NOT BE
FORCED TO PUT A BECOME DOOR IN
EVERY CELL PHONE EVERYONE HAS.
THAT CREATES A SECURITY EX
EXPOSURE.
I THINK APPLE HAS THE RIGHT SIDE
ON THE GLOBAL DON'T MAKE DO YOU
SEE THIS TO EVERY iPHONE ON THE
MARKET.
BUT LAW ENFORCEMENT -- THIS
CONCERNS THE PHONE OF ONE OF THE
SAN DIEGO HACKERS.
FOR LAW ENFORCEMENT TO GET A
JUDICIAL SEARCH ORDER, THAT'S
HOW THE BILL OF RIGHTS OPERATES,
TO SAY APPLE, OPEN THIS PHONE,
NOT ANDERSON'S PHONE --
>> BUT APPLE SAYS THEY CAN'T DO
THAT, IT WOULD BE ON EVERYONE'S
PHONE.
>> BUT THEY DON'T HAVE TO PUT IT
ON EVERYBODY'S PHONE.
NOBODY HAS A RIGHT TO DEFY A
LEGAL SEARCH WARRANT.
BANKS ALL THE TIME KEEP
FINANCIAL RECORDS.
AND IF YOU OR I WERE A
TERRORIST, IF WE'RE A DRUG
DEALER AND A SEARCH WARRANT IS
SERVED ON YOUR BANK, THEY CAN
GET YOUR FINANCIAL RECORDS.
THAT'S HOW THE LAW ENFORCEMENT
SYSTEM WORKS AND THE BILL OF
RIGHTS PREVENTS THE GOVERNMENT
FROM SEIZING OUR INFORMATION
WITHOUT ANY EVIDENCE, BUT WHEN
YOU HAVE A CRIMINAL, WHEN YOU
HAVE A TERRORIST, WE KNOW THEY
WERE RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISTS.
IT THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION WERE
NOT IN THIS POLITICALLY CORRECT
STATE OF DENIAL, WE SHOULD ARE
DONE MORE TO PREVENT THAT ATTACK
BUT AFTER THE FACT, WE OUGHT TO
BE DOING EVERYTHING WE CAN TO
ASCERTAIN WHO THEY WERE DEALING
WITH, WHO WERE THEY TALKING TO,
WHAT TEXTS THEY'RE SENDING AND
THAT'S A BASIC MATTER KEEPING
OUR COUNTRY SAFE.
>> WE LEARNED WHILE WE WERE ON
THE AIR THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA IS
GOING TO BE VISITING CUBA.
IS THAT SOMETHING YOU WOULD DO?
>> IT IS NOT AS LONG AS THE
CASTROS ARE IN POWER.
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S FOREIGN POLICY
HAS CONSISTENT LIVE ALIENATED
AND ABANDONED OUR FRIENDS IN HAS
NEVER BEEN AN ADMINISTRATION
MORE HOSTILE AND ANTAGONIST TOUK
ISRAEL THAN THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION AND WHAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS SHOWN TO OUR
ENEMIES IS WEAKNESS AND
APPEASEMENT.
SO HIS POLICY CONCERNING CUBA
AND IRAN HAVE PARALLELS WHERE
HE'S ALLOWING BILLIONS TO GO TO
TYRANTS WHO HATE AMERICA, WHO
ARE STATE SPONSOR OF TERRORISM,
WHO ARE FIGHTING AGAINST OUR
NATION PIP THINK IT'S A REAL
MACE TAKE.
THE PRESIDENT OUGHT TO BE
MUSM
PUSHING FOR A FREE CUBA.
WHEN THE CUBAN OFFICIALS CAME TO
WASHINGTON WITH THE OPENING OF
THE EMBASSY, A CUBAN DISSIDENT
CAME AND CAME TO THE PRESS CON
PRESENCE AND WANTED TO ASK A
QUESTION AND THE JOHN KERRY
STATE DEPARTMENT SAID IF SHE
ASKED A QUESTION, SHE WOULD BE
FORCIBLY AND PHYSICALLY REMOVED.
SHE WAS ASTONISHED.
SHE SAID I EXPECTED THAT IN
CUBA.
WITH YOU THE OBAMA STATE
DEPARTMENT WAS HAPPY TO EYE
SENSE A DISSIDENT TO PREVENT THE
CUBANS FROM ASKING QUESTIONS.
MY DAD FOUGHT WITH CASTRO IN THE
REVOLUTION AND WAS IMPRISONED
AND TORTURED AND MY AUNT WAS
IMPRISONED AND TORTURED BY
CASTRO.
MY FAMILY HAS SEEN FIRSTHAND THE
EVIL AND OPPRESSION IN CUBA AND
WE NEED TO HAVE A PRESIDENT THAT
STANDS UP TO OUR ENEMIES, THAT
DOESN'T -- YOU KNOW, IF YOU LOOK
AT CUBA WHEN THE SOVIET UNION
COLLAPSED, THEY LOST THEIR
SOURCE OF MONEY.
WITH YOU THEN VENEZUELA STEPPED
IN AND BECAME A PATRON AND YOU
SAW THE OIL REVENUES AND CUBA
HAD A CORRUPT BARGAIN WHERE THEY
WOULD SEND THUGS, SOLDIERS DOWN
TO VENEZUELA, THAT THEY WOULD
USE TO OPPRESS THE CITIZENS
THERE AND IN EXCHANGE VENEZUELA
WOULD SEND MONEY.
AS OIL TPRICES HAVE BEEN TANKIN
AND THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION
STEPS IN WITH A LIFELINE.
AND ONE OF THE OTHER THINGS I'M
VERY CONCERNED ABOUT IT S THAT
OBAMA IS EMPTYING GAUANTANAMO.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT WILL HAVE TO
SEND SOLDIERS TAUGHT CAPTURE
THEM AGAIN OR KILL THEM WHEN
THEY RETURN TO WAGING JIHAD.
I FEAR BY THE END OF THIS YEAR
PRESIDENT OBAMA PLANS TO GIVE
THE GUANTANAMO NAVY BASE BACK TO
CUBA.
I HOPE HE DOESN'T DO THAT.
I THINK IT IS A PROFOUND RISK.
>> IF TRIALS CAN'T BE BROUGHT
AGAINST THE PEOPLE IN
GUANTANAMO, WHAT WOULD YOU DID,
KEEP THEM INDEFINITELY?
>> IF THEY ARE TERRORISTS, WE
CAN HAVE MILITARY TRIBUNALS.
THE BILL OF RIGHTS DOES NOT
PROVIDE TO FOREIGNERS WAGING WAR
AGAINST AMERICA.
THE BILL OF RIGHTS APPLIES TO
AMERICANS.
THE PEOPLE THIS GUANTANAMO AT
THIS POINT, IT'S DOWN TO THE
WORST OF THE WORST.
A REALLY ALARMING PERCENTAGE OF
THE PEOPLE RELEASED FROM
GUANTANAMO RETURN IMMEDIATELY TO
WAGING JIHAD, RETURN IMMEDIATELY
TO GOING BACK TRYING TO MURDER
AMERICANS AND PART OF THE
CONSEQUENCE OF OBAMA IS HE
ENGAMGS IN THIS POLITICALLY
CORRECT DENIAL WHERE HE AND
HILLARY CLINTON AND BERNIE
SANDERS AND THE WHOLE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY, THEY WON'T EVEN SAY THE
WORDS RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM,
THEY DON'T ACKNOWLEDGE FIGHTING
AND IT'S PART OF THE REASON WHY
WE'RE SO VULNERABLE.
>> PROBABLY THE TOUGHEST
QUESTION OF THE NIGHT FOR YOU.
WHICH SIDE ARE YOU ON, CLEMSON
OR SOUTH CAROLINA?
>> ON THIS I AM GOING TO
SHAMELESSLY WAFFLE AND SAY I
LOVE THEM BOTH.
>> ALL RIGHT, GOOD ANSWER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET THE
PRESIDENT OF UPSTATE REPUBLICAN
WOMAN, SHE SAID SHE IS STILL
UNDECIDED.
DONNA?
>> WELCOME, SENATOR CRUZ.
AS OUR GOVERNOR WOULD SAY, IT'S
A GREAT DAY IN SOUTH CAROLINA.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> SENATOR, REALIZING THAT IN A
CLOSE HUSBAND-WIFE RELATIONSHIP,
A WIFE HAS EARNED GREAT DALE OF
SPREEKT FROM HER HUSBAND AND IS
A TRUSTED ADVISER AND CONFIDENT
IN EVERYTHING EXCEPT FOR SPECIAL
SECRET MATTERS.
IN THESE ISSUES, WHETHER IN
AMERICA OR ABROAD, WHAT ISSUES
DO YOU THINK YOUR WIFE WOULD BE
SIGNIFICANTLY INTERESTED IN AND
POSSIBLY SUPPORT THEIR CAUSE?
>> WELL, DONNA, THANK YOU FOR
THAT QUESTION AND THANK YOU VERY
MUCH FOR YOUR LEADERSHIP.
YOU KNOW, I HAVE BEEN BLESSED IN
MANY REGARDS BUT IN NO WAY GREAT
ARE THAN MARRY BEIING THE LOVE Y
LIFE, HEIDI CRUZ.
SHE IS THE DAUGHTER OF CHRISTIAN
MISSIONARIES.
SO HEIDI AS LITTLE GIRL LIVED IN
AFRICA, IN KENYA AND NIGERIA,
HER PARENTS WERE MISSIONARY
THERE IS, HER BROTHERS IS A
MISSIONARY IN HAITI RIGHT NOW.
I MET HEIDI ON JANUARY 2nd OF
2000, WE WERE BOTH WORK ON THE
GEORGE W. BUSH CAMPAIGN.
IT WAS LOVE AT FIRST SITE.
I WAS SMITTEN BY HER HEART.
SHE IS BEAUTIFUL, SHE'S
BRILLIANT, SHE'SES SAN UNBELIEVE
BUSINESS WOMAN BUT SHE'S ALSO
THE MOST LOVING MOM AND WIFE.
WE ARE BEST FRIENDS.
WE'RE ON THE PHONE TWO, THREE,
FOUR TIMES TOGETHER.
WE CALL EACH OTHER ON
EVERYTHING, WE COOPERATE ON
EVERYTHING.
SHE IS OUT ON THE TRAIL.
CAN I NOT TELL YOU HOW MANY
PEOPLE AS I TRAVELED AROUND,
WHEN I GOT ELECTED TO SENATE
SAID, LISTEN, TED, YOU'RE FINE
ONE WE LOVE HEIDI SO WE'RE
VOTING FOR YOU FOR HEIDI.
I WAS LIKE, WELL, I'M THRILLED
AND I'LL TAKE IT.
SHE'S GOT A REAL HEART FOR
ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT.
WHEN YOU'VE SEEN AS A LITTLE
GIRL POVERTY IN AFRICA, WHEN
YOU'VE SEEN SUFFERING, HEIDI AND
I TRAVELED DOWN TO NICARAGUA
WITH A MISSION TRIP TO DRILL A
WATER WELL IN AN IMPOVERISHED
VILLAGE.
WHEN YOU SEE PEOPLE THAT ARE
REALLY HURTING, UNDERSTAND THAT
YOU NEED POLICY TO LIFT PEOPLE
OUT OF POVERTY AND HEIDI HAS A
HEART TO LIFT PEOPLE OUT OF
POVERTY BY EMPOWERING THEM TO
START SMALL BUSINESSES AND I
CHIEF THE AMERICAN DREAM AND A
PART OF THAT IS EDUCATIONAL
OPTIONS AND SCHOOL CHOICE.
I THINK SCHOOL CHOICE IS THE
CIVIL RIGHTS ISSUE OF THE 21st
DR
CENTURY.
I THINK EVERY CHILD IN AMERICA
DESERVES A COLLEGE EDUCATION.
I'M ON THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL, MY
DAD'S ON THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL, OUR
LITTLE GIRLS AT TIMES ON THE
CAMPAIGN TRAIL.
I THINK SHE'LL BE INVOLVED IN A
LOT OF THINGS IF WE WERE TO WIN
BUT HER PASSION IS ECONOMIC UM
POWERMENT, ESPECIALLY WOMEN,
HISPANICS AND AFRICAN-AMERICAN,
THOSE STRUGGLING, HELPING THEM
ACHIEVE THE AMERICAN DREAM BY
UNDERSTANDING THE PRINCIPLES OF
BUSINESS, EXPANDING AND CREATING
GREATER OPPORTUNITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I DON'T WANT TOMORROW BARES
YOU AT ALL BUT YOUR WIFE
MENTIONED TO CNN A WHILE BACK
THAT OCCASIONALLY WHEN YOU CALL
HER ON THE PHONE, YOU SING TO
HER, IS THAT TRUE IN.
>> WELL, EMBARRASSINGLY ENOUGH,
YES.
AND I AM A PAINFULLY HORRIBLE
SINGER.
>> IS THIS PUNISHMENT OR --
>> I'M HOPING IT IS SORT OF
SINCERE AND ENDEARING.
LOOK --
>> WHAT'S YOUR FAVORITE MUSICAL?
>> I ACTUALLY DON'T SING
MUSICALS.
I WILL SING THINGS LIKE,
OH, MY DARLING, OH, MY DA
DARLING, OH, MY DARLING
HEIDI-TINE
I USED TO CALL HER AT HER OFFICE
TO EMBARRASS HER OR I CALL AND
SING
I JUST CALLED TO SAY I LOVE
YOU, I JUST CALLED TO SAY I
CARE."
>> BOBBY?
>> I ATTENDED CITADEL DOWN IN
SOUTH CAROLINA AND DURING MY
SENIOR YEAR, THE ACTUAL 9/11
ATTACKS OCCURRED.
UPON GRADUATION, I WENT INTO THE
ARMY AND I DEPLOYED FOUR TIMES
TO IRAQ.
DURING THAT TIME WE WERE IN
IRAQ, WE FELT LIKE WE WERE PUCK
PUTING THE IRAQI GOVERNMENT ON A
STABLE GROUND.
FAST FORWARD A COUPLE OF YEARS
LATER WHEN THE ACTUAL CITIES
THAT WE HAD ACTUALLY FOUGHT TO
PROTECT WITH SO MUCH EFFORT,
TIME AND BLOOD WERE RETAKEN BY
ISIS.
SO THERE WAS A FRUSTRATION THERE
WITH A LOT OF MY MEN THOUGHT
THAT THEIR TIME HAD BEEN
SQUANDERED OVERSEAS BASED UPON
THE LACK OF THE U.S. POLITICAL
WILL TO REALLY SEE VICTORY.
I WANT TO ASK YOU AS COMMANDER
IN CHIEF, IF YOU TAKE ON THAT
MANTLE OF LEADERSHIP, WHAT WOULD
YOU DID TO ENSURE THE SERVICE
MEMBERS AND THEIR FAMILIES AND
THEIR SACRIFICES ARE NOT -- SBL
FIRST OF ALL, LET ME SAY THANK
UP FOR WHY ARE SERVICE AND YOUR
SACRIFICE.
AS I TRAVEL SOUTH CAROLINA, I
MEET EVERY DAY ACTIVE MILITARY,
EVERY DAY VETERANS WHO ARE SO
UNHAPPY WITH THE DIRECTION WE'RE
GOING RIGHT NOW.
FOR SEVEN YEARS WE'VE HAD A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF WHO DOESN'T
BELIEVE IN THE MISSION OF THE
MILITARY, WHO DOESN'T STAND BY
THEM, WHO HAS WEAKENED ADD
DEGRADED THE MILITARY IN A WAY
THAT IT'S UNDERMINED ITS
READINESS AND MADE US FAR LESS
ABLE TO DEFEND OURSELVES.
YESTERDAY I ROLLED OUT A
COMPREHENSIVE PLAN TO REBUILD
THE MILITARY.
IF YOU THINK ABOUT THE LAST TIME
OUR MILITARY WAS BADLY WEAKENED,
IT WAS 1980.
IT WAS FOLLOWING THE JIMMY
CARTER ADMINISTRATION, ANOTHER
WEAK, DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENT WHO
UNDERMINED THE MILITARY AND WHEN
REAGAN CAME IN, WHAT REAGAN DID
IS HE STARTED WITH TAX REFORM
AND REGULATORY REFORM.
HE LIFTED THE BURDENS ON SMALL
BUSINE
BUSINESSES.
THAT UNCHANGED THE AMERICAN FREE
ENTERPRISE SYSTEM.
THAT GROWTH PROVIDED TRILLIONS
IN NEW FEDERAL REVENUE, HE
INVESTED THAT REVENUE IN
REBUILDING THE MILITARY AND BY
DOING IS HE BANKRUPTED THE
SOVIET UNION AND WON THE COLD
WAR.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT IN 2017 MOE
DOES THE EXACT SAME THING WITH
REGARD TO RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM.
THAT IS WHAT I INTEND O DO IS
START WITH TAX REFORM AND
REGULATORY REFORM, UNLEASH THE
AMERICAN ECONOMY AND USE THAT
ECONOMIC GROWTH TO REBUILD THE
MILITARY.
SO, FOR EXAMPLE, AS YOU KNOW,
PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS PROPOSED
REDUCING THE REGULAR ARMY TO
450,000.
I THINK THAT IS FAR BELOW WHAT
IS NEEDED TO KEEP THIS COUNTRY
SAFE.
I INTEND TO INCREASE IT TO A
MINUTE NUMBER 525,000 SOLDIERS.
THE AIR FORCE HAS BEEN REDUCED
IN 4,000 PLANES.
WE NEED TO INCREASE THAT TO A
MINIMUM OF 6,000 PLANES SO WE
CAN PROJECT POWER AND USE OUR
AIR POWER SUPERIORITY.
THE NAVY WEEKS HAVE 272 SHIPS
PATCH CENT AT THIS AGO WAS THE
LAST TIME WA HAD A NAVY WITH
THAT KNEW SHIPS.
WE NEED TO INCREASE THAT TO A
MINUTE MONTH OF 350 SHIPS AND WE
NEED A FORCE LEVEL OF 1.4
MILLION TROOPS AT A MINIMUM AND
WE NEED TO DRAMATICALLY EXPAND
MISSILE DEFENSE, AS WE SEE ROGUE
NATIONS AND WE NEED TO BE ABLE
TO DEFEND OURSELVES AND EXPAND
CYBER DEFENSE.
WITH YOU WE ALSO NEED TO FOCUS
OUR FOREIGN POLICY AND MILITARY
POLICY ON IDENTIFYING AND
DEFEATING THE REAL ENEMIES.
I'VE GOT STRONG DISAGREEMENTS
WITH THE MISTAKES OF THE
OBAMA/CLINTON FOREIGN POLICY THE
LAST SEVEN YEARS.
ONE PERFECT EXAMPLE IS LIBYA.
LIBYA, PRESIDENT OBAMA AND
HILLARY CLINTON LED THE WORLD IN
TOPPLING THE GOVERNMENT IN LIBYA
AND SLADE THEY WERE SUPPORTED BY
MORE THAN A FEW ESTABLISHMENT
REPUBLICANS, INCLUDING SEVERAL
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
THAT HAS PROVEN TO BE A
CATASTROPHIC MISTAKE.
TOPPLING THE GOVERNMENT IN LIBYA
MEANT WE HANDED THAT GOVERNMENT
OVER TO RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISTS.
THEY ARE AN ACUTE NATIONAL
SECURITY THREAT O THIS COUNTRY
AND IT LED DIRECTLY TO FAILURES.
OBAMA/CLINTON FOREIGN POLICY
THAT LED DIRECTLY TO THE TRAGEDY
OF BENGHAZI, RATHER AND THEN
GAUGING IN TRYING TO TOPPLE
GFRTS IN THE MIDDLE EAST AND
NATION BUILD, IT THINK THE FOCUS
OF THE MILITARY NEEDS TO BE
DEFENDING THIS COUNTRY,
PROTECTING OUR NATIONAL SECURITY
INTERESTS.
SO WHAT SHOULD WE BE DOING?
BY THE WAY, MANY OF THOSE SAMS
FOLKS ARE NOW SAYING WE SHOULD
DO THE SAME THING IN SYRIA,
TAPLE ASSAD.
ASSAD'S A BAD MAN.
INSTEAD OF GETTING IN THE
MIDDLE.
CIVIL WARS, WE OUGHT TO BE
FOCUSING ON THE ENEMIES OF
AMERICA AND UTTERLY DESTROYING
ISIS, USING OVERWHELMING AIR
POWER, ARM BEING THE KURDS,
USING THE TOOLS TO UTTERLY AND
COMPLETELY DESTROY THEM.
WHEN IT COMES TO THE MEN AND
WOMEN OF THE MILITARY, I DON'T
THINK THE MILITARY SHOULD BE
GOVERNED BY POLITICAL
CORRECTNESS, SHOULD BE USED
AS -- FOR SOCIAL EXPERIMENTS.
FOR EXAMPLE, IF I AM SELECTED
PRESIDENT, WE WILL NOT BE
DRAFTING OUR DAUGHTERS INTO
COMBAT ON THE FRONT LINES.
I WAS ASTONISHED THREE DEBATES
AGO WHEN OTHER CANDIDATES STOOD
UP AND SUPPORTED DRAFTING WOMEN
INTO COMBAT.
THAT DOESN'T MAKE ANY SENSE.
I KIND OF WONDERED IF ROD
STERLING WAS GOING TO WALK OUT
AND SAY "YOU ENTERED THE
TWILIGHT ZONE."
I'M THE FATHER IT WOULD HAVE
DAUG --
OF TWO DAUGHTERS, THEY CAN DO
ANYTHING, BUT THE IDEA THAT THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WITH FORCIBLY
CONSCRIPT THEM INTO THE
MILITARY, THAT MAKES NO SENSE AT
ALL.
AND ANOTHER SHAMEFUL THIS
EVENING IS WE ARE SENDING OUR
MEN AND WOMEN INTO COMBAT WITH
RULES OF ENGAGEMENT THAT HAVE
THEIR ARMS TIED BEHIND THEIR
BACK, THAT HAVE IT IMPOSSIBLE TO
FIGHT AND DEFEND THEM SERVICES
AND WIN.
I THINK A IS AMORAL, IT IS WRONG
AND I GIVE YOU MY WORD AS
COMMANDER IN CHIEF THAT, WILL
END ON JANUARY 20th, 2017.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DONALD TRUMP HAS SAID THAT
GEORGE W. BUSH DIDN'T KEEP THIS
COUNTRY SAFE BECAUSE 9/11
HAPPENED ON HIS WATCH.
WHAT DO YOU THINK ABOUT THAT?
>> I THOUGHT IT WAS RIDICULOUS.
I LIKE DONALD.
I AM NOT GOING TO ENGAGE IN
PERSONAL ATTACKS BUT I THINK HIS
POLICY POSITIONS HAVE NOT MADE
ANY SENSE.
WHEN HE STOOD UP AND DEFENDED
IMPEACHING GEORGE W. BUSH, THAT
WAS HIS POSITION, HE SHOULD HAVE
BEEN IMPEACHED.
I'M A CONSTITUTIONALIST.
MY ENTIRE ADULT LIFE HAS BEEN
DEFENDING THE CONSTITUTION, THE
BILL OF RIGHTS.
THE STANDARD FOR IMPEACHMENT MI.
HE SAID ON THE STAGE IT WAS A
MISTAKES.
YOU DON'T IMPEACH PEOPLE FOR
I HAVE TO SAY TO SEE ON A
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL STAGE A
CANDIDATE SUGGEST WE GO SHOULD
HAVE IMPEACHED GEORGE W. BUSH, I
THINK THAT REALLY DRAWS INTO
QUESTION THE JUDGMENT OF THAT
CANDIDATE TO BE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF.
TO.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET PASTOR
TRAVIS HAYES, HE'S FROM THE
REDEMPTION CHURCH.
>> GOOD EVENING, SENATOR.
>> PASTOR.
>> AS WE SEE WHAT APPEARS TO BE
MORE AND MORE OPPOSITION TO
CHRISTIAN CONSERVATIVE VALUES,
WHAT WILL YOU DO TO HELP PROTECT
THOSE VALUES IF YOU'RE ELECTED
PRESIDENT IS IT.
>> PASTOR, THANK YOU FOR BEING
HERE BEING THANK YOU FOR YOUR
MINISTRY.
YOU ARE RIGHT, WE ARE SEEING AN
SAW THE ON JUDEO-CHRISTIAN
VALUES AND WE NEED A PRESIDENT
WHO WILL STAND UP UNAMBIGUOUSLY
AND PROTECT THOSE VALUES.
LIFE,  MARRIAGE, RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY.
MY SUGGESTION, PASTOR IS DON'T
LISTEN TO WHAT ANYONE OF US SAY.
INSTEAD FOLLOW THE BIBLICAL
TEST.
YOU SHALL KNOW THEM BY THEIR
FRUITS.
ASK OF ANY CANDIDATE, DON'T TELL
ME YOU'RE PRO-LIFE, TELL ME WHAT
YOU'VE DONE IT DEFEND THE RIGHT
IT LIFE.
BEFORE I WAS IN THE SENATE, I
WAS THE SOLICITOR GENERAL OF
TEXAS, CHIEF LAWYER FOR THE
STATE IN FRONT OF THE U.S.
SUPREME COURT.
WE BROUGHT TOGETHER A COALITION
OF STATES DEFENDING THE FEDERAL
BAN ON PARTIAL BIRTH ABORTION.
WE WON 5-4.
WE BROUGHT TOGETHER OTHER
COALITION OF STATES DEFENDING
NEW HAMPSHIRE'S LAW AND WE WON
UNANIMOUSLY.
AND IN TEXAS WHEN A FEDERAL
DISTRICT STRUCK DOWN THE LAW
GOING TO PAND PARENTHOOD AND I
ARGUED THE APPEAL, WE WON
UNANIMOUSLY REINSTATING THAT LAW
AND DEFUNDING PLANNED
PARENTHOOD.
A IN JUNE OF LAST YEAR, WE SAW A
DECISION FROM THE SUPREME COURT.
IT WAS NOTHING SHORT OF TRAGIC.
SELF OF THE REASON CANDIDATES
WHEN THAT DECISION CAME DOWN PUT
OUT STATEMENTS THAT ESSENTIALLY
SAID IT IS THE SETTLED LAW OF
THE LAND, WE MUST ACCEPT, ITER
AND MOVE ON.
THOSE ARE ALMOST WORD FOR WORD
THE TALKING POINT OF BARACK
OBAMA.
I THINK THERE'S SOMETHING WRONG
WRONG WHEN REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES
ARE ECHOING THE BE POINTS OF
BARACK OBAMA.
I THINK THAT WAS FUNDAMENTALLY
ILLEGITIMATE, IT WAS LAWLESS.
AND RELIGIOUS LIBERTY HAS BEEN A
LIFE LONG PASSION, I'VE SPENTS
THE LAST TWO DECADES.
>> WE WENT TO THE U.S. SUPREME
COURT AND WE WON 35-4 UPHOLDING
THE TEN COMMANDMENTS.
WE DEFENDED THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE, THE WORD "ONE NATION
UNDER GOD," WE WENT AND I
REPRESENTED OVER 3/MILLION
VETERANS, FOR FREE, DEFENDING
THE MOJAVE DESERT'S VETERAN
MEMORIAL.
THIS IS A LOAN WHITE.
>> THE ACLU SUED ARGUING COULD
YOU NOT DISPLAY A CROSS ON
PUBLIC LAND.
THEY WON IN THE DISTRICT COURT,
THEY WON IN THE COURT OF
APPEALS.
THE COURT ORDERED A GIANT SACK
TO BE PLACED OVER THE VETERANS'
MEMORIAL WITH A CHANGE AND A
PADLOCK AT THE BOTTOM.
I REPRESENTED 3/MILLION VETERANS
DEFENDING THE MOJAVE DESERT
MEMORIAL AND WE WON 5-4.
THE MEDIA BELITTLES THROATS TO
RELIGION LIBERTY.
THEY SAY THEY DON'T EXIST,
THEY'RE NOT REAL.
AT BOB JONES UNIVERSITY, WE
BROUGHT IN HERO, ORDINARY
PEOPLE, A FLORIST, A BAKER,
T-SHIRT SALEMAN, A FIRE IF YOU
GO TO OUR WEB SITE, IT TED DRT
CRUZ.ORG, YOU CAN WATCH THESE
STORY AND THEY WILL HONOR MY
FAITH OR DO I GIVE IN TO THE
GOVERNMENT AND BE PERCENT IT.
>> AND EVERY OTHER FEDERAL
AGENCY, THAT THE PERSECUTION OF
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY ENDS TODAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT YOU TO ME -- THIS IS
DR. AMIR AGOB.
HE WAS GOING TO VOTE ON SATURDAY
BUT HE'S STILL UNDECIDED.
YOU.
>> KNOW THE OIL MARKET IS BIG
OPEC HAS DONE NOTHING TO
STABILIZE THE OIL PRICES AND
THAT IS AFFECTING THE ECONOMY.
RECENTLY RUSSIA, CUT YOU ARE
AND.
>> THEY HAVE BEEN ALLIES AT
TIMES BUT THEY HAVE BEEN PAYING
OFF THE WOLVES IN HOPES THEY LOO
L DEFOUR OTHERSER THAT THAN
DEVOUR OF MONARCHY.
I THINK WOO NEED TO HOLD OUR
FRIENDS O ACCOUNT, THAT FRIENDS
DO NOT SEEK I'LL TELL WHEN YOU I
HAVE TRAVELED ABOARD AND SET
WITH THAT THEY EVER AND
AMERICAN.
DOESN'T STAM BY I THINK WHAT WE
OUGHT TO BE DOING WHEN IT COMES
TO ENERGY IS TWO THINGS --
NUMBER ONE, A SIGNIFICANT PART
OF THE REASON THAT OIL PRICES
AND COMMODITY PRICE
RACEFLUCTUATED LIKE MANY MANYLE
IT ENDS UP SENDING COMMODITY O
PRICES SOARING AND PLUM ELTING
AND SOARING AND PLUMMETING.
WE NEED TO, NUMBER ONE, AUDIT
THE FEDERAL RESERVE AND NUMBER
TWO, MOVE O IT ALWAYS.
>> WE SAD TODAY, TOMORROW AND
YESTERDAY AND A SIGNIFICANT PART
OF THE VOLATILITY IN THE OIL
MARKET IS DRIVEN BY THE
FLUCTUATIONS IN THE DOLLAR.
WHEN IT COMES TO BRRM.
>> GRRNL ZPRCHL AND MY VIEW ON
ENERGY IS WE OUGHT TO SUPPORT
ALL OF THE ABOVE.
BUT YOU SHOULDN'T HAVE
GOVE
GOVERNMENT.
>> SBFRMT ARE WHICH WILL ALLOW
THE ENERGY MARKET TO EXPAND,
CREATE HIGH PAYING JOBS AND TO
JUMP START THE AMERICAN ECONOMY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR YOUR
QUESTION.
THIS IS JULIE HERSHEY, PRESIDENT
OF A LOCAL NONT PROFIT.
SHE SAID SHE'S COMMITTED TO
VOTING FOR YOU.
SO DON'T BLOW IT HERE.
>> JULIE.
>> I DON'T THINK HE CAN.
AND POSSIBLE LITIGATION, WILL
YOU PLEASE JUSTIFY
CONSTITUTIONALLY YOUR LEGAL
RIGHT TO BE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES AS IT RELATES TO
YOUR NATURAL BORN STATUS?
>> SLUR, I'M HEAR TO.
THANK YOU FOR THAT QUESTION.
THE LAW UNDER THE CONSTITUTION
AND FEDERAL LAW HAS BEEN CLEAR
SINCE THE VERY FIRST DAYS OF THE
REPUBLICAN.
THE CHILD OF A U.S. CITIZENS
BORN ABROAD IS TO BE A NATURAL
BORN CITIZEN.
SO IF YOU OR I TRAVEL ABROAD AND
WE HAVE A CHILD OVERSEAS, THAT
CHILD IS A U.S. CITIZENS BY
VIRTUE OF BIRTH.
BOBBY MENTIONED HE HAD A COUPLE
DEPLOYMENTS.
HE HAD CHILD OVERSAERKS THAT
CHILD IS A NATURAL BORN PANAMA.
HIS PARENTS WERE U.S. CITIZENS.
THAT'S WHY GEORGE ROMNEY, MITT
ROMNEY'S DAD, WAS A THE AUTHORS
OF THE -- NOW, MY MOTHER WAS
BORN IN WILMINGTON, DELAWARE.
SHE IS A NATURAL-BORN CITIZEN.
I WAS BORN IN CANADA, AS YOU
HAVE HEARD BY NOW.
>> I'VE HEARD THAT.
>> BUT I WAS A CITIZEN BY BIRTH
BY VIRTUE OF MY'S IT WAS THE ACT
OF BEING BORN THAT MADE ME A
U.S. CITIZEN.
SO UNDER THE CLAW THE QUESTION
IS CLEAR.
THERE WILL STILL BE SOME THAT
HIGH TO WORK POLITICAL MYSTERIES
TO IT.
>> SOME SAY JP HAVE A STANDING.
>> CAN YOU NEVER WRITE OFF THE
POSSIBILITY OF DONALD TRUMP
SUING YOU.
[ LAUGHTER ]
.
>> HE IS WELCOME TO FILE
WHATEVER LAULT HE WANTS.
IF HE WANTS TO FILE A LAWSUIT,
WE HE CAN FILE IT AND LOSE BUT
THE LEGAL MERITS OF THE MATTER
ARE CLEAR.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A SHORT
BREAK AND HAVE MORE QUESTIONS
FOR FIRST SENATOR CRUZ.
WHEN WE COME BACK, MORE
QUESTIONS FROM THE VOTERS.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> WELCOME BACK.
YOU'RE ON A SENATE JUDICIARY
COMMITTEE.
IF PRESIDENT OBAMA SENDS UP A
N
NOMINEE, SHOULD THEY HEAR IT.
>> THEY SHOULD NOT.
>> SHOULD THEY GET A HEARING?
>> I DON'T THINK THEY SHOULD
BECAUSE IT'S NOT ABOUT THE
PARTICULAR NOMINEE.
I THINK WHAT HEARING WOULD END
UP VERY POLITICIZED.
AND I DON'T THINK IT WOULD BE
FAIR TO THE NOMINEE.
I THINK THIS IS A MATTER OF
POLICY, THAT DURING A LAME DUCK
PERIOD WE SHOULD NOT BE
CONFIRMING A SUPREME COURT
NOMINATION -- PARTICULARLY, LUKE
AT JUSTICE SCALIA'S PASSING.
JUSTICE SCALIA WAS A LION OF THE
LAW.
HE WAS SOMEONE I KNEW FOR 20
YEARS.
HE WAS BRILLIANT, PRINCIPLED.
LIKE RONALD REAGAN WAS TO THE
PRESIDENCY, SO JUSTICE SCALIA
WAS TO THE SUPREME COURT.
AND HIS PASSING LEAVES A HUGE
VOID ON THAT COURT.
AND THIS NOMINATION HAS THE
FO
POTENTIAL TO DRAMATICALLY SHIFT
THE BALANCE OF POWER.
THE LAST REPUBLICAN DEBATE CAME
THE SAME DAY WE LEARNED JUSTICE
SCALIA PASSED.
I THINK THAT SHIFTED -- IT
REALLY MADE PEOPLE FOCUS ON THE
GRAVITY OF THE STAKES HERE.
YOU MENTIONED BEFORE THE NEW
POLL TODAY THAT HAS US IN FIRST
PLACE NATIONWIDE, IT'S THE FIRST
TIME DONALD TRUMP HAS NOT BEEN
IN FIRST PLACE IN MANY, MANY
MONTHS AND I THINK THIS IS AN
IMPORTANT REASON WHY, THAT
PEOPLE WERE LOOK AT THIS STAGE
AND SAY HOG DO I KNOW ABOUT
BEYOND A SHADOW OF A DOUBT WOULD
NOMINATE AND FIGHT TO NOMINATE
PRINCIPLED JURISTS.
WE ARE ONE LIBERAL JUSTICE AWAY
FROM THE SUPREME COURT STRIKING
DON'T EVERY RESTRICTION ON
ABORTION THAT'S BEEN PUT IN
PLACE THE LAST FOUR YEARS.
ONE ONE LIBERAL JUSTICE AWAY
FROM THE SUPREME COURT WRITING
THE SECOND AMENDMENT OUT OF
CONSTITUTION.
WE ARE ONE LIBERAL JUSTICE AWAY
FROM THE SUPREME COURT ORDERING
COMMANDMENT MONUMENTS TO BE TORN
DOWN.
AND I THINK ONE.
MOST IMPORTANT QUESTIONS IN THIS
ELECTION IS WHO UNDERSTANDS AND
IS PREPARED AND COMMITTED TO
FIGHT FOR PRINCIPLED SUPREME
COURT JUSTICES THAT WILL FOLLOW
THE CONSTITUTION.
AND I GOT IT TELL YOU, ANDERSON,
I CANNOT WAIT TO STAND ON THAT
DEBATE STAGE WITH HILLARY
CLINTON AND BERNIE SANDERS AND
TAKE IT TO THE AMERICAN PEOPLE,
THEIR VISION OF THE SUPREME
COURT OF THE CONSTITUTION
MANDATES UNLIMITED ABORTION ON
DEMAND, TAKES AWAY OUR RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY, I DON'T THINK THAT'S
WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE BELIEVE
IN, BUT WE OUGHT TO TAKE IT TO
THE ELECTION.
IF THE DEMOCRATS WANT TO
NOMINATE LIBERAL, THEY HAVE TO
WIN THE ELECTION.
ONE OF THE REASONS I THINK
CONSERVATIVES ARE UNITING BEHIND
MY CAMPAIGN IS THEY'RE COMING TO
THE REALIZATION STLA THE
EXPERIENCE AND THE COMMITMENT TO
MAKE THAT COMMITMENT BAGAINST
HILLARY CLINTON AND BERNIE
SANDERS.
>> DONALD TRUMP AND MARCO RUBIO
HAVE SAID YOU'RE A LIAR.
ARE THEY LYING ABOUT THAT?
>> THIS IS A STRANGE ELECTION
SEASON IN MANY WAYS.
BOTH DONALD TRUMP AND MARCO
RUBIO ARE FOLLOWING THIS PATTERN
THAT WHENEVER ANYONE POINTS IT
THEIR ACTUAL RECORD, TO WHAT
THEY'VE SAID TO WHAT THEY'VE
VOTED ON TO WHAT THEY'VE DONE,
THEY START SCREAMING LIAR, LIAR,
LIAR.
IT IS THE ODDEST THING I CAN'T
THINK ANY PRECEDENT IN ANY
PREVIOUS REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
ELECTION.
NOW, FROM MY END, I HAVE NOT AND
WILL NOT RESPOND IN KIND.
IF THEY WANT TO ENGAGE IN
PERSONAL INSULTS, IF THEY WANT
TO GO TO THE MUD, I'M NOT GOING
TO SAY THE SAME THING ABOUT
THEM.
I THINK THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA DESERVE MORE THAN
PEOPLE JUST THROWING MUD AT EACH
OTHER.
I MENTIONED ON SATURDAY ON THE
DEBATE STAGE THAT DONALD TRUMP
FOR 60 YEARS OF HIS LIFE HAS
DESCRIBED HIMSELF AS PRO
ABORTION, AND EVEN NOW SUPPORTS
TAXPAYER FUNDING FOR PLANNED
PARENTHOOD.
HIS RESPONSE WAS TO BEL BELLOW
"LIAR, LIAR."
YOU SAID ON NATIONAL TELEVISION
YOU THINK PLANNED PARENTHOOD
DOES WONDERFUL THINGS.
AND THEN, ANDERSON, DONALD
PROCEEDED TO SAY ON DEET BAIT
STAGE ONCE AGAIN HE THINKS
PLANNED PARENTHOOD DOES
WONDERFUL THINGS.
THE VERY THING HE CALLED ME A
LIAR FOR, HE SAID AGAIN ON THE
STAGE.
>> I LIKE MARCO RUBIO.
HE'S A FRIEND OF MINE.
I MADE THREE STATEMENTS ABOUT
MARCO'S IMMIGRATION DURING THE
DEBATE.
I THINK NUMBER ONE, MARCO RIGHT
NOW SUPPORTS GRANTING
CITIZENSHIP TO THE 12 MILLION
PEOPLE WHO ARE HERE ILLEGALLY.
NOW, THAT IS A FACT.
HE SAID THAT ON DEET BALT STAGE
TWO OR THREE DEBATES AGO.
IN FACT, ON "MEET THE PRESS"
WITH CHUCK TODD A FEW WEEKS AGO,
MARCO SAID HE SHOULD GRANT
CITIZENSHIP TO PEOPLE HERE
ILLEGALLY EVEN IF THEY HAVE
CRIMINAL CONVICTIONS.
THE SECOND THING I SAID HE SAID
WHEN HE WAS IN FLORIDA, HE
SUPPORTED IN HAD OF STATE
TUITION FOR ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS.
THAT'S A FACT.
AND THE THIRD THING I SAID IS HE
WENT ON UNIVISION AND IN SPANISH
SAID HE WOULD NOT RESCIND THE
ILLEGAL EXECUTIVE ACTION ON
IMMIGRATION.
MARCO FOLLOWED THE SAME
STRATEGY, JUST SCREAMED LIAR,
LIAR, LIAR.
HE DIDN'T DISPUTE THE SUBSTANCE.
HE SAID HOW WOULD YOU KNOW WHAT
I SAID ON UNIVISION.
YOU DON'T SPEAK SPAN IR.
WELL, MARCO WAS INCORRECT ON
THAT.
BUT, LOOK, TRUTH MATTERS.
EVERY ONE OF THESE ISSUES,
DONALD AND MARCO ARE ON VIDEO ON
NATIONAL TELEVISION STATING
THEIR POSITIONS AND JUST YELLING
LIAR DOESN'T MAKE IT SO.
AND I WOULD NOTE, BY THE WAY, IF
MARCO IS RIGHT THAT I'M LYING,
THEY BE I'LL TELL YOU ELSE HAS
TO BE LYING, JEFF SESSIONS HAS
TO BE BUYLYING, RUSH LIMBAUGH,
JAMES DOBSON HAS TO BE LYING
BECAUSE EVERY ONE OF THEM HAS
SAID THE EXACT SAME THING I DID,
MOST OF THOSE FOLKS HAVEN'T
ENDORSED ME, THEY'RE NOT
SUPPORTING ME, BUT THEY'VE
SPOKEN THE TRUTH.
ONE OF THE THINGS I LOVE ABOUT
THE PEOPLE IN SOUTH CAROLINA IS
HOW SERIOUSLY THEY TAKE THE
RESPONSIBILITY TO VET THE
CANDIDATES.
CAN YOU GO TO OUR WEB SITE AND
WATCH THE VIDEO AND SEE MARCO
AND DONALD STATING THEIR
POSITIONS.
>> THIS IS ROBERT TUCKER, A L
LAWYER.
HE SAID HE'S STILL DECIDING
BETWEEN YOU AND MARCO RUBIO.
>> WELCOME.
>> WELCOME BACK TO GREENVILLE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> GO WE'VE SEEN ARTICLES THAT
YOU DON'T GET ALONG WITH SOME OF
YOUR REPUBLICAN SENATORS, YOUR
COLLEAGUES IN WASHINGTON.
IF YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE A
PROBLEM WITH THEM, WHAT ARE YOU
GOING TO SAY TO THEM AS
PRESIDENT TO GET THEM ON BOARD
SO WE CAN GET LEGISLATION
PASSED?
>> IT'S A GREAT QUESTION,
ROBERT, THANK YOU FOR ASKING IT.
THE REASON WHY THAT IS IS
SIMPLE.
IT'S NOT THAT I SPEAK WITH AK
LACK OF CIVILITY OR RESPECT.
YOU'VE SEEN IN THIS PRESIDENTIAL
CAMPAIGN AS OTHER OS INSULT ME
OR IMPUGN MY INTEGRITY, I DON'T
RESPOND IN KIND.
I HAVE NOT ATTACKED OR
INASSAULTED MY COLLEAGUES IN THE
SENATE, DEMOCRATIC OR
REPUBLICAN.
I'LL TELL YOU WHY THEY SAY TED
IS UNLIKABLE IN WASHINGTON.
BECAUSE I'M ACTUALLY HONORING
THE COMMITMENTS THAT I MADE TO
THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO ELECTED
ME.
FOR EXAMPLE, ON PLANNED
PARENTHOOD, I LED THE FIGHT FOR
TO US USE THE BUDGETARY POWER OF
CONGRESS TO STOP GIVING $500
MILLION TO PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
THE REPUBLICAN LEADERSHIP WANTED
TO HAVE A SHOW VOTE, LOSE THE
SHOW VOTE AND THEN FUND ALL OF
OBAMA'S AGENDA INCLUDING PLANNED
PARENTHOOD.
WHAT'S UNLIKABLE IS WHEN YOU
STAND UP AND SAY HOW ABOUT WE DO
WHAT WE SAID WE WOULD DO.
WHEN I STOOD UP AND LED THE
FIGHT AGAINST THE RUBIO/SCHUMER
AMNESTY BILL, THEY SAID THAT WAS
UNLIKABLE.
YOU KNOW WHY?
BECAUSE ALL THE MONEY IN
WASHINGTON AND ALL THE LOBBYISTS
IN WASHINGTON WANTED AMNESTY.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE SPECIAL
INTEREST, AMNESTY, THEY IT'S ITS
GREAT, IT'S CHEAP LABOR.
AND, BY THE WAY, THE WAY WE WON
THESE FIGHTS IS THAT I STOOD UP
AND TRIED TO SHINE A LIGHT ON
THEM, SHINE ATTENTION ON THEM
AND EMPOWER THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
RUBIO/SCHUMER AMNESTY PASSED.
IT WAS HEADED TO THE HOUSE IT
PASS.
JOHN BOEHNER INTENDED TO TAKE IT
UP, PASS IT WITH ALL THE
DEMOCRATS AND A HANDFUL OF
REPUBLICANS, ROLL OVER ABOUT 200
HOUSE REPUBLICANS.
AND I STOOD WITH JEFF SESSIONS
AND STEVE KING AND WE TOOK THE
CASE TO THE AMERICAN PEOPLE AND
WHAT HAPPENED IS MILLIONS OF
AMERICAN PEOPLE ROSE UP, LIT UP
THE PHONES TO CONGRESS AND SAID
DON'T DO THIS AND WE DEDEE
FEATED THE RUBIO/SCHUMER AMNESTY
BILL IN THE HOUSE.
IN THE WORLD OF WASHINGTON,
THAT'S CONSIDERED UNLIKABLE.
WHEN REPUBLICAN LEADERSHIP -- I
WROTE A BOOK LAST YEAR CALLED "A
TIME FOR TRUTH "OUP.
THE OPENING CHAPTER DESIGHTS THE
INSIDE STORY WHACHD ON THE DEBT
CEILING, WHERE REPUBLICAN
LEADERSHIP WANTED TO MAKE IT
EASIER FOR HARRY REID TO ADD
TRILLIONS IN DEBT TO OUR COUNTRY
AND I OBJECTED TO THAT, THE ACT
OF HONORING THE PROMISE I MADE
TO THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO ELECTED
ME ENGENDER MORE ANIMOSITY THAN
ANYTHING I'VE DONE IN MY TIME IN
THE SENATE.
JUST THIS MORNING SENATOR JIM
DEMI
DEMINT WAS IN A RADIO QUESTION
AND ADDRESSED THIS YES.
HE SAID TED IS A FRIEND, ANYONE
WHO SAYS HE'S UNLIKABLE IS BEING
RIDICULOUS, HE SAID THEY SAID
THE THING ABOUT ME BECAUSE JIM
DEMINT HONORED THE COMMITMENTS
HE MADE TO SOUTH CAROLINA.
REPUBLICAN LEADERSHIP HATED JIM
DEMINT.
NOT BECAUSE HE SPEAK MEAN ABOUT
THEM BUT BECAUSE HE'S ACTUALLY
SAID LET'S DO WHAT HE SAID WE
WOULD DO.
SO LOTS TAKE THE SECOND HALF OF
YOUR QUESTION.
HOW DO WE FIX THE PROBLEMS?
A PRESIDENT HAS THREE LEVERS OF
PRESIDENTIAL AUTHORITY TO CHANGE
THE DIRECTION OF THIS COUNTRY.
NUMBER ONE IS EXECUTIVE POW
PERSON THAT'S BEEN THE ONE OBAMA
HAS ABUSED SO MUCH.
THE SILVER LINING IS EVERYTHING
DONE WITH EXECUTIVE POWER CAN BE
UNDONE WITH EXECUTIVE POW PERSON
THAT'S WHY I PLEDGE PLEDGED TO
RESINT EVERY SINGLE ILLEGAL
EXECUTIVE ACTION UNDER PRESIDENT
OBAMA.
IT'S WHY I PLEDGED TO END THE
PERSECUTION INDIVIDUAL LIBERTY
AND WHY I PLEDGE TO INSTRUCT
THAT COMMON CORE ENDS TODAY.
USING LEGITIMATE EXECUTIVE POW
EXYOU CAN END MANY OF THE ABUSES
OF OBAMA IF YOU HAVE A PRESIDENT
WILLING TO USE THE POWER.
THE SECOND AVENUE OF EXECUTIVE
POWER TO CHANGE THE DIRECTION OF
THIS COUNTRY IS FOREIGN POLICY.
THAT'S WHY I PLEDGED ON DAY ONE
TO RIP THIS SHREDS THE IRAN
NUCLEAR DEAL AND IT'S WORTH
REMEMBERING THIS SAME NATION,
IRAN, RELEASED OUR HOSTAGES THE
DAY THAT RONALD REAGAN WAS SWORN
IN.
THE THIRD AVENUE TO CHANGE THE
DIRECTION OF THE COUNTRY IS
LEGISLATION.
LEGISLATION IS NOT EASY WITH
THIS BROKEN CONGRESS.
I'M RUNNING ON TWO BIG
LEGISLATIVE INITIATIVES.
NUMBER ONE, REPEALING EVERY WORD
OF OBAMACARE AND, NUMBER IT
WOULD BE, ADOPTING A SIMPLE FLAT
TAX AND ABOLISHING THE IRS.
NOW, NEITHER ONE OF THOSE ARE
EASY.
I'M NOT REMOTELY NAIVE OR POLLY
ANISH.
COULD I GET THOSE DONE IN THIS
CONGRESS?
NO.
BUT THINK ABOUT THE LAST TIME WE
BEAT THE WASHINGTON CARTEL.
IT WAS 1980.
REAGAN IN '76, PRIMARY GERALD
FORD.
YOU WANT TO MAKE REPUBLICAN
LEADERSHIP LOATH YOU, COME
WITHIN AN INCH OF BEATING THE
INCUMBENT REPUBLICAN PRESIDENT
IN A PRIMARY.
YOU THINK THEY DISLIKE ME?
THEY HATED REAGAN WITH THE HEAT
OF A THOUSAND WHITE HOT SUNS.
HE WAS UNLIKABLE.
YET WHAT DID REAGAN DO IN '77,
'78, '79, HE DIDN'T FLY TO
WASHINGTON AND SIT DOWN WITH THE
OLD BULLS AND SAY LET'S DO
SOMETHING.
HE KNEW THAT WOULDN'T HAPPEN.
WHEN YOU GO TO THE PEOPLE, IT
TRANSFORMED THE INCENTIVES.
CAN YOU NOT FIND A REPUBLICAN
WHO WILL NOT SWEAR THAT RONALD
REAGAN IS TATTOOED SOMEWHERE ON
THEIR BODY.
BUT THE REASON IS HE TOOK THE
CASE TO THE PEOPLE AND HE
CHANGED THE INCENTIVES.
HOW DO WE ABOLISH ---Y REPEAL
OBAMACARE AND MAKE A FLAT TAX,
WE MAKE IT A REFERENDUM SO WE
COME OUT IN 2016 WITH A MANDATE
FROM THE PEOPLE.
THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT I INTEND DO.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
>> THIS IS SUSAN HARVEY.
SHE'S A LOCAL TRAVEL AGENT.
SHE'S STILL UNDECIDED.
>> GOOD EVENING, SUSAN.
>> HI.
IF YOU'RE ELECTED, WHAT POSITION
THIS YOUR CABINET WOULD THE MOST
IMPORTANT TO FILL FIRST AND WHY?
>> THAT IS A VERY GOOD QUESTION.
I WOULD SAY IT WOULD BE A
THREE-WAY TIE BETWEEN SECRETARY
OF STATE, SECRETARY OF DEFENSE
AND ATTORNEY GENERAL.
ALL THREE ARE CRITICALLY
IMPORTANT.
STATE AND DEFENSE, WE NEED O
START REBUILDING OUR MILITARY
IMMEDIATELY WHEN.
IT COMES IT STATE, WE HAVE
ABANDONED OUR FRIEND AND ALLIES
NATIONALLY.
IT'S PART OF THE REASON I
MENTIONED BEFORE RIPPING TO
SHREDS THE IRANIAN NUCLEAR DEAL
AND MOVING THE AMERICAN EMBASSY
TO JERUSALEM, BOTH OF THOSE ARE
WITHIN THE POWER OF THE
PRESIDENT BUT THEY'RE ALSO
POWERFULLY SYMBOLIC.
MOVING THE EMBASSY TO ISRAEL
TELLS ISRAEL, OUR ALLIES AND OUR
ENEMIES AMERICA IS BACK.
OBAMA IN HIS OPENING WEEKS, HE
SENT BACK THE BUST OF WINSTON
CHURCHILL TO THE UNITED KINGDOM.
IF I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT,
WINSTON CHURCHILL IS COMING BACK
TO THE OVAL OFFICE.
AS SECRETARY OF STATE WEEK NEED
SOMEONE STRONG, SOMEONE WHO
DEFENDS THIS COUNTRY, SOMEONE
WHO REPRESENTS THIS COUNTRY.
I'M NOT IN THE POSITION RIGHT
NOW TO BE NAMING CABINET
APPOINTMENTS, BUT A SECRETARY OF
STATE IN THE CRUZ TRAGS WOULD BE
SOMEONE LIKE JOHN BOLTON,
SOMEONE WHO IS STRONG, WHO
DEFENDS HAD COUNTRY, WHO SFWANDS
OUR ALLIES AND STAND UP TO OUR
ENEMIES.
LOOKING AT ATTORNEY GENERAL,
ATTORNEY GENERAL, THE
LAWLESSNESS OF THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION, HAS BEEN ONE OF
THE SADDEST LEGACIES.
AND YOU KNOW ONE OF THE MOST
REVEALING ASPECTS -- ANDERSON,
IF YOU ASK REPORTERS IN
WASHINGTON, OFF THE RECORD, YOU
GET THEM AT THE BAR HAVING A
COUPLE DRINKS AND YOU SAY IS
HILLARY GOING TO BE INDICTED?
INSELF-ABLY THE ANSWER THEY
GIVER YOU THEY'RE GOING TO SAY,
WELL, IT DEPENDS ON IF THE OBAMA
WHITE HOUSE DECIDES THEY WANT TO
THROW HER OVERBOARD.
IT THEY DECIDE THEY WANT TO KEEP
HER, NO, SHE WON'T BE INDICTED
AND IF THEY DECIDE THEY'RE DONE
WITH HER, SHE WILL.
HOW HOWE SAD IS IT THAT THE
MEDIA ACCEPTS AS A GIVEN THAT
WHETHER SOMEONE IS PROSECUTED
UNDER THE POLITICAL WILL YOU
DEPENDS ON WHAT SOME POLITICAL
HACK IN THE WEST WING THINKS.
I USED TO BE AN ASSOCIATE DEPUTY
ATTORNEY GENERAL ANDISM SPENT
FIVE AND A HALF YEARS AS
SOLICITOR GENERAL IN THE STATE
OF TEXAS.
LAW ENFORCEMENT IN THE
ADMINISTRATION OF LAW IS
CRITICALLY IMPORTANT.
AND I GIVE YOU MY WORD THAT THE
ATTORNEY GENERAL IN MY
ADMINISTRATION WILL BE BLIND TO
PARTY OR IDEOLOGY.
IT WILL NOT BE A PARTISAN
POSITION.
THE ONLY FIDELITY OF THE
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE WILL BE TO
THE LAWS AND THE CONSTITUTION OF
THE UNITED STATES.
THAT'S THE WAY IT'S MEANT TO
WORK.
>> WE HAVE A FEW MINUTES LEFT.
DO YOU WANT TO TELL ME WHAT
REPORTERS YOU'RE HAVING DRINKS
WITH IN D.C.?
>> I GUESS NOT.
>> WHAT'S YOUR FAVORITE
COCKTAIL?
>> I'M A SCOTCH MAN.
>> I UNDERSTAND YOU'RE ALSO A
NIGHT OWL.
DO YOU HAVE A GUILTY PLEASURE,
DO YOU WATCH TELEVISION?
>> I USED TO WATCH TV.
I'M A HUGE MOVIE BUFF.
I LOVE MOVIES.
I LIKE VIDEO GAMES.
ONE OF THE THINGS -- IF YOU
ASKED MY WIFE, IF YOU ASKED
HEIDI WHAT DRIVES HER CRAZE OWE
ABOUT ME THE MOST, IT IS MY
iPHONE.
IF SHE COULD FLING MY iPHONE OUT
THE WINDOW AND INTO THE TRASH,
SHE WILL BE THRILLED, I'M ON MY
iPHONE PLAYING PLANTS VERSUS
ZOMBIES, CANDY CRUSH.
MY GIRLS LOVE IT.
>> I KNOW YOU'VE DONE A LOT OF
IMPERSONATIONS ON THE CAMPAIGN
TRAIL.
WHAT'S YOUR FAVORITE ONE AND DO
YOU WANT TO GRACE US WITH IT?
>> PART IT HAVE IS YOU WANT TO
HAVE FUN.
A LOT OF TIMESISM GET THE
QUESTIONS IN TOWN HALLS.
HOW DO REPUBLICANS REACH YOUNG
PEOPLE?
PART IT HAVE IS SUBSTANTIAL BEEP
HAVE TO MAKE THE CASE THAT THE
OBAMA AGENDA IS HAMMERING YOUNG
PEOPLE.
FOR SEVEN YEARS PEOPLE COME OUT
OF SCHOOL WITH ECONOMIC
STAGNATION, THEY CAN'T GET A
JOB, THEY DON'T HAVE A FUTURE.
PART OF GETTING YOUNG PEOPLE IS
GETTING PEOPLE TO LOOSEN UP.
WOULD IT KILL THE REPUBLICANS TO
CRACK A JOKE?
I'M REMINDED OF A FEW YEARS BACK
I WAS OUT IN L.A. TRAVELING
THROUGHOUT.
THE WEEK BEFORE I ARRIVED THESE
POSTERS BEGAN APPEARING ALL OVER
TOWN.
AND THEY'RE POSTERS OF MY HEAD
ON A SHIRTLESS TORSO THAT IS
RIPPED.
AND IT'S COVERED WITH TATTOO, A
GIANT EAGLE ON MY CHEST, TWO SIX
SHOOTERS ON MY ABS --
>> YOU EVER SOUND LESS THAN CON
VINCED.
>> A CIGARETTE DANGLING OUT OF
MY TO MOUTH AND ABOVE IT THE
LEGEND "BLACK LISTED AND LOVING
IT."
WE HAD NOTHING IT DID WITH THESE
POSTERS.
IT WAS A LOCAL STRAIGHT ARTIST
IN L.A. AND WE DECIDED TO HAVE
SOME FUN WITH THEM.
WE POSTED ON FACEBOOK AND SAID
FOR WHATEVER REASON THESE
POSTERS STARTED APPEARING ALL
AROUND WHO WILL' WOOD.
I SAID I HAVE TO SAY I NOTICED A
GLARING ERROR, I DON'T SMOKE
CIGARETTES.
>> A SPECIAL THANKS TO ALL THE
VOTERS BEING HERE AND ASKING THE
QUES
QUESTIONS AND FOR THE VIEWERS AT
HOME, I HOPE YOU'LL JOIN US.
OUR COVERAGE CONTINUES WITH DON
LEMON RIGHT AFTER THIS.