>> GOOD EVENING.
I'M JOHN DICKERSON OF CBS NEWS
IN DES MOINES, IOWA.
THE DEBATE YOU'VE TUNED IN TO
SEE TONIGHT IS A SYMBOL OF THE
FREEDOM WE ALL CHERISH.
LAST NIGHT, THE WORLD WATCHED IN
HORROR AS FREEDOM WAS SAVAGELY
ATTACKED IN THE HEART OF PARIS.
AT LEAST 129 PEOPLE WERE KILLED
AND MANY MORE WOUNDED IN A
COORDINATED SERIES OF TERROR
ATTACKS.
TONIGHT, AS FRANCE MOURNS, SO
DOES AMERICA.
SO BEFORE WE BEGIN TONIGHT'S
SECOND DEBATE WITH THESE
CANDIDATES FOR THE DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL NOMINATION, WE ASK
YOU TO JOIN US IN OBSERVING A
MOMENT OF SILENCE.
NOW, PLEASE WELCOME TO DRAKE
UNIVERSITY, FORMER SECRETARY OF
STATE HILLARY CLINTON.
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS OF
VERMONT.
( APPLAUSE )
AND MARTIN O'MALLEY, THE FORMER
GOVERNOR OF MARYLAND.
( APPLAUSE )
JOINING ME IN THE QUESTIONING
TONIGHT ARE CBS NEWS
CONGRESSIONAL CORRESPONDENT
NANCY CORDES.
ANCHOR KEVIN COONEY OF OUR CBS
DES MOINES AFFILIATE KCCI.
AND POLITICAL COLUMNIST KATHIE
OBRADOVICH OF THE "DES MOINES
REGISTER."
( APPLAUSE )
TWITTER IS ANOTHER OF OUR
PARTNERS FOR THIS DEBATE.
TWEETS WILL HELP US FOLLOW THE
REACTION TO WHAT THE CANDIDATES
SAY.
SO PLEASE SEND US YOUR COMMENTS
USING THE HASHTAG #DEMDEBATE.
AND WE'LL BEGIN IN JUST A
MOMENT.
( APPLAUSE )
>> THIS IS A PEOPLE'S CAMPAIGN.
I.
>> I AM A REAL PERSON WITH ALL
THE PLUSE PLUSES AND MINUSES THO
ALONG WITH THAT.
>> YOU START WHERE YOU START
THROUGH YOUR OWN HARD WORK.
>> I'M RUNNING TO HELP WORKING
FAMILIES GET A RAISE.
>> THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE SICK
AND TIRED OF HEARING ABOUT YOUR
DAMN E-MAILS.
>> THEY ARE DEAD WRONG FOR
21st CENTURY AMERICA.
WE'RE GOING FORWARD.
WE'RE NOT GOING BACK!
>> TONIGHT, LIVE FROM DRAKE
UNIVERSITY IN DES MOINES, IOWA,
CBS NEWS BRINGS YOU THE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
>> BEFORE WE-- BEFORE WE START
THE DEBATE, HERE ARE THE RULES.
THE CANDIDATES HAVE ONE MINUTE
TO RESPOND TO OUR QUESTIONS AND
30 SECONDS TOY RESPOND TO OUR
FOLLOW-UPS.
ANY CANDIDATE WHO IS ATTACKED BY
ANOTHER CANDIDATE GETS 30
SECONDS FOR REBUTTAL.
HERE'S HOW WE'LL KEEP TIME.
AFTER A QUESTION IS ASKING, THE
GREEN LIGHT GOES ON.
WHEN THERE ARE 15 SECONDS LEFT,
THE CANDIDATE GETS A YELLOW
WARNING LIGHT.
AND WHEN TIME SUP, THE LIGHT
TURNS RED.
THAT MEANS STOP TALKING.
( LAUGHTER )
THOSE ARE THE RULES.
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
YOU WILL EACH HAVE ONE MINUTE
FOR AN OPENING STATEMENT TO
SHARE YOUR THOUGHTS ABOUT THE
ATTACKS IN PARIS AND LAY OUT
YOUR VISION FOR AMERICA.
FIRST, SENATOR SANDERS.
>> WELL, JOHN, LET ME CONCUR
WITH YOU AND WITH ALL AMERICANS
WHO ARE SHOCKED AND DISGUSTED BY
WHAT WE SAW IN PARIS YESTERDAY.
TOGETHER, LEADING THE WORLD,
THIS COUNTRY WILL RID OUR PLANET
OF THIS BARBARIS ORGANIZATION
CALLED ISIS.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
BECAUSE AS I GO AROUND THIS
NATION, I TALK TO A LOT OF
PEOPLE, AND WHAT I HEAR IS
PEOPLE'S CONCERN THAT THE
ECONOMY WE HAVE IS A RIGGED
ECONOMY.
PEOPLE ARE WORKING LONGER HOURS
FOR LOWER WAGEAND ALMOST ALL OF
THE NEW INCOME AND WEALTH GOES
TO THE TOP 1%.
AND THEN ON TOP OF THAT, WE'VE
GOT A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN FINANCE
SYSTEM IN WHICH MILLIONAIRES AND
BILLIONAIRES ARE POURING HUGE
SUMS OF MONEY INTO SUPER PACS
HEAVILY INFLUENCING THE
POLITICAL PROCESS.
WHAT MY CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT IS A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION.
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE STANDING UP
AND SAYING, "ENOUGH IS ENOUGH.
OUR GOVERNMENT BELONGS TO ALL OF
US AND NOT JUST THE HAND FULL OF
BILLIONAIRES."
>> ALL RIGHT, SENATOR SANDERS.
SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> WELL, OUR PRAYERS ARE WITH
THE PEOPLE OF FRANCE TONIGHT,
BUT THAT IS NOT ENOUGH.
WE NEED TO HAVE A RESOLVE THAT
WILL BRING THE WORLD TOGETHER TO
ROOT OUT THE KIND OF RADICAL
JIHADIST IDEOLOGY THAT MOTIVATES
ORGANIZATIONS LIKE ISIS, A
BARBARIC, RUTHLESS, VIOLENT
JIHADIST TERRORIST GROUP.
THIS ELECTION IS NOT ONLY
ABOUTING ELECTING A PRESIDENT.
IT'S ALSO ABOUT CHOOSING OUR
NEXT COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
AND I WILL BE LAYING OUT IN
DETAIL WHAT I THINK WE NEED TO
DO WITH OUR FRIENDS AND ALLIES
IN EUROPE AND ELSEWHERE TO DO A
BETTER JOB OF COORDINATING
EFFORTS AGAINST THE SCOURGE OF
TERRORISM.
OUR COUNTRY DESERVES NO LESS
BECAUSE ALL OF THE OTHER ISSUES
WE WANT TO DEAL WITH DEPEND UPON
US BEING SECURE AND STRONG.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> MY HEART, LIKE ALL OF US IN
THIS ROOM, JOHN, AND ALL THE
PEOPLE ACROSS OUR COUNTRY, MY
HEARTS GO OUT TO THE PEOPLE OF
FRANCE IN THIS MOMENT OF LOSS.
PARENTS AND SONS AND DAUGHTERS
AND FAMILY MEMBERS AND AS OUR
HEARTS GO OUT TO THEM AND AS OUR
PRAYERS GO OUT TO THEM, WE MUST
REMEMBER THIS, THAT THIS IS THE
NEW FACE OF CONFLICT AND
WARFARE, NOT IN THE 20th
CENTURY BUT THE NEW FACE OF
CONFLICT AND WARFARE IN THE
21st CENTURY.
AND THERE IS NO NATION ON THE
PLANET BETTER ABLE TO ADAPT TO
THIS CHANGE THAN OUR NATION.
WE MUST ABLE TO WORK
COLLABORATIVELY WITH OTHERS.
WE MUST ANTICIPATE THESE THREATS
BEFORE THEY HAPPEN.
THIS IS THE NEW SORT OF
CHALLENGE, THE NEW SORT OF
THREAT THAT DOES, IN FACT,
REQUIRE NEW THINKING, FRESH
APPROACHES AND NEW LEADERSHIP.
AS A FORMER MAYOR AND A FORMER
GOVERNOR, THERE WAS NEVER A
SINGLE DAY, JOHN, WHEN I WENT TO
BED OR WOKE UP WITHOUT REALIZING
THAT THIS COULD HAPPEN IN OUR
OWN COUNTRY.
WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO TO
BETTER PREPARE OUR NATION AND TO
BETTER LEAD THIS WORLD INTO THIS
NEW CENTURY.
>> ALL RIGHT, THANK YOU,
GOVERNOR.
THANK ALL OF YOU.
THE TERROR ATTACKS LAST NIGHT
UNDERSCORE BIGGEST CHALLENGE
FACING THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
AT A TIME OF CRISIS, THE COUNTRY
AND THE WORLD LOOK TO THE
PRESIDENT FOR LEADERSHIP AND FOR
ANSWERS.
SO, SECRETARY CLINTON, I'D LIKE
TO START WITH YOU.
HOURS BEFORE THE ATTACKS,
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID "I DON'T
THINK ISIS IS GAINING STRENGTH."
72% OF AMERICANS THINK THE FIGHT
AGAINST ISIS IS GOING BADLY.
WON'T THE LEGACY OF THIS
ADMINISTRATION, WHICH IS-- WHICH
YOU WERE A PART OF, WON'T THAT
LEGACY BE THAT IT UNDERESTIMATED
THE THREAT FROM ISIS?
>> WELL, JOHN, I THINK THAT WE
HAVE TO LOOK AT ISIS AS THE
LEADING THREAT OF AN
INTERNATIONAL TERROR NETWORK.
IT CANNOT BE CONTAINED.
IT MUST BE DEFEATED.
THERE IS NO QUESTION IN MY MIND
THAT IF WE SUMMON OUR RESOURCES,
BOTH OUR LEADERSHIP RESOURCESSOS
AND ALL OF THE TOOLS AT OUR
DISPOSAL, NOT JUST MILITARY
FORCE, WHICH SHOULD BE USED AS A
LAST RESORT, BUT OUR DIPLOMACY,
OUR DEVELOPMENT AID, LAW
ENFORCEMENT, SHARING OF
INTELLIGENCE IN A MUCH MORE OPEN
AND COOPERATIVE WAY, THAT WE CAN
BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER.
BUT IT CANNOT BE AN AMERICAN
FIGHT.
AND I THINK WHAT THE PRESIDENT
HAS CONSISTENTLY SAID-- WHICH I
AGREE WITH-- IS THAT WE WILL
SUPPORT THOSE WHO TAKE THE FIGHT
TO ISIS.
THAT IS WHY WE HAVE TROOPS IN
IRAQ THAT ARE HELPING TO TRAIN
AND BUILD BACK UP THE IRAQI
MILITARY.
WHY WE HAVE SPECIAL OPERATORS IN
SYRIA WORKING WITH THE KURDS AND
ARABS SO THAT WE CAN BE
SUPPORTIVE.
BUT THIS CANNOT BE AN AMERICAN
FIGHT, ALTHOUGH AMERICAN
LEADERSHIP IS ESSENTIAL.
>> BUT, SECRETARY CLINTON, THE
QUESTION WAS ABOUT WAS ISIS
UNDERESTIMATED?
I'LL JUST ADD, THE PRESIDENT
REFERRED TO ISIS AS THE J.V.U.,
IN A SPEECH.
"I COULD NOT HAVE PREDICTED THE
EXTENT TO WHICH ISIS COULD BE
EFFECTIVE IN SEIZING CITIES IN
IRAQ."
SO YOU'VE GOT PRESCRIPTIONS FOR
THE FUTURE, BUT HOW DO WE EVEN
THOSE PRESCRIPTION PRESCRIPTIOND
IF YOU MISSED IT IN THE PAST?
>> WELL, JOHN, LOOK, I THINK
THAT WHAT HAPPENED WHEN WE
ABIDED BY THE AGREEMENT THAT
GEORGE W. BUSH MADE WITH THE
IRAQIS TO LEAVE BY 2011 IS THAT
AN IRAQI ARMY WAS LEFT THAT HAD
BEEN TRAINED AND THAT WAS
PREPARED TO DEFEND IRAQ.
UNFORTUNATELY, NOURI AL-MALIKI,
THE PRIME MINISTER, SET ABOUT
DECIMATING IT.
AND THEN, WITH THE REVOLUTION
AGAINST ASSAD-- AND I DID EARLY
ON SAY WE NEEDED TO TRY TO FIND
A WAY TO TRAIN AND EQUIP MOD
RAITS VERY EARLY SO THAT WE
WOULD HAVE A BETTER IDEA OF HOW
TO DEAL WITH ASSAD BECAUSE I
THOUGHT THERE WOULD BE EXTREMIST
GROUPS FILLING THE VACUUM.
SO, YES, THIS HAS DEVELOPED.
I THINK THAT THERE ARE MANY
OTHER REASONS WHY IT HAS IN
ADDITION TO WHAT HAPPENED IN THE
REGION, BUT I DON'T THINK THAT
THE UNITED STATES HAS THE BULK
OF THE RESPONSIBILITY.
I REALLY PUT THAT ON ASSAD AND
ON THE IRAQIS AND ON THE REGION
ITSELF.
>> OKAY, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY,
WOULD YOU CRITIQUE THE
ADMINISTRATION'S RESPONSE TO
ISIS.
IF THE UNITED STATES DOESN'T
LEAD, WHO LEADS?
>> I WOULD DISAGREE WITH
SECRETARY CLINTON RESPECTFULLY
ON THIS SCORE.
THIS ACTUALLY IS AMERICA'S
FIGHT.
IT CANNOT SOLELY BE AMERICA'S
AMERICA IS BEST WHEN WE WORK IN
COLLABORATION WITH OUR ALLIES.
AMERICA IS BEST WHEN WE ARE
ACTUALLY STANDING UP TO EVIL IN
THIS WORLD.
AND ISIS, MAKE NO MISTAKE ABOUT
IT, IS AN EVIL IN THIS WORLD.
ISIS HAS BROUGHT DOWN A RUSSIAN
AIRLINER.
ISIS HAS NOW ATTACKED A WESTERN
DEMOCRACY IN FRANCE.
AND WE DO HAVE A ROLE IN THIS.
NOT SOLELY OURS, BUT WE MUST
WORK COLLABORATIVELY WITH OTHER
NATIONS.
THE GREAT FAILING OF THESE LAST
10 OR 15 YEARS, JOHN, HAS BEEN
OUR FAILING OF HUMAN
INTELLIGENCE ON THE GROUND.
OUR ROLE IN THE WORLD IS NOT TO
ROAM THE GLOBE LOOKING FOR NEW
DICTATORS TO TOPPLE.
OUR ROLE IN THE WORLD IS TO MAKE
OURSELVES A BEACON OF HOPE.
MAKE OURSELVES STRONGER AT HOME,
BUT ALSO OUR ROLE IN THE WORLD,
YES, IS ALSO TO CONFRONT EVIL
WHEN IT RISES.
WE TOOK OUT THE SAFE HAVEN IN
AFGHANISTAN, BUT NOW THERE IS,
UNDOUBTEDLY, A LARGER SAFE HAVEN
AND WE MUST RISE TO THIS
OCCASION IN COLLABORATION AND
WITH ALLIANCES TO CONFRONT IT
AND INVEST IN THE FUTURE MUCH
BETTER HUMAN INTELLIGENCE SO WE
KNOW WHAT THE NEXT STEPS ARE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU SAID YOU
WANT TO RID THE PLANET OF ISIS.
IN THE PREVIOUS DEBATE YOU SAID
THE GREATEST THREAT TO NATIONAL
SECURITY WAS CLIMATE CHANGE.
DO YOU STILL BELIEVE THAT?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
IN FACT, CLIMATE CHANGE IS
DIRECTLY RELATED TO THE GROWTH
OF TERRORISM.
AND IF WE DO NOT GET OUR ACT
TOGETHER AND LISTEN TO WHAT THE
SCIENTISTS SAY, YOU'RE GOING TO
SEE COUNTRIES ALL OVER THE
WORLD-- THIS I THIS IS WHAT THE.
SAYS-- THEY'RE GOING TO BE
STRUGGLING OVER LIMITED AMOUNTS
OF WATER, LIMITED AMOUNTS OF
LAND TO GROW THEIR CROPS ASK
YOU'RE GOING TO SEE ALL KINDS OF
INTERNATIONAL CONFLICT.
BUT, OF COURSE, INTERNATIONAL
TERRORISM IS A MAJOR ISSUE THAT
WE HAVE GOT TO ADDRESS TODAY.
AND I AGREE WITH MUCH OF WHAT
THE SECRETARY AND THE GOVERNOR
HAVE SAID.
BUT LET ME HAVE ONE AREA OF
DISAGREEMENT WITH THE SECRETARY.
I THINK SHE SAID SOMETHING LIKE
THE BULK OF THE RESPONSIBILITY
IS NOT OURS.
WELL, IN FACT, I WOULD ARGUE
THAT THE DISASTROUS INVASION OF
IRAQ, SOMETHING THAT I STRONGLY
OPPOSED, HAS UNRAVELED THE
REGION COMPLETELY AND LED TO THE
RISE OF AL QAEDA AND TO ISIS.
NOW, IN FACT, WHAT WE HAVE GOT
TO DO-- AND I THINK THERE IS
WIDESPREAD AGREEMENT HERE-- IS
THE UNITED STATES CANNOT DO IT
ALONE.
WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS LEAD AN
INTERNATIONAL COALITION WHICH
INCLUDESES VERY SIGNIFICANTLY
THE MUSLIM NATIONS IN THAT
REGION WHO ARE GOING TO HAVE TO
FIGHT AND DEFEND THEIR WAY OF
LIFE.
>> QUICKLY, JUST LET ME ASK YOU
A FOLLOW-UP ON THAT, SENATOR
SANDERS.
WHEN YOU SAY THE DISASTROUS VOTE
ON IRAQ, LET'S JUST BE CLEAR
ABOUT WHAT YOU'RE SAYING.
YOU'RE SAYING SECRETARY CLINTON,
WHO WAS THEN SENATOR CLINTON,
VOTED FOR THE IRAQ WAR.
ARE YOU MAKING A DIRECT LINK
BETWEEN THER VOTE FOR THAT WAR
AND WHAT'S HAPPENING NOW FOR
ISIS, JUST SO EVERYBODY--
>> I DON'T THINK ANY SENSIBLE
PERSON WOULD DISAGREE THAT THE
INVASION OF IRAQ LED TO THE
MASSIVE LEVEL OF INSTABILITY WE
ARE SEEING RIGHT NOW.
I THINK THAT WAS ONE OF THE
WORST FOREIGN POLICY BLUNDERS IN
THE MORE THAN HISTORY OF THE
UNITED STATES.
>> LET'S LET SECRETARY CLINTON
RESPOND TO THAT.
>> THANK YOU, JOHN.
WELL, I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT WE
PUT THIS IN HISTORIC CONTEXT.
THE UNITED STATES HAS,
UNFORTUNATELY, BEEN VICTIMIZED
BY TERRORISM GOING BACK DECADES.
IN THE 1980s, IT WAS IN
BEIRUT, LEBANON, UNDER PRESIDENT
REAGAN'S ADMINISTRATION, AND 258
AMERICANS, MARINES, EMBASSY
PERSONNEL, AND OTHERS WERE
MURDERED.
WE ALSO HAD ATTACKS ON TWO OF
OUR EMBASSIES IN TANZANIA AND
KENYA.
WHEN MY HUSBAND WAS PRESIDENT.
AGAIN, AMERICANS MURDERED.
AND THEN, OF COURSE, 9/11
HAPPENED, WHICH HAPPENED BEFORE
THERE WAS AN INVASION OF IRAQ.
I HAVE SAID THE INVASION OF IRAQ
WAS A MISTAKE.
BUT I THINK IF WE'RE EVER GOING
TO REALLY TACKLE THE PROBLEMS
POSED BY JIHADI EXTREME
TERRORISM, WE NEED TO UNDERSTAND
IT AND REALIZE THAT IT HAS
ANTECEDENTS TO WHAT HAPPENED IN
IRAQ AND WE HAVE TO CONTINUE TO
BE VIGILANT ABOUT IT.
>> SENATOR SANDERS LET ME FOLLOW
THIS LINE OF THINKING.
YOU CRITICIZED THEN-SENATOR
CLINTON'S VOTE.
DO YOU HAVE ANYTHING TO
CRITICIZE IN THE WAY SHE
PERFORMED AS SECRETARY OF STATE?
>> I THINK WE HAVE A
DISAGREEMENT, AND THE
DISAGREEMENT IS THAT NOT ONLY
DID I VOTE AGAINST THE WAR IN
IRAQ.
IF YOU LOOK AT HISTORY, JOHN,
YOU WILL FIND THAT REGIME CHAN
CHANGE, WHETHER IT WAS IN THE
EARLY 50s IN IRAN, WHETHER IT
WAS TOPPLING SALVADOR IN CHILE,
WHETHER IT WAS OVERTHROWING THE
GOVERNMENT OF GUATEMALA WAY BACK
WHEN, THESE INVASIONS, THESE
TOPPLING OF GOVERNMENTS, REGIME
CHANGES HAVE UNINTENDED
CONSEQUENCES.
I WOULD SAY THAT ON THIS ISSUE,
I'M A LITTLE BIT MORE
CONSERVATIVE THAN THE SECRETARY.
AND I AM NOT A GREAT FAN OF
REGIME CHANGE.
>> SENATOR--
>> JOHN, MAY I INTERJECT HERE?
SECRETARY CLINTON ALSO SAID WE--
IT WAS NOT JUST THE INVASION OF
IRAQ WHICH SECRETARY CLINTON
VOTED FOR AND HAS SINCE SAID WAS
A BIG MISTAKE-- AND, INDEED, IT
WAS.
BUT IT WAS ALSO THE CASCADING
EFFECTS THAT FOLLOWED THAT.
IT WAS ALSO THE DISBANDING OF
MANY ELEMENTS OF THE IRAQI ARMY
THAT ARE NOW SHOWING UP AS PART
OF ISIS.
IT WAS COUNTRY AFTER COUNTRY
WITHOUT MAKING THE INVESTMENT IN
HUMAN INTELLIGENCE TO UNDERSTAND
WHO THE NEW LEADERS WERE AND THE
NEW FORCES WERE THAT ARE COMING
UP.
WE NEED TO BE MUCH MORE FAR
THINKING IN THIS NEW 21st
CENTURY ERA OF NATION STATE
FAILURES AND CONFLICT.
IT'S NOT JUST ABOUT GETTING RID
OF A SINGLE DICTATOR.
IT IS ABOUT UNDERSTANDING THE
SECONDARY AND THIRD CONSEQUENCES
THAT FALL NEXT.
>> ALL RIGHT, SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> OF COURSE, EACH OF THESE
CASES NEEDS TO BE LOOKED AT
INDIVIDUALLY AND ANALYZED.
PART OF THE PROBLEM THAT WE HAVE
CURRENTLY IN THE MIDDLE EAST IS
THAT ASSAD HAS HUNG ON TO POWER
WITH THE VERY STRONG SUPPORT OF
RUSSIA AND IRAN AND WITH THE
PROXY OF HEZBOLLAH BEING THERE
BASICALLY FIGHTING HIS BATTLES.
SO I DON'T THINK YOU CAN PAINT
WITH A BROAD BRUSH.
THIS IS AN INCREDIBLY
COMPLICATED REGION OF THE WORLD.
IT'S BECOME MORE COMPLICATED.
AND MANY OF THE FIGHTS THAT ARE
GOING ON ARE NOT ONES THAT THE
UNITED STATES HAS EITHER STARTED
OR HAVE A ROLE IN.
THE SHI'A-SUNNI SPLIT.
THE DICTATOR STHAPS HAVE
SUPPRESSED PEOPLE'S ASPIRATIONS.
THE INCREASING GLOBALIZATION
WITHOUT ANY REAL SAFETY VALVE
FOR PEOPLE TO HAVE A BETTER
LIFE.
WE SAW THAT IN EGYPT.
WE SAW A DICTATOR OVERTHROWN.
WE SAW A MUSLIM BROTHERHOOD
PRESIDENT INSTALLED, AND THEN WE
SAW HIM OUSTED AND THE ARMY
BACK.
I THINK WE'VE GOT TO UNDERSTAND
THE COMPLEXITY OF THE WORLD THAT
WE ARE FACING AND NO PLACE IS
MORE SO THAN IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
>> I UNDERSTAND.
QUICKLY, SENATOR.
>> THE SECRETARY'S OBVIOUSLY
RIGHT.
IT IS ENORMOUSLY COMPLICATED.
BUT HERE'S SOMETHING THAT I
BELIEVE WE HAVE TO DO AS WE PUT
TOGETHER AN INTERNATIONAL
COALITION, AND THAT IS WE HAVE
TO UNDERSTAND THAT THE MUSLIM
NATIONS IN THE REGION-- SAUDI
ARABIA, IRAN, TURKEY, JORDAN--
ALL OF THESE NATIONS, THEY'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO GET THEIR HANDS
DIRTY, THEIR BOOTS ON THE
GROUND.
THEY ARE GOING TO HAVE TO TAKE
ON ISIS.
THIS IS A WAR FOR THE SOUL OF
ISLAM.
AND THOSE COUNTRIES WHO ARE
OPPOSED TO ISLAM, THEY ARE GOING
TO HAVE TO GET DEEPLY INVOLVED
IN A WAY THAT IS NOT THE CASE
TODAY.
WE SHOULD BE SUPPORTIVE OF THAT
EFFORT.
SO SHOULD THE U.K.
SHOW SHOULD FRANCE.
BUT THOSE MUSLIM COUNTRIES ARE
GOING TO HAVE TO LEAD THE
EFFORT.
THEY ARE NOT DOING IT NOW.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> I THINK THAT IS VERY UNFAIR
TO A FEW YOU MENTIONED, MOST
PARTICULARLY JORDAN, WHICH HAS
PUT A LOT ON THE LINE FOR THE
UNITED STATES, HAS ALSO TAKEN IN
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF
REFUGEES FROM SYRIA AND HAS BEEN
THEREFORE SUBJECTED TO THREATS
AND ATTACKS BY EXTREMISTS
THEMSELVES.
I DO AGREE THAT IN PARTICULAR,
TURKEY AND THE GULF ?RAGZ GOT TO
MAKE UP THEIR MINDS.
ARE THEY GOING TO STAND WITH US
AGAINST THIS KIND OF JIHADI
RADICALISM OR NOT?
AND THERE ARE MANY WAYS OF DOING
IT.
THEY CAN PROVIDE FORCES.
THEY CAN PROVIDE RESOURCES.
BUT THEY NEED TO BE ABSOLUTELY
CLEAR ABOUT WHERE THEY STAND.
>> LET ME ASK YOU, SECRETARY
CLINTON, A QUESTION ABOUT
LEADERSHIP.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT WHAT ROLE
DOES AMERICA TAKE.
LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT LIBYA.
SO LIBYA IS A COUNTRY IN WHICH
ISIS HAS TAKEN HOLD IN PART
BECAUSE OF THE CHAOS AFTER
MUAMMAR GADDAFI.
THAT WAS AN OPERATION YOU
CHAMPIONED.
PRESUME SAYS THIS IS THE LESSON
HE TOOK FROM THAT OPERATION.
IN AN INTERVIEW HE SAID THE
LESSON WAS, "DO WE HAVE AN
ANSWER FOR THE DAY AFTER?"
WASN'T THAT SUPPOSE TO BE ONE OF
THE LESSONS THAT WE LEARNED
AFTER THE IRAQ WAR?
AND HOW DID YOU GET IT WRONG
WITH LIBYA IF THE KEY LESSON OF
THE IRAQ WAR IS HAVE A PLAN FOR
AFTER?
>> WELL, WE DID HAVE A PLAN, AND
I THINK IT'S FAIR TO SAY THAT OF
ALL OF THE ARAB LEADERS, GADDAFI
PROBABLY HAD MORE BLOOD ON HIS
HANDS OF AMERICANS THAN ANYBODY
ELSE.
AND WHEN HE MOVED ON HIS OWN
PEOPLE, THREATENING A MASSACRE,
GENOCIDE, THE EUROPEANS AND THE
ARABS, OUR ALLIES AND PARTNERS,
DID ASK FOR AMERICAN HELP AND WE
PROVIDED IT.
WE DIDN'T PUT A SINGLE BOOT ON
THE GROUND, AND GADDAFI WAS
DEPOSED.
THE LIBYANS TURNED OUT FOR ONE
OF THE MOST SUCCESSFUL FAIREST
ELECTIONS THAT ANY ARAB COUNTRY
HAS HAD.
THEY ELECTED MODERATE LEADERS.
NOW THERE HAS BEEN A LOT OF
TURMOIL AND TROUBLE AS THEY HAVE
TRIED TO DEAL WITH THESE RADICAL
ELEMENTS WHICH YOU FIND IN THIS
ARC OF INSTABILITY FROM NORTH
AFRICA TO AFGHANISTAN.
AND IT IS IMPERATIVE THAT WE DO
MORE NOT ONLY TO HELP OUR
FRIENDS AND PARTNERS PROTECT
THEMSELVES AND PROTECT OUR OWN
HOMELAND, BUT ALSO TO WORK TO
TRY TO DEAL WITH THIS ARC OF
INSTABILITY, WHICH DOES HAVE A
LOT OF IMPACT ON WHAT HAPPENS IN
A COUNTRY LIKE LIBYA.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY I WANT TO
ASK YOU A QUESTION, AND YOU CAN
ADD WHATEVER YOU'D LIKE TO.
LET ME ASK YOU, IS THE WORLD TOO
DANGEROUS A PLACE FOR A GOVERNOR
WHO HAS NO FOREIGN POLICY
EXPERIENCE?
>> JOHN, THE WORLD IS A VERY
DANGEROUS PLACE BUT THE WORLD IS
NOT TOO DANGEROUS A PLACE FOR
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
PROVIDED WE ACT ACCORDING TO OUR
PRINCIPLES, PROIFDING WE ACT
INTELLIGENTLY.
LET'S TALK ABOUT THIS ARC OF
INSTABILITY THAT SECRETARY
CLINTON TALKED ABOUT.
LIBYA IS NOW A MESS.
SYRIA IS A MESS.
IRAQ IS A MESS.
AFGHANISTAN IS A MESS.
AS AMERICANS, WE HAVE SHOWN
OURSELVES TO HAVE THE GREATEST
MILITARY ON THE FACE OF THE
PLANET, BUT WE ARE NOT SO VERY
GOOD AT ANTICIPATING THREATS AND
APPRECIATING JUST HOW DIFFICULT
IT IS TO BUILD UP STABLE
DEMOCRACIES, TO MAKE THE
INVESTMENTS AND SUSTAINABLE
DEVELOPMENT THAT WE MUST AS A
NATION IF WE ARE TO ATTACK THE
ROOT CAUSES OF THESE SORTS OF
INSTABILITY.
AND I WANTED TO ADD ONE OTHER
THING, JOHN, AND I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT FOR ALL OF US ON THIS
STAGE.
I WAS IN BURLINGTON, IOWA, AND A
MOM OF A SERVICE MEMBER OF OURS
WHO SERVED TWO DUTIES IN IRAQ
SAID, "GOVERNOR O'MALLEY,
PLEASE, WHEN YOU'RE WITH YOUR
OTHER CANDIDATES AND COLLEAGUES
ON STAGE, PLEASE DON'T USE THE
TERM 'BOOTS ON THE GROUND'.
LET'S DON'T USE THE TERM 'BOOTS
ON THE GROUND'.
MY SON IS NOT A PAIR OF BOOTS ON
THE GROUND.
THESE ARE AMERICAN SOLDIERS AND
WE FAIL THEM WHEN WE FAIL TO
TAKE INTO ACCOUNT WHAT HAPPENS
THE DAY AFTER A DICTATOR FALLS
AND WHEN WE FAIL TO ACT WHEN A
WHOLE OF GOVERNMENT APPROACH
WITH SUSTAINABLE DEVELOPMENT,
DIPLOMACY, AND OUR ECONOMIC
POWER IN ALIGN AM WITH OUR
PRINCIPLES.
>> WELL, I THINK IT'S PERFECTLY
FAIR TO SAY THAT WE INVESTED
QUITE A BIT IN DEVELOPMENT, AID.
SOME OF THE BRAVEST PEOPLE THAT
I HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF WORKING
WITH AS SECRETARY OF STATE WERE
OUR DEVELOPMENT PROFESSIONALS
WHO WENT, SOMETIMES ALONE,
SOMETIMES WITH OUR MILITARY,
INTO VERY DANGEROUS PLACES IN
IRAQ, IN AFGHANISTAN, ELSEWHERE.
SO THERE DOES NEED TO BE A WHOLE
OF GOVERNMENT APPROACH, BUT JUST
BECAUSE WE'RE INVOLVED AND WE
HAVE A STRATEGY DOESN'T MEAN
WE'RE GOING TO BE ABLE TO
DICTATE THE OUTCOME.
THESE ARE OFTEN VERY LONG-TERM
KINDS OF INVESTMENTS THAT HAVE
TO BE MADE.
>> WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT THE
LONG-TERM CONSEQUENCES OF WAR,
LET'S TALK ABOUT THE MEN AND
WOMEN WHO CAME HOME FROM WAR,
THE 500,000 WHO CAME HOME WITH
P.T.S.D., AND TRAUMATIC BRAIN
INJURY.
AND I WOULD HOPE IN THE MIDST OF
ALL OF THIS DISCUSSION, THIS
COUNTRY MAKES CERTAIN THAT WE DO
NOT TURN OUR BACKS ON THE MEN
AND WOMEN WHO PUT THEIR LIVES ON
THE LINE TO DEFEND US AND THAT
WE STAND WITH THEM AS THEY HAVE
STOOD WITH US.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU
MENTIONED RADICAL JIHADISTS.
MARCO RUBIO, ALSO RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT, SAID THIS ATTACK
SHOWED IT'S ATTACK IN PARIS
SHOWED THAT WE ARE AT WAR WITH
RADICAL ISLAM.
DO YOU AGREE WITH THAT
CHARACTERIZATION "RADICAL
ISLAM?"
>> I DON'T THINK WE'RE AT WAR
WITH ISLAM.
I DON'T THINK WE'RE AT WAR WITH
ALL MUSLIMS.
I THINK WE'RE AT WAR WITH
JIHADISTS --
>> JUST TO INTERRUPT.
HE DIDN'T SAY ALL MUSLIMS.
HE SAID "RADICAL ISLAM."
>> I THINK YOU CAN TALK ABOUT
ISLAMISTS WHO CLEARLY ARE ALSO
JIHADISTS, BUT I THINK IT'S NOT
PARTICULARLY HELPFUL TO MAKE THE
CASE THAT SENATOR SANDERS WAS
JUST MAKING THAT I AGREE WITH
THAT WE'VE GOT TO REACH OUT TO
MUSLIM COUNTRIES.
WE'VE GOT TO HAVE THEM BE PART
OF OUR COALITION.
IF THEY HEAR PEOPLE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT WHO BASICALLY SHORTCUT
IT TO SAY WE ARE SOMEHOW AGAINST
ISLAM, THAT WAS ONE OF THE REAL
CONTRIBUTIONS, DESPITE ALL THE
OTHER PROBLEMS, THAT GEORGE W.
BUSH MADE AFTER 9/11 WHEN HE
BASICALLY SAID AFTER GOING TO A
MOSQUE IN WASHINGTON, WE ARE NOT
AT WAR WITH ISLAM OR MUSLIMS.
WE ARE AT WAR WITH VIOLENT
EXTREMISM.
WE ARE AT WAR WITH PEOPLE WHO
USE THEIR RELIGION FOR PURPOSES
OF POWER AND OPPRESSION.
AND, YES, WE ARE AT WAR WITH
THOSE PEOPLE.
BUT I DON'T WANT US TO BE
PAINTING WITH TOO BROAD A BRUSH.
>> THE REASON I ASK IS YOU GAVE
A SPEECH AT GEORGETOWN
UNIVERSITY IN WHICH YOU SAID IT
WAS IMPORTANT TO SHOW, "RESPECT,
EVEN FOR ONE'S ENEMIES.
TRYING TO UNDERSTAND AND IN SO
FAR AS PSYCHOLOGICALLY POSSIBLE
EMPATHIZE WITH THEIR PERSPECTIVE
AND POINT OF VIEW."
CAN YOU EXPLAIN WHAT YOU MEAN IN
THE CONTEXT OF THIS KIND OF
BARBARISM?
>> I THINK WITH THIS KIND OF
BARBARISM AND NIHILISM IT'S VERY
LARD TO UNDERSTAND, OTHER THAN
THE LUST FOR POWER, THE
REJECTION OF MODERNITY, THE
TOTAL DISREGARD OF HUMAN RIGHTS,
FREEDOM, OR ANY OTHER VALUE WE
KNOW AND RESPECT.
HISTORICALLY, IT IS IMPORTANT TO
TRY TO UNDERSTAND YOUR ADVERSARY
IN ORDER TO FIGURE OUT HOW THEY
ARE THINKING, WHAT THEY WILL BE
DOING, HOW THEY WILL REACT.
I PLEAD THAT IT'S VERY DIFFICULT
WHEN YOU DEAL WITH ISIS AND
ORGANIZATIONS LIKE THAT WHOSE
BEHAVIOR IS SO BARBARIC AND SO
VICIOUS THAT IT DOESN'T SEEM TO
HAVE ANY PURPOSE OTHER THAN LUST
FOR KILLING AND POWER AND THAT'S
VERY DIFFICULT TO PUT OURSELVES
IN THE OTHER SHOE.
>> JUST QUICKLY, DO EITHER OF
YOU, RADICAL ISLAM, DO EITHER OF
YOU USE THAT PHRASE.
>> I DON'T THINK THE TERM IS
WHAT'S IMPORTANT.
WHAT IS IMPORTANT TO UNDERSTAND
IS WE HAVE ORGANIZATIONS,
WHETHER IT IS ISIS OR AL QAEDA,
WHO DO BELIEVE WE SHOULD GO BACK
SEVERAL THOUSAND YEARS.
WE SHOULD MAKE WOMEN THIRD-CLASS
CITIZENS, THAT WE SHOULD ALLOW
CHILDREN TO BE SEXUALLY
ASSAULTED, THAT THEY ARE A
DANGER TO MODERN SOCIETY, AND
THAT THIS WORLD, WITH AMERICAN
LEADERSHIP, CAN AND MUST COME
TOGETHER TO DESTROY THEM.
WE CAN DO THAT.
AND IT REQUIRES AN ENTIRE WORLD
TO COME TOGETHER, INCLUDING IN A
VERY ACTIVE WAY THE MUSLIM
NATIONS.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOU HAVE
BEEN MAKING THE CASE WHEN YOU
TALK ABOUT LACK OF FORWARD
VISION, YOU'RE ESSENTIALLY
SAYING THAT SECRETARY CLINTON
LACKS THAT VISION AND THIS
CRITIQUE MATCHES UP WITH THIS
DISCUSSION OF LANGUAGE.
THE CRITIQUE IS THE SOFTNESS OF
LANGUAGE BETRAYS A SOFTNESS OF
APPROACH.
SO IF THIS LANGUAGE-- IF YOU
DON'T CALL IT BY WHAT IT IS, HOW
CAN YOUR APPROACH BE EFFECTIVE
TO THE CAUSE?
THAT'S THE CRITIQUE.
>> I BELIEVE CALLING IT WHAT IT
IS IS TO SAY RADICAL JIHADIS.
THAT'S CALLING IT WHAT IT IS.
JOHN, LET'S NOT FALL INTO THE
TRAP OF THINKING THAT ALL OF OUR
MUSLIM AMERICAN NEIGHBORS IN
THIS COUNTRY ARE SOMEHOW OUR
ENEMIES HERE.
THEY ARE OUR FIRST LINE OF
DEFENSE.
AND WE ARE GOING TO BE ABLE TO
DEFEAT ISIS ON THE GROUND THERE,
AS WELL AS IN THIS WORLD,
BECAUSE OF THE MUSLIM AMERICANS
IN OUR COUNTRY AND THROUGHOUT
THE WORLD WHO UNDERSTAND THAT
THIS BRUTAL AND BARBARIC GROUP
IS PERVERTING THE NAMEAVE GREAT
WORLD RELIGION.
AND NOW, LIKE NEVER BEFORE, WE
NEED OUR MUSLIM AMERICAN
NEIGHBORS TO STAND UP AND TO--
AND TO BE A PART OF THIS.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THE FRENCH
PRESIDENT HAS CALLED THIS ATTACK
AN ACT OF WAR.
>> YES.
>> A COUPLE OF DAYS AGO YOU WERE
ASKED IF YOU WOULD DECLARE WAR
ON ISIS AND YOU SAID NO.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY NOW?
>> WELL, WE HAVE AN
AUTHORIZATION TO USE MILITARY
FORCE AGAINST TERRORISTS.
WE PASSED IT AFTER 9/11.
>> AND YOU THINK THAT COVERS ALL
OF THIS?
>> IT CERTAINLY DOES COVER IT.
I WOULD LIKE TO SEE IT UPDATED.
>> IF YOU WERE IN THE SENATE,
WOULD YOU BE OKAY WITH THE
COMMANDER IN CHIEF DOING THAT
WITHOUT COMING BACK TO YOU?
>> NO, IT WOULD HAVE TO GO
THROUGH THE CONGRESS, AND I KNOW
THE WHITE HOUSE HAS ACTUALLY
BEEN WORKING WITH MEMBERS OF
CONGRESS, MAYBE NOW WE CAN GET
IT MOVING AGAIN SO THAT WE CAN
UPGRADE IT SO THAT IT DOES
INCLUDE ALL THE TOOLS AND
EVERYTHING IN OUR ARSENAL THAT
WE CAN USE TO TRY TO WORK WITH
OUR ALLIES AND OUR FRIENDS, COME
UP WITH BETTER INTELLIGENCE.
YOU KNOW, IT IS DIFFICULT
FINDING INTELLIGENCE THAT IS
ACTIONABLE IN A LOT OF THESE
PLACES BUT WE HAVE TO KEEP
TRYING.
AND WE HAVE TO DO MORE TO
PREVENT THE FLOOD OF FOREIGN
FIGHTERS THAT HAVE GONE TO
SYRIA,EP THE ONES WITH WESTERN
PASSPORTS, TO COME BACK.
SO THERE'S A LOT OF WORK WE NEED
TO DO AND I WANT TO BE SURE
WHAT'S CALLED THE A.U.M.F., HAS
THE AUTHORITY THAT IS NEEDED
GOING FORWARD.
>> SENATOR, LET ME JUST-- LET'S
ADD TO WHATEVER YOU'VE GOT TO
SAY, REFUGEES.
YOU'VE BEEN A LITTLE VAGUE ON
WHAT YOU WOULD DO ABOUT THE
SYRIAN REFUGEES.
WHAT'S YOUR VIEW.
>> LET ME PICK UP ON AN
IMPORTANT ISSUE WE HAVE NOT YET
DISCUSSED.
THIS NATION IS THE MOST POWERFUL
MILITARY IN THE WORLD.
WE'RE SPENDING OVER $600 BILLION
ON THE MILITARY AND LESS THAN
10% OF THAT MONEY SUESED TO BE
FIGHTING INTERNATIONAL
TERRORISM.
WE ARE SPENDING HUNDREDS OF
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS MAINTAINING
5,000 NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
I THINK WE NEED MAJOR REFORM IN
THE MILITARY, MAKING IT MORE
COST EFFECTIVE, BUT ALSO
FOCUSING ON THE REAL CRISIS THAT
FACES US.
THE COLD WAR IS OVER.
AND OUR FOCUS HAS GOT TO BE ON
INTELLIGENCE, INCREASED
MANPOWER, FIGHTING
INTERNATIONALLY.
IN TERMS OF REFUGEES, I BELIEVE
THE UNITED STATES HAS THE MORAL
RESPONSIBILITY WITH EUROPE, WITH
GULF COUNTRIES LIKE SAUDI
ARABIA, TO MAKE SURE THAT WHEN
PEOPLE LEAVE COUNTRIES LIKE
AFGHANISTAN AND SYRIA WITH
NOTHING MORE THAN THE CLOTHING
ON THEIR BACK THAT, OF COURSE,
WE REACH OUT.
NOW, WHAT THE MAGIC NUMBER SI
DON'T KNOW BECAUSE WE DON'T KNOW
THE EXTENT OF THE PROBLEM.
BUT I CERTAINLY THINK THAT THE
UNITED STATES SHOULD TAKE ITS
FULL RESPONSIBILITY IN HELPING
THOSE PEOPLE.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOU HAVE A
MAGIC NUMBER.
I BELIEVE IT'S 65,000.
DOES THAT NUMBER GO UP OR DOWN
BASED ON WHAT HAPPENED
YESTERDAY?
>> JOHN, I WAS THE FIRST PERSON
ON THIS STAGE TO SAY THAT WE
SHOULD ACCEPT THE 65,000 SYRIAN
REFUGEES THAT WERE FLEEING THE
SORT OF MURDER OF ISIL, AND I
BELIEVE THAT THAT NEEDS TO BE
DONE WITH PROPER SCREENING.
BUT ACCOMMODATING 65,000
REFUGEES IN OUR COUNTRY TODAY,
PEOPLE OF 320 MILLION, IS AKIN
TO MAKE ROOM FOR 6.5 MORE PEOPLE
IN A BASEBALL STADIUM WITH
32,000.
THERE ARE OTHER WAYS TO LEAD AND
TO BE A MORAL LEADER IN THIS
WORLD, RATHER THAN AT THE
OPPOSITE END OF A DRONE STRIKE.
BUT I WOULD WANT TO AGREE WITH
SOMETHING THAT SENATOR SANDERS
SAYS.
THE NATURE OF WARFARE HAS
CHANGED.
THIS IS NOT A CONFLICT WHERE WE
SEND IN THE THIRD DIVISION OF
MARINES.
THIS IS A NEW ERRAV CONFLICT
WHERE TRADITIONAL WAYS OF HUGE
STANDING ARMIES ARE NOT-- SERVE
OUR PURPOSES AS WELL AS SPECIAL
OPS, BETTER INTELLIGENCE AND
BEING MORE PROACTIVE.
>> 65,000, THE NUMBER STAYS?
>> THAT'S WHAT I UNDERSTAND IS
THE REQUEST FROM THE
INTERNATIONAL--
>> BUT FOR YOU, WHAT WOULD YOU
WANT?
>> I WOULD WANT US TO TAKE OUR
PLACE AMONG THE NATIONS OF THE
WORLD TO ALLEVIATE THIS SORT OF
DEATH AND THE SPECTER WE SAW OF
LITTLE KIDS' BODIES WASHING UP
ON A BEACH.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON LET ME ASK
YOU A QUESTION FROM TWITTER
WHICH HAS COME IN AND THIS IS A
QUESTION ON THIS ISSUE OF
REFUGEES.
THE QUESTION IS, WITH THE U.S.
PREPARING TO ABSORB SYRIAN
REFUGEES, HOW DO YOU PROPOSE WE
SCREEN THOSE COMING IN TO KEEP
CITIZENS SAFE?
>> I THINK THAT IS THE NUMBER
ONE REQUIREMENT.
I ALSO SAID THAT WE SHOULD TAKE
INCREASE NUMBERS OF REFUGEES.
THE ADMINISTRATION ORIGINALLY
SAID 10.
I SAID WE SHOULD GO TO 65, BUT
ONLY IF WE HAVE AS CAREFUL A
SCREENING AND VETTING PROCESS AS
WE CAN IMAGINE, WHENEVER
RESOURCES IT TAKES.
I DO NOT WANT US TO IN ANY WAY
INADVERTENTLY ALLOW PEOPLE WHO
WISH US HARM TO COME INTO OUR
COUNTRY.
BUT I WANT TO SAY A QUICK WORD
ABOUT WHAT SENATOR SANDERS AND
THEN GOVERNOR O'MALLEY SAID.
WE DO HAVE TO TAKE A HARD LOOK
AT THE DEFENSE BUDGET, AND WE DO
HAVE TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE GET
READY TO FIGHT THE ADVERSARIES
OF THE FUTURE, NOT THE PAST.
BUT WE HAVE TO ALSO BE VERY
CLEAR THAT WE DO HAVE CONTINUING
CHALLENGES.
WE'VE GOT CHALLENGES IN THE
SOUTH CHINA SEA BECAUSE OF WHAT
CHINA IS DOING IN BUILDING UP
THESE MILITARY INSTALLATIONS.
WE HAVE PROBLEMS WITH RUSSIA.
JUST THE OTHER DAY, RUSSIA
ALLOWED A TELEVISION CAMERA TO
SEE THE PLANS FOR A DRONE
SUBMARINE THAT COULD CARRY A
TACTICAL NUCLEAR WEAPON.
SO WE'VE GOT TO LOOK AT THE FULL
RANGE AND THEN COME TO SOME
SMART DECISIONS ABOUT HAVING A
MORE STREAMLINED AND FOCUSED
APPROACH.
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO TAKE A
BREAK NOW.
WE WILL HAVE MORE OF THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE HERE FROM
DRAKE UNIVERSITY IN DES MOINES,
IOWA.
( APPLAUSE )
TERRORISM TO ANOTHER IMPORTANT
ISSUE FOR MANY AMERICANS, THE
FINANCIAL SQUEEZE ON THE THE
MIDDLE CLASS.
FOR THAT, WE GO TO MY CBS NEWS
COLLEAGUE NANCY CORDES.
NANCY.
>> JOHN, THANKS SO MUCH.
WE'VE LEARNED A LOT DURING THE
COURSE OF THIS CAMPAIGN ABOUT
THE THINGS THAT YOU'D LIKE TO DO
THAT YOU SAY WILL HELP THE
MIDDLE CLASS BUT WE HAVEN'T
HEARD QUITE AS MUCH ABOUT WHO
WOULD PICK UP THE TAB.
SECRETARY CLINTON, FIRST TO YOU.
YOU WANT TO CAP INDIVIDUALS'
PRESCRIPTION DRUG COSTS AT $250
A MONTH.
YOU WANT TO MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGE
DEBT-FREE.
YOU WANT COMMUNITY COLLEGE TO BE
FREE ALTOGETHER.
AND YOU WANT MANDATORY PAID
FAMILY LEAVE.
SO WHO PAYS FOR ALL THAT?
IS IT EMPLOYERS?
IS IT THE TAXPAYERS?
AND WHICH TAXPAYERS?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, IT ISN'T
THE MIDDLE CLASS.
I HAVE MADE VERY CLEAR THAT
HARDWORKING, MIDDLE-CLASS
FAMILIES NEED A RAISE, NOT A TAX
INCREASE.
IN FACT, WAGES ADJUSTED FOR
INFLATION HAVEN'T RISEN SINCE
THE TURN OF THE LAST CENTURY,
AFTER MY HUSBAND'S
ADMINISTRATION.
SO WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO
TO GET JOBS GOING AGAIN, GET
INCOMES RISING AGAIN.
AND I HAVE LAID OUT SPECIFIC
PLANS-- YOU CAN GO TO MY WEB
SITE HILLARYCLINTON.COM, AND
READ THE DETAILS.
AND I WILL PAY FOR IT BY, YES,
TAXING THE WEALTHY MORE.
CLOSING CORPORATE LOOPHOLES.
DEDUCTIONS, AND OTHER KINDS OF
FAVORABLE TREATMENT.
AND I CAN DO IT WITHOUT RAISING
THE DEBT, WITHOUT RAISING TAXES
ON THE MIDDLE CLASS, AND MAKING
IT REASONABLY MESSENGERRABLE
WITHIN OUR BUDGET SO THAT WE CAN
BE FISCALLY RESPONSIBLE AT THE
SAME TIME.
>> A QUICK FOLLOW-UP ON THE
$250-A-MONTH CAP.
WOULDN'T THE PHARMACEUTICAL
COMPANIES AND THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES JUST PASS THAT COST ON
TO THE CONSUMERS IN THE FORM OF
HIGHER PREMIUMS?
>> WELL, WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
REDO THE WAY THE PRESCRIPTION
DRUG INDUSTRY DOES BUSINESS.
FOR EXAMPLE, IT IS OUTRAGEOUS
THAT WE DON'T HAVE AN
OPPORTUNITY FOR MEDICARE TO
NEGOTIATE FOR LOWER PRICES.
IN FACT, AMERICAN CONSUMERS PAY
THE HIGHEST PRICES IN THE WORLD
FOR DRUGS THAT WE HELP TO BE
DEVELOP THROUGH THE NATIONAL
INSTITUTES OF HEALTH AND THAT WE
THEN TESTED THROUGH THE F.D.A.
THERE'S MORE TO MY PLAN THAN
JUST THE CAP.
WE HAVE TO GO AFTER PRICE
GOUGING AND MONOPOLISTIC
PRACTICES AND GIVE MEDICARE THE
AUTHORITY TO NO,.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOU ALSO
WANT TO MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGE
DEBT-FREE.
I WANT STATES TO FREEZE TUITION.
YOU HAVE YOUR OWN FAMILY LEAVE
PLAN.
HOW WOULD YOU PAY FOR IT?
IN MARYLAND YOU RAISED THE SALES
TAX, YOU RAISED THE GAS TAX, AND
RAISED TAXES ON FAMILIES MAKING
OVER $250,000 A YEAR.
IS THAT THE BLUEPRINT?
THE BLUEPRINT IN MARYLAND THAT
WE FOLLOWED IS WE RAISED THE
SALES TAX BY A PENNY AND MADE
OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS THE BEST
PUBLIC SCHOOLS IN AMERICA FOR
FIVE YEARS IN A ROW WITH THAT
INVESTMENT.
AND YES, WE DID ASK EVERYONE--
THE TOP 14% OF EARNERS IN OUR
STATE TO PAY MORE IN THEIR
INCOME TAX AND WE WERE THE ONLY
STATE TO GO FOUR YEARS IN A ROW
WITHOUT A PENNY'S INCREASE TO
COLLEGE TUITIONS.
SO WHILE OTHER CANDIDATES WILL
TALK ABOUT THE THINGS THEY WOULD
LIKE TO DO.
I ACTUALLY GOT THESE THINGS DONE
IN A STATE THAT DEFENDED NOT
ONLY A AAA BOND RATING BUT THE
HIGHEST MEDIAN INCOME IN
AMERICA.
I BELIEVE WE PAY FOR MANY OF THE
THINGS WE NEED TO DO AGAIN AS A
NATION-- INVESTING IN THE SKILLS
OF OUR PEOPLE, OUR
INFRASTRUCTURE, AND RESEARCH AND
DEVELOPMENT, AND ALSO CLIMATE
CHANGE BY THE ELIMINATION OF ONE
BIG ENTITLEMENT THAT WE CAN NO
LONGER AFFORD AS A PEOPLE, AND
THAT IS THE ENTITLEMENT THAT
MANY OF OUR SUPER WEALTHIEST
CITIZENS FEEL THEY ARE ENTITLED
TO PAY-- NAMELY, A MUCH LOWER
INCOME TAX RATE AND A LOWER TAX
RATE ON CAPITAL GAINS.
I BELIEVE CAPITAL GAINS, FOR THE
MOST PART, SHOULD BE TAXED THE
SAME WAY WE TAX INCOME FROM HARD
WORK, SWEAT, AND TOIL.
AND IF WE DO THOSE THINGS WE CAN
BE A COUNTRY THAT ACTUALLY CAN
AFFORD DEBT-FREE COLLEGE AGAIN.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU WANT TO
MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGE FREE
ALTOGETHER.
YOU WANT TO INCREASE SOCIAL
SECURITY BENEFITS AND YOU WANT
TO SPEND $1 TRILLION ON
INFRASTRUCTURE.
YOU SAID TO DO SOME OF THESE
THINGS YOU'LL IMPOSE A TAX ON
TOP EARNERS.
HOW HIGH WOULD THEIR RATE GO IN
A SANDERS ADMINISTRATION?
>> LET ME PUT THOSE PROPOSALS--
AND YOU'RE ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
THAT IS WHAT I WANT TO DO.
THAT IS WHAT IS GOING TO HAVE TO
HAPPEN IF WE WANT TO REVITALIZE
AND REBUILD THE CRUMBLING MIDDLE
CLASS.
IN THE LAST 30 YEARS, THERE HAS
BEEN A MASSIVE REDISTRIBUTION OF
WEALTH.
AND I KNOW THAT TERM GETS MY
REPUBLICAN FRIENDS NERVOUS.
THE PROBLEM IS, THIS
REDISTRIBUTION HAS GONE IN THE
WRONG DIRECTION.
TRILLIONS OF DOLLARS HAVE GONE
FROM THE MIDDLE CLASS AND
WORKING FAMILY TO THE TOP
ONE-TENTH OF 1% WHO HAVE DOUBLED
THE PERCENTAGE OF WEALTHY.
YES, I DO BELIEVE WE MUST END
CORPORATE LOOPHOLES SUCH THAT
MAJOR CORPORATIONS YEAR AFTER
YEAR PAY VIRTUALLY ZERO IN
FEDERAL INCOME TAX BECAUSE
THEY'RE STASHING THE MONEY IN
THE CAYMEN ISLANDS.
YES, I DO BELIEVE THERE MUST BE
A TAX ON WALL STREET
SPECULATION.
WE BAILED OUT WALL STREET.
IT'S THEIR TIME TO BAIL OUT THE
MIDDLE CLASS.
HELP OUR KIDS BE ABLE TO GO TO
COLLEGE TUITION FREE.
SO WE PAY FOR THIS BY DO
DEMANDING THAT THE WEALTHIEST
PEOPLE AND THE LARGEST
CORPORATIONS WHO HAVE GOTTEN
AWAY WITH MURDER FOR YEARS NOW
PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE.
>> LET'S GET SPECIFIC.
HOW HIGH WOULD YOU GO INSPECT?
YOU SAID BEFORE ABOVE 50%.
>> WE HAVEN'T COME UP WITH AN
EXACT NUMBER YET BUT IT WILL NOT
BE AS HIGH AS THE NUMBER UNDER
DWIGHT D. EISENHOWER.
WHICH WAS 90%.
I'M NOT THAT MUCHAVE SOCIALIST
COMPARED TO EISENHOWER.
( LAUGHTER )
( APPLAUSE )
BUT, BUT, WE ARE GOING TO END
THE ABSURDITY AS WARREN BUFFET
OFTEN REMINDS US THAT
BILLIONAIRES PAY AN EFFECTIVE
TAX RATE LOWER THAN NURSES OR
TRUCK DRIVERS.
THAT MAKES NO SENSE AT ALL.
THERE HAS TO BE REAL TAX REFORM
AND THE WEALTHIEST AND LARGE
CORPORATIONS WILL PAY WHEN I'M
PRESIDENT.
>> MAY I POINT OUT UNDER RONALD
REAGAN'S FIRST TERM THE HIGHEST
MARGINAL RATE WAS 70%.
IN TALKING TO A LOT OF OUR
NEIGHBORS WHO ARE IN THE SUPER
WEALTHY MILLIONAIRE AND
BILLIONAIRE CATEGORIES, A GREAT
NUMBER OF THEM LOVE THEIR
COUNTRY ENOUGH TO DO MORE AGAIN
IN ORDER TO CREATE MORE
OPPORTUNITY FOR AMERICA'S MIDDLE
CLASS.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, AMERICANS
SAY HEALTH CARE COSTS AND WAGES
ARE THEIR TOP FINANCIAL
CONCERNS.
AND HEALTH CARE DEDUCTIBLES
ALONE HAVE RISEN 67% OVER THE
PAST FIVE YEARS.
IS THIS SOMETHING THAT OBAMACARE
WAS DESIGNED TO ADDRESS?
AND IF NOT, WHY NOT?
>> WELL, LOOK, I BELIEVE THAT
WE'VE MADE GREAT PROGRESS AS A
COUNTRY WITH THE AFFORDABLE CARE
ACT.
WE'VE BEEN STRUGGLING TO GET
THIS DONE SINCE HARRY TRUMAN.
AND IT WAS NOT ONLY A GREAT
ACCOMPLISHMENT OF THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY, BUT OF PRESIDENT OBAMA.
I DO THINK THAT IT'S IMPORTANT
TO DEFEND IT.
THE REPUBLICANS HAVE VOTED TO
REPEAL IT NEAR 60 TIMES.
THEY WOULD LIKE TO RIP IT UP AND
START ALL OVER AGAIN, THROW OUR
NATION BACK INTO THIS REALLY
CONTENTIOUS DEBATE THAT WE'VE
HAD ABOUT HEALTH CARE FOR QUITE
SOME TIME NOW.
I WANT TO BUILD ON AND IMPROVE
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
I WOULD CERTAINLY TACKLE THE
COST ISSUES BECAUSE I THINK THAT
ONCE THE FOUNDATION WAS LAID
WITH A SYSTEM TO TRY TO GET AS
MANY PEOPLE AS POSSIBLE INTO IT,
TO END INSURANCE DISCRIMINATION
AGAINST PEOPLE WITH PREEXISTING
CONDITIONS OR WOMEN, FOR
EXAMPLE, THAT, YES, WE ARE GOING
TO HAVE TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO GET
MORE COMPETITION IN THE
INSURANCE MARKET, HOW TO GET THE
COSTS OF PARTICULARLY
PRESCRIPTION DRUGS BUT OTHER
OUT-OF-POCKET EXPENSES DOWN.
BUT I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO
UNDERSTAND THERE'S A SIGNIFICANT
DIFFERENCE THAT I HAVE WITH
SENATOR SANDERS ABOUT HOW BEST
TO PROVIDE QUALITY, AFFORDABLE
HEALTH CARE FOR EVERYONE.
AND IT'S-- IT'S A WORTHY DEBATE.
IT'S AN IMPORTANT ONE THAT WE
SHOULD BE ENGAGED IN.
>> IT IS A WORTHY DEBATE.
SENATOR SANDERS AIR, QUICK
RESPONSE, AND THEN WE'LL GET
INTO HEALTH CARE AGAIN LATER.
>> I AM ON THE COMMITTEE THAT
HELPED WRITE THE AFFORDABLE CARE
ACT.
WE HAVE MADE SOME GOOD PROGRESS.
NOW WHAT WE HAVE TO TAKE ON IS
THE PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY THAT
IS RIPPING OFF THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE EVERY SINGLE DAY.
I AM PROUD THAT I WAS THE FIRST
MEMBER OF CONGRESS TO TAKE
AMERICANS OVER THE CANADIAN
BORDER TO BUY BREAST CANCER
DRUGS FOR 1-TENTH THE PRICE THEY
WERE PAYING IN THE UNITED
STATES.
BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY, NO
DOUBT, THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT
IS A STEP FORWARD.
I THINK WE ALL SUPPORT IT.
I BELIEVE WE'VE GOT TO GO
FURTHER.
I WANT TO END THE INTERNATIONAL
EMBARRASSMENT OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA BEING THE ONLY
MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH THAT
DOESN'T GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO
ALL PEOPLE AS A RIGHT NOT A
PRIVILEGE.
( APPLAUSE )
( CHEERS )
AND, ALSO, ALSO, WHAT WE SHOULD
BE CLEAR ABOUT IS WE END UP
SPEND AGO AND I THINK THE
SECRETARY KNOWS THIS-- FAR MORE
PER CAPITA ON HEALTH CARE THAN
ANY OTHER MAJOR COUNTRY, AND OUR
OUTCOMES, HEALTH CARE
OUTCRIMINALS NOT NECESSARILY
THAT GOOD.
>> NANCY, I REALLY WISH YOU'D
COME BACK TO ME ON THIS--
>> I APOLOGIZE.
>> WE HAVE FOUND A WAY TO REDUCE
HOSPITAL COSTS.
>> GOVERNOR, YOU'RE BREAKING THE
RULES.
( LAUGHTER )
I'M SORRY, WE'RE GOING TO HAVE
TO CUT FOR A COMMERCIAL.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK HERE FROM
DRAKE UNIVERSITY HERE IN DES
MOINES, IOWA.
>> IT CANNOT BE AN AMERICAN
FIGHT.
WE WILL SUPPORT THOSE WHO TAKE
THE FIGHT TO ISIS.
>> THIS ACTUALLY IS AMERICA'S
FIGHT.
IT CANNOT SOLELY BE AMERICA'S
>> THERE'S A LOT OF PRESIDENTIAL
HISTORY HERE IN IOWA.
HOLDS THE NIRS-IN-THE-NATION
CAUCUSES.
TONIGHT WE ARE IN POLK COUNTY,
NAMED FOR OUR 11th PRESIDENT
WITH THREE PEOPLE WHO HOPE TO BE
NUMBER 45.
JOINING ME TO QUESTION THEM ARE
KEVIN COONEY OF KCCI, AND KATHIE
OBRADOVICH OF THE "DES MOINES
REGISTER."
KEVIN.
>> THANKS, JOHN.
CANDIDATES, WE'VE ALREADY HEARD
YOUR ANSWERS ON WHAT YOU WOULD
DO WITH SYRIAN REFUGEES, BUT A
CRUCIAL PART OF THE IMMIGRATION
DEBATE HERE AT HOME IS CONTROL
OF OUR OWN BORDERS.
REPUBLICANS SAY THE BORDERS,
SECURING BORDERS IS A TOP
PRIORITY.
DEMOCRATS SAY THEY WANT TO PLAN
FOR COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
SO GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, ARE YOU
WILLING TO COMPROMISE ON THIS
PARTICULAR ISSUE TO FOCUS ON
BORDER SECURITY FIRST IN FAVOR
OF KEEPING THE COUNTRY SAFE?
>> WELL, MR. COONEY, WE'VE
ACTUALLY BEEN FOCUSING ON BORDER
SECURITY TO THE EXCLUSION OF
TALKING ABOUT COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
IN FACT, IF MORE BORDER SECURITY
AND THESE-- AND MORE AND MORE
DEPORTATIONS WERE GOING TO BRING
OUR REPUBLICAN BROTHERS AND
SISTERS TO THE TABLE, IT WOULD
HAVE HAPPENED LONG AGO.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS-- AND
LET'S SAY IT IN OUR DEBATE
BECAUSE YOU'LL NEVER HEAR THIS
FROM THAT IMMIGRATION-BASHING
CARNIVAL BARKER DONALD TRUMP,
THE TRUTH.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS NET
IMMIGRATION FROM MEXICO LAST
YEAR WAS ZERO.
FACT CHECK ME.
GO AHEAD.
CHECK IT OUT.
BUT THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS,
IF WE WANT WAGES TO GOUM, WE'VE
GOT TO GET 11 MILLION OF OUR
NEIGHBORS OFF THE SHADOW ECONOMY
AND INTO THE FULL LIGHT OF AN
AMERICAN ECONOMY.
THAT'S WHAT OUR PARENTS AND
GRANDPARENTS ALWAYS DID.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO AS A
NATION.
YES, WE MUST PROTECT OUR
BORDERS.
BUT THERE IS NO SUBSTITUTE FOR
HAVING COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM WITH A PATHWAY TO
CITIZENSHIP FOR 11 MILLION
PEOPLE, MANY OF WHOM HAVE KNOWN
NO OTHER COUNTRY BUT THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
OUR SILL BOL IS THE STATUE OF
LIBERTY.
IT IS NOT A BARBED WIRE FENCE.
( APPLAUSE ).
>> THANK YOU.
NOW, SECRETARY CLINTON YOU HAVE
SAID YOU WOULD GO FURTHER THAN
THE PRESIDENT WHEN IT COMES TO
TAKING EXECUTIVE ACTION HAD IT
COMES TO IMPLEMENTING
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
BUT THE PRESIDENT IS ALREADY
FACING LEGAL TROUBLE ON THIS.
HOW WOULD YOU GO FURTHER WITH
EXECUTIVE ACTION?
>> FIRST, I KNOW THE PRESIDENT
HAS APPEALED THE DECISION TO THE
SUPREME COURT.
AND MY READING OF THE LAW AND
THE CONSTITUTION CONVINCES ME
THAT THE PRESIDENT HAS THE
AUTHORITY THAT HE IS ATTEMPTING
TO EXERCISE WITH RESPECT TO
DREAMERS AND THEIR PARENTS
BECAUSE I THINK ALL OF US ON
THIS STAGE AGREE THAT WE NEED
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION REFORM
WITH A PATH TO CITIZENSHIP.
BORDER SECURITY HAS ALWAYS BEEN
A PART OF THAT DEBATE.
AND IT IS A FACT THAT THE NET
IMMIGRATION FROM MEXICO AND
SOUTH HAS BASICALLY ZEROED OUT.
SO WHAT WE WANT TO DO IS TO SAY,
LOOK, WE HAVE 11 MILLION PEOPLE
WHO HAVE BEEN HERE, MANY OF THEM
FOR DECADES.
THEY HAVE CHILDREN WHO ARE DOING
SO WELL, I'VE MET AND WORKED
WITH DREAMERS.
I THINK ANY PARENT WOULD BE SO
PROUD OF THEM.
SO LET'S MOVE TOWARD WHAT WE
SHOULD BE DOING AS A NATION AND
FOLLOW THE VALUES OF OUR
IMMIGRATION HISTORY AND BEGIN TO
MAKE IT POSSIBLE FOR THEM TO
COME OUT OF THE SHADOWS AND TO
HAVE A FUTURE THAT GIVES THEM A
FULL CHANCE OF CITIZENSHIP.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
>> KATHIE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU'VE
ACTUALLY TALKED ABOUT
IMMIGRATION AS BEING A WAGE
ISSUE IN THE UNITED STATES.
AND I WANT TO ACTUALLY GO
DIRECTLY TO THE WAGE ISSUE NOW.
YOU HAVE CALLED FOR RAISING THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO $15 AN HOUR
EVERYWHERE IN THE COUNTRY.
BUT THE PRESIDENT'S FORMER CHAIR
OF THE COUNCIL OF ECONOMIC
ADVISERS ALAN KRUEGER, HAS SAID
A NATIONAL INCREASE OF $15 COULD
LEAD TO UNDESIRABLE AND
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES OF JOB
LOSS.
WHAT LEVEL OF JOB LOSS WOULD YOU
CONSIDER UNACCEPTABLE?
>> KATHIE, LET ME SAY THIS.
YOU KNOW, NO PUBLIC POLICY
DOESN'T HAPPEN, IN SOME CASES
NEGATIVE CONSEQUENCES.
BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY, WHAT
YOU HAVE RIGHT NOW ARE MILLIONS
OF AMERICANS WORKING TWO OR
THREE JOBS BECAUSE THEIR WAGES
THAT THEY ARE EARNING ARE JUST
TOO LOW.
REAL INFLATION ACCOUNTED FOR
WAGES HAS DECLINED PRECIPITOUSLY
OVER THE YEARS.
I BELIEVE IN FACT THIS COUNTRY
NEEDS TO MOVE TOWARDS A LIVING
WAGE.
IT IS NOT A RADICAL IDEA TO SAY
THAT IF SOMEBODY WORKS 40 HOURS
A WEEK, THAT PERSON SHOULD NOT
BE LIVING IN POVERTY.
IT IS NOT A RADICAL IDEA TO SAY
THAT A SINGLE MOM SHOULD BE
EARNING ENOUGH MONEY TO TAKE
CARE OF HER KIDS.
SO I BELIEVE THAT OVER THE NEXT
FEW YEARS, NOT TOMORROW, BUT
OVER THE NEXT FEW YEARS WE HAVE
GOT TO MOVE THE MINIMUM WAGE TO
A LIVING WAGE, 15 BUCKS AN HOUR.
AND I APOLOGIZE TO NOBODY FOR
THAT.
( APPLAUSE ).
>> YOU SAID THERE ARE
CONSEQUENCES-- YOU SAID THERE
ARE CONSEQUENCES FOR ANY POLICY.
DO YOU THINK JOB LOSSES ARE A
CONSEQUENCE THAT IS ACCEPTABLE?
>> THIS IS WHAT MANY ECONOMISTS
BELIEVE THAT ONE OF THE REASONS
THAT REAL UNEMPLOYMENT IN THIS
COUNTRY IS 10%, ONE OF THE
REASONS THAT AFRICAN AMERICAN
YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT AND
UNDEREMPLOYMENT IS 51% IS THE
AVERAGE WORKENER AMERICA DOESN'T
HAVE ANY DISPOSABLE INCOME.
YOU HAVE NO DISPOSABLE INCOME
WHEN YOU ARE MAKE 10, 12 BUCKS
AN HOUR.
WHEN WE PUT MONEY INTO THE HANDS
OF WORKING PEOPLE, THEY'RE GOING
TO GO OUT AND BUY GOODS, THEY'RE
GOING TO BUY SERVICES AND
THEY'RE GOING TO CREATE JOBS IN
DOING THAT.
THAT IS THE KIND OF ECONOMY I
BELIEVE, PUT MONEY IN THE HANDS
OF WORKING PEOPLE, RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO 15 BUCKANS HOUR.
>> KATHIE, THIS WAS NOT MERELY
THEORY IN MARYLAND.
WE ACTUALLY DID IT.
NOT ONLY WERE WE THE FIRST STATE
IN THE NATION TO PASS A LIVING
WAGE.
WE WERE THE FIRST TO PASS A
MINIMUM WAGE.
AND THE U.S. CHAMBER OF
COMMERCE, WHICH HARDLY EVER SAYS
NICE THINGS ABOUT DEMOCRATIC
GOVERNORS ANYWHERE, NAMED OUR
STATE NUMBER ONE FOR INNOVATION
AND ENTREPRENEURSHIP.
WE DEFENDED THE HIGHEST MEDIAN
INCOME IN THE COUNTRY.
AND SO, LOOK, THE WAY THAT-- A
STRONGER MIDDLE CLASS IS
ACTUALLY THE SOURCE OF ECONOMIC
GROWTH.
AND IF OUR MIDDLE CLASS MAKES
MORE MONEY, THEY SPEND MORE
MONEY, AND OUR WHOLE ECONOMY
GROWS UPON.
WE DID IT AND IT WORKED AND
NOBODY HEADED FOR THE HILLS OR
LEFT THE STATE BECAUSE OF IT.
>> YOU'RE CALLING FOR A $15 AN
HOUR WAGE NOW BUT WHY DID YOU
STOP AT 10.10.
>> 10.10 WAS ALL I COULD GET THE
STATE TO DO BUT TWO OF OUR
COUNTRIES 2112.EIGHTY AND THEIR
COUNTY EXECUTIVES IF THEY WERE
HERE TONIGHT WOULD ALSO TELL YOU
THAT IT WORKS.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, THE
MORE OUR PEOPLE EARN, THE MORE
MONEY THEY SPEND AND THE MORE
OUR WHOLE ECONOMY GROWS.
THAT'S AMERICAN CAPITALISM.
>> LET ME JUST--
>> KATHIE, THE--
>> LET ME JUST ADD TO THAT.
THIS IS NOT AN ESOTERIC
ARGUMENT.
YOU'RE SEEING CITIES LIKE
SEATTLE.
YOU'RE SEEING STAYS LIKE SAN
FRANCISCO, CITIES LIKE LOS
ANGELES DOING IT, AND THEY ARE
DOING IT WELL AND WORKERS ARE
ABLE TO HAVE MORE DISPOSABLE
INCOME.
>> BUT I DO TAKE WHAT ALAN
KRUEGER SAID SERIOUSLY.
HE IS THE FOREMOST EXPERT IN OUR
COUNTRY ON THE MINIMUM WAGE AND
WHAT ITS EFFECTS ARE.
AND THE OVERALL MESSAGE IS THAT
IT DOESN'T RESULT IN JOB LOSS.
HOWEVER, WHAT ALAN KRUEGER SAID
IN THE PIECE YOU'RE REFERRING TO
IS IF WE WENT TO $15, THERE ARE
NO INTERNATIONAL COMPARISONS.
THAT IS WHY I SUPPORT A $12
NATIONAL OFFICIAL MINIMUM WAGE.
THAT IS WHAT THE DEMOCRATS IN
THE SENATE HAVE PUT FORWARD AS A
PROPOSAL.
BUT I DO BELIEVE THAT IS A
MINIMUM.
AND PLACES LIKE SEATTLE, LIKE
LOS ANGELES, LIKE NEW YORK CITY,
THEY CAN GO HIGHER.
IT'S WHAT HAPPENED IN GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY'S STATE.
THERE WAS A MINIMUM WAGE AT THE
STATE LEVEL, AND SOME PLACES
WENT HIGHER.
I THINK THAT IS--
>> DIDN'T JUST HAPPEN.
>> I THINKs THAT IS THE
SMARTEST WAY TO BE ABLE TO MOVE
FORWARD.
IF YOU GO TO 12 IT WOULD BE THE
HIGHEST HISTORICAL AVERAGE WE
HAVE EVER HAD NOW.
>> COME ON NOW.
IT SHOULD ALWAYS BE GOING UP.
>> BUT YOU WOULD INDEX IT TO THE
MEDIAN WAGE.
OF COURSE, YOU WOULD DO THE 12
AND YOU WOULD INDEX IT.
BUT--
>> I THINK WE NEED TO STOP
TAKING OUR ADVICE FROM
ECONOMISTS ON WALL STREET AND
START TAKING ADVICE--
>> HE'S NOT WALL STREET.
THAT'S NOT FAIR.
HE'S A PROGRESSIVE ECONOMIST.
>> IT'S A GOOD ISSUE TO TALK
ABOUT.
>> A MOLD OF ECONOMIC--
>> LET ME JUST SAY--
>> SENATOR, SENATOR, YOU HAVE
GIVEN ME THE PERFECT SEGUE.
WE ARE GOING TO TALK ABOUT WALL
STREET, BUT NOW WE'VE GOT TO GO
DO A COMMERCIAL.
( LAUGHTER )
WE'RE COMING TO THE END OF THE
FIRST HOUR.
BUT THERE'S ANOTHER HOUR BEHIND
IT AND WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT
WALL STREET SO HANG WITH US.
>> THIS COUNTRY WILL RID OUR
PLANET OF ISIS.
>> WE HAVE TO LOOK AT ISIS AS
THE LEADING THREAT OF AN
INTERNATIONAL TERROR NETWORK.
>> THE WORLD IS A VERY DANGEROUS
PLACE, BUT NOT TOO DANGEROUS FOR
A PLACE FOR THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
>> THIS IS AN INCREDIBLY
COMPLICATED REGION OF THE WORLD.
>> THIS WORLD, WITH AMERICAN
LEADERSHIP, CAN AND MUST COME
TOGETHER TO DESTROY THEM.
>> WE'VE GOT TO UNDERSTAND THE
COMPLEXITY OF THE WORD WE ARE
FACING AND NO PLACE IS MORE SO
THAN IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
>> LIVE FROM DRAKE UNIVERSITY IN
DES MOINES, IOWA, CBS NEWS
BRINGS YOU THE DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
HERE AGAIN JOHN DICKERSON.
( APPLAUSE ).
>> GOOD EVENING AGAIN AS WE
BEGIN THE SECOND HALF OF THE
DEBATE.
JOINING ME IN THE QUESTIONING OF
THE CANDIDATES ARE CBS NEWS
CONGRESSIONAL CORRESPONDENT
NANCY CORDES.
KEVIN COONEY OF CBS DES MOINES
AFFILIATE KCCI, AND KATHIE
OBRADOVICH OF THE "DES MOINES
REGISTER."
AS THOSE WHO WATCHED THE FIRST
HOUR KNOW, OUR TOPIC IS WALL
STREET FOR THOSE JUST JOINING
US, WELCOME.
SENATOR-- SKEWS ME.
SECRETARY CLINTON, I WENT TO THE
PAST THERE FOR A MOMENT.
SENATOR SANDERS RECENTLY SAID,
"PEOPLE SHOULD BE SUSPECT OF
CANDIDATES WHO RECEIVE LARGE
SUMS OF MONEY FROM WALL STREET
AND THEN GO OUT AND SAY 'TRUST
ME.
I'M GOING TO REALLY REG LAILT
WALL STREET'."
YOU HAVE RECEIVED MONEY FROM
WALL STREET.
HOW WILL YOU CONVINCE VOTERS YOU
WILL LEVEL THE PLAIRG FIELD WHEN
YOU'RE INDEBTEDDED TO SOME OF
ITS BIGGEST PLAYERS?
>> I THINK IT'S PRETTY CLEAR
THAT THEY KNOW THEY WILL.
YOU HAVE TWO BILLIONAIRE HEDGE
FUND MANAGERS WHO START AID
SUPERPAC AND THEY'RE ADVERTISING
AGAINST ME IN IOWA AS WE SPEAK
SO THEY CLEARLY THINK I WILL DO
WHAT I SAY I WILL DO AND YOU CAN
LOOK AT WHAT I DID IN THE
SENATE.
I INTRODUCED LEGISLATION TO
REIGN IN WAGE.
AND SPECIFICALLY, SAID TO WALL
STREET, THAT WHAT THEY WERE
DOING IN THE MORTGAGE MARKET WAS
BRINGING OUR COUNTRY DOWN.
I'VE LAID OUT A VERY AGGRESSIVE
PLAN TO REIGN IN WALL STREET--
NOT JUST THE BIG BANKS.
THAT'S A PART OF THE PROBLEM.
I AM GOING RIGHT AT THEM.
I HAVE A COMPREHENSIVE TOUGH
PLAN.
WE HAVE TO GO AFTER WHAT IS
CALLED THE SHADOW BANKING
INDUSTRY.
THOSE HEDGE FUNDS.
LOOK WHAT HAPPENED IN '08, AIG,
LEHMAN BROTHERS AN INVESTMENT
BANK, HELPED BRING OUR ECONOMY
DOWN.
I WANT TO LOOK AT THE WHOLE
PROBLEM AND THAT'S WHY MY
PROPOSAL IS MUCH MORE
COMPREHENSIVE THAN ANYTHING PUT
FORT.
>> SENATOR SANDERS YOU SAID THE
DONATIONS TO SECRETARY CLINTON
ARE COMPROMISING.
SO WHAT DID YOU THINK OF HER
ANSWER?
>> NOT GOOD ENOUGH.
( APPLAUSE )
HERE'S THE STORY.
I MEAN, YOU KNOW, LET'S NOT BE
NAIVE ABOUT IT.
WHY DO-- WHY, OVE POLITICAL
CAREER, HAS WALL STREET BEEN A
MAJOR-- THE MAJOR CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTOR TO HILLARY CLINTON?
NOW, MAYBE THEY'RE DUMB AND THEY
DON'T KNOW WHAT THEY'RE GOING TO
GET, BUT I DON'T THINK SO.
HERE IS THE MAJOR ISSUE WHEN WE
TALK ABOUT WALL STREET-- IT
AIN'T COMPLICATED.
YOU HAVE SIX FINANCIAL
INSTITUTIONS TODAY THAT HAVE
ASSETS OF-- EQUIVALENT TO 56% OF
THE G.D.P. IN AMERICA.
THEY ISSUE TWO-THIRDS OF THE
CREDIT CARDS AND ONE-THIRD OF
THE MORTGAGES.
IF TEDDY ROOSEVELT, A GOOD
REPUBLICAN, WERE ALIVE TODAY,
YOU KNOW WHAT HE'D SAY?
BREAK THEM UP.
REESTABLISH GLASS-STEAGLE AND
TEDDY ROOSEVELT IS RIGHT.
THAT IS THE ISSUE.
THE AM THE ONLY CANDIDATE UP
HERE THAT DOESN'T HAVE A
SUPERPAC.
I AM NOT ASKING WALL STREET OR
THE BILLIONAIRES FOR MONEY.
I WILL BREAK UP THESE BANKS.
SUPPORT THE COMMUNITY BANKS AND
CREDIT UNIONS.
THAT'S THE FUTURE OF AMERICA.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON YOU WILL
GET A CHANCE TO RESPOND.
YOU SAID THEY KNOW WHAT THEY'RE
GOING TO GET.
WHAT ARE THEY GOING TO GET?
>> I HAVE NEVER HEARD A
CANDIDATE NEVER WHO HAS RECEIVED
HUGE AMOUNTS OF MONEY FROM OIL,
FROM COAL, FROM WALL STREET FROM
THE MILITARY INDUSTRIAL COMPLEX,
NOT ONE CANDIDATE-- OH, THESE
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS WILL NOT
INFLUENCE ME.
I'M GOING TO BE INDEPENDENT.
WELL, WHY DO THEY MAKE MILLIONS
OF DOLLARS OF CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS?
THEY EXPECT TO GET SOMETHING.
EVERYBODY KNOWS THAT.
ONCE AGAIN, I AM RUNNING A
CAMPAIGN DIFFERENTLY THAN ANY
OTHER CANDIDATE.
WE ARE RELYING ON SMALL CAMPAIGN
DONORS, 750,000 OF THEM, 30
BUCKS A PIECE.
THAT'S WHO I'M INDEBTED TO.
>> JOHN, WAIT A MINUTE, WAIT A
MINUTE, HE HAS BASICALLY USED
HIS ANSWER TO IMPUGN MY
INTELLECT.
LET'S BE FRANK HERE.
>> NO, I HAVE NOT.
>> OH, WAIT A MINUTE, SENATOR.
YOU KNOW, NOT ONLY DO I HAVE
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF DONORS,
MOST OF THEM SMALL AND I'M VERY
PROUD THAT FOR THE FIRST TIME A
MAJORITY OF MY DONORS ARE WOMEN,
60%.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
SO I-- I REPRESENTED NEW YORK,
AND I REPRESENTED NEW YORK ON
9/11 WHEN WE WERE ATTACKED.
WHERE WERE WE ATTACKED?
WE WERE ATTACKED IN DOWNTOWN
MANHATTAN WHERE WALL STREET IS.
I DID SPEND A WHOLE LOT OF TIME
AND EFFORT HELPING THEM REBUILD.
THAT WAS GOOD FOR NEW YORK.
IT WAS GOOD FOR THE ECONOMY, AND
IT WAS A WAY TO REBUKE THE
TERRORISTS WHO HAD ATTACKED OUR
COUNTRY.
IT'S FINE FOR YOU TO SAY WHAT
YOU'RE GOING TO SAY, BUT I
LOOKED VERY CAREFULLY AT YOUR
PROPOSAL, REINSTATING
GLASS-STEAGLE IS A PART OF WHAT
VERY WELL COULD HELP, BUT IT IS
NOWHERE NEAR ENOUGH.
MY PROPOSAL IS TOUGHER, MORE
EFFECTIVE, AND MORE
COMPREHENSIVE BECAUSE I GO AFTER
ALL OF WALL STREET NOT JUST THE
BIG BANKS.
>> JOHN, PLEASE, IT'S-- PERSONAL
PRIVILEGE, JOHN.
>> HOLD ON.
HE WAS ATTACKED.
( APPLAUSE ).
>> JOHN.
>> HOLD OHE WAS ATTACKED.
>> SO WAS I, JOHN.
>> THIS ISSUE TOUCHES ON TWO
BROAD ISSUES.
IT'S NOT JUST WALL STREET.
IT'S CAMPAIGN, A CORRUPT
CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM.
AND IT IS EASY TO TALK THE TALK
ABOUT ENDING CITIZENS UNITED,
BUT WHAT I THINK WE NEED TO DO
IS SHOW BY EXAMPLE THAT WE ARE
PREPARED TO NOT RELY ON LARGE
CORPORATIONS AND WALL STREET FOR
CAMPAIGNAND
THAT'S WHAT I'M DOING.
IN TERMS OF WALL STREET, I
RESPECTFULLY DISAGREE WITH YOU,
MADAM SECRETARY, IN THE SENSE
THAT THE ISSUE HERE IS WHEN YOU
HAVE SUCH INCREDIBLE POWER AND
SUCH INCREDIBLE WEALTH, WHEN YOU
HAVE WALL STREET SPENDING $5
BILLION OVER A 10-YEAR PERIOD TO
GET-- TO GET DEREGULATED THE
ONLY ANSWER THEY KNOW IS BREAK
THEM UP, REESTABLISH
GLASS-STEAGLE.
>> SENATOR, WE HAVE TO GET
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY IN.
GOVERNOR, ALONG WITH YOUR
ANSWER, HOW MANY WALL STREET
VETERANS WOULD YOU HAVE IN YOUR
ADMINISTRATION?
>> WELL, I'LL TELL YOU WHAT,
I'VE SAID THIS BEFORE.
I DON'T-- I BELIEVE THAT WE
ACTUALLY NEED SOME NEW ECONOMIC
THINKING IN THE WHITE HOUSE.
AND I WOULD NOT HAVE ROBERT
RUBIN OR LARRY SUMMERS, WITH ALL
DUE RESPECT, SECRETARY CLINTON,
BACK ON MY COUNCIL OF ECONOMIC
ADVISERS.
>> ANYONE FROM WALL STREET?
>> THEY ARE THE ARCHITECT ARCHI-
SURE, WE'LL HAVE AN INCLUSIVE
GROUP BUT I WON'T BE TAKING MY
ORDERS FROM WALL STREET.
LOOK, LET ME SAY THIS.
I PUT OUT A PROPOSAL IEFS ON THE
FRONT LINES WHEN PEOPLE LOST
THEIR HOMES, WHEN PEOPLE LOST
THEIR JOBS.
I WAS ON THE FRONT LINES AS A
GOVERNOR FIGHTING AGAINST--
FIGHTING THAT BATTLE.
OUR ECONOMY WAS WRECKED BY THE
BIG BANKS OF WALL STREET.
AND SECRETARY CLINTON, WHEN YOU
PUT OUT YOUR PROPOSAL ON WALL
STREET, IT WAS GREETED BY MANY
AS-- QUOTE, UNQUOTE-- WEAK TEA.
IT IS WEAK TEA.
IT IS NOT WHAT THE PEOPLE EXPECT
OF OUR COUNTRY.
WE EXPECT THAT OUR PRESIDENT
WILL PROTECT THE MAIN STREET
ECONOMY FROM EXCESSES ON WALL
STREET.
AND THAT'S WHY BERNIE'S RIGHT.
WE NEED TO REINSTATE A MODERN
VERSION OF GLASS-STEEG EXPEL WE
SHOULD HAVE DONE IT ALREADY.
( APPLAUSE )
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, GOVERNOR, I
KNOW THAT WHEN YOU HAD A CHANCE
TO APPOINT A COMMISSIONER FOR
FINANCIAL REGULATION, YOU CHOSE
AN INVESTMENT BANKER IN 2010.
SO FOR ME, IT IS LOOKING AT WHAT
WORKS AND WHAT WE NEED TO DO TO
TRY TO MOVE PAST WHAT HAPPENED
IN '08.
>> HEAR, HEAR.
>> AND I WILL GO BACK AND SAY
AGAIN, A.I.G. WAS NOT A BIG
BANK.
HAD TO BE BAILED OUT AND IT
NEARLY DESTROYED US.
LEHMAN BROTHERS WAS NOT A BIG
BANK.
IT WAS AN INVESTMENT BANK.
AND ITS BANKRUPTCY AND ITS
FAILURE NEARLY DESTROYED US.
SO I'VE SAID, IF THE BIG BANKS
DON'T PLAY BY THE RULES, I WILL
BREAK THEM UP.
>> THE BIG BANKS--
>> AND I WILL ALSO GO AFTER
EXECUTIVES WHO ARE RESPONSIBLE
FOR THE DECISIONS THAT HAVE SUCH
BAD CONSEQUENCES FOR OUR
COUNTRY.
( APPLAUSE )
>> LOOK--
>> HOLD ON.
>> IF I DON'T-- WITHULE DUE
RESPECT TO THE SECRETARY-- WALL
STREET PLAY BY THE RULES?
WHO ARE WE KIDDING?
THE BUSINESS MODEL OF WALL
STREET IS FRAUD.
THAT'S WHAT IT IS.
( APPLAUSE )
AND LET ME MAKE THIS PROMISE.
ONE OF THE PROBLEMS WE HAVE
HAD-- I THINK ALL AMERICANS
UNDERSTAND THIS-- IS WHETHER
IT'S REPUBLICAN ADMINISTRATIONS
OR DEMOCRATIC ADMINISTRATIONS,
WE HAVE SEEN WITH THE AND
GOLDMAN SACHS DOMINATE
ADMINISTRATIONS.
HERE'S MY PROMISE-- WALL STREET
REPRESENTATIVES WILL NOT BE IN
( APPLAUSE )
>> ALL RIGHT, I WANT TO SWITCH
TO THE-- SWITCH TO THE ISSUE OF
GUNSHOT HERE.
SECRETARY CLINTON, SAID SENATOR
SAND SERS NOT TOUGH ENOUGH ON
GUNS, BUT BASICALLY HE NOW
SUPPORTS ROUGHLY THE SAME THINGS
YOU DO.
SO YOU CAN TELL US WHAT THE
EXACT DIFFERENCE IS GOING
FORWARD BETWEEN THE TWO OF YOU
ON THE ISSUE OF GUN CONTROL?
>> WELL, I THINK THERE ARE
DIFFERENT RECORDS.
I-- YOU KNOW, KNOW THAT SENATOR
SANDERS HAD A DIFFERENT VOTE
THAN I DID WHEN IT CAME TO
GIVING IMMUNITY TO GUN MAKERS
AND SELLERS.
THAT WAS A TERRIBLE MISTAKE.
IT BASICALLY GAVE THE GUN LOBBY
EVEN MORE POWER TO INTIMIDATE
LEGISLATORS, NOT JUST IN
WASHINGTON BUT ACROSS THE
COUNTRY.
BUT JUST THINK ABOUT THIS--
SINCE WE LAST DEBATED IN LAS
VEGAS, NEARLY 3,000 PEOPLE HAVE
BEEN KILLED BY GUNS.
21 MASS SHOOTINGS, INCLUDING ONE
LAST WEEKEND IN DES MOINES WHERE
THREE WERE MURDERED.
200 CHILDREN HAVE BEEN KILLED.
THIS IS AN EMERGENCY.
THERE ARE A LOT OF THINGS WE'VE
GOT TO DO IN OUR COUNTRY--
REIGNING IN WALL STREET IS
CERTAINLY ONE OF THEM.
I AGREE WITH THAT.
THAT'S WHY I'VE GOT SUCH A GOOD
PLAN.
BUT WE HAVE TO ALSO GO AFTER THE
GUN LOBBY AND 92% OF AMERICANS
AGREE WE SHOULD HAVE UNIVERSAL
BACKGROUND CHECKS.
CLOSE THE GUN SHOW LOOPHOLE,
CLOSE THE ONLINE LOOPHOLE AND--
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I WANT
TO--
>> I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN AS
PRESIDENT TO GET THAT
ACCOMPLISHED.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, JUST A
QUICK FOLLOW-UP, YOU SAY THAT
SENATOR SANDERS TOOK A VOTE
THAT-- ON IMMUNITY THAT YOU
DON'T LIKE.
SO IF HE CAN BE TATTOOED BY A
SINGLE VOTE AND THAT RUINS ALL
FUTURE OPINIONS BY HIM ON THIS
ISSUE, WHY THEN ISN'T HE RIGHT
WHEN HE SAYS YOUR WRONG VOTE ON
IRAQ TATTOOS YOU FOREVER IN YOUR
JUDGMENT.
>> I SAID I MADE A MISTAKE ON
IRAQ, AND I'D LOVE TO SEE
SENATOR SANDERS JOIN WITH SOME
OF MY COLLEAGUE IN ADDITION THE
SENATE THAT I SEE IN THE
AUDIENCE.
LET'S REVERSE THE IMMUNITY.
LET'S PUT THE GUN MAKERS AND
SELLERS ON NOTICE THAT THEY'RE
NOT GOING TO GET AWAY WITH IT.
( APPLAUSE ).
>> LET'S DO MORE-- LET'S DO MORE
THAN REVERSE THE IMMUNITY.
LET'S--
>> WAS THAT A MISTAKE, SENATOR?
>> LET ME HEAR IF THERE'S ANY
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE SECRETARY
AND MYSELF.
I HAVE VOTED TIME AND AGAIN TO--
FOR THE BACKGROUND CHECK, AND I
WANT TO SEE IT IMPROVED AND
EXPANDED.
I WANT TO SEE US DO AWAY WITH
THE GUN SHOW LOOPHOLE.
IN 1988, I LOST AN ELECTION
BECAUSE I SAID WE SHOULD NOT
HAVE ASSAULT WEAPONS ON THE
STREETS OF AMERICA.
WE HAVE TO DO AWAY WITH THE
STRAWMAN PROPOSAL.
WE NEED RADICAL CHANGES IN
MENTAL HEALTH IN AMERICA.
SO SOMEBODY WHO IS SUICIDAL OR
HOMICIDALITY CAN GET THE
EMERGENCY CARE THEY NEED.
WE HAVE-- I DON'T KNOW THAT
THERE'S ANY DISAGREEMENT HERE.
>> OH, YES THERE IS.
>> WE HAVE TO COME FORWARD WITH
A CONSENSUS THAT IN FACT WILL
WORK.
>> SENATOR, I A MISTAKE OR NOT,
YOUR IMMUNITY VOTE.
>> THERE ARE PARTS OF THAT BILL
I AGREE WITH, PARTS I DISAGREE.
I AM CERTAINLY, ABSOLUTELY,
WILLING TO LOOK AT THAT BILL
AGAIN AND MAKE SURE THERE'S A
STRONGER BILL.
>> SO NOT A MISTAKE.
>> JOHN, THIS IS ANOTHER ONE OF
THOSE EXAMPLES.
WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO AND
WE'RE THE ONLY NATION ON THE
PLANET THAT BURIES AS MANY OF
OUR PEOPLE FROM GUN VIOLENCE AS
WE DO.
IN MY OWN STATE, AFTER THE
CHILDREN IN THAT CONNECTICUT
CLASSROOM WERE GUNNED DOWN, WE
PASSED COMPREHENSIVE GUN SAFETY
LEGISLATION WITH BACKGROUND
CHECKS, BAN ON ASSAULT WEAPONS,
AND, SENATE, I THINK WE DO NEED
TO REPEAL THAT IMMUNITY THAT YOU
GRANTED TO THE GUN INDUSTRY.
BUT, SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU'VE
BEEN ON THREE SIDES OF THIS.
WHEN YOU RAN IN 2000, YOU SAID
WE NEEDED FEDERAL ROBUST
REGULATIONS.
THEN, IN 2008, YOU WERE
PORTRAYING YOURSELF ANNE'S
OAKLEY AND SAYING WE DON'T NEED
THOSE REGULATIONS ON THE FEDERAL
LEVEL AND NOW YOU COME BACK
AROUND HERE.
SO, JOHN, THERE'S A BIG
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN LEADING BY
POLLS AND LEADING WITH
PRINCIPLE.
WE GOT IT DONE IN MY STATE BY
LEADINLEAD WITH PRINCIPAL AND TS
WHAT WE NEED TO DO AS A COUNTRY.
>> I THINK IT'S FAIR TO SAY
BALTIMORE IS NOT NOW ONE OF THE
SAFEST CITIES IN AMERICA.
>> IT'S SAVED A LOT OF LIVES
ALONG THE WAY, SENATOR.
>> I BELIEVE THIS, AND I BELIEVE
THIS HONESTLY, AND I DON'T KNOW
THE DIFFERENCE ON GUNS BETWEEN
US.
BUT I BELIEVE COMING FROM A
STATE THAT HAS VIRTUALLY NO GUN
CONTROL, I BELIEVE THAT I AM IN
POSITION TO REACH OUT TO THE 60%
OR 70% OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
WHO AGREE WITH US ON THOSE
ISSUES.
THE PROBLEM IS--
>> HOLD ON.
>> PEOPLE ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY-- NOT YOU, SECRETARY
CLINTON-- ARE SHOUTING AT EACH
OTHER.
AND WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS BRING
PEOPLE TOGETHER TO WORK ON THE
AGREEMENT WHERE THERE IS BROAD
CONSENSUS AND THAT'S WHAT I
INTEND TO DO.
>> I'D LIKE TO TAKE A MATTER OF
PERSONAL PRIVILEGE HERE--
>> SENATOR, THERE IS BROAD
CONSENSUS.
92% IN THE MOST RECENTLY POLL OF
AMERICANS WANT GUN SAFETY
MEASURES.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> AND 85% OF GUN OWNERS AGREE.
>> YES.
>> WE'VE GOT THE CONSENSUS.
WHAT WE'RE LACKING IS POLITICAL
LEADERSHIP.
>> YES.
>> AND THAT'S WHAT YOU AND
OTHERS CAN START PROVIDING IN
THE SENATE.
>> YI AGREE.
>> I'M GOING TO BRING IN NANCY
CORDES WITH A QUESTION FROM
TWITTER ABOUT THIS EXCHANGE.
>> THERE WAS A LOT OF
CONVERSATION ON TWITTER ABOUT
GUNS.
BUT ALSO ABOUT YOUR CONVERSATION
ON CAMPAIGN FINANCE.
AND, SECRETARY CLINTON, ONE OF
THE TWEETS WE SAW SAID THIS,
"I'VE NEVER SEEN A CANDIDATE
INVOKE 9/11 TO JUSTIFY MILLIONS
OF WALL STREET DONATIONS UNTIL
NOW."
THE IDEA BEING, YES, YOU WERE A
CHAMPION OF THE COMMUNITY AFTER
9/11, BUT WHAT DOES THAT HAVE TO
DO WITH TAKING BIG DONATIONS?
>> WELL, I'M SORRY THAT WHOEVER
TWEETED THAT HAD THAT IMPRESSION
BECAUSE I WORKED CLOSELY WITH
NEW YORKERS AFTER 9/11 FOR MY
ENTIRE FIRST TERM TO REBUILD.
SO, YES, I DID KNOW PEOPLE.
I'VE HAD A LOT OF FOLKS GIVE ME
DONATIONS FROM ALL KINDS OF
BACKGROUNDS SAY, "I DON'T AGREE
WITH YOU ON EVERYTHING, BUT I
LIKE WHAT YOU DO.
I LIKE HOW YOU STAND UP.
I'M GOING TO SUPPORT YOU."
AND I THINK THAT IS ABSOLUTELY
APPROPRIATE.
( APPLAUSE )
>> WELL, I-- IF I MIGHT.
I THINK THE ISSUE HERE IS-- AND
I APPLAUD SECRETARY CLINTON.
SHE DID.
SHE'S THE SENATOR FROM NEW YORK.
SHE WORKED-- AND MANY OF US
SUPPORTED YOU-- IN TRYING TO
REBUILD THAT DEVASTATION.
BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY, WALL
STREET TODAY HAS ENORMOUS
ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL POWER.
THEIR BUSINESS MODEL IS GREED
AND FRAUD.
AND FOR THE SAKE OF OUR ECONOMY,
THEY MUST-- THE MAJOR BANKS--
MUST BE BROKEN UP.
>> HOLD ON.
>> JOHN, I THINK SOMEWHERE
BETWEEN--
>> SENATOR SANDERS, BUT WHAT IS
IT IN SECRETARY CLINTON'S RECORD
THAT SHOWS YOU THAT SHE'S BEEN
INFLUENCED BY THOSE DONATIONS?
>> WELL, THE MAJOR ISSUE RIGHT
NOW IS WHETHER OR NOT WE
REESTABLISH GLASS-STEAGLE.
I LED THE EFFORT, UNFORTUNATELY
UNSUCCESSFULLY, AGAINST
DEREGULATION BECAUSE I KNEW WHEN
YOU MERGE LARGE INSURANCE
COMPANIES AND INVESTMENT BANKS
AND COMMERCIAL BANKS IT WAS NOT
GOING TO BE GOOD.
THE ISSUE NOW IS DO WE BREAK
THEM ?UP DO WE REESTABLISH
GLASS-STEEG EXPEL SECRETARY
CLINTON, UNFORTUNATELY, IS ON
THE WRONG SIDE.
>> I WILL TELL YOU WHO IS ON MY
SIDE.
PAUL KRUGMAN, THE NOBEL
PRIZE-WINNING ECONOMIST WHO SAID
MY PLAN FOR WHAT WE SHOULD DO TO
REIGN IN WALL STREET WAS MORE
COMPREHENSIVE AND BETTER.
PAUL VOLCKER, ONE OF THE LEADING
LIGHTS OF TRYING TO REIGN IN THE
EXCESSES, HAS ALSO SAID HE DOES
NOT SUPPORT REINSTATING
GLASS-STEAGLE.
THIS MAY SEEM LIKE A BIT OF AN
ARCANE DISCUSSION.
I HAVE NOTHING AGAINST THE
PASSION THAT MY TWO FRIENDS HERE
HAVE ABOUT REINSTATING
GLASS-STEAGLE.
I JUST DON'T THINK IT WOULD GET
THE JOB DONE.
I'M ALL ABOUT MAKING SURE WE
ACTUALLY GET RESULTS FOR
WHATEVER WE DO.
( APPLAUSE )
>> FINAL WORD.
FINAL WORD, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY,
BEFORE WE GO TO COMMERCIAL.
>> JOHN, THERE IS NOT A SERIOUS
ECONOMIST WHO WOULD DISAGREE
THAT THE SIX BIG BANKS OF WALL
STREET HAVE TAKEN ON SO MUCH
POWER AND THAT ALL OF US ARE
STILL ON THE HOOK TO BAIL THEM
OUT ON THEIR BAD BETS.
THAT'S NOT CAPITALISM, SECRETARY
CLINTON.
THAT'S CRONY CAPITALISM.
THAT'S A WONDERFUL BUSINESS
MODEL.
IF YOU PLACE BAD BETS, THE
TAXPAYERS BAIL YOU OUT.
BUT IF YOU PLACE GOOD ONES, YOU
POCKET IT.
LOOK, I DON'T BELIEVE THERE'S
THE MODEL-- THERE ARE LOTS OF
GOOD PEOPLE WHO WORK IN FINANCE,
SECRETARY SANDERS, BUT SECRETARY
CLINTON, WE NEED TO STEP UP AND
WE NEED TO PROTECT MAIN STREET
FROM WALL STREET AND YOU CAN'T
DO THAT BY-- BY CAMPAIGNING AS
THE CANDIDATE OF WALL STREET.
I AM NOT THE CANDIDATE OF WALL
STREET, AND I ENCOURAGE
EVERYBODY WATCHING THIS TONIGHT
TO, PLEASE, ACKNOWLEDGE THAT BY
GOING ONLINE AT
MARTINO'MALLEY.COM AND HELP ME
WAGE THIS CAMPAIGN FOR REAL
AMERICAN CAPITALISM.
>> WE HAVE TO GO FOR A
COMMERCIAL, SENATOR.
I'M SORRY.
WE HAVE TO GO FOR A COMMERCIAL
THE CANDIDATES FOR THE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL
NOMINATION.
SENATOR SANDERS, I WANT TO START
WITH YOU.
LET'S SAY YOU'RE ELECTED
PRESIDENT.
CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THANK YOU.
( APPLAUSE )
LOOKING FORWARD TO IT.
>> YOU'VE SAID YOU'LL HAVE A
REVOLUTION.
>> YES.
>> BUT THERE'S A CONSERVATIVE
REVOLUTION GOING ON IN AMERICA
RIGHT NOW.
AS JOHN BOEHNER KNOWS AND AS
DEMOCRATS KNOW WHO HAVE LOST IN
STATE HOUSES ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
>> RIGHT.
>> THOSE CONSERVATIVES ARE
WATCHING TONIGHT AND PROBABLY
SHAKING THEIR HEADS.
SO HOW DO YOU DEAL WITH THAT
PART OF THE COUNTRY?
THE REVOLUTION'S ALREADY
HAPPENING BUT ON THE OTHER SIDE.
>> AND WE ARE GOING TO DO A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION WHICH
BRINGS WORKING PEOPLE, YOUNG
PEOPLE, SENIOR CITIZENS,
MINORITIES TOGETHER.
BECAUSE EVERY ISSUE THAT I AM
TALKING ABOUT-- PAID FAMILY AND
MEDICAL LEAVE, BREAKING UP THE
BANKS ON WALL STREET, ASKING THE
WEALTH TOW PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE
OF TAX, REBUILDING OUR CRUMBLING
INFRASTRUCTURE, RAISING THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO 15 BUCKS AN
HOUR-- EVERY ONE OF THOSE ISSUES
IS SUPPORTED BY A SIGNIFICANT
MAJORITY OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
THE PROBLEM IS THAT AS A RESULT
OF A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN FINANCE
SYSTEM, CONGRESS IS NOT
LISTENING TO THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
IT'S LISTENING TO THE BIG MONEY
INTEREST.
WHAT THE POLITICAL REVOLUTION IS
ABOUT IS BRINGING PEOPLE
TOGETHER TO FINALLY SAY ENOUGH
IS ENOUGH.
THIS GOVERNMENT BELONGS TO US.
NOT JUST THE BILLIONAIRES.
>> SENATOR, AS A 30-SECOND
FOLLOW-UP, WE'VE HEARD ALREADY
TONIGHT THIS FIGURE 92% OF
SUPPORT FOR BACKGROUND CHECKS.
LET'S LOOK AT THAT AS AN
EXAMPLE.
THERE WAS SOMETHING 92% OF THE
PUBLIC WAS FOR.
THERE HAVE BEEN THESE MASS
SHOOTINGS.
THERE WAS EMOTIONAL SUPPORT
BEHIND IT.
>> YES.
>> BIPARTISAN SUPPORT.
>> THE PRESIDENT, THE FULL FORCE
OF HIS OFFICE.
IT WENT NOWHERE.
THAT'S THE MODEL YOU'RE TALKING
ABOUT.
NOTHING HAPPENED.
>> WHAT WE NEED IS LEADERSHIP IN
THIS COUNTRY WHICH REVITALIZES
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY AND MAKES
PEOPLE UNDERSTAND THAT IF THEY
STAND UP AND FIGHT BACK AND TAKE
ON THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS, WE CAN
BRING ABOUT THE CHANGE THAT WE
NEED.
IF WE ARE NOT SUCCESSFUL, IF WE
CONTINUE THE SAME OLD-SAME OLD
OF WASHINGTON BEING RUN BY
CORPORATE LOBBYISTS AND
BIG-MONEY INTERESTS, NOTHING
CHANGES.
I AM VERY HAPPY IN THIS CAMPAIGN
THAT WE HAVE HAD RALLIES WITH
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE,
MOSTLY YOUNG PEOPLE.
WHAT THE POLLS ARE SHOWING IS
THAT WE ARE ACTUALLY DEEFFECT
THE SECRETARY AMONG YOUNGER
PEOPLE.
WE'RE GIVING YOUNG PEOPLE AND
WORKING PEOPLE HOPE THAT REAL
CHANGE CAN TAKE PLACE IN
AMERICA.
THAT'S WHAT THE POLITICAL
REVOLUTION IS ABOUT.
>> A QUESTION FROM KATHIE
OBRADOVICH.
>> YES, SENATOR SANDERS, YOU
FAMOUSLY SAID IN THE LAST DEBATE
THAT YOU WERE SICK AND TIRED OF
HEARING ABOUT YOUR DAMN E-MAILS.
BUT THEN YOU TOLD THE "WALL
STREET JOURNAL" THAT THE
QUESTIONS ABOUT WHETHER OR NOT
SECRETARY CLINTON'S E-MAILS
COMPROMISED CLASSIFIED
INFORMATION WERE VALID
QUESTIONS.
SO WHICH IS IT?
IS IT AN ISSUE OR IS IT NOT?
>> THAT'S JUST MEDIA STUFF.
I WAS SICK AND TIRED OF HILLARY
CLINTON'S E-MAIL.
I AM STILL SICK AND TIRED OF
HILLARY CLINTON'S E-MAILS.
AND THE ISSUE IS, THE PROBLEM
IS, THE FRONT PAGES EVERY DAY
WERE DEALING WITH IT.
I DIDN'T KNOW I HAD SO MUCH
POWER.
BUT AFTER I SAID THAT, WE'RE NOT
HEARING SO MUCH ABOUT HILLARY
CLINTON'S E-MAILS.
WHAT I WOULD LIKE FOR THE MEDIA
NOW IS FOR US TO BE TALKING
ABOUT WHY THE MIDDLE CLASS IS
DISAPPEARING, WHY WE HAVE MORE
PEOPLE IN JAIL THAN ANY OTHER
COUNTRY, WHY WE HAVE MASSIVE
LEVELS OF INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY, AND WE'RE THE ONLY
MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH WITHOUT
PAID FAMILY AND MEDICAL LEAVE.
WE'VE GOTTEN OFF THE HILLARY'S
E-MAILS, GOOD.
LET'S GO TO THE MAJOR ISSUES
FACING AMERICA.
( APPLAUSE )
>> LET ME JUST--
>> I'M SORRY, I COULDN'T HEAR
YOU.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, YOUR
RESPONSE.
>> I AGREE COMPLETELY.
( APPLAUSE )
I COULDN'T HAVE SAID IT BETTER
MYSELF.
BUT I DID WANT-- I WANTED TO
FOLLOW UP.
LOOK, WE NEED MORE AMERICANS TO
BE INVOLVED IN THE POLITICAL
PROCESS.
AND I GIVE SENATOR SANDERS A LOT
OF CREDIT FOR REALLY LIGHTING A
FIRE UNDER MANY PEOPLE-- YOUNG,
OLD, EVERYBODY-- WHO SEES A
CHANCE TO BE INVOLVED AND HAVE
THEIR VOICE HEARD.
LOOK AT WHAT'S HAPPENING WITH
THE REPUBLICANS.
THEY ARE DOING EVERYTHING THEY
CAN TO PREVENT THE VOICES OF
AMERICANS TO BE HEARD.
( APPLAUSE )
THEY'RE TRYING TO PREVENT PEOPLE
FROM REGISTERING TO VOTE.
SO WE DO NEED TO TAKE ON THE
REPUBLICANS VERY CLEARLY AND
DIRECTLY.
BUT THE OTHER THING I JUST
WANTED QUICKLY TO SAY IS I THINK
PRESIDENT OBAMA DESERVES MORE
CREDIT THAN HE GETS FOR WHAT HE
GOT DONE IN WASHINGTON DESPITE
THE REPUBLICAN OBSTRUCTIONISTS.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, JUST ONE
MORE QUESTION ON THE E-MAIL
QUESTION.
FOR DEMOCRATS, THERE'S AN F.B.I.
INVESTIGATION GOING ON.
CAN YOU SATISFY DEMOCRATS WHO
MIGHT WORRY ABOUT AN ANOTHER
SHOE DROPPING THAT YOU AND YOUR
STAFF HAVE BEEN TOTALLY TRUTHFUL
TO THEM AND THAT ANOTHER SHOE IS
NOT GOING TO DROP?
>> I THINK AFTER 11 HOURS,
THAT'S PRETTY CLEAR, YES.
( APPLAUSE )
AND, YOU KNOW, I DO THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT TO DO EXACTLY WHAT
SENATOR SANDERS SAID, AND THAT
IS TO START TALKING ABOUT THE
ISSUES THAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
REALLY CARE ABOUT AND THAT THEY
TALK TO EACH OF US ABOUT.
AND TO CONTRAST, EVEN-- THERE
ARE DIFFERENCES AMONG US.
YOU'VE HEARD SOME OF THOSE
TONIGHT.
I STILL WANT TO GET BACK TO
HEALTH CARE BECAUSE I THINK
THAT'S A WORTHY TOPIC TO
EXPLORE.
BUT THE DIFFERENCES AMONG US
PALE COMPARED TO WHAT'S
HAPPENING ON THE REPUBLICAN
SIDE.
AND IF YOU LISTEN TO WHAT THEY
SAY-- AND I HAD A CHANCE OVER
THOSE 11 HOURS TO WATCH AND
LISTEN AS WELL AS WHAT I SEE IN
THEIR DEBATES -- THEY ARE
PUTTING FORTH ALARMING PLANS.
I MEAN ALL OF US SUPPORT FUNDING
PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
ALL OF US BELIEVE CLIMATE CHANGE
IS REAL.
ALL OF US WANT EQUAL PAY FOR
EQUAL WORK.
THEY DON'T BELIEVE IN ANY OF
THAT.
SO LET'S FOCUS ON WHAT THIS
ELECTION IS REALLY GOING TO BE
ABOUT.
( APPLAUSE )
>> RACE RELATIONS IS ANOTHER
ISSUE EVERYONE CARES ABOUT AND
WE'RE GOING TO SWITCH TO THAT
NOW.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, LET ME ASK
YOU A QUESTION.
THE HEAD OF THE F.B.I. RECENTLY
SAID IT MIGHT BE POSSIBLE THAT
SOME POLICE FORCES ARE NOT
ENFORCING THE LAW BECAUSE
THEY'RE WORRIED ABOUT BEING
CAUGHT ON CAMERA.
THE ACTING HEAD OF THE DRUG
ENFORCEMENT ADMINISTRATION SAID
A SIMILAR THING.
WHERE ARE YOU ON THIS QUESTION?
AND WHAT WOULD DO YOU IF YOU
WERE PRESIDENT AND TWO TOP
MEMBERS OF YOUR ADMINISTRATION
WERE FLOATING THAT IDEA?
>> JOHN, I THINK THE-- I THINK
THE CALL OF YOUR QUESTION IS HOW
CAN WE IMPROVE BOTH PUBLIC
SAFETY IN AMERICA AND RACE
RELATIONS IN AMERICA,
UNDERSTANDING HOW VERY
INTERTWINED BOTH OF THOSE ISSUES
ARE IN A VERY, VERY DIFFICULT
AND PAINFUL WAY FOR US AS A
PEOPLE.
LOOK, THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS
THAT WE SHOULD ALL FEEL A SENSE
OF RESPONSIBILITY AS AMERICANS
TO LOOK FOR THE THINGS THAT
ACTUALLY WORK TO SAVE AND REDEEM
LIVES AND TO DO MORE OF THEM AND
TO STOP DOING THE THINGS THAT
DON'T.
FOR MY PART, THAT'S WHAT I HAVE
DONE IN 15 YEARS OF EXPERIENCE
AS A MAYOR AND AS A GOVERNOR.
WE RESTORED VOTING RIGHTS TO
52,000 PEOPLE.
WE DECRIMINALIZED POSSESSION OF
SMALL AMOUNTS OF MARIJUANA.
I REPEALED THE DEATH PENALTY.
AND WE ALSO PUT IN PLACE A
CIVILIAN REVIEW BOARD.
WE REPORTED OPENLY DISCOURTESY
AND LETHAL FORCE AND BRUTALITY
COMPLAINTS.
THIS IS SOMETHING THAT-- AND I
PUT FORWARD A NEW AGENDA FOR
CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORM THAT IS
INFORMED BY THAT EXPERIENCE.
SO AS PRESIDENT, I WOULD LEAD
THESE EFFORTS AND, I WOULD COSO
WITH MORE EXPERIENCE AND
PROBABLY THE ATTENDANCE AT MORE
GRAVESITES THAN ANY OF THE THREE
OF US ON THIS STAGE WHEN IT
COMES TO URBAN CRIME, LOSS OF
LIVES.
AND THE TRUTH IS I HAVE LEARNED
ON A VERY DAILY BASIS THAT, YES,
INDEED, BLACK LIVES MATTER.
>> ALL RIGHT, GOVERNOR--
( APPLAUSE )
SENATOR SANDERS, ONE OF YOUR
FORMER COLLEAGUES, AN AFRICAN
AMERICAN MEMBER OF CONGRESS SAID
TO ME RECENTLY THAT A YOUNG
AFRICAN AMERICAN MAN HAD ASKED
HIM WHERE TO FIND HOPE IN LIFE.
AND HE SAID, "I JUST DON'T KNOW
WHAT TO TELL HIM ABOUT BEING
YOUNG AND BLACK IN AMERICA
TODAY."
WHAT WOULD YOU TELL THAT YOUNG
AFRICAN AMERICAN MAN?
>> WELL, THIS IS WHAT I WOULD
SAY, AND THE CONGRESSMAN WAS
RIGHT.
ACCORDING TO THE STATISTICS THAT
I'M FAMILIAR WITH, A BLACK MALE
BABY BORN TODAY STANDS A ONE IN
FOUR CHANCE OF ENDING UP IN THE
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
51% OF HIGH SCHOOL AFRICAN
AMERICAN GRADUATES ARE
UNEMPLOYED OR UNDEREMPLOYED.
WE HAVE MORE PEOPLE IN JAIL
TODAY THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY ON
EARTH.
WE'RE SPENDING $80 BILLION
LOCKING PEOPLE UP
DISPROPORTIONATELY LATINO AND
AFRICAN AMERICAN.
WE NEED, VERY CLEARLY, MAJOR,
MAJOR REFORM IN A BROKEN
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
FROM TOP TO BOTTOM.
AND THAT MEANS WHEN POLICE
OFFICERS OUT IN A COMMUNITY
COILLEGAL ACTIVITY, KILL PEOPLE
WHO ARE UNARMED WHO SHOULD NOT
BE KILLED, THEY MUST BE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE.
IT MEANS THAT WE END MINIMUM
SENTENCING FOR THOSE PEOPLE
ARRESTED.
IT MEANS THAT WE TAKE MARIJUANA
OUT OF THE FEDERAL LAW AS A
CRIME AND GIVE STATES THE
FREEDOM TO GO FORWARD WITH
LEGALIZING MARIJUANA.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU TOLD
SOME BLACK LIVES MATTER
ACTIVISTS RECENTLY THAT THERE'S
A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN RHETORIC IN
ACTIVISM AND WHAT YOU WERE
TRYING TO DO, GET LAWS PASSED
THAT WOULD HELP WHAT THEY WERE
PUSHING FOR.
BUT RECENTLY AT THE UNIVERSITY
OF MISSOURI, THAT ACTIVISM WAS
VERY, VERY EFFECTIVE.
SO WOULD YOU SUGGEST THAT KIND
OF ACTIVISM TAKE PLACE AT OTHER
UNIVERSITIES ACROSS THE COUNTRY?
>> WELL, JOHN, I COME FROM THE
60s, A LONG TIME AGO.
THERE WAS A LOT OF ACTIVISM ON
CAMPUS-- CIVIL RIGHTS ACTIVISM,
ANTIWAR ACTIVISM, WOMEN'S RIGHTS
ACTIVISM-- AND I DO APPRECIATE
THE WAY YOUNG PEOPLE ARE
STANDING UP AND SPEAKING OUT.
OBVIOUSLY, I BELIEVE THAT ON A
COLLEGE CAMPUS THERE SHOULD BE
ENOUGH RESPECT SO PEOPLE HEAR
EACH OTHER.
BUT WHAT HAPPENED AT THE
UNIVERSITY THERE, WHAT'S
HAPPENING AT OTHER UNIVERSITIES,
I THINK REFLECTS THE DEEP SENSE
OF, YOU KNOW, CONCERN, EVEN
DESPAIR THAT SO MANY YOUNG
PEOPLE, PARTICULARLY OF COLOR,
HAVE.
YOU KNOW, I RECENTLY MET WITH A
GROUP OF MOTHERS WHO LOST THEIR
CHILDREN TO EITHER KILLINGS BY
POLICE OR RANDOM KILLINGS IN
THEIR NEIGHBORHOODS, AND HEARING
THEIR STORIES WAS SO INCREDIBLY,
PROFOUNDLY HEARTBREAKING.
EACH ONE OF THEM, YOU KNOW,
DESCRIBED THEIR CHILD, HAD A
PICTURE, YOU KNOW, THE MOTHER OF
THE YOUNG MAN WITH HIS FRIENDS
IN THE CAR WHO WAS PLAYING LOUD
MUSIC AND, YOU KNOW, SOME OLDER
WHITE MAN PULLED OUT A GUN AND
SHOT HIM BECAUSE THEY WOULDN'T
TURN THE RADIO DOWN.
OR A YOUNG WOMAN WHO HAD BEEN
PERFORMING AT PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
SECOND INAUGURATION COMING HOME,
ABSOLUTELY STELLAR YOUNG WOMAN,
HANGING OUT WITH HER FRIENDS IN
A PARK GETTING SHOT BY A GANG
MEMBER.
AND, OF COURSE, I MET THE
MOTHERS OF ERIC GARNER AND TAMIR
RICE, AND MICHAEL BROWN AND
TRAYVON MARTIN AND SO MANY OF
THEM WHO HAVE LOST THEIR
CHILDREN.
SO YOUR ORIGINAL QUESTION IS THE
RIGHT QUESTION.
AND IT'S NOT JUST A QUESTION FOR
PARENTS AND GRANDPARENTS TO
ANSWER.
IT'S REALLY A QUESTION FOR ALL
OF US TO ANSWER, EVERY SINGLE
ONE OF OUR CHILDREN DESERVES THE
CHANCE TO LIVE UP TO HIS OR HER
GOD-GIVEN POTENTIAL.
AND THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO BE
DOING TO THE BEST OF OUR ABILITY
IN OUR COUNTRY.
>> ALL RIGHT, OVER TO KEVIN
COONEY.
( APPLAUSE )
>> SENATOR, SENATOR SANDERS,
WE'VE HEARD A LOT ABOUT THIS,
YOUR OFFER-- YOU WANT TO OFFER
FREE TUITION TO PUBLIC
UNIVERSITIES AND COLLEGES.
A COUPLE OF QUESTIONS ABOUT
THIS.
63% OF THOSE WHO ENROLL
GRADUATE.
FIRST QUESTION, ISN'T THIS
THROWING A LOT OF MONEY AWAY IF
WE'RE LOOKING AT A THIRD OF
THESE PEOPLE ARE NOT GOING TO
COMPLETE COLLEGE?
>> NO, IT IS NOT THROWING-- IT
IS AN EXTRAORDINARY INVESTMENT
FOR THIS COUNTRY.
GERMANY, MANY OTHER COUNTRIES DO
IT ALREADY.
IN FACT, IF YOU REMEMBER, 50, 60
YEARS AGO, THE UNIVERSITY OF
CALIFORNIA, CITY UNIVERSITY OF
NEW YORK WERE VIRTUALLY
TUITION-FREE.
HERE IS THE STORY-- IT'S NOT
JUST THE COLLEGE GRADUATE SHOULD
BE $50,000 OR $100,000 IN DEBT.
MORE IMPORTANTLY, I WANT KIDS IN
BURLINGTON, VERM, OR BALTIMORE,
MARYLAND, WHO ARE IN THE SIXTH
GRADE OR THE EIGHTH GRADE, WHO
DON'T HAVE A LOT OF MONEY, WHOSE
PARENTS-- LIKE MY PARENTS-- MAY
NEVER HAVE GONE TO COLLEGE.
DO YOU KNOW WHAT I WANT, KEVIN?
I WANT THOSE KIDS TO KNOW IF
THEY STUDY HARD, THEY DO THEIR
HOMEWORK, REGARDLESS OF THE
INCOME OF THEIR FAMILIES, THEY
WILL IN FACT BE ABLE TO GET A
COLLEGE EDUCATION BECAUSE WE ARE
GOING TO MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGES
AND UNIVERSITIES TUITION-FREE.
THIS IS REVOLUTIONARY FOR
EDUCATION IN AMERICA.
IT WILL GIVE HOPE TO MILLIONS OF
YOUNG PEOPLE.
>> WELL, ONE OF THE THINGS YOU
WANT TO DO IS TO HAVE THE STATES
PAY FOR ABOUT A THIRD OF THE $70
BILLION PLAN, CORRECT.
THERE ARE 16 STATES RUNNING
BUDGET DEFICITS RIGHT NOW.
WHERE ARE ARE THEY EXPECTED TO
COME UP WITH THIS?
>> I THINK THEY WILL BE PRETTY
SMART.
I THINK A LOT OF THE STATES WILL
DO THE RIGHT THING AND I THINK
THOSE STATES THAT DON'T WILL PAY
A HEAVY PENALTY.
BOTTOM LINE, IN THE YEAR 2013,
WE SHOULD LOOK AT A COLLEGE
DEGREE THE SAME WAY WE LOOKED AT
A HIGH SCHOOL DEGREE 50 OR 60
YEARS AGO.
IF YOU WANT TO MAKE IT INTO THE
MIDDLE CLASS-- I'M NOT SAYING IN
ALL CASES.
WE MEADE PLUMBERS AND CARPENTERS
AND ELECTRICKSES, THAT'S FOR
SURE.
BUT BUT THE BOTTOM LINE NOW, IN
AMERICA, IN 2015, ANY PERSON WHO
HAS THE ABILITY AND DESIRE
SHOULD BE ABLE TO GET AN
EDUCATION, COLLEGE EDUCATION,
REGARDLESS OF THE INCOME OF HIS
OR HER FAMILY.
AND WE MUST SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER,
AS MY LEGISLATION DOES, INTEREST
RATES ON STUDENT DEBT.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, JUMP IN,
YEAH.
>> OKAY, THANK YOU.
( APPLAUSE )
I HAVE-- LOOK, I WOULD AGREE
WITH MUCH OF WHAT SENATOR
SANDERS SAYS, KEVIN.
I BELIEVE THAT ACTUALLY
AFFORDABLE COLLEGE, DEBT-FREE
COLLEGE IS THE GOAL WE NEED TO
ATTAIN AS A NATION.
AND UNLIKE MY TWO DISTINGUISHED
COLLEAGUES ON THIS STAGE, I
ACTUALLY MADE COLLEGE MORE
AFFORDABLE AND WAS THE ONLY
STATE THAT WENT FOUR YEARS IN A
ROW WITHOUT A PENNY'S INCREASE
TO COLLEGE TUITION.
I RESPECTFULLY DISAGREE WITH
SENATOR SANDER'S APPROACH.
I BELIEVE THE GOAL SHOULD BE
DEBT-FREE COLLEGE.
I BELIEVE THAT OUR FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT NEEDS TO DO MORE ON
PEL GRANTS.
STATES NEED TO STOP CUTTING
HIGHER EDUCATION AND WE SHOULD
CREATE A NEW BLOCK GRANT PROGRAM
THAT KEEPS THE STATES' SKIN IN
THE GAME, AND WE SHOULD LOWER
THESE OUTRAGEOUS INTEREST RATES
THAT PARENTS AND KIDS ARE BEING
CHARGED BY THEIR OWN GOVERNMENT,
7% AND 8% TO GO TO COLLEGE?
I MEAN, MY DAD WENT TO COLLEGE
ON A G.I. BILL AFTER COMING HOME
FROM JAPAN FLYING 33 MISSIONS.
MY DAUGHTERS WENT TO COLLEGE ON
A MOUNTAIN OF BILLS.
WE WERE PROUD OF THEM ON
GRADUATION DAY, BUT WE'RE GOING
TO BE PROUD EVERY MONTH FOR THE
REST OF OUR NATURAL LIVES.
( LAUGHTER )
( APPLAUSE )
IT DOESN'T NEED TO BE THAT WAY.
WE CAN HAVE DEBT-FREE COLLEGE IN
THE UNITED STATES.
>> KIFFEN, IF I COULD JUST JUMP
NI BELIEVE WE SHOULD MAKE
COMMUNITY COLLEGE FREE.
WE SHOULD HAVE DEBT-FREE COLLEGE
IF YOU GO TO A PUBLIC COLLEGE OR
UNIVERSITY.
YOU SHOULD NOT HAVE TO BORROW A
DIME TO PAY TUITION.
I WANT TO USE PEL GRANTS TO HELP
DEFRAY THE LIVING EXPENSES THAT
OFTEN MAKE A DIFFERENCE, WHETHER
A YOUNG PERSON CAN STAY IN
SCHOOL OR NOT.
I DISAGREE WITH FREE COLLEGE FOR
EVERYBODY.
I DON'T THINK TAXPAYERS SHOULD
BE PAYING TO SEND DONALD TRUMP'S
KIDS TO COLLEGE.
I THINK IT OUGHT TO BE A EXACT--
FAMILY CONTRIBUTE, KIDS
CONTRIBUTE.
AND TOGETHER WE MAKE IT POSSIBLE
FOR A NEW GENERATION OF YOUNG
PEOPLE TO REFINANCE THEIR DEBT
AND NOT COME OUT WITH DEBT IN
THE FUTURE.
>> ALL RIGHT, NANCY CORDES HAS A
QUESTION.
>> BACK TO HEALTH CARE, BY
POPULAR DEMAND.
FIRST TO YOU, SENATOR SANDERS.
YOU'D PREFER TO SCRAP OBAMACARE
AND MOVE TO A SINGLE-PAYER
SYSTEM, ESSENTIALLY MEDICARE FOR
ALL.
YOU SAY YOU WANT TO PUT THE
PRIVATE INSURANCE COMPANIES OUT
OF BUSINESS.
IS IT REALISTIC TO THINK THAT
YOU CAN PULL THE PLUG ON A $1
TRILLION INDUSTRY?
>> IT'S NOT GOING TO HAPPEN
TOMORROW.
AND IT'S PROBABLY NOT GOING TO
HAPPEN UNTIL WE HAVE REAL
CAMPAIGN FINANCE REFORM AND GET
RID OF ALL THESE SUPERPACS AND
THE POWER OF THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES AND THE DRUG
COMPANIES.
BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY,
NANCY, HERE IS THE QUESTION-- IN
THIS GREAT COUNTRY OF OURS, WITH
SO MUCH INTELLIGENCE AND SO MUCH
CAPABILITY, WHY DO WE REMAIN THE
ONLY MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH THAT
DOES NOT GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE
TO ALL PEOPLE AS A RIGHT?
WHY DO WE CONTINUE TO GET RIPPED
OFF BY THE DRUG COMPANIES WHO
CAN CHARGE US ANY PRICES THEY
WANT?
WHY IS IT THAT WE ARE SPENDING
PER CAPITA FAR, FAR MORE THAN
CANADA, WHICH IS 100 MILES AWAY
FROM MY DOOR, THAT GUARANTEES
HEALTH CARE TO ALL PEOPLE?
IT WILL NOT HAPPEN TOMORROW.
BUT WHEN MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
STAND UP AND ARE PREPARED TO
TAKE ON THE INSURANCE COMPANIES
AND THE DRUG COMPANIES, IT WILL
HAPPEN, AND I WILL LEAD THAT
EFFORT.
MEDICARE FOR ALL, SINGLE-PAYER
SYSTEM IS THE WAY WE SHOULD GO.
( APPLAUSE ).
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, BACK IN--
SECRETARY CLINTON, BACK IN 1994,
YOU SAID THAT MOMENTUM FOR A
SINGLE-PAYER SYSTEM WOULD SWEEP
THE COUNTRY.
THAT SOUNDS SANDERS-ESQUE.
BUT YOU DON'T FEEL THAT WAY
ANYMORE, WHY NOT?
>> REVOLUTION NEVER CAME.
I WAITED AND I GOT THE SCARS TO
SHOW FOR IT.
WE NOW HAVE THIS GREAT
ACCOMPLISHMENT KNOWN AS THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, AND I DON'T
THINK WE SHOULD HAVE TO BE
DEFENDING IT AMONG DEMOCRATS.
WE OUGHT TO BE WORKING TO
IMPROVE IT AND PREVENT
REPUBLICANS FROM BOTH
UNDERMINING IT AND EVEN
REPEALING IT.
( APPLAUSE )
I HAVE LOOKED AT-- I HAVE LOOKED
AT THE LEGISLATION THAT SENATOR
SANDERS HAS PROPOSED, AND
BASICALLY, HE DOES ELIMINATE THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, LIMB NAITS
PRIVATE INSURANCE, LIMB NAITS
MEDICARE, LIMB NAITS MEDICAID,
TRICARE, CHILDREN'S HEALTH
INSURANCE PROGRAM, PUTS IT ALL
TOGETHER IN A BIG PROGRAM WHICH
HE THEN HANDS OVER TO THE STATES
TO ADMINISTER.
AND I HAVE TO TELL YOU, I WOULD
NOT WANT-- IF I LIVED IN IOWA,
TERRY BRANDSTEAD ADMINISTERING
MY HEALTH CARE.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
I-- I THINK-- I THINK AS
DEMOCRATS WE OUGHT TO PROUDLY
SUPPORT THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT,
IMPROVE IT, AND MAKE IT THE
MODEL THAT WE KNOW IT CAN BE.
>> WELL, LET ME JUST SAY
SOMETHING.
>> 30 SECONDS.
>> WE DON'T ELIMINATE MEDICARE.
WE EXPAND MEDICARE TO ALL
PEOPLE.
AND WE WILL NOT, UNDER THIS
PROPOSAL, HAVE A SITUATION THAT
WE HAVE RIGHT NOW WITH THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT WHERE YOU
HAVE STATES LIKE SOUTH CAROLINA,
AND MANY OTHER REPUBLICAN
STATES, THAT BECAUSE OF THEIR
RIGHT WING POLITICAL IDEOLOGY
ARE DENYING MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
THE EXPANSION OF MEDICAID THAT
WE PASSED IN THE AFFORDABLE CARE
ACT.
ULTIMATELY, WE HAVE GOT TO SAY
AS A NATION, SECRETARY CLINTON,
IS HEALTH CARE A RIGHT OF ALL
PEOPLE OR IS IT NOT?
I BELIEVE IT IS A RIGHT.
>> I'M SORRY, GOVERNOR, WE'VE
GOT TO TAKE A BREAK OR THE
MACHINE BREAKS DOWN.
YOU'RE WATCHING THE DEMOCRATIC
DEBATE HERE ON CBS.
( APPLAUSE )
>> WE BEGIN THE FINAL SEGMENT OF
THIS DEBATE WITH SOMETHING NONE
OF YOU SAW COMING, SOMETHING
QUITE UNEXPECTED.
SOON AFTER YOUR INAUGURATION,
YOU WILL FACE A CRISIS.
ALL PRESIDENTS TO.
WHAT CRISIS YOU HAVE EXPERIENCED
IN YOUR LIFE THAT SUGGESTS
YOU'VE BEEN TESTD AND CAN FACE
THAT INEVITABLE CHALLENGE?
SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU FIRST.
>> WELL, THERE ARE SO MANY, I
DON'T KNOW WHERE TO START.
( LAUGHTER )
I GUESS THE ONE I-- I WOULD PICK
IS THE FACT THAT I WAS PART OF A
VERY SMALL GROUP THAT HAD TO
ADVISE THE PRESIDENT ABOUT
WHETHER OR NOT TO GO AFTER BIN
LADEN.
I SPENT A LOT OF TIME IN THE
SITUATION ROOM AS SECRETARY OF
STATE, AND THERE WERE MANY VERY
DIFFICULT CHOICES PRESENTED TO
US.
BUT PROBABLY THAT WAS THE MOST
CHALLENGING BECAUSE THERE WAS NO
CERTAINTY ATTACHED TO IT.
THE INTELLIGENCE WAS BY NO MEANS
ABSOLUTE.
WE HAD ALL KINDS OF QUESTIONS
THAT WE DISCUSSED, AND, YOU
KNOW, AT THE END, I RECOMMENDED
TO THE PRESIDENT THAT WE TAKE
THE CHANCE TO DO WHAT WE COULD
TO FIND OUT WHETHER THAT WAS BIN
LADEN AND TO FINALLY BRING HIM
TO JUSTICE.
IT WAS AN EXCRUCIATING
EXPERIENCE.
I COULDN'T TALK TO ANYBODY ABOUT
IT.
IN FACT, AFTER IT HAPPENED, THE
PRESIDENT CALLED MY HUSBAND-- HE
CALLED ALL THE FORMER PRESIDENTS
AND HE SAID, "I ASSUME HILLARY
HAS TOLD YOU ABOUT THIS."
HE SAID, "NO, NO, SHE HASN'T."
THERE WAS NOBODY TO TALK TO AND
IT REALLY DID GIVE ME AN INSIGHT
INTO THE VERY DIFFICULT PROBLEMS
PRESIDENTS FACE.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, WHAT
CRISIS PROVES THAT YOU'RE
TESTED.
>> JOHN, I DON'T THINK THAT
THERE IS A CRISIS AT THE STATE
OR LOCAL LEVEL THAT REALLY YOU
CAN POINT TO AND SAY,
"THEREFORE, I AM PREPARED FOR
THE SORT OF CRISES THAT ANY MAN
OR WOMAN WHO IS COMMANDER IN
CHIEF OF OUR COUNTRY HAS TO DEAL
WITH."
BUT I CAN TELL YOU THIS.
I CAN TELL YOU THAT AS A MAYOR
AND AS A GOVERNOR, I LEARNED
CERTAIN DISCIPLINES WHICH I
BELIEVE ARE DIRECTLY APPLICABLE
TO THAT VERY, VERY POWERFUL AND
MOST IMPORTANT OF ALL, JOBS IN
THE UNITED STATES, PRESIDENT,
WHOSE FIRST AND PRIMARY DUTY IS
TO PROTECT THE PEOPLE OF OUR
COUNTRY.
YOU LEARN THAT THREATS ALWAYS
CHANGE.
YOU LEARN TO CREATE A SECURITY
CABINET.
YOU LEARN TO CREATE FEEDBACK
MECHANISMS.
YOU LEARN TO CONSTANTLY EVALUATE
AND UNDERSTAND THE NAME OF THE
THREATS THAT YOU ARE BEING FACED
WITH.
I HAVE BEEN TRIED UNDER MANY
DIFFERENT EMERGENCIES, AND I CAN
TELL YOU THAT IN EACH OF THOSE
EMERGENCIES, WHETHER THEY WERE
INFLICTED BY DRUG GANGS, WHETHER
THEY WERE NATURAL EMERGENCIES, I
KNEW HOW TO LEAD, AND I KNEW HOW
TO GOVERN BECAUSE I KNOW HOW TO
MANAGE PEOPLE IN A CRISIS AND BE
VERY CLEAR ABOUT THE GOAL OF
PROTECTING HUMAN LIFE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS WHAT,
EXPERIENCE WOULD YOU DRAW ON IN
A CRISIS?
>> JOHN, I HAD THE HONOR OF
BEING CHAIRMAN OF THE U.S.
SENATE COMMITTEE ON VETERANS
AFFAIRS FOR TWO YEARS.
AND IN THAT CAPACITY, I MET WITH
JUST AN EXTRAORDINARY GROUP OF
PEOPLE FROM WORLD WAR II, FROM
KOREA, VIETNAM, ALL OF THE WARS.
PEOPLE CAME BACK FROM IRAQ AND
AFGHANISTAN WITHOUT LEGS,
WITHOUT ARMS.
AND I WAS DETERMINED TO DO
EVERYTHING THAT I COULD TO MAKE
V.A. HEALTH CARE THE BEST IN THE
WORLD, TO EXPAND BENEFITS TO THE
MEN AND WOMEN WHO PUT THEIR
LIVES ON THE LINE TO DEFEND ME.
WE BROUGHT TOGETHER LEGISLATION
SUPPORTED BY THE AMERICAN
LEGION, THE VFW, ALL THE
VETERANS ORGANIZATIONS, WHICH
WAS COMPREHENSIVE CLEARLY THE
BEST PIECE OF VETERANS
LEGISLATION BROUGHT FORTH IN
DECADES.
I COULD ONLY GET TWO REPUBLICAN
VOTES ON THAT.
WE ENDED UP WITH 56 VOTES.
WE NEEDED 60.
SO WHAT I HAD TO DO THEN IS GO
BACK AND START WORKING ON A BILL
THAT WASN'T THE BILL THAT I
WANTED.
SIT DOWN WITH PEOPLE LIKE JOHN
McCAIN.
SIT DOWN WITH PEOPLE LIKE JEFF
MILLER, THE REPUBLICAN CHAIRMAN
OF THE HOUSE, AND WORK ON A
BILL.
IT WASN'T THE BILL THAT I
WANTED, BUT YET IT TURNED OUT TO
BE ONE OF THE MORE SIGNIFICANT
PIECES OF VETERANS LEGISLATION
PASSED IN RECENT HISTORY.
SO THE CRISIS WAS I LOST WHAT I
WANTED.
BUT I HAD TO STAND UP AND COME
BACK AND GET THE BEST THAT WE
COULD.
>> ALL RIGHT, SENATOR SANDERS.
( APPLAUSE )
WE'VE ENDED THE EVENING ON
CRISIS, WHICH UNDERSCORES AND
REMINDS US AGAIN OF WHAT
HAPPENED LAST NIGHT.
NOW, LET'S MOVE TO CLOSING
STATEMENTS.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOU'RE FIRST.
>> JOHN, THANK YOU.
AND TO ALL OF THE PEOPLE IN
IOWA, FOR THE ROLE YOU HAVE
PERFORMED IN THIS PRESIDENTIAL
SELECTION PROCESS, IF YOU
BELIEVE THAT OUR COUNTRY'S
PROBLEMS AND THE THREATS THAT WE
FACE IN THIS WORLD CAN ONLY BE
MET WITH NEW THINKING, NEW AND
FRESH APPROACHES, THEN I ASK YOU
TO JOIN MY CAMPAIGN.
GO ON TO MARTINO'MALLEY.COM.
NO HOUR IS TOO SHORT, NO DOLLAR
TOO SMALL.
WE WILL NOT SOLVE OUR NATION'S
PROBLEMS BY RESORTING TO THE
DIVISIVE IDEOLOGIES OF OUR PAST
OR BY RETURNING TO POLARIZING
FIGURESES FROM OUR PAST.
WE ARE AT THE THRESHOLD OF A NEW
ERA OF AMERICAN PROGRESS, BUT
IT'S GOING TO REQUIRE THAT WE
ACT AS AMERICANS BASED ON OUR
PRINCIPLES, HERE AT HOME, MAKING
AN ECONOMY THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
US.
AND, ALSO, ACTING ACCORDING TO
OUR PRINCIPLES AND CONSTRUCTING
A NEW FOREIGN POLICY OF
ENGAGEMENT AND COLLABORATION AND
DOING A MUCH BETTER JOB OF
IDENTIFYING THREATS BEFORE THEY
BACK UP INTO MILITARY
CORNERRERS.
THERE IS NO CHALLENGE TOO GREAT
FOR THE UNITED STATES TO
CONFRONT, PROVIDED WE HAVE THE
ABILITY AND THE COURAGE TO PUT
FORWARD NEW LEADERSHIP THAT CAN
MOVE US TO THOSE BETTER AND
SAFER AND MORE PROSPEROUS DAYS.
I NEED YOUR HELP.
THANK YOU VERY, VERY MUCH.
( APPLAUSE )
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> WELL, THANK YOU VERY MUCH TO
CBS AND EVERYONE HERE THIS
EVENING FOR GIVING US ANOTHER
CHANCE TO APPEAR BEFORE YOU.
I'VE HEARD A LOT ABOUT ME IN
THIS DEBATE, AND I'M GOING TO
KEEP TALKING AND THINKING ABOUT
ALL OF YOU BECAUSE ULTIMATELY, I
THINK THE PRESIDENT'S JOB IS TO
DO EVERYTHING POSSIBLE,
EVERYTHING THAT SHE CAN DO TO
LIFT UP THE PEOPLE OF THIS
COUNTRY.
( APPLAUSE )
STARTING WITH OUR CHILDREN AND
MOVING FORWARD.
I'VE SPENT MY ENTIRE LIFE SINCE
I STARTED AS A YOUNG LAWYER FOR
THE CHILDRENS DEFENSE FUND,
TRYING TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE CAN
EVEN THE ODDS FOR SO MANY PEOPLE
IN AMERICA, THIS GREAT COUNTRY
OF OURS, WHO ARE BEHIND, WHO
DON'T HAVE A CHANCE.
AND THAT'S WHAT I WILL DO AS
YOUR PRESIDENT.
I WILL WORK MY HEART OUT.
I NEED YOUR HELP.
ALL OF YOU IN IOWA, I NEED YOU
TO CAUCUS FOR ME.
PLEASE GO TO HILLARY ITS
CLINTON.COM AND BE PART OF
MAKING THIS COUNTRY WHAT WE KNOW
IT CAN AND SHOULD BE.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> JOHN, JOHN, THIS COUNTRY
TODAY HAS MORE INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY THAN ANY MAJOR
COUNTRY ON EARTH.
WE HAVE A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM DOMINATED BY
SUPERPACS.
WE ARE THE ONLY MAJOR COUNTRY ON
EARTH THAT DOESN'T GUARANTEE
HEALTH CARE TO ALL PEOPLE.
WE HAVE THE HIGHEST RATE OF
CHILDHOOD POVERTY, AND WEERT
ONLY COUNTRY IN THE WORLD,
VIRTUALLY THE ONLY COUNTRY THAT
DOESN'T GUARANTEE PAID FAMILY
AND MEDICAL LEAVE.
THAT'S NOT THE AMERICA THAT I
THINK WE SHOULD BE.
BUT IN ORDER TO BRING ABOUT THE
CHANGES THAT WE NEED, WE NEED A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION.
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE ARE GOING TO
HAVE TO STAND UP, TURN OFF THE
TV, GET INVOLVED IN THE
POLITICAL PROCESS, AND TELL THE
BIG-MONEY INTERESTS THAT WE ARE
TAKING BACK OUR COUNTRY.
PLEASE GO TO
BERNIESANDERERS.COM.
PLEASE BECOME PART OF THE
POLITICAL REVOLUTION.
THANK YOU.
( CHEERS AND APPLAUSE )
>> ALL RIGHT, BACK WITH SOME
FINAL THOUGHTS IN A MOMENT.
EACH OTHER FOR A GOOD DEBATE.
CLINTON, SANDERS, AND O'MALLEY
NOW HAVE TWO DEBATES IN THE BOOK
WITH FOUR MORE TO COME.
SO MAKE, HOW DID THEY DO TONIGHT
AND WHAT'S GETTING THE MOST
TALKED ABOUT ON TWITTER?
MAJOR GARRETT IS WITH US IN THE
SPIN ALLEY.
>> SO, JOHN, OUR PARTNERSHIP
WITH TWITTER REVEALS THE MOST
TALKED ABOUT MOMENTS FOR EACH OF
THE THREE CANDIDACY.
NOW, WHEN YOU'RE HAVING THIS
KIND OF CONVERSATION, IT DOESN'T
MEAN IT'S ALL GOOD.
WHAT DROVE THE CONVERSATION
MOST, HILLARY CLINTON WHEN SHE
DEFENDED HER INTEGRITY ON
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS AND
MENTIONED 60% OF HER DONORS WERE
WOMEN.
FOR BERNIE SANDERS WHICH WHEN WE
CALLED DWIGHT D. EISENHOWER A
NOTED SOCIALIST FOR REFERRING TO
HIS INCOME BRACKETS BEING HIGH.
AND FOR GOVERNOR O'MALLEY IT WAS
WHEN HE CALLED DONALD TRUMP AN
IMMIGRANT-BASHING CARNIVAL
BARKER.
IMMIGRANT BASHING, CARNIVAL
THOSE WERE THE THREE SPIKE
MOMENTS ACCORDING TO TWITTER.
OUR PARTNERSHIP WITH THEM HAS
REVEALED THE MOST INTERESTING
MOMENTS OF CONVERSATION AS
DEFINED BY THE THREE CANDIDATES,
JOHN.
>> THANKS SO MUCH, MAJOR
GARRETT.
THANK ALWAYS OF YOU FOR JOINING
US FOR THIS DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE HOSTED BY
DRAKE UNIVERSITY IN DES MOINES,
IOWA.
CBS NEWS WILL BRING YOU A DEBATE
AMONG THE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES
FEBRUARY 13 FROM GREENVILLE,
SOUTH CAROLINA.
I WILL HAVE MUCH MORE ABOUT THE
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATES AND THE
PARIS ATTACKS TOMORROW ON "FACE
THE NATION."
OUR GUESTS INCLUDE SENATOR
SANDERS.
YOU CAN SEE MORE POSTDEBATE
COVERAGE ON CBSN.
IT'S AVAILABLE ON ALL DEVICES
AT cbsnews.com.
FOR MY CBS NEWS COLLEAGUES,
MAJOR GARRETT AND NANCY CORDES,
KEVIN COONEY FROM KCCI, AND
KATHIE OBRADOVICH FROM THE "DES
MOINES REGISTER," AND WITH
THANKS TO ALL THE FOLKS HERE AT
DRAKE FOR THEIR HOSPITALITY, I'M
JOHN DICKERSON.
GOOD NIGHT.
( APPLAUSE )