>>.
>>> THE MIDDLE CLASS NEEDS A
RAISE AND WE'RE GOING TO GIVE IT
TO YOU.
>> THIS IS NOT AN AMERICAN
ECONOMY.
IT IS A RIGGED ECONOMY.
>> I VOTED FOR COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM, SENATOR
SANDERS VOTED AGAINST IT.
>> I VOTED AGAINST IT BECAUSE
THE GUEST WORKER PROGRAMS WERE
AKINTON SLAVERY.
>> THE KIND OF CRITICISM THAT
WE'VE HEARD FROM SENATOR SANDERS
ABOUT OUR PRESIDENT I DO NOT
EXPECT FROM SOMEONE RUNNING FOR
THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINATION.
>> MADAME SECRETARY, THAT IS A
LOW BLOW.
ONE OF US RAN AGAINST BARACK
OBAMA.
I WAS NOT THAT CANDIDATE.
>> I IS WORK MY HEART OUT TO
MAKE PROGRESS IN OUR COUNTRY.
GIVE US ALL THE OPPORTUNITY THAT
WE SHOULD HAVE YOU.
>> IT IS JUST TOO LATE FOR THE
SAME OLD ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS.
THE PEOPLE WANT REAL CHANGE.
>> THE CLINTON, SANDERS FWOUN
HALL LIVE FROM LAS VEGAS,
NEVADA.
HERE NOW CHUCK TODD AND JOSE
DIAZ-BALART.
>>> GOOD EVENING, AND WELCOME TO
THE MSNBC TELEMUNDO
CLINTON-SANDERS TOWN HALL.
>> WE'RE LIVE FROM LAS VEGAS AT
THIS UNIQUE SPACE DESIGNED BY
RENOWNED ARCHITECT FRANK GEHRY.
[ SPEAKING SPANISH ]
>> THANK YOU TO THE NEVADA
DEMOCRATIC PARTY FOR HELPING US
PUT THIS TOGETHER TONIGHT.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
WHAT A GREAT SPACE.
>> WE CANVASSED THE STATE AND
TALKED TO MANY PEOPLE ABOUT WHAT
THEY WANT TO ASK AND CHOSE THIS
AUDIENCE OF ABOUT 350 PEOPLE.
AND MANY OF THEM WILL GET A
CHANCE TO HAVE THEIR SAY WITH
THE CANDIDATES.
>> WE WILL SPEND TIME FOCUSING
ON TOPICS THAT RESONATE WITH
LATINO VOTERS.
FIRST CHANCE TO DO THAT DURING
THIS CAMPAIGN.
BUT FIRST, JOSE AND I WILL HAVE
A COUPLE OF QUESTIONS THAT WE'D
LIKE TO ASK BOTH OF THE
CANDIDATES.
WE'LL BE STARTING WITH SENATOR
BERNIE SANDERS TONIGHT.
HE WON A COIN TOSS, WHICH MEANS
HE WILL BE COMING OUT HERE
FIRST.
SO PLEASE JOIN US IN WELCOMING
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, A PLEASURE TO SEE
YOU.
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> SENATOR, IT'S GREAT TO SEE
YOU.
HOW YOU DOING?
>> I AM GREAT.
>> GOOD.
WE'RE HAPPY YOU'RE HERE WITH US.
SENATOR, LET ME START BY TELLING
YOU A LITTLE BIT ABOUT SECRETARY
CLINTON WHO HAS BEEN DESCRIBING
YOU RECENTLY AS A SINGLE ISSUE
CANDIDATE.
YOU DISAGREE WITH THAT
CHARACTERIZATION.
THERE WEEK YOU TOLD MY COLLEAGUE
THAT YOU'RE ONE LITMUS TEST FOR
SUPREME COURT NOMINEE IS
OVERTURNING CITIZENS UNITED.
WHY DOESN'T THAT PROVE AN WHAT
SHE SAYS BUT?
YOU DIDN'T SAY YOU HAVE A ROE
VERSUS WADE LITMUS TEST.
A MARRIAGE EQUALITY LITMUS TEST.
>> I DON'T THINK WHAT'S THAT
SECRETARY CLINTON IS ACTUALLY
TALKING ABOUT.
IF SHE HAPPENED TO COME TO ONE
OF MY RALLIES, WHICH SHE HAS NOT
YET, BUT I WELCOME HER, SHE
WOULD HEAR ME SPEAKING FOR ABOUT
AN HOUR AND A HALF FOR AN HOUR
AND 15 MINUTES.
AND WE WOULD COVER 15 OR 20
SEPARATE ISSUES.
I'M NOT QUITE SURE WHERE SHE
COMES UP WITH THIS SINGLE ISSUE
IDEA.
BUT DO I BELIEVE THAT THERE HAS
TO BE A MAJOR FOCUS ON THE
ECONOMY WHEN THE MIDDLE CLASS IS
DISAPPEARING, WHEN PEOPLE IN
NEVADA AND ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY
ARE WORKING LONGER HOURS FOR
LOWER WAGES AND ALMOST ALL NEW
INCOME IS GOING TO THE TOP 1%?
YES, I'M GOING TO FOCUS ON THAT.
TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION ABOUT
CITIZENS UNITES, WHY IS THAT A
TEST FOR ME?
BECAUSE IF WE CONTINUE GOING THE
WAY WE ARE GOING, JOSE, IN TERMS
OF A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN FINANCE
SYSTEM, YOU KNOW WHAT'S GOING TO
END UP HAPPENING?
A HANDFUL OF BILLIONAIRES WILL
CONTROL THE POLITICAL LIFE OF
THIS COUNTRY AND UNDERMINE
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY AND WHAT MEN
AND WOMEN HAVE FOUGHT TO DEFEND.
SO TO ME, THERE IS AN UNDERLYING
ENORMOUS ISSUE.
>> BUT THAT IS THE PRIORITY.
IT IS THE LITMUS TEST.
NOT ONE OF THEM, IT'S THE LITMUS
TEST.
>>> THAT'S NOT WHAT WE IS
TALKING ABOUT.
I THINK SHE'S TALKING ABOUT MY
FOCUS ON WALL STREET.
IF YOU ARE ASKING ME DO I THINK
WE HAVE GOT TO OVERTURN THIS
DISASTROUS CITIZENS UNITED
SUPREME COURT DECISION, SO THAT
BILLIONAIRES WILL NOT BE ABLE TO
PUMP UNLIMITED SUMS OF MONEY
INTO SUPER PACS AND BUY
ELECTIONS, I DO BELIEVE THAT IS
AN ENORMOUSLY IMPORTANT ISSUE.
>> TALK ABOUT A JUDGE THIS WEEK
IN CALIFORNIA THAT ORDERED APPLE
TO HELP THE FBI UNLOCK AN iPHONE
BELONGING TO ONE OF THE TWO
TERRORISTS THAT KILLED 14 PEOPLE
AND INJURED 22 OTHERS IN SAN
BERNARDINO, CALIFORNIA.
IN RESPONSE, TIM COOK WROTE AN
OPEN LETTER TO CALL ATTENTION TO
WHAT HE CALLS THE CHILLING
IMPLICATIONS OF COMPLYING WITH
THE COURT'S ORDER.
HE WROTE AMONG OTHER THINGS
ULTIMATELY WE FEAR THIS DEMAND
WOULD UNDERMINE THE VET FREEDOMS
AND LIBERTY OUR GOVERNMENT IS
MEANT TO PROTECT.
I KNOW YOU'VE TALKED A LOT ABOUT
BIG BROTHER.
WLOS SIDE ARE YOU ON, APPLE OR
THE FBI'S?
>> I'M ON BOTH.
THIS IS A VERY COMPLICATED
ISSUE.
HERE'S WHAT THE ISSUE IS.
COOK HAS A VERY IMPORTANT POINT
TO BE MADE.
I AM VERY FEARFUL IN AMERICA
ABOUT BIG BROTHER.
AND THAT MEANS NOT ONLY THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT GETTING INTO
THE -- INTO YOUR E-MAILS OR
KNOWING WHAT BOOKS YOU'RE TAKING
OUT OF THE LIBRARY, OR PRIVATE
CORPORATIONS KNOWING EVERYTHING
THERE ALSO TO KNOW ABOUT YOU IN
TERMS OF YOUR HEALTH RECORDS,
YOUR BANKING RECORDS, YOUR
CONSUMER PRACTICES, I WORRY
ABOUT THAT VERY, VERY MUCH.
ON THE OTHER HAND, WHAT I ALSO
WORRY ABOUT IS THE POSSIBILITY
OF ANOTHER TERRORIST ATTACK
AGAINST OUR COUNTRY.
AND FRANKLY.
>> Reporter: THINK THERE IS A
MIDDLE GROUND THAT CAN BE
REACHED.
CLEARLY, ALL OF US WOULD BE VERY
DISMAYED IF WE LEARNED THAT WE
COULD HAVE PICKED UP INFORMATION
ABOUT A POTENTIAL TERRORIST ACT
AND WE DIDN'T DO THAT.
PEOPLE WOULD NOT FEEL GOOD ABOUT
THIS.
I THINK THERE HAS GOT TO BE A
BALANCE.
COUNT ME IN AS SOMEBODY WHO IS A
VERY STRONG CIVIL LISH ARIANE
WHO BELIEVES THAT WE CAN FIGHT
TERRORISM WITHOUT UNDERMINING
OUR CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT AND OUR
PRIVACY RIGHTS INSTITUTE
SENATOR, A COUPLE MORE BEFORE WE
GET TO THE AUDIENCE.
LAST WEEK YOU SAID IT WAS A LO
BLOW FOR SECRETARY CLINTON TO
BRING UP PAST CRITICISMS YOU HAD
FOR PRESIDENT OBAMA.
YOU SAID YOU HAD EVERY RIGHT TO
DISAGREE WITH HIM.
THIS IS YOU CALLING FOR A
PRIMARY CHALLENGE AND IT WAS ON
A RADIO SHOW.
I'M GOING TO PLAY IT AND GET YOU
TO REACT TO IT ON THE OTHER
SIDE.
>> ONE OF THE REASONS THE
PRESIDENT HAS BEEN ABLE TO BE
MOVE SO FAR ARE TO THE RIGHT,
THERE IS NO PRIMARY OPPOSITION
TO HIM.
I THINK IT WOULD DO THIS COUNTRY
A GOOD DEAL OF SERVICE IF PEOPLE
STARTED THINKING ABOUT
CANDIDATES OUT THERE TO BEGIN
CONTRASTING WHAT IS A
PROGRESSIVE AGENDA AS OPPOSED TO
WHAT OBAMA IS DOING.
>> THAT WAS YOU IN 2011.
I UNDERSTAND THAT.
>> BUT THAT WAS IN RESPONSE TO A
QUESTION ON A RADIO SHOW.
>> AND I GET THAT.
BUT THERE ARE SOME DEMOCRATS WHO
WANT TO CONTINUE THE PRESIDENT'S
POLICIES.
WHY SHOULD THEY TRUST YOU AS
SOMEBODY WHO WANTED HIM
APPEARED?
YOU SAID IT WOULD HAVE BEEN A
GOOD IDEA IF HE WOULD HAVE BEEN
PRIMARIED.
>> BY THE WAY, THERE IS ONE OF
THE TWO DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES
HERE WHO ACTUALLY RAN AGAINST
BARACK OBAMA.
IT WASN'T ME.
ALL RIGHT.
SECOND OF ALL, YOU KNOW, I HAVE
WORKED VERY CLOSELY WITH
PRESIDENT OBAMA OVER THE LAST
SEVEN YEARS.
HE IS A FRIEND OF MINE.
AND WE HAVE GONE A LONG WAY
TOGETHER TO MOVE THIS COUNTRY
FORWARD FROM THE DISASTROUS
POSITION WE WERE IN WHEN BUSH
LEFT OFFICE.
WHEN BUSH LEFT OFFICE, WE WERE
LOSING 800,000 JOBS A MONTH.
AND THE WORLD'S FINANCIAL SYSTEM
WAS ON THE VERGE OF COLLAPSE.
AND APPLAUD PRESIDENT OBAMA AND
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN FOR THE
WORK THEY DID AND I WORKED WITH
THEM.
BUT TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, DO
WE HAVE A RIGHT TO HAVE
DIFFERENCES OF OPINION WITH
PRESIDENT OBAMA?
I HAVE HAD A NUMBER.
FOR EXAMPLE, I HAVE DISAGREED
WITH HIM VERY STRONGLY ON HIS
VIEWS ON TRADE.
HE IS FOR THE TPP, I AM AGAINST
THE TPP.
HE HAS SEVERAL YEARS AGO
CONTINUED BUSH'S TAX BREAKS FOR
THE VERY WEALTHIEST PEOPLE IN
THIS COUNTRY.
I WAS ON THE FLOOR FOR 8 1/2
HOURS IN DISAGREEMENT WITH HIM.
OVERALL, I THINK THE PRESIDENT
HAS DONE AN OUTSTANDING JOB.
AND THE IDEA THAT THERE CAN BE A
PRIMARY WHERE DIFFERENT IDEAS
GET FLOATED AND DEBATED, I DON'T
THINK THAT THAT IS TERRIBLE.
>> YOU STILL THINK HE SHOULD
HAVE BEEN PRIMARIED.
>> THIS IS A MEDIA ISSUE.
THIS IS ONE THING I SAID ON ONE
RADIO SHOW MANY, MANY YEARS AGO.
MEDIA LIKES THAT ISSUE.
BOTTOM LINE IS, I HAPPEN TO
THINK THAT THE PRESIDENT HAS
DONE AN EXTRAORDINARILY GOOD
JOB.
HAVE I WORKED WITH HIM ON ISSUE
OF AN ISSUE.
>> NOW, QUICKLY, I THIS HAPPENED
EARLIER TODAY ON YOUR PLANE
DURING A QUICK PRESS GAGGLE.
YOU WERE PRETTY TOUGH ON BILL
CLINTON'S RECORD AND YOU SAID
YOU HIT HIS RECORD ON WALL
STREET AND SAID HE WANTED TO
DEREGULATE WALL STREET, FOR
WELFARE REFORM, THE WELFARE
REFORM ACT YOU DIDN'T LIKE AND
GOT NAFTA LIKE.
IT DIDN'T SOUND LIKE A
PRESIDENCY YOU WERE VERY PLEASED
WITH.
>> I WAS ASKED TO COMMENT ON
BILL CLINTON'S VERY, VERY STRONG
CRITICISMS OF ME.
CHUCK, PUT IT INTO CONTEXT.
I DIDN'T GO AROUND ATTACKING
BILL CLINTON.
IT WAS BILL CLINTON HAS BEEN ON
THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL MAKING SOME
VERY NASTY COMMENTS ABOUT ME.
I WAS ASKED ABOUT THAT.
SO I HAPPEN TO THINK BILL
CLINTON DID A PRETTY GOOD JOB AS
PRESIDENT.
LET'S BE CLEAR.
I HAPPEN TO THINK TRADE
AGREEMENTS FROM NAFTA THROUGH
TPP HAVE BEEN A DISASTER.
NAFTA WAS PUSHED THROUGH BY
PRESIDENT CLINTON.
I FOUGHT VERY HARD AGAINST THE
DEREGULATION OF WALL STREET.
WALL STREET PUT BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS IN ORDER TO GET
DEREGULATED SEWED THAT LARGE
INSURANCE COMPANIES, AND
INVESTOR BANKS AND COMMERCIAL
BANKS COULD BE MERGED TOGETHER.
I THOUGHT THAT WAS A BAD IDEA.
THAT WAS WHART OF WHAT THE
CLINTON ADMINISTRATION WAS
PUSHING.
IN TERMS OF SO-CALLED WELFARE
REFORM, THAT LEGISLATION ENDED
UP INCREASING EXTREME POVERTY IN
AMERICA.
THE POOREST CHILDREN IN THIS
COUNTRY.
I SPOKE OUT AGAINST THAT.
I THOUGHT THAT WAS SCAPEGOATING
SOME OF THE MOST VULNERABLE
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY.
OVERALL, DO I THINK CLINTON DID
A GOOD JOB, I DO.
BUT THOSE ARE THREE AREAS WHERE
I DISAGREE WITH HIM.
LET ME BE VERY CLEAR.
IF ANYBODY THINKS THAT A MEMBER
OF THE UNITED STATES SENATE OR
THE UNITED STATES HOUSE HAS TO
AGREE WITH SOMEBODY IN HIS OWN
PARTY WHO IS PRESIDENT, WELL,
YOU KNOW, ALL OF THE TIME, THAT
IS NOT MY UNDERSTANDING OF THE
DEMOCRACY.
>> GIVEN THAT WE HARRY REID IN
THE AUDIENCE, I THINK HE KNOWS
HOW HARD IT IS TO HERD PEOPLE IN
YOUR OWN PARTY.
I WILL GRANT YOU.
IT IS TIME TO GET QUESTIONS FROM
THE AUDIENCE.
SO LET'S GET STARTED THERE.
>> LET ME JUST IF I MIGHT, JUST
SAY THERE AS I SEE HARRY REID,
THE PEOPLE OF NEVADA I BELIEVE
ARE GOING TO MISS HIM FOR ALL OF
LIS ENORMOUS ACCOMPLISHMENTS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AS WILL THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED
STATES.
IT IS TOUGH TO BE A DEMOCRATIC
LEADER.
WE ARE PROGRESSIVES.
YOU'VE GOT MORE CONSERVATIVE
PEOPLE.
HE'S KEPT THAT COALITION GOING.
THIS COUNTRY OWES HARRY REID A
REAL DEBT OF GRATITUDE.
>> THANK YOU.
NOW, AS WE SAID, WE HAVE A ABOUT
350 PEOPLE HERE.
FULL DISCLOSURE, EACH CAMPAIGN
GOT ABOUT 30 SEATS.
THERE WERE ABOUT 40 PEOPLE FROM
THE NEVADA DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
BUT MOSTLY WE WENT OUT AND FOUND
PEOPLE WHO WERE INTERESTED IN
THE CAMPAIGN AND WANT TO KNOW
MORE ABOUT EACH CANDIDATE.
WE'RE STARTING TONIGHT WITH THE
TOPIC OF IMMIGRATION.
THIS IS AN UNDOCUMENTED
20-YEAR-OLD WHO CAN LEGALLY STAY
IN THIS COUNTRY BECAUSE OF THE
PRESIDENT'S EXECUTIVE ACTION
THAT HOLDS KIDS AVAILABLE TO
STAY IN THIS COUNTRY EVEN THOUGH
THEY WERE BROUGHT HERER
ILLEGALLY TO STAY AS LONG AS
THEY'RE WORKING IN OR IN SCHOOL.
THEY CALL THEMSELVES DREAMERS.
HE SAYS HE SUPERIORS CLINTON.
WHAT IS YOUR QUESTION?
[ SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
>> SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS, YOU
STATED IN THE PAST THAT THE
REASON WHY YOU VOTED AGAINST
IMMIGRATION REFORM IN 2007 WAS
BECAUSE IT WASN'T PERFECT.
AS PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU VETO OUR
SHOT AT IMMIGRATION REFORM IF IT
WASN'T DEEMED PERFECT BY YOU?
>> WELL, I VOTED FOR IMMIGRATION
REFORM IN 2013 BECAUSE IT WAS A
MUCH BETTER PIECE OF
LEGISLATION.
I VOTED AGAINST THE
LEGISLATIONING IN 2007 IN
INGREDIENT WITH GROUPS LIKE
LULAC, ONE OF THE LARGE LATINO
ORGANIZATIONS IN AGREEMENT WITH
THE AFLCIO FOR A NUMBER OF
REASONS.
I'LL TELL YOU ONE OF THEM.
INCLUDED IN THAT LEGISLATION WAS
A GUEST WORKER PROVISION WHICH
ORGANIZATIONS SAW AS ALMOST
AKINTON SLAVERY.
GUEST WORKERS CAME IN.
AND IF THEY DIDN'T DO WHAT THEIR
BOSSES WANTED THEM TO DO, IF
THEY DIDN'T ACCEPT EXPLOITATION
AND CHEATING, THEN THEY'RE GOING
TO BE THROWN OUT OF THIS
COUNTRY.
AND MANY OF THOSE WORKERS WERE
TERRIBLY, TERRIBLY EXPLOITED.
AND THAT WAS THE MAJOR REASON
THAT I VOTED AGAINST THAT.
I DON'T WANT TO SEE WORKERS IN
THIS COUNTRY EXPLOITED.
BUT I DID VOTE FOR THE 2013 --
AND LET ME SAY THIS MORE
IMPORTANTLY.
I WANT TO TAKE 11 MILLION
UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY OUT OF THE SHADOWS.
OUT OF THE FEAR THAT THEY ARE
EXPERIENCING EVERY SINGLE DAY.
I WANT CONGRESS TO DO ITS JOB
UNDER SENATOR REID, WE DID PASS
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
UNFORTUNATELY, THE HOUSE DID
NOT.
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL DO
EVERYTHING THAT I CAN TO PASS
IMMIGRATION REFORM AND A PATH
TOWARD CITIZENSHIP FOR THOSE WHO
TODAY ARE UNDOCUMENTED.
>> EVEN IF IT'S NOT TO YOUR BEST
LIKING.
>> OF COURSE.
LOOK, IT'S NOT THAT I DIDN'T
THINK IT WAS PERFECT.
YOU KNOW, IT'S NOT A QUESTION OF
BEING PERFECT.
NOTHING IS PERFECT.
THAT WAS HAD PARTICULAR
EGREGIOUS PROVISIONS IN IT.
>>
[ SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
>> AND NOW I'D LIKE TO SAY HELLO
TO AURORA.
LIKE SO MANY MILLIONS OF OTHERS,
BE SHE IS PART OF A MIXED STATUS
FAMILY THAT LIVES WITH THE FEAR
OF DEPORTATION OF A LOVED ONE.
>> YES, MY QUESTION TO YOU, SIR,
IF YOU BECOME THE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES, WHAT WOULD
YOU DO ABOUT THE BARS?
MY HUSBAND, I'M AN AMERICAN
CITIZEN.
MY GIRS ARE AMERICAN CITIZENS.
MY HUSBAND WAS HERE 18 YEARS.
I TRIED TO BRING HIM OUT OF THE
SHADOWS AND I PETITIONED HIM AND
THEY GAVE HIM A TEN-YEAR BAR.
HE'S BEEN IN MEXICO DOING HIS
TEN YEARS, SIX YEARS NOW WE'VE
BEEN SEPARATED.
MY LITTLE GIRL WAS IN
KINDERGARTEN WHEN HE LEFT.
THE ONE IN THE PINK RIGHT THERE.
>> HOW ARE YOU?
>> AND THE OTHER ONE WAS IN
MIDDLE SCHOOL AND NOW SHE'S
GOING TO GRADUATE HIGH SCHOOL
THIS YEAR AND HER DAD IS NOT
HERE TO SEE THAT.
WHAT WOULD YOU DO TO BRING MY
HUSBAND HOME.
>> WHAT YOU JUST DESCRIBED IS
UNACCEPTABLE AND SHOULD NOT BE
HAPPENING.
MY IMMIGRATION POLICY IS TO
UNITE FAMILIES, NOT TO DIVIDE
FAMILIES.
WHEN I WAS HERE IN LAS VEGAS A
COUPLE OF MONTHS AGO, I HEARD A
STORY, A YOUNG MAN WHO WAS IN
THE UNITED STATES MILITARY WHILE
HE WAS IN THE UNITED STATES
MILITARY, HIS WIFE WAS DEPORTED.
CAN YOU BELIEVE THAT.
>> YES.
>> ALL RIGHT.
CLEARLY THOSE ARE NOT THE
POLICIES -- CLEARLY THOSE ARE
NOT THE POLS THAT I WANT TO SEE
AND I WILL CHANGE THOSE
POLICIES.
>> WHEN YOU CHANGE, WHEN YOU GET
THERE, HOW LONG WOULD IT TAKE TO
CHANGE THOSE POLICIES?
BECAUSE I'VE BEEN WAITING SIX
YEARS OUT OF MY LIFE.
>> WELL, I CAN'T -- WE WILL USE
OUR EXECUTIVE OFFICE AND POWER
AS MUCH AS WE CAN HOPEFULLY
WE'LL HAVE THE COOPERATION OF
THE UNITED STATES CONGRESS.
>> THANK YOU.
>> HE ALL RIGHT, WE'LL STICK
WITH THE TOPIC OF IMMIGRATION.
WAYNE SMITH HAS ANOTHER QUESTION
ON IMMIGRATION.
HE HAPPENS TO BE A VETERAN.
COME ON UP.
>> YEAH, SENATOR SANDERS.
I'M HERE BOTH AS THE VICE
CHAIRMAN OF THE NEVADA
DEMOCRATIC VETERANS AND MILITARY
FAMILIES AND AS AN UNDECIDED
VOTER.
WE HAVE BECOME AWARE THAT YOU IN
THE LAST 20 YEARS THERE HAVE
BEEN HUNDREDS OF VETERANS WHO
HAVE SERVED HONORABLY AS LEGAL
U.S. RESIDENTS IN THE MILITARY.
AFTER DISCHARGE, THEY RAN AFOUL
OF THE LAW FOR POSSESSION OF
ILLEGAL DRUGS OR ANOTHER
NONVIOLENT CRIME.
AS A RESULT, THEIR LEGAL STATUS
WAS REVOKED AND THEY WERE
DEPORTED.
IN MANY CASES THESE VETERANS
ENDED UP IN COUNTRIES THEY LEFT
WHEN SMALL CHILDREN OFTEN OF
UNABLE TO EVEN SPEAK THE
LANGUAGE.
REMEMBER WE'RE TALKING ABOUT
VETERANS HERE WHO SERVED OUR
COUNTRY AND PEOPLE THAT ARE
COMRADES OF MINE IN ARMS.
IS THIS POLICY FAIR AND WHAT
WOULD YOU DO ABOUT IT IF YOU'RE
ELECTED PRESIDENT?
>> WELL, I WAS THE FORMER
CHAIRMAN OF THE U.S. SENATE
COMMITTEE ON VETERANS AFFAIRS.
AND IN THAT CAPACITY, I DID ALL
THAT I COULD TO EXPAND HEALTH
CARE AND PROVIDE THE BENEFITS
THAT OUR VETERANS ARE ENTITLED
TO.
WHAT YOU ARE DESCRIBING TO ME
SEEMS TO ME TO BE AN OUTRAGE.
IF PEOPLE PUT THEIR LIVES ON THE
LINE TO DEFEND THIS COUNTRY ARE
WILLING TO DIE FOR THIS COUNTRY,
I DON'T THINK YOU DEPORT THOSE
PEOPLE.
>> SENATOR, WHAT IS YOUR LINE
WHEN IT COMES TO WHO GETS
DEPORTED AND WHO IS NOT?
>> I DIDN'T HEAR THAT.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS DEPORTED
MORE FOLKS THAN ANY PRESIDENT.
>> YES.
>> WHAT IS YOUR CRITERIA FOR
DEPORTATION FOR FOLKS HERE IN
THIS COUNTRY UNDOCUMENTED AND
WHAT IS CRIMINAL?
BECAUSE SOME PEOPLE THINK JUST
BEING HERE UNDOCUMENTED.
>> NOT FOR NONVIOLENT TYPE
CRIMES.
IF SOMEBODY'S A VIOLENT
CRIMINAL, THEY SHOULD BE
DEPORTED.
AS I SAID, MY OWN VIEW IS THAT
OUR POLICY AS A NATION AND WHAT
I BELIEVE IS WE SHOULD UNITE
FAMILIES NOT DIVIDE FAMILIES.
WE SHOULD NOT BE SENDING PEOPLE
BACK TO A COUNTRY THAT THEY
COULD BARELY REMEMBER AND A
LANGUAGE THEY MAY NOT EVEN BE
ABLE TO SPEAK.
>> HOW QUICKLY WILL YOU GET
IMMIGRATION REFORM DONE.
>> IT IS A PRIORITY.
IT HAS TO DO WITH A LITTLE BIT
OF COOPERATION FROM THE
CONGRESS.
BUT IT IS A MAJOR PRIORITY.
WHEN YOU HAVE 11 MILLION PEOPLE
LIVING IN THE SHADOWS, I THINK
WE OWE IT TO THEM TO MOVE AS
EXPEDITIOUSLY AS WE CAN.
IF CONGRESS DOES NOT ACT, I WILL
CONTINUE PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
EFFORTS TO USE EXECUTIVE POWERS.
>> SENATOR, WE'RE GOING TO
CHANGE THE SUBJECT.
MY NEXT QUESTION COMES FROM
TAYLOR.
HE TELLS US HE IS SUPPORTING
CLINTON BUT HE HAS A QUESTION
REGARDING YOUR ECONOMIC.
>> ANYBODY HERE SUPPORTING ME?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, DON'T WORRY.
>> JUST WANTED TO MAKE SURE,
CHUCK.
YOU KNOW.
>> DON'T WORRY.
WE'RE JUST DOING FULL DISCLOSURE
HERE.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> OFTENTIMES YOU TREAT RACIAL
CONCERNS AS IF THEY WERE
ECONOMIC ONES SAYING REDUCING
INCOME INEQUALITY IS THE
SOLUTION.
HOW IS CREATING JOBS FOR LOW
INCOME EARN ARES GOING TO STOP A
SYSTEM OF POLICE BRUTALITY
TOWARD BLACK AMERICANS A SYSTEM
OF MASS INCARCERATION FOR BLACK
MEN OR A POOR EDUCATION FOR THE
PREDOMINANTLY BLACK CITIES
ACROSS AMERICA.
>> I WOULD SUGGEST YOU GO TO MY
WEBSITE, BERNIE SANDERS.COM
WHICH HAS A VERY, VERY EXTENSIVE
PROGRAM REGARDING THE ISSUES
THAT YOU TALKED ABOUT.
LET'S TALK ABOUT IT.
ALL RIGHT.
WE'VE GOT MORE PEOPLE IN JAIL
TODAY IN THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY
ON EARTH.
2.2 MILLION PEOPLE LARGELY
AFRICAN-AMERICAN AND HISPANIC
WE'RE SPENDING $80 BILLION A
YEAR TO LOCK PEOPLE UP.
MAKE ANY SENSE TO ANYBODY?
NOT TO ME.
WHAT DO WE HAVE TO DO.
>> A LOT OF THINGS.
IS THERE A CONNECTION BETWEEN
ECONOMICS AND PEOPLE ENDING UP
IN JAIL?
LET ME TELL YOU SOMETHING,
TODAY, DO YOU KNOW WHAT THE
YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT FOR
AFRICAN-AMERICAN KIDS IS?
IT IS 51%.
AND SOMETIMES KIDS GET INTO
TROUBLE WHEN THEY DON'T HAVE
JOBS.
WE'RE GOING TO INVEST IN
EDUCATION AND JOBS, NOT MORE
JAILS INCARCERATION.
NUMBER TWO --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> NUMBER TWO, EVERY PERSON IN
THIS COUNTRY I HOPE, BLACK,
WHITE, LATINO,ING IS DISGUSTED
WHEN WE TURN ON THE TELEVISION
AND WE SEE VIDEOS OF UNARMED
PEOPLE OFTEN AFRICAN-AMERICANS
BEING SHOT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> OKAY?
WE NEED REAL POLICE REFORM IN
THIS COUNTRY.
POLICE DEPARTMENTS ARE RUN BY
LOCAL DEPARTMENTS.
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CAN PLAY A
MAJOR ROLE.
SO WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO IS
MAKE IT CLEAR THROUGHOUT THIS
COUNTRY THAT IF A POLICE OFFICER
BREAKS THE LAW LIKE ANY OTHER
PUBLIC OFFICIAL, THAT POLICE
OFFICER WILL BE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
WE VERY GOT TO DEMILITARIZE
LOCAL POLICE DEPARTMENTS SO THAT
HE OF THEY DO NOT LOOK LIKE
OCCUPYING ARMIES.
WE HAVE GOT TO THE MAKE POLICE
DEPARTMENTS LOOK LIKE THE
DIVERSITY OF THE COMMUNITIES
THAT THEY ARE BE.
THERE IS A WHOLE LOT THAT HAS TO
BE DONE AND I WOULD LOVE TO
CONTINUE THE DISCUSSION.
BUT PLEASE, WE'RE IN A CAMPAIGN.
AND THE SECRETARY WILL SAY WHAT
THEY'LL SAY.
I WAS ARRESTED WHEN I WAS 22
YEARS OLD AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
CHICAGO.
YOU KNOW WHAT I WAS ARRESTED
FOR?
FIGHTING SEGREGATION.
SO I HAVE THIS ISSUE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I KNOW NAY DATE MYSELF WHEN
I TELL YOU THAT IN 1963, I WAS
THERE IN WASHINGTON FOR THE
MARCH ON WASHINGTON FOR THE
MARCH ON WASHINGTON FOR JOBS AND
FREEDOM WITH DR. MARTIN LUTH ARE
KING.
THIS HAS BEEN SOMETHING THAT I
HAVE FELT STRONGLY ABOUT MY
ENTIRE LIFE.
>> I WANT TO FOLLOW UP SOMETHING
YOU SAID LAST WEEK.
YOU SAID RACE RELATIONS WOULD BE
BETTER UNDER A PRESIDENT SANDERS
THAN THEY'VE BEEN UNDER
PRESIDENT OBAMA.
WHY DO YOU BELIEVE THAT.
>> WHAT I BELIEVE IS PRESIDENT
OBAMA HAS MADE SIGNIFICANT
PROGRESS AND WE'RE GOING TO
BUILD ON THAT PROGRESS.
WE CAN ALWAYS DO BETTER.
THE PROGRESS WE CAN BUILD ON IS
TO UNDERSTAND THAT WE SHOULD NOT
HAVE THE 35% OF AFRICAN-AMERICAN
KIDS IN THIS COUNTRY LIVING IN
POVERTY.
WE SHOULD NOT HAVE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE NEED REAL POLICE REFORM.
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT WHEN
PEOPLE ARE IN JAIL, OFTEN
AFRICAN-AMERICAN AND LATINO,
THERE IS A PATH BACK, BACK TO
CIVIL SOCIETY.
SO THAT WE DON'T HAVE THE RACE
OF RECIDIVISM THAT WE DO RIGHT
NOW.
WE HAVE GOT TO DO AWAY WITH
MANDATORY MINIMUM SENTENCES.
AND I'LL GIVE YOU ONE EXAMPLE
WHERE WE CAN MAKE HUGE PROGRESS.
RIGHT NOW, IT TURNS OUT THAT THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY AND
THE WHITE COMMUNITY SMOKE
MARIJUANA AT ABOUT EQUAL LEVELS.
OKAY?
BUT IT ALSO TURNS OUT THAT
BLACKS ARE FOUR TIMES MORE
LIKELY TO BE ARRESTED THAN
WHITES FOR POSSESSION OF
MARIJUANA.
OKAY?
AND THAT IS WHY I BELIEVE THAT
WE SHOULD TAKE MARIJUANA OUT OF
THE FEDERAL CONTROLLED SUBSTANCE
ACT.
TOO MANY LIVES HAVE BEEN
DESTROYED, TOO MANY YOUNG PEOPLE
HAVE INCURRED POLICE RECORDS FOR
POSSESSION OF MARIJUANA.
>> ALL RIGHT, SENATOR.
THANK YOU.
WE HAVE A QUESTION NOW.
GO AHEAD FROM, SANDRA JIMENEZ ON
THE ISSUE OF FEMINISM.
>> GOOD EVENING, SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS.
MY QUESTION IS, DO YOU CONSIDER
YOURSELF A FEMINIST?
IF SO, HOW DO YOU AS A WHITE
MALE UNDERSTAND THE IDENTITIES
THAT PEOPLE OF COLORED FACE
ESPECIALLY WHETHER HE ENTERING
HIGH POSITIONS OF POWER WITHIN
BUSINESS OR GOVERNMENT.
>> I CONSIDER MYSELF A STRONG
FEMINIST.
AND IN FACT, GLORIA STEINEM,
EVERYBODY KNOWS GLORIA IS ONE OF
THE LEADING FEMINISTS IN AMERICA
MADE ME AN HONOR WOMAN MANY,
MANY YEARS AGO.
I DON'T KNOW EXACTLY WHAT HA
MEANT BUT I ACCEPTED IT WHEN SHE
CAME TO CAMPAIGN FOR ME.
LOOK, RIGHT NOW IN THIS COUNTRY,
WOMEN ARE MAKING 79 CENTS ON THE
DOLLAR COMPARED TO MEN.
MINORITY WOMEN, WOMEN OF COLOR
ARE MAKING SUBSTANTIALLY LESS.
AFRICAN-AMERICAN WOMEN ARE
MAKING 54 CENTS ON THE DOLLAR.
THIS IS ABSURD.
THIS HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH
ECONOMICS.
IT HAS EVERYTHING TO DO WITH
SEXISM.
I WILL FIGHT AS HARD AS I CAN.
I WORK WITH HARRY REID.
WE HAVE TRIED DESPERATELY TO
PASS PAY EQUITY FOR WOMEN.
I WILL CONTINUE THAT FIGHT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, UP NEXT IS CAMERON
MILLER.
HE IS A FILMMAKER WHO HAS A
QUESTION ABOUT MINIMUM WAGE.
CAMERON, GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
I'M ALL ABOUT EVERYONE MAKING AS
MUCH MONEY AS THEY POSSIBLY CAN.
HOWEVER, IF WE INCREASE THE
MINIMUM WAGE, HOW DO WE ENSURE
THAT THAT COST ISN'T PASSED ONTO
THE CONSUMER?
>> OKAY.
HERE'S WHERE WE ARE RIGHT NOW.
WE HAVE A FEDERAL MINIMUM WAGE
OF $7.25 AN HOUR.
THAT'S WHERE WE ARE AT.
YOU COULD DO THE AN RITMATIC AS
WELL AS I DO.
MULTIPLE THAT NUMBER BY NINE
BUCKS AN HOUR, 10 BUCKS AN HOUR,
40 HOURS A WEEK, 50 WEEKS A
YEAR.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
YOU COME UP WITH A SUM WITH AN
INCOMING THAT NOBODY CAN LIVE ON
AND CERTAINLY CANNOT BRING UP A
FAMILY ON.
ALL RIGHT?
SO HERE IS MY RADICAL IDEA.
ARE YOU READY FOR A RADICAL
IDEA?
ALL RIGHT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
MY RADICAL IDEA IS THAT IN
AMERICA, IF SOMEBODY WORKS 40
HOURS A WEEK THAT, PERSON SHOULD
NOT LIVE IN POVERTY.
ALL RIGHT?
THAT'S THE RADICAL IDEA.
I BELIEVE WE SHOULD RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO A LIVING WAGE
AND THAT IS 15 BUCKS AN HOUR
OVER THE NEXT SEVERAL YEARS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I AM PROUD TO TELL YOU HAVE
I BEEN ON PICKET LINES WITH FAST
FOOD WORKERS IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
AND ELSEWHERE, AND THESE PEOPLE
DESERVE AN ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF
CREDIT FOR THEIR COURAGE AND WE
ARE MAKING REAL PROGRESS.
CITIES NOW LIKE SEATTLE,
LOS ANGELES, SAN FRANCISCO, ARE
BEGINNING, HAVE PASSED
LEGISLATION TO RAISE THE MINIMUM
WAGE OVER A PERIOD OF YEARS TO
15 BUCKS AN LAWYER.
BOTTOM LINE IS IN AMERICA TODAY,
WE HAVE MASSIVE LEVELS OF INCOME
AND WEALTH INEQUALITY.
RICH ARE GETTING MUCH, MUCH
RICHER.
TOP 20 WEALTHIEST PEOPLE IN
AMERICA NOW OWN MORE WEALTH THAN
THE BOTTOM 508% OF AMERICA, 150
MILLION PEOPLE.
WHAT MY CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT IS
SAYING WE ARE GOING OG HAVING AN
ECONOMY THAT WORKS FOR WORKING
FAMILIES AND NOT JUST THE TOP
1%.
ONE PART OF THAT IS TO RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO A LIVING WAGE,
15 BUCKS AN HOUR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HOW DO WE ENSURE THAT ONCE WE
INCREASE THAT IS TO $15 AN HOUR
THAT, WE'RE NOT CREATING A
SITUATION WHERE THOSE SAME
PEOPLE ARE NOW BELOW THE POVERTY
LINE BECAUSE PRICES ARE GOING
TO -- I WOULD ASSUME PRICES ARE
GOING TO INCREASE.
>> THE TRUTH IS, YES, YOU MAY
END UP PAYING A FEW CENTS MORE
FOR A HAMBURGER AT McDONALD'S.
BUT YOU WILL BE, IF YOU'RE THAT
WORKER GOING FROM $8 OR $10 TO
$15 AN HOUR, YOU'LL BE A LOT
BETTER OFF.
I'LL TELL YOU SOMETHING ELSE.
WE HAVE 47 MILLION PEOPLE LIVING
IN POVERTY TODAY.
WE HAVE PEOPLE GO TO EMERGENCY
FOOD SHELVES WHO WORK 40 HOURS A
WEEK BUT ARE NOT EARNING ENOUGH
MONEY TO PROVIDE FOR THEIR
FAMILY.
WHEN WE PUT MONEY INTO THE HANDS
OF WORKING PEOPLE, YOU KNOW
WHAT, THEY CAN GO OUT AND BUY
PRODUCTS.
THEY CAN GO SHOPPING.
WHEN THEY DO THAT, THEY CREATE
JOBS.
SO INSTEAD OF GIVING TAX BREAKS
TO BILLIONAIRES AND THINKING
THAT'S GOING TO TRICKLE ON DOWN,
MY VIEW IS YOU PUT MONEY INTO
THE HANDS OF WORKING PEOPLE WHO
SPEND IT AND THEN CREATE MORE
JOBS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SENATOR, ONE QUESTION
CONSEQUENCE FROM HIGH SCHOOLER
JESS KAES WHO WILL BE VOTING FOR
OT FIRST TIME THIS YEAR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> JESSICA?
>> SO MY QUESTION TO YOU IS I'M
A STUDENT.
SO I LIKE HOW YOU WANT FREE
EDUCATION.
BUT WHAT IS YOUR PLAN TOP
POSSIBLY ACHIEVE THIS BEING THAT
IT WOULD COST ABOUT $70 BILLION
PER YEAR MORE THAN TWICE WHAT
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SPENDS ON
PEL GRANTS.
>> EXCELLENT.
>> WAIT, I'M NOT FINISHED.
>> OH.
>> SO WOULD FREE COLLEGE MAKE
HIGHER EDUCATION MORE EFFICIENT,
MORE INNOVATIVE AND HIGHER
QUALITY.
>> I'M SORRY, I DIDN'T GET THE
POINT OF THE LAST.
>> SO WOULD FREE COLLEGE MAKE
HIGHER EDUCATION MORE EFFICIENT,
MORE INNOVATIVE AND HIGHER
QUALITY?
>> LET ME ANSWER IT IN THIS WAY.
OKAY, AND THIS IS SOMETHING I
FEEL VERY STRONGLY ABOUT.
00, 150 YEARS AGO, VERY BRAVE
AMERICANS FOUGHT FOR THE CONCEPT
OF FREE PUBLIC EDUCATION.
AND WHAT THEY WERE SAYING IS YOU
KNOW, WORKING CLASS KIDS, LOW
INCOME PEOPLE, THEIR KIDS HAVE A
RIGHT TO GET FREE EDUCATION, IT
SHOULDN'T JUST BE AVAILABLE TO
WEALTHY FAMILIES.
THEIR KIDS SHOULDN'T HAVE TO
WORK IN FACTORIES OR ON FARMS.
HUGE ACHIEVEMENT.
WHAT PUBLIC EDUCATION HAS BEEN
IN THIS COUNTRY FROM DAY ONE IS
SAYING FREE EDUCATION FOR THE
FIRST GRADE THROUGH GRADE 12.
THAT'S GREAT.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT?
THE WORLD HAS CHANGED.
TODAY IN 2016, IN MANY RESPECTS,
A COLLEGE DEGREE IS THE
EQUIVALENT OF WHAT A HIGH SCHOOL
DEGREE WAS 50 OR 60 YEARS AGO IN
TERMS OF GOING OUT AND GETTING A
GOOD JOB.
I BELIEVE THAT TODAY, WHEN WE
TALK ABOUT PUBLIC EDUCATION, IT
SHOULD INCLUDE FREE TUITION AT
PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES.
THAT'S WHAT I BELIEVE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND WHY THAT IS A REVOLUTIONARY
IDEA, MY PARENTS MY DAD CAME TO
THIS COUNTRY FROM POLAND
IMMIGRATED HERE, DROPPED OUT OF
HIGH SCHOOL.
MOM NEVER WENT TO COLLEGE.
THERE ARE MILLIONS FROM KIDS IN
THIS COUNTRY WHO TODAY BECAUSE
OF THEIR ECONOMIC CIRCUMSTANCES
NEVER BELIEVED THEY'RE GOING TO
BE ABLE TO MAKE IT TO COLLEGE.
WLA WANT IS FOR EVERY CHILD IN
AMERICA REGARDLESS OF THE INCOME
OF HIS OR HER FAMILY TO KNOW
THAT IF THEY STUDY HARD, TAKE
SCHOOL SERIOUSLY, YES, THEY WILL
BE ABLE TO GET A COLLEGE
EDUCATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW, TO ANSWER YOU RAISED A VERY
GOOD QUESTION AND YOUR NUMBER
WAS EXACTLY RIGHT.
THE OTHER THING THAT I WANT TO
THE DO IS LOWER STUDENT DEBT IN
THIS COUNTRY.
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE ARE BEING
CRUSHED WITH HIGH STUDENT DEBT.
EVERY PLACE I GO, $50,000,
$100,000, $300,000 GOING TO
MEDICAL SCHOOL.
WE ARE FIGHTING FOR BOTH OF
THOSE PROVISIONS.
NOW, YOU'RE RIGHT.
IT WILL COST $70 BILLION A YEAR.
THAT'S A LOT OF MONEY.
A LOT OF MONEY.
HOW AM I GOING TO PAY FOR IT?
TELL YOU HOW I'M GOING TO PAY
FOR IT.
WHEN WALL STREET'S ILLEGAL
ACTIVITIES HELPED DESTROY THIS
ECONOMY AND LIT THE STATE OF
NEVADA PROBABLY HARDER THAN ANY
OTHER STATE IN THIS COUNTRY, YOU
KNOW WHAT HAPPENED?
CONGRESS BAILED OUT THE ILLEGAL
BEHAVIOR ON WALL STREET.
WELL, YOU KNOW WHAT?
WALL STREET'S DOING OKAY NOW.
I THINK WE SHOULD IMPOSE A TAX
ON WALL STREET SPECULATION.
IT IS WALL STREET'S TIME TO HELP
THE MIDDLE CLASS OF THIS
COUNTRY.
THAT WILL RAISE ALL THE MONEY
THAT WE NEED.
>> THANK YOU.
WE ARE GOING TO TAKE A SHORT
BREAK.
WHETHER HE WE COME BACK, WE'RE
GOING TO BE TALKING ABOUT
AFFORDABLE HEALTH CARE AND A
WHOLE LOT MORE.
[ SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
WELCOME BACK HERE TO LAS VEGAS,
OUR CLINTON-SAND AREAS TOWN
HALL.
SENATOR SANDERS IS UP.
WE HAVE SOME VETERANS ISSUES.
THIS IS A STATE, OF COURSE,
WHERE THE UNEMPLOYMENT RATE FOR
VETERANS IS MORE THAN A THIRD
HIGHER THAN THE RATE FOR
VETERANS NATIONWIDE.
I WANT TO BRING UP VANESSA.
SHE SERVED IN IRAQ AND IS A
MEMBER OF THE ARMY RESERVES.
SHE HAS A QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> GOOD EVENING, SENATOR.
NOW, VETERANS ARE ALWAYS THANKED
FOR THEIR SERVICE AND ALL OF THE
CANDIDATES SAY THAT THEY SUPPORT
VETERANS.
BUT UNFORTUNATELY, THAT SUPPORT
HAS NOT TRANSLATED INTO JOBS,
AND I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW HOW
YOUAL ENSURE THAT SUPPORT
TRANSLATES INTO GETTING VETERANS
HIRED AND NOT ONLY HIRED BUT
GETTING THEM JOBS THAT ARE
COMMENSURATE WITH THEIR SKILLS
AND ABILITIES.
>> WELL, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YOUR POINT IS WELL TAKEN.
EVERYBODY THANKS THE VETERANS
BUT SOMETIMES AFTER THEY COME
HOME, WE HAVE A TENDENCY TO
FORGET ABOUT THEM.
AND THE STRUGGLES THAT THEY GO
THROUGH.
I WAS CHAIRMAN OF THE VETERANS
COMMITTEE FOR TWO YEARS.
AND IN THAT CAPACITY, PASSED IN
A BIPARTISAN WAY THE MOST
COMPREHENSIVE VETERANS HEALTH
CARE LEGISLATION PASSED IN THE
MODERN HISTORY OF THIS COUNTRY.
AND WE ALSO DID SOME OTHER
THINGS IN THAT LEGISLATION.
TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, WE'VE
GOT TO DO A NUMBER OF THINGS.
IN OTHER WORDS, WE HAVE TO GIVE
A PRIORITY IN TERMS OF FEDERAL
EMPLOYMENT.
AND SECOND OF ALL WHAT WE HAVE
TO DO WHICH WE DON'T DO ENOUGH
IS PEOPLE IN THE MILITARY
DEVELOP A LOT OF REALLY GOOD
SKILLS.
YOU KNOW, WHETHER IT'S DRIVING A
TRUCK OR BEING A PARAMEDIC.
WE HAVE GOT TO MAKE SURE THAT
THE SKILLS THAT THEY HAVE
ACQUIRED IN THE MILITARY ARE
TRANSFERABLE TO THE CIVIL
SOCIETY.
SO WHEN THEY WALK IN -- AND THAT
IS NOT OFTEN THE CASE.
SO IN OTHER WORDS, IN THE CIVIL
SOCIETY, YOU WORK THREE YEARS,
YOU KNOW, AND THEN YOU GO TO
ANOTHER JOB, YOU GET CREDIT FOR
THOSE THREE YEARS.
OFTEN THAT'S NOT THE CASE IN THE
MILITARY.
SO WE'VE GOT TO THE PRIORITIZE
MAKING SURE THAT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT AND THE PRIVATE
SECTOR HIRE VETERANS WHO OFTEN,
BY THE WAY ARE, VERY, VERY GOOD
WORKERS.
VERY GOOD WORKERS BECAUSE OF THE
DISCIPLINE THEY HAVE INCURRED IN
THE MILITARY.
THERE'S A LOT TO BE DONE, BUT
THE BOTTOM LINE IS WHEN PEOPLE
PUT THEIR LIVES ON THE LINE TO
DEFEND US, WE HAVE GOT TO
PROTECT THEM IN EVERY WAY THAT
ATHLETIC.
-- THAT WE CAN.
>> I WANT TO STICK WITH VETERANS
ISSUES HERE.
IT'S A LESS THAN 10% OF THE
POPULATION.
HERE'S VETERANS ABOUT HALF OF
THEM ARE ENROLLED IN THE VA
SYSTEM.
HE HAS A QUESTION FOR YOU AND WE
JUST LEARNED TODAY THAT HE'S A
VOLUNTEER FOR THE CLINTON
CAMPAIGN BUT I THINK THE
QUESTION IS STILL RELEVANT.
>> THANKS.
THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS, YOUR
CHAIRMANSHIP OF VETERANS AFFAIR
COMMITTEE IN CHARGE OF OVERSIGHT
FOR VA IS ARGUABLY THE MOST
IMPORTANT POSITION AND HIGHEST
RANKING YOU HELD IN GOVERNMENT.
YOU WERE A MAJOR DEFENDER OF VA
CARE DESPITE SEVEN PLUS IG
REPORTS OF MISMANAGEMENT.
AND MY VETERANS ON WEIGHT LIST.
YOU WENT TO CALL IT A SCANDAL BY
THE KOCH BROTHERS.
WE NEED SOMEONE WHO WOULD FIX
THE ISSUE, NOW THE ASCRIBE THE
BLAME.
IF ELECTED AS PRESIDENT, HOW
WILL YOU FIX THE VA TO INSURE ME
AND MY FELLOW VETERANS THAT
WE'LL RECEIVE THE CARE THAT WE
NEED.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WELL, GUESS WHAT, THE KOCH
BROTHERS AND MANY OF THEIR
ALLIES DO PRECISELY WANT TO
PRIVATIZE THE VA.
THAT'S WHAT THEY WANT TO DO.
I BELIEVE ALONG WITH THE
AMERICAN LEGION, THE VFQ, THE
DAV, VIETNAM VETS AND VIRTUALLY
ALL OF THE VETERANS ORGANIZATION
THAT IS A PRETTY BAD IDEA
BECAUSE VETERANS HAVE THEIR OWN
SPECIAL HEALTH CARE NEEDS BASED
ON THEIR SERVICE TO THIS
COUNTRY.
I WILL FIGHT TO PROTECT AND
PRESERVE THE VETERANS
ADMINISTRATION.
AS IT HAPPENED AS I JUST
MENTIONED, UNDER MY LEADERSHIP,
WITH THE SUPPORT OF SENATOR
REID, WE MANAGED TO PASS THE
LARGEST AND MOST COMPREHENSIVE
CAN VA HEALTH CARE LEGISLATION
IN THE MODERN HISTORY OF THIS
COUNTRY.
APPROXIMATELY $17 BILLION.
WHAT WE DID IS PUT BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS INTO THE VA TO PRECISELY
ADDRESS THE ISSUE OF WAITING
LISTS.
NOW, IT'S GOOD FOR SOME PEOPLE
TO SAY WELL, THERE'S A PROBLEM
BUT WE ADDRESS THE PROBLEM.
WHY WAS THERE A WAITING LIST.
>> THERE WAS A WAITING LIST IN
PHOENIX AND MANY OTHER PARTS OF
THIS COUNTRY BECAUSE THERE WERE
NOT ENOUGH DOCTORS AND NURSES,
NOT ENOUGH MEDICAL PERSONNEL.
AND WE ADDRESSED THAT ISSUE WHEN
WE ADDRESSED A FLUB OF OTHER
EDUCATIONAL ISSUES.
WE BROUGHT MANY, MANY NEW HEALTH
CARE FACILITIES COMMUNITY-BASED
OUTREACH CLINICS AROUND THIS
COUNTRY.
SO I APOLOGIZE TO NOBODY FOR MY
WORK AS CHAIRMAN OF THE VA.
WE MADE SIGNIFICANT PROGRESS IN
IMPROVING HEALTH CARE AND
EXPEDITING BENEFITS FOR THE
VETERANS OF OUR COUNTRY WHO
DESERVE, BY THE WAY, THE HIGHEST
QUALITY HEALTH CARE WE CAN
PROVIDE.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I WANT TO
TURN TOP FAISAL SUBA, A DOCTOR
FROM THERE AREA WHO IS HERE WITH
HIS WIFE.
HE IS KIND ENOUGH, BECAUSE HE
SPEAKS FIVE LANGUAGES FLUENTLY
WHICH MAKES US BILINGUALS FEEL
BAD ALL OF A SUDDEN, HE'S KIND
ENOUGH TO AGREE TO DO THIS IN
ENGLISH MOSTLY.
HOW ARE YOU?
>> THAT'S GOOD.
THAT'S VERY GOOD.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I'M A
PHYSICIAN IN TOWN.
AND MY WIFE DOES A LOT OF
VOLUNTEER WORK IN TOWN.
WE TRY TIRELESSLY TO BE HUMANITY
EVERYDAY.
>> THANK YOU.
>> WE ARE ALSO PROUD PEACE
LOVING AMERICAN MUSLIMS.
WE'RE THE PARENTS OF TWO
CHILDREN.
AND WE'RE VERY CONCERNED ABOUT
THE SAFETY OF OUR CHILDREN WITH
THE ISLAMAPHOBIA THAT'S RAMPANT
RIGHT NOW, AS YOU KNOW.
>> YES, I DO.
>> AS PRESIDENT, HOW WOULD YOU
ADDRESS ISLA MA POEBIA?
>> BLUNTLY AND DIRECTLY.
YOU KNOW, THERE COUNTRY, THIS
COUNTRY'S GREATNESS RELIES ON
THE REALITY THAT THROUGHOUT OUR
HISTORY, WE HAVE WELCOMED PEOPLE
INTO THIS COUNTRY.
AS I MENTIONED MY DAD CAME FROM
POLAND AT THE AGE OF 17.
PEOPLE CAN DISAGREE ABOUT
IMMIGRATION AND IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
I BELIEVE WE NEED COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
TAKING PEOPLE OUT OF THE
SHADOWS.
BUT IT IS ABSOLUTELY
UNACCEPTABLE TO ME THAT HE IN
THE YEAR 2016, WE HAVE PEOPLE
LIKE DONALD TRUMP AND OTHERS WHO
ARE TRYING TO GAIN VOTES BY
SCAPEGOATING PEOPLE HO MAY BE
MUSLIMS OR PEOPLE WHO MAY BE
LATINOS.
THAT IS UNACCEPTABLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THIS COUNTRY -- THIS COUNTRY HAS
STRUGGLED TOO MUCH FOR TOO MANY
YEARS.
AND BY THE WAY, I AM APPALLED,
YOU KNOW, PEOPLE CAN AGREE WITH
BARACK OBAMA.
YOU CAN DISAGREE WITH BARACK
OBAMA.
BUT ANYBODY WHO DOESN'T
UNDERSTAND THAT THE KIND OF
OBSTRUCTIONISM AND HATRED THROWN
AT THERE MAN, THE IDEA OF MAKING
HIM A DELEGITIMATE PRESIDENT BY
SUGGESTING HE WAS NOT BORN IN
AMERICA BECAUSE HIS DAD CAME
FROM KENYA, NO ONE ASKED ME
WHETHER AIM I CITIZEN OR NOT.
MY FATHER CAME FROM POLAND.
GEE, WHAT'S THE DIFFERENCE?
MAYBE THE COLOR OF OUR SKIN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AMESO I PROMISE YOU, YOU KNOW,
WHAT MOAT HAVE AS ME IS WHAT
DR. MARTIN LUTHER KING SAID.
HE SAID PARAPHRASING, WE'VE GOT
TO JUDGE PEOPLE BASED ON THEIR
CHARACTER, NOT THE COLOR OF THE
SKIN, NOT THE COUNTRY THAT THEY
CAME FROM.
THAT'S THE AMERICA WE HAVE GOT
TO FIGHT FOR AND ALL OF US
TOGETHER HAVE GOT TO SAY NO TO
ZEN KNOW PHOBIA AND TO RACISM
AND TO BIGOTRY OF ALL FORMS.
AND BY THE WAY, THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR BEING IN OUR COUNTRY,
FOR PRACTICING MEDICINE.
AND FOR HELPING YOUR FELLOW
HUMAN BEINGS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT TO, SENATOR, I WANT TO
BRING AIDEN TARR HERE.
SHE'S GOT A QUESTION ABOUT THE
TWO-PARTY SYSTEM.
>> ABOUT THE WHAT?
>> SHE'S A HIGH SCHOOL STUDENT.
IS THIS YOUR FIRST TIME VOTING?
>>.
>> YES, IT WILL BE.
>> THERE YOU GO.
ANOTHER FIRST TIME VOTER.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> SEEING AS IT IS NEARLY
IMPOSSIBLE FOR A THIRD PARTY
CANDIDATE TO BE ELECTED AND THE
FACT YOU HAD TO SWITCH FROM AN
INDEPENDENT TO DEMOCRATIC TO BE
CONSIDERED AS A LEGITIMATE
CANDIDATE, SINCE REFORMATION OF
OUR PARTY SYSTEM HAS NEVER BEEN
ADDRESSED BY A PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATE, HOW WOULD YOU SUGGEST
TO REFORM OUR SYSTEM AND ALLOW
FOR OTHER PARTIES AND IDEAS TO
BE REPRESENTED?
>> WELL, I PROBABLY KNOW MORE
ABOUT THAT ISSUE THAN ANY HUMAN
BEING IN THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU KNOW, WHEN I BECAME MAYOR
OF THE CITY OF BURLINGTON, I
WILL TO TAKE ON DEMOCRATS AND
REPUBLICANS AND SO FORTH.
YOUR POINT IS WELL TAKEN.
I CHOSE TO RUN PROUDLY IN THE
DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY AND CAUCUS
PROCESS.
AND I LOOK FORWARD TO WINNING
THAT PROCESS.
BUT CLEARLY, AS A NATION, I
THINK WE FLOURISH WHEN THERE ARE
DIFFERENT IDEAS OUT THERE, WHEN
THERE ARE MORE DIFFERENCES OF
OPINIONS.
IF YOU GO TO EUROPE, FOR
EXAMPLE, THERE ARE.MANY
POLITICAL PARTIES.
AND WHAT HAPPENS IN THIS COUNTRY
IS SOMETIMES THE TWO-PARTY
SYSTEM MAKES IT VERY, VERY
DIFFICULT TO GET ON THE BALLOT.
IF YOU ARE A THIRD PARTY.
AND I THINK THAT THAT'S WRONG.
I THINK WE SHOULD WELCOME
COMPETITION, WELCOME DIFFERENT
IDEAS.
AND I THINK THE TWO PARTIES
SHOULD BE OPEN TO MAKING SURE
THAT PEOPLE HAVE A FAIR SHAKE IF
THEY WANT TO RUN ON ANOTHER
PARTY.
>> BY THE WAY, SENATOR, I JUST
WANT TO SHOW YOU, SHE REALLY
WORKED ON THIS.
SHE WROTE IT ON A PIECE OF
PAPER.
I WAS VERY IMPRESSED.
>> LET ME JUST ANSWER YOU IF I
MIGHT.
AS A NATION WHEN WE TALK ABOUT
THE POLITICAL PROCESS, NOBODY IN
THIS ROOM NO MATTER WHO YOU'RE
SUPPORTING SHOULD BE PROUD THAT
WE HAVE ONE OF THE LOWEST VOTER
TURNOUTS OF ANY MAJOR NATION ON
EARTH.
NOBODY SHOULD BE PROUD THAT WE
HAVE REPUBLICAN GOVERNORS AND
LEGISLATURES WHO ARE WORKING
OVERTIME TRYING TO SUPPRESS THE
VOTE.
WE WANT TO MAKE IT EASIER FOR
PEOPLE TO VOTE, NOT HARDER FOR
PEOPLE TO VOTE.
WHICH IS WHAT MANY REPUBLICAN
GOVERNORS ARE DOING.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> SENATOR, IF I COULD, KIND OF
TO PIGGY BACK OFF THAT QUESTION,
BY THE WAY, I AGREE WITH YOU,
CHUCK.
A MILLENIAL USING PEN AND PAPER
IS USUAL.
>> OLD SCHOOL.
WELL DONE.
>> SENATOR, YOU HAVE OFTEN
TALKED OF THE NEED FOR A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION IN THE
UNITED STATES.
>> YES.
>> YOU'RE A DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALIST.
WHEN SOME LATINOS HEAR THOSE
WORDS, THEY THINK VENEZUELA AND
CUBA, CHAVEZ AND CASTRO
BROTHERS, 57 YEARS OF
DICTATORSHIP.
TALK TO THE PEOPLE WHO ESCAPED
THOSE REGIMES TODAY AND HEAR YOU
USE THOSE WORDS AND WONDER
EXACTLY WHAT YOU HAVE IN MIND.
>> SURE.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALISM, YOU KNOW WHAT I'M
TALKING ABOUT?
SOCIAL SECURITY.
ONE OF THE MOST POPULAR AND
IMPORTANT PROGRAMS IN THIS
COUNTRY DEVELOPED BY FDR TO GIVE
DIGNITY AND SECURITY TO SENIORS.
AND IT HAS BEEN ENORMOUSLY
SUCCESSFUL AT REDUCING POVERTY
AMONG SENIORS.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALISM, I AM TALKING ABOUT
MEDICARE, A SINGLE PAIR HEALTH
CARE SYSTEM FOR THE ELDERLY.
AND IN MY VIEW, WE SHOULD EXPAND
THAT CONCEPT TO ALL PEOPLE.
I BELIEVE THAT EVERYBODY IN THIS
COUNTRY SHOULD BE ENTITLED TO
HEALTH CARE AS A RIGHT AND THE
MOST EFFECTIVE WAY TO DO IT IS
THROUGH A MEDICARE FOR ALL
SINGLE PAIR PROGRAM.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALISM, I'M NOT LOOKING AT
VENEZUELA.
I'M NOT LOOKING AT CUBA.
I'M LOOKING AT COUNTRIES LIKE
DENMARK AND SWEDEN.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT GOES ON IN
THOSE COUNTRIES?
ALL OF THE KIDS WHO HAVE THE
ABILITY AND THE DESIRE GO TO
COLLEGE.
AND YOU KNOW HOW MUCH IT COUGHS?
IT IS FREE.
THEY HAVE CHILD CARE SYSTEMS
WHICH ARE OUTSTANDING.
THEY HAVE PUBLIC EDUCATIONAL
SYSTEMS WHICH ARE EXTREMELY
STRONG.
THE RETIREMENT BENEFIT
INFERIORER THAT ELDERLY MUCH
BETTER THAN THEY ARE IN THE
UNITED STATES.
BOTTOM LINE IS, WHEN I TALK
ABOUT DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM WHAT
I MEAN IS MOVING AWAY FROM WHERE
WE ARE RIGHT NOW.
AS A MEMBER OF THE SENATE, LET
ME BREAK THE BAD NEWS TO ALL OF
YOU.
WE HAVE A CONGRESS RIGHT NOW THE
WHICH IS DOMINATED BY WALL
STREET AND BIG MONEY INTERESTS.
THE MEMBERS OF CONGRESS ARE NOT
WORRIED ABOUT THE PEOPLE MAKING
9 BUCKS AN HOUR.
THEY'RE NOT WORRYING ABOUT THE
KIDS WHO CAN'T CONFERRED TO GO
TO COLLEGE.
THEY'RE NOT WORRYING ABOUT
PEOPLE WHO HAVE NO HEALTH
INSURANCE.
THAT'S NOT THEIR WORRY.
THEIR WORRY IS GETTING CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS FROM VERY, VERY
WEALTHY PEOPLE AND PROVIDING TAX
BREAKS FOR THOSE WHO DON'T NEED
IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SO?
ONE SENSE, JOSE, WE'RE NOT
TALKING ABOUT VENEZUELA, WE'RE
NOT TALKING ABOUT CUBA.
WE ARE TALKING ABOUT THE CONCEPT
WHICH I DON'T THINK IS IT A
RADICAL IDEA.
OF HAVING A GOVERNMENT WHICH
WORKSING TO REPRESENT THE NEEDS
OF THE MIDDLE CLASS AND WORKING
FAMILIES RATHER THAN JUST THE
TOP 1%.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO INTRODUCE YOU TO
SOMEONE WHO SPEAKS ENGLISH AND
SPANISH BUT MORE COMFORTABLE IN
SPANISH.
STHEEL ASK THE QUESTION IN THAT
LANGUAGE AND I'LL TRANSLATE IT
INTO ENGLISH FOR YOU.
[ SPEAKING FOREIGN LANGUAGE ]
>> YOU HAVE EXPRESSED SUPPORT
FOR AFFORDABLE CHILD CARE BUT
HAVE YOU TALKED LITTLE ABOUT HOW
QUALITY CARE IS DEPENDENT ON A
STRONG WORKFORCE.
WHAT DO YOU PLAN TO DO TO
STRENGTHEN THE CHILD CARE
WORKFORCE WITH THE WAGES THEY
NEED TO STAY IN THE FIELD AND
PROVIDE AFFORDABLE CARE FOR
PARENTS AND FAMILIESER FROM.
>> WONDERFUL.
VERY IMPORTANT QUESTION WHICH IS
VERY RARELY DISCUSSED.
EVERY PSYCHOLOGIST WHO STUDIES
THE ISSUE UNDERSTANDS AND HAS
TOLD US THAT THE MOST IMPORTANT
YEARS OF HUMAN DEVELOPMENT
INTELLECTUALLY AND EMOTIONALLY
IS 0 THROUGH 4.
IN THIS COUNTRY TODAY, WE HAVE
MILLIONS OF WORKING FAMILIES,
MOM GOES TO WORK, DAD GOES TO
WORK.
THEY DON'T MAKE A WHOLE LOT OF
MONEY.
THEY ARE DESPERATELY SEARCHING
FOR QUALITY AFFORDABLE CHILD
CARE AND ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY
INCLUDING MY OWN STATE OF
VERMONT, IT IS HARD TO FIND.
SO TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION,
NUMBER ONE, WHEN WE LOOK AT THE
INSTRUCTORS, THE EDUCATORS WHO
WORK WITH THE LITTLE ONES, YOU
KNOW WHAT?
THEIR WORK IS AS IMPORTANT OR
MORE IMPORTANT THAN COLLEGE
PROFESSORS.
WE HAVE GOT TO RETHINK HOW WE
DEAL AND TREAT THE YOUNGEST AND
MOST VULNERABLE AMONG US.
THE IDEA THAT TODAY, AND I HAVE
TALKED TO THESE WORKERS, WE HAVE
CHALD CARE WORKER WHO ARE MAKING
$8, 9 BUCKS AN HOUR WHO HAVE NO
HEALTH INSURANCE WHO ARE NOT
MAKING A CAREER OF THE IMPORTANT
WORK THEY ARE DOING.
WHAT OTHER COUNTRIES ARE DOING
AND WHAT WE MUST DO IS SAY
TAKING CARE CONFIDENT LITTLEST
ONES IS ONE OF OUR MAJOR
PRIORITIES TO DO THAT, WE NEED A
WELL TRAINED, WELL EDUCATED, AND
WELL PAID WORKFORCE.
AND THIS MEANS CHANGING OUR
NATIONAL PRIORITIES.
MY REPUBLICAN COLLEAGUES WANT TO
GIVE HUNDREDS OF BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS IN TAX BREAKS TO THE TOP
.2 OF 1%.
NOT ME.
I'M GOING TO TAX THE WEALTHIEST
PEOPLE AND THE LARGEST
CORPORATIONS AN WE'RE GOING TO
USE SOME OF THAT MONEY TO
PROVIDE QUALITY CHILD CARE FOR
ALL WORKING FAMILIES AND MAKE
SURE THAT THOSE WHO IS WORK WITH
THE LITTLE KIDS ARE WELL PAID
AND WELL TRAINED.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
>> QUICK BEFORE I GET TO THE
NEXT QUESTION, SENATOR, I WANTED
TO FOLLOW UP ON SOMETHING.
YOU WERE TALKING ABOUT THE INGLE
PAIR, REFERRED TO SINGLE PAIR
LET CARE AND TALKING ABOUT SOME
OF THE EUROPEAN SYSTEMS.
A COMMON COMPLAINT IN THOSE
EUROPEAN SYSTEMS HAS TO DO WITH
WAIT TIMES FOR TREATMENT AND FOR
SEEING SPECIALISTS.
HOW DO YOU PROPOSE IN YOUR
MEDICARE FOR ALL SYSTEM TO NOT
HAVE AMERICANS HAVE TO DEAL WITH
RATIONING OF CARE?
THIS IS A COMMON CRITIQUE IN
CANADA AND THE UK IN PARTICULAR.
>> WHOA.
LET MENS ANSWER YOUR QUESTION.
YOU KNOW, THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES AND THE DRUG COMPANIES
AND THEIR MOUTHPIECES THEY GO
AROUND AND TELLING US HOW
TERRIBLE HEALTH CARE IS ALL OVER
THE WORLD.
ALL THESE TERRIBLE WAITING
LINES.
AND YET, WHEN THEY DO
INTERNATIONAL STUDIES, AND THEY
ASK PEOPLE HOW THEY THINK AND
HOW THEY FEEL ABOUT THEIR HEALTH
CARE SYSTEM, YOU KNOW WHAT?
THE UNITED STATES IS OFTEN DOWN
BELOW MANY OF THESE COUNTRIES
ARE MUCH HIGHER LEVELS.
WE ARE THE ONLY COUNTRY IN THE
INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD THAT
DOESN'T GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO
ALL PEOPLE.
I HAVE BEEN CRITICIZED FOR
SAYING THAT LET ME SAY IT AGAIN.
I BELIEVE HEALTH CARE IS A RIGHT
OF ALL PEOPLE.
I WILL FIGHT FOR MEDICARE FOR
ALL SINGLE PAIR SYSTEM.
SECOND OF ALL, YOU WANT TO TALK
ABOUT RATIONING?
YOU GOT 29 MILLION PEOPLE IN
THIS COUNTRY WHO HAVE NO HEALTH
INSURANCE.
HOW IS THAT FOR RATIONING?
THEY CAN'T GO TO THE DOCTOR.
AND THEN YOU'VE GOT EVEN MORE
WHO ARE UNDER INSURED WITH HIGH
DEDUCTIBLES AND HIGH COPAYMENTS.
I HAVE TALKED TO DOCTORS WHO
HAVE TOLD ME THAT PEOPLE WALK IN
THE DOOR EXTREMELY SICK AND THE
DOCTORS SAY, WHY DIDN'T YOU COME
IN HERE SIX MONTHS AGO WHEN YOU
FIRST FELT YOUR SYMPTOMS?
AND PEOPLE SAID, I WILL NO
HEALTH INSURANCE.
OR I HAD A HIGH DEDUCTIBLE.
CHUCK, SOME OF THOSE PEOPLE DIE
OR THEY END UP IN THE HOSPITAL.
YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT
RATIONING, THAT'S RATIONING.
TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, WE
SPEND ALMOST THREE TIMES MORE
PER PERSON THAN THE PEOPLE IN
THE UK, 50% MORE THAN THE PEOPLE
IN FRANCE.
WE CAN'T HAVE A WORLD CLASS
HEALTH CARE SYSTEM WITHOUT
WAITING LINES SPENDING THE SAME
AMOUNT OF MONEY WE'RE SPENDING
RIGHT NOW.
>> WITH ALL DUE RESPECT, THE VA
WHICH IS A SYSTEM.
>> THE VA WHICH IS A SYSTEM THAT
IS DESIGNED TO ESSENTIALLY BE
UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE FOR
VETERANS HAD WAIT TIMES.
HAD A RATIONING SITUATION.
I KNOW YOU TRIED TO CORRECT
THAT.
WE JUST HAD AN EXPERIMENT WHICH
WE GOT, HOW DO YOU GUARANTEE
THAT YOUR PLAN ISN'T GOING TO
EXPERIENCE THE SAME PROBLEM.
>> I'VE JUST INDICATED TO YOU,
IF FOR EXAMPLE, THERE ARE
SYSTEMS, YOU'RE RIGHT, WHERE IF
YOU NEEDED A KNEE REPLACE THE OR
SOMETHING LIKE THAT, YOU MIGHT
HAVE TO WAIT FOR THAT.
BUT WHEN YOU'RE SICK, YOU GO
INTO THE DOCTOR WHEN YOU NEED TO
GO.
MY POINT IS, CHUCK, THERE'S
MASSIVE RATIONING IN AMERICA.
IT IS RATIONING BASED ON MONEY.
IF YOU DON'T HAVE MONEY AND YOU
DON'T HAVE INSURANCE AND YOU
DON'T HAVE -- YOU HAVE A HIGH
DEDUCTIBLE AND YOU DON'T GO TO
THE DOCTOR WHEN YOU SHOULD, ONE
OUT OF FIVE AMERICANS TODAY
CANNOT AFFORD THE PRESCRIPTION
DRUGS THEIR DOCTORS WRITE.
WHAT DO YOU DEFINE THAT AS?
OTHER COUNTRIES AROUND THE WORLD
MAKE SURE THAT THE PEOPLE HAVE
THE MEDICINE THEY NEED.
WHEN ONE OUT OF FIVE PEOPLE
CAN'T AFFORD THOSE
PRESCRIPTIONS, MAN I CALL THAT
RATIONING.
WE CAN DO A LOT BETTER THAN
WE'RE CURRENTLY DOING.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
LET ME INTRODUCE YOU, I'M GOING
TO INTRODUCE YOU TO
MR. ANDERSON.
TALK ABOUT AN ISSUE THAT'S
PRETTY IMPORTANT TO A LOT OF
PEOPLE OUT WEST, LAND ISSUES.
MR. ANDERSON.
>> FIRST OF ALL, VERY HONORED TO
BE HERE AND GO AHEAD AND PRESENT
THIS QUESTION TO YOU.
BUT UNDER OBAMA, THERE HAS BEEN
AREAS HERE THAT'S BEEN
DESIGNATED AS NATIONAL MONUMENTS
AND AT THIS POINT, MY PEOPLE THE
SOUTHERN PIE YOU'DS WE'RE TRYING
TO WORK TO GET GOLD BEAUTY AS A
NATIONAL MONUMENT, TOO.
>> OKAY.
>> AND THERE'S A LOT OF RECENT
ISSUES THAT CAME UP HERE AND
WHAT I WANT TO ASK IS THAT THERE
ARE THOSE WHO IS OPPOSE THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE'S OWNERSHIP OF
PUBLIC LANDS.
AND WOULD SEE THOSE LANDS SOLD
TO PRIVATE INTERESTS.
AS PRESIDENT, HOW WOULD YOU
ENSURE THAT OUR PUBLIC LANDS
REMAIN IN PUBLIC HANDS AND
PRESERVE OUR HERITAGE AND LIVES
BY STOPPING CORPORATIONS FROM
DESTROYING MOTHER EARTH?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I DON'T HAVE TO EXPLAIN TO
YOU OR I HOPE ANYBODY IN THIS
ROOM OR ANYBODY WATCHING THE
OUTRAGEOUS WAY AND UNFAIR WAY
THAT GOVERNMENTS HAVE TREATED
NATIVE AMERICANS FROM DAY ONE.
IT IS A DISGRACE.
NUMBER TWO, I WILL, YOU KNOW,
YOU'RE RAISING ISSUES IN TERMS
OF EXTRACTION OF FOS TILL FUELS
FOR EXAMPLE, I BELIEVE THAT
CLIMATE CHANGE IS ONE OF THE
GREAT CHALLENGES FACING THIS
PLANET.
AND WLA HAVE INTRODUCED
LEGISLATION TO DO BY THE WAY, IS
TO SAY THAT WE WILL NOT EXTRACT
FOSSIL FUELS IN THE FUTURE FROM
ANY PUBLIC LANDS.
NUMBER THREE, I UNDERSTAND THAT
IT IS ABSOLUTELY IMPORTANT THAT
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT DO MUCH
MORE THAN IT IS NOW DOING TO
WORK WITH THE NATIVE AMERICAN HE
COMMUNITY IN PRESERVING THEIR
HERITAGE AND THEIR WAY OF LIFE.
AND I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN
DO BRINGING THAT ABOUT.
THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> JOSE.
>> SENATOR, SAY HELLO TO ALEX
TURNER.
>> HELLO, SIR.
>> I GOT THIS ALEX.
GO AHEAD.
>> THE U.S. VISA PROGRAM ARE
CURRENTLY IN THE SPOTLIGHT AS A
POSSIBLE HOPE LAND SECURITY RISK
AND BEFORE THAT IT WAS A CONCERN
IT WAS BEING USED TO TRAFFIC
YOUNG WOMEN FROM FOREIGN
COUNTRIES.
WHAT MEASURES DO YOU INTEND TO
TAKE TO ENSURE THAT THIS PROGRAM
ISN'T USED TO ATTACK THE
>> HUMAN TRAFFICKING, TAKING
GIRLS OR YOUNG BOYS AND DOING
SOMETHING HORRIBLE WITH THEM IS
SOMETHING WE HAVE TO DO
EVERYTHING WE CAN TO STOP AND I
WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO STOP
IT.
IN TERMS OF MAKING SURE AS I
UNDERSTAND YOUR QUESTION THAT
PEOPLE DO NOT COME INTO THIS
COUNTRY -- LET ME BACK UP AND
SAY THAT I BELIEVE GIVEN THE
HUMANITARIAN CRISIS IN SYRIA AND
THE HUMANITARIAN CRISIS IN
AFGHANISTAN THAT THE UNITED
STATES AND THE REST OF THE WORLD
HAVE GOT TO MAKE SURE THAT
REFUGEES CAN GET THEIR LIVES
TOGETHER AND THAT WE SHOULD
WELCOME THOSE PEOPLE IN THE
UNITED STATES, ALONG WITH OTHER
COUNTRIES AROUND THE WORLD, BUT
WHEN WE DO THAT WE HAVE GOT TO
MAKE VERY SURE THAT THE VETTING
PROCESS IS STRONG, THAT PEOPLE
WHO WE WELCOME INTO THIS COUNTRY
TO HELP DO NOT DO TERRIBLE
THINGS TO OUR OWN PEOPLE.
>> HOW DO YOU DO THAT, SENATOR?
>> YOU DO THAT BY HAVING A MUCH
STRONGER SECURITY APPROACH TO
VETTING PEOPLE WHO ARE COMING
IN, TO KNOWING WHAT THEIR
BACKGROUND IS, TO MAKING SURE
THAT THEY HAVE NOT BEEN INVOLVED
IN TERRORIST ACTIVITY AND THERE
ARE A VARIETY OF WAYS THAT YOU
CAN DO THAT, BUT THAT IS WHAT
WE'VE GOT DO.
>> SIR, THERE'S SEVERAL TIER TWO
COUNTRIES THAT ARE ON THE VISA
WAVER PROGRAMS THAT INDIVIDUALS
CAN GET ANNEX PA INDICTED WAVER
AND THOSE TIER TWO COUNTRIES
DON'T MEET THE MINIMUM STANDARDS
TO DEFEND PEOPLE FROM HUMAN
TRAFFICKING.
>> THAT'S SOMETHING WE HAVE TO
ADDRESS.
I AGREE WITH YOU.
IT'S A VERY SERIOUS CONCERN.
>> THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO TAKE A
BREAK HERE.
SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU VERY
MUCH.
COMING UP, WE'RE GOING TO HEAR
FROM SENATOR HILLARY CLINTON SO
LET'S SNEAK IN A QUICK BREAK AND
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>> WE ARE BACK HERE IN LAS VEGAS
AND IT'S TIME FOR THE SECOND
PART OF OUR TOWN HALL.
PLEASE JOIN US IN WELCOMING
FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE
HILLARY CLINTON TO THE STAGE
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> HI, CHUCK.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> HI.
HOW ARE YOU?
HELLO, HELLO.
>> IT'S GOOD TO SEE YOU,
SECRETARY.
>> IT'S GREAT TO SEE YOU TOO.
>> WE'RE GOING TO DO WITH WHAT
WE DID WITH SENATOR SANDERS.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A FEW
QUESTIONS.
AS YOU KNOW PRESIDENT OBAMA SAYS
HE REGRETS VOTING TO FILIBUSTER
THROWING SAND IN THE GEARS OF
THE CONFIRMATION PROCESS WAS A
REGRET.
YOU JOINED 24 OTHER DEMOCRATS.
YOU VOTED AGAINST ALITO AND
JUSTICE ROBERTS DO YOU REGRET
THAT CONSIDERING THE SITUATION
THAT WE'RE IN NOW DO YOU LIKE
PRESIDENT OBAMA FEELS I WISH I
HADN'T PARTICIPATED IN SOMETHING
LIKE THAT?
>> THE WAY I LOOK AT IT IS THIS,
I DID OPPOSE JUSTICE ALITO AND
AS YOU SEE CHIEF JUSTICE ROBERTS
BECAUSE AFTER MEETING WITH THEM,
LISTENING TO THEM, I DID NOT
BELIEVE THAT THEIR JUD CHILL
FILLY WOULD BE THE BEST FOR THE
COUNTRY.
I VOTED AGAINST HIM.
WE HAD A PROCESS.
THE NOMINATION WAS MADE AND WE
WENT THROUGH THE PROCESS AND
WHAT THE REPUBLICANS TODAY ARE
SAYING IS YOU CAN'T VOTE ON
ANYTHING.
WE DON'T WANT THE PRESIDENT TO
SEND US A NOMINEE.
I THINK THAT IS VERY DIFFERENT
AND WHAT AM I SAYING IS THE
PRESIDENT HAS THE RIGHT AND THE
OBLIGATION UNDER THE
CONSTITUTION TO SEND FORTH A
NOMINEE AND THE SENATE HAS AN
OBLIGATION UNDER THE
CONSTITUTION TO DECIDE WHETHER
TO APPROVE OR NOT.
THAT'S VERY DIFFERENT THAN ON
THE FLOOR OF THE SENATE MAKING
YOUR ARGUMENT.
>> A FILIBUSTER, IF YOU HAD BEEN
SUCCESSFUL, THEN JUDGE ALITO
WOULD NOT HAVE GOTTEN A VOTE.
>> THAT'S THE WAY THE SENATE
OPERATES.
YOU GET TO HAVE A VOTE.
YOU GET TO USE THE RULES AND
HARRY REID IS SITTING HERE, HE'S
AN EXPERT ON THE RULES, A MASTER
ON THE RULES, YOU GET TO USE THE
RULES.
THAT HAPPENS A LOT AND SO I'M
NOT IN THE POSITION THAT THE
PRESIDENT IS RIGHT NOW TRYING TO
TALK SOME SENSE INTO THE SENATE
REPUBLICANS TO ACTUALLY DO THEIR
CONSTITUTIONAL DUTY, BUT ONCE A
NOMINEE GOES TO THE SENATE, THEN
YOU GO THROUGH THE PROCESS.
THERE SHOULD BE HEARINGS BOTH
FROM THE NOMINEE AND OTHER
WITNESSES, THEN IT SHOULD BE
PRESENT TO THE FLOOR AND THEN
YOU USE THE PROCEDURES THAT ARE
AVAILABLE AND EVENTUALLY AS YOU
KNOW JUSTICE ALITO WAS
CONFIRMED.
>> SOME OF YOUR LINES OF ATTACK
AGAINST SENATOR SANDERS IN THIS
CAMPAIGN SOUNDS FAMILIAR AND WE
HAVE A CLIP WE WANT TO PLAY.
>> YOU ARE NOT GOING TO WAVE A
MAGIC WAND AND HAVE A SPECIAL
INTEREST DISAPPEAR.
I WISH THAT WE COULD ELECT A
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENT WHO COULD
WAVE A MAGIC WAND AND SAY WE
SHALL DO THIS AND WE SHALL DO
THAT.
THAT AIN'T THE REAL WORLD WE'RE
LIVING IN.
>> ALL RIGHT.
FIRST CLIP WAS FROM A MONTH AGO,
SECOND CLIP WAS FROM EIGHT YEARS
AGO.
MANY DEMOCRATIC VOTERS DIDN'T
BELIEVE YOUR THAT YOUR CRITICISM
WAS FAIR.
WHY SHOULD THEY BELIEVE THAT
IT'S NOT JUST AS UNFAIR AS THEY
THOUGHT EIGHT YEARS AGO?
>> I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT FOR
DEMOCRATIC VOTERS TO TAKE A HARD
LOOK AT ALL AT CANDIDATES AND IN
THIS CASE SENATOR SANDERS AND
MYSELF AND TO EVALUATE WHO HAS
THE BEST PLANS, WHO HAS THE MOST
EXPERIENCE, WHO IS READY TO DO
ALL PARTS OF THE JOB ON DAY ONE
NOT ONLY BEING PRESIDENT, BUT
COMMANDER IN CHIEF AND I THINK
IT'S FAIR FOR VOTERS TO TAKE A
HARD LOOK AT WHERE WE ARE AND
WHAT WE NEED TO ACCOMPLISH IN
ORDER TO HAVE THE KIND OF
PROGRESS THAT I'M ADVOCATING.
I'M A PROGRESSIVE WHO LIKES TO
MAKE PROGRESS.
I KNOW HOW HARD IT IS.
I DON'T WANT TO MAKE PROMISES I
CAN'T KEEP.
I WANT PEOPLE TO ACTUALLY HOLD
ME ACCOUNTABLE FOR WHAT I SAY
AND WHAT I PRESENT AND THEN THEY
MAKE THEIR DECISION.
>> SO THIS MAGIC THEY SHOULD NOT
DISCOUNT YOUR CRITICISM THIS
TIME EVEN IF THEY DID EIGHT
YEARS AGO?
>> I HAVE A NUMBER OF
DIFFERENCES WITH SENATOR SANDERS
AND WE'VE BEEN LAYING THOSE OUT
AND WE'LL CONTINUE TO DO THAT.
>> A FEDERAL JUDGE THIS WEEK
ORDERED APPLE TO DISABLE THE
PRIVACY FEATURE IN THE iPHONE
USED BY ONE OF THE SAN
BERNARDINO TERRORISTS SO LAW
ENFORCEMENT CAN ACCESS THE DATA.
APPLE CEO IS PLEDGING TO FIGHT
IT CALLING IT A DANGEROUS
PRECEDENT AND SAYING THE
GOVERNMENT IS ASKING APPLE TO
HACK OUR OWN USERS.
WHO DO YOU THINK IS RIGHT HERE?
>> LOOK, I THINK BECAUSE THIS IS
ONE OF THE MOST DIFFICULT DEM
MAUS THAT WE'RE FACED WITH.
OF COURSE LAW ENFORCEMENT HAS
EVERY REASON TO WANT TO GET
INFORMATION OFF OF A KILLER'S
CELL PHONE.
ONE OF THE SAN BERNARDINO
KILLERS CELL PHONES THAT THEY
CAN'T OPEN.
THEY'RE ASKING FOR HELP.
APPLE UNDERSTANDABLY IS WORRIED
ABOUT OPENING THE DOOR, CREATING
WHAT THEY CALL A BACK DOOR INTO
ENCRYPTION THAT WOULD NOT JUST
HAVE TO FIELD REQUESTS FROM THE
UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT, BUT
FROM THE CHINESE, RUSSIAN,
IRANIAN GOVERNMENTS.
THIS IS A VERY HARD DEM MAU AND
WHAT I KEEP CALLING FOR IS TO
TRY TO GET THE GOVERNMENT AND
OUR GREAT TECH COMPANIES TO
FIGURE OUT WHAT IS THE PATH
FORWARD BECAUSE I DON'T KNOW
WHAT THIS JUDGE IS GOING TO DO
IN THIS CASE.
I ASSUME IT WILL BE APPEALED.
IT WILL HAVE LOTS OF
RAMIFICATIONS, BUT I SEE BOTH
SIDES AND I THINK MOST CITIZENS
SEE BOTH SIDES.
WE DON'T WANT PRIVACY AND
ENCRYPTION DESTROYED AND WE WANT
TO CATCH AND MAKE SURE THERE'S
NOBODY ELSE OUT THERE WHOSE
INFORMATION IS ON THE CELL PHONE
OF THAT KILLER.
THIS IS WHY YOU NEED PEOPLE IN
OFFICE WHO CAN TRY TO BRING
FOLKS TOGETHER TO FIND SOME
COMMON GROUNDS.
THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT I WOULD DO.
I'M WELL AWARE THAT THE
GOVERNMENT HAS ITS NEEDS.
OBVIOUSLY APPLE AND THE OTHER
TECH COMPANIES ARE CONCERNED
ABOUT THIS, BUT AS SMART AS WE
ARE, THERE'S GOT TO BE SOME WAY
ON A VERY SPECIFIC BASIS WE
COULD TRY TO HELP GET
INFORMATION AROUND CRIMES AND
TERRORISM.
>> BUT THE PROBLEM IS THAT IF
YOU OPEN UP THAT BACK DOOR THAT
DOESN'T EXIST RIGHT NOW, AS YOU
SAID THE UNITED STATES IS
LOOKING FOR INFORMATION FROM A
CELL PHONE THAT WAS USED BY A
TERRORIST, BUT DOES CHINA HAVE
THE SAME INTENTIONS AND DOES
RUSSIA AND DOES CUBA AND NORTH
KOREA.
>> THAT'S WHY I SAID IT'S A
DELEMIA.
>> I'M NOT SAYING WHAT SHOULD BE
DONE, I'M DESCRIBING THE
DIFFICULT ISSUE WE'RE CAUGHT IN
IN REALLY MAKING A PLEA THAT THE
GOVERNMENT AND THE TECH
COMPANIES KEEP WORKING TOGETHER
TO SEE IF THERE ISN'T SOME
LEGITIMATE WAY TO HELP DEAL WITH
THESE KINDS OF VERY REAL WORLD
PROBLEMS THAT WE FACE.
>> ON HIS PLANE RIDE OR FLIGHT
HERE SENATOR SANDERS ATTACKED
YOUR HUSBAND'S LEGACY.
HE SAID BILL CLINTON WAS THE
PRESIDENT WHO LED THE EFFORT TO
DEREGULATE WALL STREET, WAS THE
PRESIDENT WHO FOUGHT FOR THE
DISASTROUS NAFTA TRADE
AGREEMENT, PUSHED WELL FORM
REFORM FOR LOW INCOME PEOPLE.
SHOULD YOU BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE
FOR YOUR HUSBAND'S --
>> HE WAS THE PRESIDENT WHO
CREATED 23 MILLION JOBS, WHO
RAISED INCOMES FOR EVERY GROUP
IN AMERICA, NOT JUST THOSE AT
THE TOP, AFRICAN-AMERICAN FAMES,
LATINO FAMILIES HAD A HIGHER
THAN AVERAGE INCREASE IN INCOME.
CREATED GREAT ECONOMIC PROGRAMS
LIKE THE NEW MARKET TAX CREDITS,
SO I KNOW THAT SENATOR SANDERS
HAS ALSO ATTACKED PRESIDENT
OBAMA.
HE'S CALLED HIM WEAK,
DISAPPOINTING.
HE TRIED TO GET SOMEONE TO RUN
AGAINST HIM IN THE 2012 ELECTION
IN THE PRIMARY.
I JUST DON'T KNOW WHERE ALL THIS
COMES FROM BECAUSE MAYBE IT'S
THAT SENATOR SANDERS WASN'T
REALLY A DEMOCRAT UNTIL HE
DECIDED TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT.
HE DOESN'T KNOW WHAT THE LAST
TWO DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTS DID.
WELL, IT'S TRUE.
IT'S TRUE.
YOU KNOW IT'S TRUE.
I MEAN, IT HAPPENS TO BE TRUE.
I GOT TO TELL YOU, I LOOK AT OUR
LAST TWO DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTS,
WERE THEY PERFECT?
NO.
NO PERSON IS.
BUT I'LL TELL YOU WHAT, I WOULD
TAKE THE TWO OF THEM OVER ANY
REPUBLICAN ANY TIME ANYWHERE.
>> THANK YOU.
I THINK WE SHOULD HEAR FROM THE
PEOPLE.
BY THE WAY, YOU BOTH HAVE BEEN
BOOED AT SOME TIME.
WE CAN TELL THIS IS A
COMPETITIVE RACE.
>> THAT'S GOOD.
WE LIKE THE FACTS.
THE FACTS ARE OUR FRIENDS SO
LET'S TALK ABOUT THEM.
>> FAIR ENOUGH.
MADAM SECRETARY, WE'RE GOING TO
GO AND START WITH THE SAME ISSUE
THAT WE STARTED WITH SENATOR
SANDERS AND IT'S THE ISSUE OF
IMMIGRATION.
AS YOU KNOW NEVADA IS ALMOST 28%
HISPANIC AND LATINOS ARE THE
FASTEST GROWING GROUP IN THE
STATE.
PEOPLE ARE CONCERNED WITH
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION, AND TO
REFORM THE CURRENT SYSTEM.
SO I'M GOING TO TURN IT OVER.
HE'S GOING TO ASK HOW A CLINTON
ADMINISTRATION WOULD DEAL WITH
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
>> IN 2007 YOU OPPOSED GIVING
DRIVER'S LICENSES TO
UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE.
WHY?
>> BACK THEN IT WAS A STATE BY
STATE DETERMINATION AND I'M
HAPPY THAT MOST STATES HAVE
MOVED IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION,
BUT WHAT WE HAVE TO DO NOW IS
GET TO COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM WITH A PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP.
I UNDERSTAND THAT SOMEBODY ASKED
SENATOR SANDERS A QUESTION
BECAUSE HER HUSBAND WAS IN
MEXICO -- I DON'T WHO ASKED THAT
QUESTION.
AND I WANT TO TELL YOU I WILL
END THE THREE AND TEN YEAR BAR
PROVISION SO YOU DO NOT HAVE TO
FACE THAT EVER AGAIN.
>> LET ME FOLLOW UP ON
SOMETHING.
I ASKED YOU A FEW TIMES ABOUT
THE PRIORITIZATION OF
IMMIGRATION REFORM AND ABOUT
YOUR FIRST 100 DAYS PRIORITIES
YOU'VE MENTIONED A LOT OF ISSUES
AN YOU HAVEN'T PUT IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
SOME ADVOCATES ARE CONCERNED IF
YOU DON'T PUT IT FIRST, HOW DO
YOU PREVENT THAT IF YOU DON'T
MAKE IT FIRST, AS YOU KNOW THESE
LEGISLATIVE LIFTS ARE HARD, IF
IT'S NOT FIRST IT MAY NOT
HAPPEN.
WHAT DO YOU SAY?
>> WHEN WE HAD A CHANCE TO VOTE
ON COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM IN 2007, THE BILL THAT
SENATOR KENNEDY CHAMPIONED I
VOTED FOR IT AND SENATOR SANDERS
VOTED AGAINST IT.
IF I'M FORTUNATE ENOUGH TO GET
THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINATION, I
WILL BEGIN WORKING ON THE
LEGISLATION THAT I WANT THE
CONGRESS TO WORK ON RIGHT AWAY
AND IMMIGRATION REFORM WILL BE
AMONG THOSE ISSUES.
FOR ME THE WAY THAT CONGRESS
WORKS AND I THINK MY FRIEND
CONGRESSWOMAN MARSHA IS HERE
SOMEWHERE, THE WAY THE CONGRESS
WORKS IS THERE ARE COMMITTEES
AND THE COMMITTEES HAVE
DIFFERENT JURISDICTION AND IF
YOU DEALING WITH IMMIGRATION
REFORM YOU GO TO ONE COMMITTEE,
IF YOU'RE DEALING WITH EQUAL PAY
FOR WOMEN YOU GO TO A DIFFERENT
COMMITTEE.
WHAT I WANT DO IS BEGIN WORKING
WITH DEMOCRATS IN THE CONGRESS
DURING THE GENERAL ELECTION.
I ALSO WANT TO DO THAT FOR
NOMINATIONS BECAUSE I WANT TO
GET THE JUDGES I WANT TO APPOINT
AND THE OTHER IMPORTANT
OFFICIALS APPOINT SO I'M NOT
GOING TO WASTE A MINUTE THAT'S
WHY I WANT TO GET THIS
NOMINATION AS QUICKLY AS
POSSIBLE SO I CAN GETS TO WORK
ON BEING YOUR PRESIDENT.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, HOW WOULD
YOU GO ABOUT CUTTING OUT THOSE
THREE AND TEN YEAR?
HOW WOULD YOU DO THAT AND HOW
LONG WOULD IT TAKE YOU TO DO?
>> I'M SO SORRY ABOUT THAT.
YOU KNOW WHAT, IT DID DOES HAVE
TO BE DONE LEDGE SLATSIVELY.
I WOULD DO IT ON A SEPARATE
PIECE OF LEGISLATION AND PART OF
A COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM, BUT WE HAVE TO GET RID
OF IT BECAUSE I MET A YOUNG
DREAMER.
SHE WAS BROUGHT HER WHEN SHE WAS
SEVEN MONTHS OLD.
HER FATHER IS A LEGAL RESIDENT.
HER MOTHER IS UNDOCUMENTED.
HER MOTHER CANNOT LEAVE HER
FAMILY FOR THREE OR TEN YEARS TO
GO BACK TO WHERE SHE CAME FROM
LEAVING HER FAMILY AND HER
DAUGHTERS ALONE TO WAIT UNTIL
SHE CAN GET IN LINE TO BE ABLE
TO COME BACK.
IT MAKES NO SENSE.
IT BREAKS UP FAMILIES.
IT IS BURDENSOME.
I'M GOING DO WHAT I CAN TO END
IT AS SOON AS POSSIBLE.
>> DO YOU PROMISE TO DEAL WITH
IMMIGRATION REFORM WITHIN THE
FIRST 100 DAYS.
>> WE'RE GOING TO INTRODUCE
LEGISLATION.
WE'RE GOING TO INTRODUCE
I'M GOING TO CALL EVERYBODY ON
THE COMMITTEE, DEMOCRATS AND
REPUBLICANS ALIKE.
>> WITHIN 100 DAYS.
>> I'M GOING TO INTRODUCE MY
PRIORITY LEGISLATION AND THIS IS
AT THE TOP OF THE LIST.
IT'S GOING TO BE INTRODUCED AND
THEN I'M GOING TO WORK AS HARD
AS I CAN TO MAKE SURE WE GET IT
MOVED THROUGH THE CONGRESSAL
PROCESS.
I CAN CONTROL THE INTRODUCTION
OF LEGISLATION, BUT CONGRESS HAS
TO GET ITS ACT IN GEAR.
THAT'S WHY WE NEED TO ELECT A
DEMOCRATIC SENATE SO WE HAVE
SOME FRIENDS.
>> SAY HELLO.
SHE SPEAKS BOTH ENGLISH AND
SPANISH.
SHE'S MORE COMFORTABLE IN
SHE WANTS TO ASK ABOUT THE
PRESIDENT'S EXECUTIVE ACTION
THAT GIVES CHILDREN BROUGHT HERE
ILLEGALLY THROUGH NO FAULT OF
THEIR OWN [ SPEAKING SPANISH ]
>> MRS. CLINTON, WHAT WOULD YOU
DO TO MAKE POSSIBLE THAT THE
STUDENTS BECOME PERMANENT
RESIDENTS?
THEY LIVE WITH A LOT OF FEAR
BECAUSE THEY HAVE TO RENEW THEIR
PERMITS EVERY TWO YEARS AND THAT
IS A TERRIFYING PROSPECT FOR
THEM.
>> RIGHT.
THAT'S WHY I SUPPORT THE
PRESIDENT'S EXECUTIVE ORDER ON
IT AND I WILL DO EVERYTHING I
CAN TO MAKE SURE THEY ARE KEPT
IN PLACE.
AS YOU KNOW THERE'S A COURT
ACTION CHALLENGING THEM.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN NOW BECAUSE OF THE
SUPREME COURT SITUATION, BUT I
WILL RENEW THEM.
I WILL GO FURTHER IF IT'S AT ALL
LEGALLY POSSIBLE AND I WILL MAKE
THIS A BIG POLITICAL ISSUE
BECAUSE WE NEED TO KEEP THOSE
YOUNG PEOPLE WORKING, GOING TO
SCHOOL, BEING PRODUCTIVE MEMBERS
OF OUR SOCIETY.
SO I HAVE TO TELL YOU, I WILL DO
WHAT I CAN AS PRESIDENT.
I'M HOPING IF WE WIN BACK THE
SENATE AND WE WIN THE WHITE
HOUSE AGAIN THE REPUBLICANS ARE
GOING TO SEE THE ERA OF THEIR
WAYS AND QUIT USING IMMIGRANTS
TO DIVIDE OUR COUNTRY AND QUIT
TAKING THE KIND OF MEAN SPIRITED
ACTIONS THAT THEY DO.
I WAS THE FIRST PERSON TO CALL
OUT DONALD TRUMP.
I SAID BUSTA.
ENOUGH OF THIS PREJUDICE AND
PARANOIA AND THE KIND OF
LANGUAGE THAT HE USES.
SO I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN.
NOT ONLY FOR THE YOUNG PEOPLE
WHO DESERVE THE HIGHEST
PROTECTION, BUT FOR THEIR
FAMILIES AS WELL.
>> SECRETARY, IF I COULD, IN THE
SUMMER OF 2014 UPD UNDOCUMENTED
CHILDREN FROM CENTRAL AMERICA
SHOULD BE SENT BACK AS SOON AS
IT CAN BE DETERMINED WHO
RESPONSIBLE ADULTS IN THEIR
FAMILY ARE, A POSITION YOU'VE
BEEN DEFENDED BY SAYING WE HAD
TO SEND A MESSAGE TO FAMILIES
AND COMMUNITIES IN CENTRAL
AMERICA NOT TO SEND THEIR
CHILDREN HERE.
THAT'S FAR FROM THE MESSAGE POPE
FRANCIS HAD YESTERDAY.
HE CRITICIZED LEADERS CALLING
MIGRANTS CANNON FODER AND HUMAN
TRAGEDY.
DO YOU STILL BELIEVE YOU HELD
THAT POSITION AND THAT IS A
RIGHT POSITION?
>> FIRST, LET ME REALLY EXPRESS
MY DEEP APPRECIATION TO POPE
FRANCIS.
HE HAS TALKED ABOUT IMMIGRANTS
AND MIGRANTS EVERYWHERE IN THE
WORLD.
HE CAME TO OUR BOARDER TO TALK
ABOUT IT AGAIN AND I REALLY
APPRECIATE HIM DOING THAT
BECAUSE I HOPE PEOPLE WILL BEGIN
TO UNDERSTAND THAT WE'VE GOT TO
SHOW OUR VALUES.
WE NEED TO PROVIDE HUH MAIN
TREATMENT.
SO HERE'S WHAT I BELIEVE.
NUMBER ONE WE NEED TO END FAMILY
DETENTION.
I'VE BEEN SAYING THAT FOR A VERY
LONG TIME.
WE NEED TO CLOSE THE PRIVATE
FAMILY DETENTION CENTERS THAT
ARE MAKING A PROFIT OFF OF
HOUSING FAMILY MEMBERS.
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT EVERY
CHILD HAS DUE PROCESS AND IS
GUARANTEED COUNSEL.
I HAVE ADD VOLUME KATD THAT.
I THANK SENATOR REID BECAUSE HE
HAS INTRODUCED LEGISLATION TO
MAKE THAT THE LAW.
THERE IS A PROCESS.
WE HAVE TO FOLLOW THE PROCESS,
BUT AT THE SAME TIME WE DON'T
WANT CHILDREN BEING HANDLED BY
SMUGGLERS AND TRAFFICKERS OFTEN
BEING ABUSE INFORMED AND
MISTREATED.
THERE IS A WAY WHERE WE NEED TO
TAKE CARE AND PROVIDE TOTAL
LEGAL DUE PROCESS INCLUDING
COUNSEL TO CHILDREN WHO GET
HERE, BUT WE NEED TO DO MORE TO
HELP FAMILIES BACK IN CENTRAL
AMERICA HAVE A BETTER LIFE, GET
RID OF THE VIOLENCE THAT STALKS
THEM.
>> SHOULD THOSE CHILDREN BE A
MESSAGE?
>> WELL, THE CHILDREN THEMSELVES
NEED TO BE TAKEN CARE OF.
THEY ARE CHILDREN.
THEY SHOULD BE GIVEN EVERY HELP
THAT WE CAN AND I THINK WE'RE
DOING A BETTER JOB OF THAT THAN
WE WERE.
>> CHUCK?
>> OUR NEXT QUESTION COMES FROM
A SANDERS SUPPORTER.
>> AS A REALTOR HERE IN NEVADA I
KNOW HOW IMPORTANT THE ECONOMY
IS TO OUR GREAT NATION.
AS A DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE WHO
HAS DELIVERED SPEECHES TO THE
LARGEST U.S. FINANCIAL
INSTITUTION IN EXCHANGE FOR
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS
IN SPEAKING FEES, WHY ARE YOU
HESITANT TO RELEASE TRANSCRIPT
OR AUDIO/VIDEO RECORDINGS OF
THOSE MEETINGS IN ORDER TO BE
TRANSPARENT WITH THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE REGARDING THE PROMISES
AND ASSURANCES THAT YOU HAVE
MADE TO THE BIG BANKS?
>> LET ME SAY THIS, I AM HAPPY
TO RELEASE ANYTHING I HAVE WHEN
EVERYBODY ELSE DOES THE SAME
BECAUSE EVERY OTHER CANDIDATE IN
THIS RACE HAS GIVEN SPEECHES TO
PRIVATE GROUPS, INCLUDING
SENATOR SANDERS, BUT LET ME GET
TO THE HEART OF YOUR QUESTION, I
WAS THE CANDIDATE WHO WENT TO
WALL STREET BEFORE THE CRASH.
I WAS THE CANDIDATE WHO WENT TO
THEM AND SAID YOU ARE WRECKING
OUR ECONOMY.
WHAT YOU ARE DOING WITH
MORTGAGES IS GOING TO BRING US
DOWN.
I CALLED TO END THE CARRIED
INTEREST LOOPHOLE FOR HEDGE FUND
MANAGERS.
I CALL TO REIGN IN CEO PAY.
I NOW HAVE THE MOST EFFECTIVE
AND COMPREHENSIVE PLAN TO DEAL
WITH THE THREATS THAT WALL
STREET POSES AND I GO FURTHER
THAN SENATOR SANDERS DOES
BECAUSE I WANT TO GO AFTER ALL
THE OTHER BAD ACTORS LIKE HEDGE
FUNDS AND THE AIG.
I TAKE A BACKSEAT TO NOBODY IN
BEING VERY CLEAR ABOUT WHAT I
WILL DO TO MAKE SURE WALL STREET
NEVER CRASHES MAIN STREET AGAIN
AND THAT YOU CAN COUNT ON.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I DO
RESPECT YOU VERY MUCH.
IN FACT, ONLY A DECADE AGO I WAS
A VERY BIG SUPPORTER OF YOURSELF
AND YOUR HUSBAND.
IT ACTUALLY BROKE MY HEART WHEN
YOU SAID MARRIAGE WAS BETWEEN A
MAN AND A WOMAN.
HOW CAN WE TRUST THAT THIS ISN'T
JUST MORE POLITICAL RHETORIC?
PLEASE JUST RELEASE THOSE
TRANSCRIPTS SO THAT WE KNOW
EXACTLY WHERE YOU STAND.
>> YOU KNOW WHERE I STAND
BECAUSE I'VE BEEN IN PUBLIC
STANDING HERE THE WHOLE TIME,
BUT LET ME SAY SOMETHING ABOUT
THIS.
I LIKE MANY AMERICANS HAVE
EVOLVED AND I'M GLAD I HAVE.
I AM A 100% SUPPORTER -- I AM
ABSOLUTELY ADAMANT ABOUT
PROTECTING MARRIAGE EQUALITY AND
I THINK IT'S SIGNIFICANT THAT
THE HUMAN RIGHTS CAMPAIGN, THE
LEADING ORGANIZATION IN OUR
COUNTRY TO ENSURE THAT THE LGBT
COMMUNITY HAS THE RIGHTS THEY
DESERVE HAVE ENDORSED ME.
NOW YOUR CANDIDATE SAID THAT'S
BECAUSE THEY'RE A MEMBER OF THE
ESTABLISHMENT.
WITH ALL DUE RESPECT THEY FIGHT
AGAINST THE ESTABLISHMENT EVERY
SINGLE DAY AND I'VE BEEN WITH
THEM FOR YEARS AND I WILL PASS
THE EQUALITY ACT TOO.
I JUST SAW ANOTHER ONE OF MY
FRIENDS CONGRESSWOMAN TITUS.
THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT
HOUSING.
IT'S A BIG PROBLEM HERE IN
NEVADA.
THIS WAS THE TOP STATE IN THE
COUNTRY FOR FORECLOSURES FOR THE
CRISIS.
>> FIRST I'D LIKE TO THANK YOU
YOU FOR YOUR LIFE LONG
COMMITMENT NO THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY AND COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
>> THANK YOU.
>> AS YOU KNOW, MANY HISPANICS
ACHIEVING HOME OWNERSHIP IS
SYNONYMOUS TO ACHIEVING THE
AMERICAN DREAM.
WE WERE HIT PARTICULARLY HARD
DURING THE GREAT RECESSION.
WHAT WOULD A CLINTON
ADMINISTRATION DO TO EASE THE
FEARS OF HOME OWNERSHIP AMONG
OUR COUNTRY.
>> I KNOW HOW HARD HIT NEVADA
WAS.
I THINK THE HIGHEST RATE OF
FORECLOSURES, YOU STILL HAVE A
LOT OF HOUSES UNDER WATER,
MEANING THAT THE VALUE IS NOT
EQUAL TO WHAT YOU HAD TO PAY FOR
IT AND WHAT THE MORTGAGE
PRINCIPAL AND INTEREST ARE, I
TAKE THAT VERY SERIOUSLY SO
HERE'S WHAT I WANT TO DO.
I WANT US TO MOVE IN ANY WAY WE
CAN IN THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO
HELP RELIEVE THE BURDEN OF
ALREADY EXISTING HOMEOWNERS.
I DON'T WANT THE KIND OF WAVE OF
FORECLOSURES THAT STRUCK THIS
STATE EVER AGAIN TO HAPPEN.
SECONDLY, WE WANT TO PROVIDE
MORE HELP SO THAT MORE
HOMEOWNERS, HISPANIC,
AFRICAN-AMERICAN HOMEOWNERS,
THOSE WHO WANT TO BE HAVE ACCESS
TO BETTER CREDIT AND SUPPORT.
CREDIT HAS TIGHTENED UP IN WAYS
THAT ARE NOT FAIR.
YOU ARE THREE TIMES MORE LIKELY
TO BE ABLE TO GET A MORTGAGE IF
YOU'RE A WHITE APPLICANT IF
YOU'RE BLACK OR HISPANIC EVEN IF
YOU HAVE THE SAME CREDENTIALS.
THAT HAS TO END.
I WILL GO AFTER THAT KIND OF
DISCRIMINATION WITH EVERYTHING
I'VE GOT USING EVERY HOUSING
AUTHORITY, THE JUSTICE
DEPARTMENT, THE U.S. ATTORNEY.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE THIS
KIND OF BIGOTRY.
I'M RUNNING DOWN TO KNOCK DOWN
THE BARRIERS THAT STAND IN THE
WAY OF PEOPLE GETTING AHEAD.
WE HAVE TO GET INCOMES UP SO YOU
HAVE MORE OF A CHANCE TO SAVE
FOR THE DOWN PAYMENT AND YOU
HAVE A BETTER CHANCE TO GET IN A
HOME AND STAY THERE.
SO I'M GOING TO USE EVERY TOOL
AT MY DISPOSAL TO MAKE THAT
DREAM A REALITY.
>> I PURCHASED A HOME SIX MONTHS
AGO AND I CAN RELATE AS THE
AMOUNT OF HOOPS THAT I HAD TO
JUMP AS A 24-YEAR-OLD HISPANIC
WERE UNPRECEDENTED.
THANK YOU FOR THAT.
>> I'M TELLING YOU IF YOU WERE
NOT A HISPANIC THERE WOULD NOT
HAVE BEEN AS MANY HOOPS.
THAT IS NOT RIGHT.
THAT HAS TO END.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THIS IS A RETIREE AND HE HAS A
QUESTION ABOUT SOCIAL SECURITY.
>> GOOD EVENING, SECRETARY.
HOW ARE YOU?
MY QUESTION HAS TO DO WITH
SOCIAL SECURITY.
HARD WORKING PEOPLE PAY INTO
SOCIAL SECURITY WITH HOPE AND
ANTICIPATION THAT IN THE FUTURE
THEY WILL RECEIVE THE BENEFIT OF
THEIR LABOR AND MONETARY
INVESTMENT.
SOCIAL SECURITY NEEDS A 21th
CENTURY UPDATE TO KEEP IT
FINANCIALLY SOUND FOR FUTURE
GENERATIONS.
THIS WILL TAKE PRESIDENTIAL
LEADERSHIP.
WHAT IS YOUR SPECIFIC PLAN TO
ADDRESS THIS ISSUE FOR THE MANY
WHO NEED IT FOR ECONOMIC
SURVIVAL?
>> SO IMPORTANT AND FIRST THING
WE HAVE TO DO IS PREVENT THE
REPUBLICANS EVER FROM
PRIVATIZING IT.
THEY ARE STILL DETERMINED TO
PRIVATIZE SOCIAL SECURITY.
HARRY REMEMBERS AFTER BUSH GOT
REELECTED IN 2004 THE FIRST
THING HE SAID WAS LET'S GO
PRIVATIZE SOCIAL SECURITY.
I WAS ONE OF THE LEADERS IN THE
SENATE WITH HARRY AND OTHERS, WE
WENT AROUND THE COUNTRY AND MADE
IT CLEAR WE WOULD NEVER LET THAT
HAPPEN.
THEIR WHOLE PLAN WAS TO GIVE THE
SOCIAL SECURITY TRUST FUND TO
WALL STREET.
IMAGINE THAT.
IF YOU THOUGHT WE HAD SCANDALS
AND COLLAPSE BEFORE, THINK OF
THAT.
THAT WILL NEVER HAPPEN ON MY
WATCH, BUT HERE'S WHAT WILL
HAPPEN.
WE NEED TO GET MORE MONEY INTO
THE SOCIAL SECURITY TRUST FUND.
THERE'S A COUPLE OF DIFFERENT
WAYS I'M LOOKING AT AND I'LL
HAVE TO TALK WITH THE CONGRESS
TO TRY TO FIGURE OUT WHAT'S THE
BEST WAY FORWARD.
WE CAN RAISE THE CAP AND GET
MORE MONEY THAT WAY.
WE CAN GO AFTER THE EXISTING
PERCENTAGE THAT COMES OUT OF
PEOPLE'S PAYCHECKS, WE CAN GO
AFTER WHAT'S CALLED PASSIVE
INCOME SO RICH PEOPLE HAVE TO
PAY ON ALL THEIR INCOME, NOT
JUST THEIR EARNED INCOME BECAUSE
THEY LIVE OFF CAPITAL GAINS AND
INVESTMENT INCOME.
WE HAVE TOO MANY SOCIAL SECURITY
RECIPIENTS RIGHT NOW WHO ARE
BARELY MAKING IT.
AND THAT'S LARGELY BECAUSE
NUMBER ONE THEY WERE LOW WAGE
WORKERS DURING THEIR LIFETIME.
THEY DIDN'T PUT THAT MUCH INTO
THE FUND SO NOW WHEN THEY NEED
IT, THEY'RE CAPPED OUT.
THEY DON'T GET WHAT THEY NEED TO
LIVE ON.
WE ALSO HAVE A PROBLEM OF OLDER
WOMEN WHO MAY NOT HAVE WORKED AT
ALL DURING THEIR LIFETIMES.
THEY TOOK CARE OF HOMES AND
FAMILIES.
THEY CONTRIBUTED TO THEIR
COMMUNITIES.
SO THEY DON'T HAVE MUCH TO DRAW
ON EITHER AND THEN ONE OF THE
SADDEST PROBLEMS I'M GOING TO GO
AFTER IS WHAT HAPPENS WHEN A
HUSBAND DIES AND THEN A WIDOW
LOSES HALF OF HER SOCIAL
SECURITY PAYMENT.
IF SHE'S NOT MAKING MUCH TO
BEGIN WITH, I'VE MET A LOT OF
THESE WOMEN, THEY'RE LOSING
THEIR HOMES, THEY'RE REALLY IN
FINANCIAL DISTRESS.
SO WE'RE GOING TO GET IT MORE
SOLVENT AND FIX SOME OF THE
PROBLEMS OF THE PEOPLE MOST IN
NEED AND THAT'S WHAT I'LL DO AS
PRESIDENT.
>> AMONG THOSE DIFFERENT ISSUES
THAT YOU MENTIONED AS YOU KNOW
PEOPLE PAY SOCIAL SECURITY TAXES
ON INCOME UP TO ABOUT $120,000.
SENATOR SANDERS WANTS TO CHANGE
THAT.
YOU ARE WERE OPPOSED TO RAISING
THE CAP IN 2008.
THIS TIME AROUND YOU SEEM TO BE
CONSIDERING IT.
SHOULD PEOPLE START PAYING
SOCIAL SECURITY INCOME TAXES ON
OVER $120,000?
>> IT COULD BE OVER $250,000.
IT COULD BE A HIGHER AMOUNT, BUT
THIS IS THE KIND OF ISSUE THAT
YOU'VE GOT TO TRY TO FIGURE OUT
WHERE THE CONGRESS MIGHT BE.
SO I'VE LAID OUT A NUMBER OF
DIFFERENT APPROACHES TO GET THE
MONEY.
THE OTHER ONE THAT I MENTIONED
TO THE GENTLEMAN IS PUTTING THE
-- PUTTING THE PERCENTAGE ON
PASSIVE INCOME SO THAT PEOPLE
WITH A LOT OF INCOME, BUT FROM
CAPITAL GAINS AND INVESTMENTS --
THEY DON'T PAY MUCH INTO SOCIAL
SECURITY, BUT THEY HAVE A LOT OF
MONEY, THEY WILL HAVE TO PAY
MORE.
SO THOSE ARE A COUPLE OF THE
OPTIONS.
I THINK WE CAN PICK ONE OR MORE
OF THOSE, BUT THE GOAL IS TO GET
MORE MONEY INTO THE TRUST FUND.
>> WOULD YOU EVER IMAGINE
RAISING THE RETIREMENT AGE IN
THE NEXT TEN YEARS?
>> NO AND I'LL TELL YOU WHY.
NO.
I'LL TELL YOU WHY.
RIGHT NOW IF YOU LOOK AT WHO
DRAWS SOCIAL SECURITY FOR THE
LONGEST TIME PEOPLE WHO HAVE
WORKED HARD FOR MANY YEARS,
PEOPLE WHO ARE OFTEN REALLY
BROKEN DOWN BY THE PHYSICAL
LABORER THE REPETITIVE LABOR
THAT THEY'VE DONE, THEIR LIFE
SPAN IS MUCH LOWER THAN THE LIFE
SPAN OF PEOPLE LIKE YOU AND ME
WHO HAD A DIFFERENT SORT OF
LIFE, MADE OUR MONIES DIFFERENT
WAYS, DIDN'T HAVE TO WORK THAT
HARD.
SO RIGHT NOW THE AVERAGE DEATH
AGE FOR A LOT OF AMERICANS AND
LATINOS AND AFRICAN-AMERICANS IS
LOWER THAN THE AVERAGE DEATH AGE
OF WHITES AND THAT'S LOWER STILL
THAN THE AGE OF PEOPLE WHO ARE
AFFLUENT AND WELL EDUCATED.
SO RAISING THE RETIREMENT AGE
WOULD VERY WELL ELIMINATE A LOT
OF HARD WORKING PEOPLE FROM
GETTING MUCH SOCIAL SECURITY AT
ALL.
I WILL NOT DO THAT.
I WANT PEOPLE TO HAVE THE BEST
POSSIBLE OLDER YEARS SO THAT IS
RULED OUT FOR ME.
>> THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A BREAK IN
HERE AND WHEN WE COME BACK A LOT
MORE ISSUES AND WE'LL HEAR FROM
A LOT MORE FOLKS.
THE TOWN HALL.
JUST TWO DAYS BEFORE NEVADA
DEMOCRATS GO AND CAUCUS.
IT'S BEEN NO SECRET MANY
DEMOCRATIC VOTERS ARE WORRIED
ABOUT SOME QUESTIONS OF TRUST.
OUR NEXT QUESTION HAS TO DO WITH
THAT.
>> GOOD EVENING.
MY NAME IS TIANA WINTERS.
I'M REPRESENTING THE GREEN SPUN
COLLEGE OF URBAN AFFAIRS.
MY QUESTION TONIGHT IS MY
GENERATION IS THE GENERATION
THAT GREW OUT OF THAT ECONOMIC
DOWN TURN.
GONE ARE THE DAYS OF AFFORDABLE
TUITION, BOOMING JOB MARKET AND
ATTAINING THAT CLASSIC AMERICAN
DREAM.
WE NEED A REBEL.
WE NEED SOMEBODY WHO IS GOING TO
BE BY OUR SIDE AND ENSURE THAT
AFTER WORKING HARD AND PUTTING
IN OUR TIME THAT WE WILL BE ABLE
TO ATTAIN THAT SUCCESS.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS BECAUSE MY
GENERATION IS A LITTLE WARY OF
PLACING ANOTHER POLITICIAN IN
THE WHITE HOUSE WITH YOUR TENURE
IN POLITICS, HOW ARE YOU GOING
TO DESERVE OUR VOTE?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I KNOW
THAT YOU THINK WITH GOOD CAUSE
EVERYTHING IS MESSED UP BECAUSE
THAT HAS BEEN YOUR PERSONAL
EXPERIENCE.
I HAVE THE DEEPEST RESPECT FOR
AND FEELING FOR YOUNG PEOPLE WHO
LITERALLY CAME OUT OF THE GREAT
RECESSION READY TO GET ON WITH
THEIR LIVES AND ARE FINDING
BARRIERS EVERYWHERE THEY TURN.
I BELIEVE WITH ALL MY HEART THAT
I'M THE BEST PERSON TO BE THE
PRESIDENT WHO WILL DELIVER FOR
YOU.
I'VE ACTUALLY BEEN IN ELECTIVE
OFFICE SHORTER PERIOD THAN
SENATOR SANDERS WHO HAS BEEN IN
THE CONGRESS 25 YEARS, I'VE BEEN
THERE FOR EIGHT, BUT I'VE BEEN
SECRETARY OF STATE AND I WAS A
VERY BIG ACTIVIST MY ENTIRE LIFE
AND I KNOW WHAT HAS TO BE DONE
AND I WILL DO IT.
THAT'S WHY I'VE LAID OUT PLANS
TO REMOVE THE ECONOMIC BARRIERS
THAT STAND IN THE WAY OF YOUNG
PEOPLE.
YOU KNOW, I WANT TO STOP BAD
ACTORS FROM DOING BAD THINGS.
THERE'S NO DISAGREEMENT THERE,
BUT I WANT TO MAKE SOME GOOD
THINGS HAPPEN.
I WANT TO GET BACK TO THE KIND
OF JOB CREATION WE HAD WHEN MY
HUSBAND WAS PRESIDENT AND GET
INCOMES RISING BECAUSE AMERICANS
HAVEN'T HAD A RISE IN 15 YEARS.
I WANT TO BE SURE THAT WE KNOCK
DOWN THE BARRIERS THAT HOLD BACK
PEOPLE BECAUSE OF RACISM, SEXISM
AND ALL THE KINDS OF PREJUDICE
AND BY BIAS THAT'S OUT THERE.
I WANT TO BE SURE THAT WOMEN GET
EQUAL PAY.
I WANT TO MAKE COLLEGE
AFFORDABLE AND I HAVE A PLAN TO
GET STUDENT DEBT DOWN TO ALLOW
YOU TO REPAY AND REFINANCE AT A
MUCH LOWER COST AND BE ABLE TO
GET OUT OF IT SOONER SO YOU'RE
NOT PAYING YOUR STUDENT DEBTS 30
YEARS FROM NOW.
THAT'S RIDICULOUS.
I DIDN'T HAVE TO DO THAT.
I HAD STUDENT DEBT AND I GOT IT
PAID BACK IN ABOUT 15 YEARS
BECAUSE I HAD A REASONABLE
AMOUNT AND I WANT TO MOVE YOUNG
PEOPLE TO WHO ARE CALLED
CONTINGENT REPAYMENT PLANS, YOU
PAY A PERCENTAGE OF WHAT YOU
EARN, NOT A FIXED INTEREST RATE.
I WANT TO TRIPLE THE AMOUNTS OF
NATIONAL SERVICE JOBS AND DOUBLE
THE AMOUNT OF EDUCATION GRANTS.
SO I HAVE A COMPREHENSIVE PLAN
AND I THINK IT'S REALLY
IMPORTANT FOR YOUNG PEOPLE TO
UNDERSTAND YOU KNOW WHAT, WE'VE
GOT TO HAVE BIG BOLD PLANS.
WE'VE GOT TO HAVE OUR IDEAS AND
OUR VALUES AND THEN WE HAVE TO
FIGURE OUT HOW ARE WE GOING TO
GET IT DONE.
HOW ARE WE GOING TO MAKE IT
HAPPEN.
I AM ABSOLUTELY CONFIDENT I CAN
DO THAT.
THAT'S WHY I'M ASKING FOR YOUR
VOTE AND YOUR SUPPORT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> MADAM SECRETARY, YOU PROBABLY
SAW THE EXIT POLLS.
WHAT ABOUT THIS IS TRUST
DEFICIT.
TO BE A SUCCESSFUL PRESIDENT
YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE TO ERASE
THIS TRUST DEFICIT THAT YOU'RE
DEALING WITH RIGHT NOW.
HOW DO YOU DEAL WITH IT?
>> I'VE WON ONE, HE'S WON ONE
AND WE HAVE 48 TO GO AND THAT'S
WHY WE'RE HERE IN NEVADA WORKING
AS HARD AS WE CAN AND THEN TO
SOUTH CAROLINA AND ALL THE OTHER
STATES THAT COME AFTER.
I AM ABSOLUTELY FOCUSSED ON
DELIVERING RESULTS FOR PEOPLE
AND ANY FAIR READING OF WHAT
I'VE DONE SINCE I WENT TO WORK
AS A YOUNG LAWYER UP UNTIL TODAY
SHOWS I KNOW HOW TO DO THAT.
IT IS OBVIOUSLY TROUBLING THAT
PEOPLE HAVE QUESTIONS ABOUT ME,
WHICH I WILL DO MY BEST TO
ANSWER, BUT I THINK THEY REALLY
COME DOWN TO SAYING LIKE THIS
YOUNG WOMAN ASKED ME YOU'VE BEEN
AROUND AWHILE, WE'VE SEEN YOUR
FACE A LONG TIME, WHAT DOES THAT
ACTUALLY MEAN.
I'VE BEEN AROUND DOING STUFF.
I'VE BEEN AROUND GETTING THINGS
THAT I BELIEVE WILL HELP PEOPLE
AND THAT'S WHAT I'M GOING TO
KEEP DOING.
WHEN I RAN FOR THE SENATE IN NEW
YORK, PEOPLE SAID THE SAME
THING, WE CAN'T TRUST HER, WE
DON'T KNOW HER.
I WON AND THEN WHEN I RAN AGAIN
SIX YEARS LATER I WAS REELECTED
WITH AN EVEN LARGE PERCENTAGE OF
THE VOTE BECAUSE PEOPLE SAW ME
IN ACTION.
PEOPLE ARE ASKING IS SHE IN IT
FOR HERSELF OR IS SHE IN IT FOR
ME.
I'VE BEEN SOMEBODY WHO BELIEVED
AND RAISED IN MY FAMILY AND MY
FAITH THAT I WITH MY BLESSINGS
HAD AN OPPORTUNITY AND
OBLIGATION TO DO WHAT I COULD TO
HELP OTHERS AND THAT'S WHAT I'LL
DO AS PRESIDENT.
>> THANK YOU.
WE HAVE A RUN ON RUNNING REBELS
WHEN IT COMES ON OUR QUESTIONS.
>> MY QUESTION IS ON YOUR DEBT
FREE COLLEGE PROPOSALS.
WILL YOUR DEBT FREE COLLEGE
PROPOSALS GIVE THE SAME
OPPORTUNITIES TO LATINOS AND
DECA AS SENATOR SANDERS TUITION
FREE PROPOSAL.
>> I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO
MAKE SURE THAT IT DOES AND I
WANT TO MAKE THAT POSSIBLE I
HOPE I CAN DO IT WITHOUT
LEGISLATIVE ACTION BUT I MIGHT
NOT BE ABLE TO AND HE MAY NOT BE
ABLE TO.
THAT'S WHY COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM IS SO
IMPORTANT BECAUSE THAT WOULD
CLEAR THIS UP.
I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING I CAN
TO MAKE SURE THE YOUNG PEOPLE --
I MET A YOUNG WOMAN WHO WANTS TO
BE A DOCTOR.
SHE CAME HERE AS A CHILD
UNDOCUMENTED.
SHE'S AT THE TOP OF HER CLASS
HERE IN LAS VEGAS.
SHE'S WORRIED.
CAN SHE GET INTO SCHOOL BEING
UNDOCUMENTED.
CAN SHE GET THE SCHOLARSHIP SHE
AND HER FAMILY WOULD NEED.
CAN THEY GRADUATE AND GO TO
MEDICAL SCHOOL.
CAN SHE GET A LICENSE.
THAT IS JUST HEART BREAKING TO
ME SO I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING
I CAN TO CLEAR ALL THE BARRIERS
AWAY SO THAT EVERY YOUNG PERSON
IN THIS COUNTRY HAS THE SAME
CHANCE TO MAKE A CONTRIBUTION AS
THAT YOUNG WOMAN WANTS TO MAKE.
>> SO BASED ON THE PROPOSAL THAT
YOU HAVE RIGHT NOW, FOR EXAMPLE
THE GRANTS THAT YOU'RE WILLING
TO GIVE TO STUDENTS, HOW WOULD
THOSE ALSO BE GRANTED TO DOCA
STUDENTS FOR EXAMPLE?
>> YES.
I THINK BOTH SENATOR SANDERS AND
I ARE SEEKING THE SAME GOAL, TO
MAKE COLLEGE AFFORDABLE FOR
EVERYBODY.
I BELIEVE MY PLAN IS A BETTER
WAY TO GET IT DONE AND THEREFORE
I'M STANDING BEHIND IT AND I AM
STRONGLY IN FAVOR OF CLEARING
AWAY ALL THESE BARRIERS.
SO YES, ANYTHING I CAN DO TO
MAKE SURE EVERY SINGLE YOUNG
PERSON WHO WANTS TO GO TO
COLLEGE IN THIS COUNTRY IS GIVEN
THE CHANCE TO DO IT.
IT'S ALSO WHY I WANT TO MAKE
COMMUNITY COLLEGE FREE BECAUSE
IF COMMUNITY COLLEGE IS FREE,
THEN A LOTS OF YOUNG PEOPLE CAN
GO TO COMMUNITY COLLEGE WITHOUT
A LOT OF THE ASSISTANCE THAT
THEY MIGHT NEED FOR A FOUR-YEAR
COLLEGE OR UNIVERSITY.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THE CAUCUS COUGH, WE KNOW
THAT WELL.
>> YES, THE COUGH.
SECRETARY, A QUICK FOLLOW UP ON
THAT AND I KNOW IT'S A STATES
ISSUE, BUT DRIVER'S LICENSE FOR
THE UNDOCUMENTED, DO YOU FORESEE
A TIME WHEN THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT WOULD BE ABLE TO
INCLUDE THE UNDOCUMENTED IN
FEDERAL GRANTS FOR EDUCATION FOR
EXAMPLE BECAUSE IF THE STATE
DOESN'T DO IT, IT DOESN'T MEAN
THAT THEY DON'T HAVE THOSE
DREAMS AND ASPIRATIONS THAT THEY
CAN'T REACH BECAUSE IN
WASHINGTON THEY DECIDE THAT
THEY'RE NOT EQUAL.
>> ABSOLUTELY TRUE.
I'M PROUD OF ALL THE STATES THAT
HAVE TAKEN STEPS TO MAKE SURE
THAT GRANTS AND COLLEGE TUITION
AND OTHER THINGS ARE TAKEN CARE
OF FOR DREAMERS, FOR OTHERS WHO
ARE UNDOCUMENTED, BUT IT SHOULD
BE A NATIONAL PRIORITY AND
THAT'S ANOTHER ELEMENT OF
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION REFORM
BECAUSE ONCE WE GET THAT, THERE
ARE NO MORE QUESTIONS.
EVERYBODY IS ENTITLED TO THE
SAME RIGHTS AND BENEFITS.
I'M NOT SURE EVERYBODY IN THE
AUDIENCE EVEN KNOWS EVERY YOO
UNDOCUMENTED WORKERS CONTRIBUTE
$12 BILLION TO THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TRUST FUND AND THE BEST
ESTIMATE IS THAT UNDER
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION REFORM
THAT AMOUNT WOULD GO UP TO 20 --
IT WOULD BE AN ADDITIONAL $20
BILLION EVERY YEAR.
YOU TALK ABOUT MAKING THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TRUST FUND SOLVENT,
GETTING PEOPLE OUT OF THE
SHADOWS AND GETTING THEM IN THE
ECONOMY TO BE ABLE TO PURSUE
THEIR DREAMS HELPS ALL OF US.
SO ABSOLUTELY WE'RE GOING TO
HEAD FOR THAT.
>> [ SPEAKING SPANISH ]
>> MONEY THEY CAN CONTRIBUTE AND
NEVER SEE ANYTHING BACK FROM.
>> THAT'S RIGHT.
THEY CONTRIBUTE FOR EVERYBODY
ELSE.
I WANT YOU TO BE ABLE TO
CONTRIBUTE AND AS A CITIZEN BE
ABLE TO DRAW IT DOWN BECAUSE
IT'S YOURS.
>> SAY HELLO.
HE HAS A QUESTION ABOUT LABOR
UNIONS.
>> GOOD EVENING, SECRETARY
CLINTON.
YOUR TIES TO CORPORATE AMERICA
HAVE BEEN AT THE CENTER OF THIS
CAMPAIGN.
AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES AND FORMER BOARD MEMBER
OF THE BOARD OF DIRECTORS OF
WALMART, WILL YOU BE SILENT ON
WALMART'S ANTI-UNION CAMPAIGN,
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY WILL YOU
PROPOSE LEGISLATION THAT
PROTECTS THE RIGHTS OF WORKERS
TO ORGANIZE IN THE WORKPLACE?
>> CAN I TELL YOU --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THE ANSWER TO THAT IS YES AND
IT'S WHY ALL THE UNIONS HAVE
ENDORSED ME AND I WANT TO TELL
YOU INCLUDING -- INCLUDING THE
UNION -- THE UNION COMMERCIALS
-- THAT IS AT THE FOREFRONT OF
THE ORGANIZING CAMPAIGN AT
WALMART, BUT MOST OF THE OTHER
UNIONS HAVE, PUBLIC UNIONS,
PRIVATE SECTOR UNIONS AND YOU
KNOW WHY, HERE WE GO.
LET'S BACK TO THE FACTS BECAUSE
I'VE ALWAYS BEEN THERE FOR THEM.
OUR GREAT SECRETARY OF LABOR WHO
IS HERE, WHERE IS TOM?
RIGHT THERE.
HE IS SOMEBODY WHO HAS BEEN ON
THE FRONT LINES STANDING UP FOR
WORKERS AND UNIONS.
HE ENDORSED ME.
LOOK AT THE FACTS.
UNIONS HAVE ENDORSED ME BECAUSE
I'M ON THEIR SIDE.
I'VE BEEN THERE YEAR IN AND YEAR
OUT AND I WILL AS PRESIDENT.
>> ONE MORE QUESTION, WILL YOU
SUPPORT A LIVING WAGE OF $15 AN
HOUR, WHICH IS AN ISSUE THAT IS
VERY -- THAT IS AT THE FOREFRONT
OF WORKING FAMILIES?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
I SUPPORT A FEDERAL MINIMUM WAGE
AND I SUPPORT STATES GOING
HIGHER THAN THE FEDERAL MINIMUM
WAGE.
THAT'S WHY I SUPPORT ANDREW
CUOMO IN NEW YORK.
I SUPPORTED WHAT THEY DID IN
L.A. AND SEATTLE.
I'M STANDING WITH THE MAJORITY
OF DEMOCRATS IN THE SENATE WHO
HAVE INTRODUCED A MINIMUM WAGE
INCREASE TO $12.
THAT WOULD PUT IT AT THE HIGHEST
IT HAS BEEN SINCE 1968.
THAT WOULD MEAN A WAGE INCREASE
FOR 35 MILLION AMERICAN WORKERS.
AND ONE IN FOUR LOW-WAGE WORKERS
WHO ARE NOW JUST BARELY GETTING
BY AND IT WOULD HELP SO MANY
WOMEN BECAUSE THE MAJORITY OF
MINIMUM WAGE WORKERS ARE WOMEN.
SO I'M ABSOLUTELY IN FAVOR OF
IT.
I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN.
WE'LL SET IT AND I WILL USE THE
BULLY PULL PIT TO CONVINCE
STATES THAT BELIEVE THEY CAN GO
FURTHER TO DO THAT.
>> MADAM SECRETARY, A SUBJECT
CHANGE HERE.
LET ME INTRODUCE YOU TO MARY
CHAPMAN.
SHE HAS A QUESTION ON FOREIGN
POLICY.
>> WHAT STRATEGIES DO YOU PLAN
TO EMPLOY IN DEALING WITH THE
CONFLICTS WITH WOMEN AND
CHILDREN'S RIGHTS VERSUS THE
PRACTICES UTILIZED BY SOME OF
OUR MIDDLE EASTERN ALLIES.
>> I WENT TO BEIJING IN 1995 AND
SAID HUMAN RIGHT ARE WOMEN'S
RIGHTS AND I BELIEVE THAT WITH
ALL MY HEART AND WHEN I WAS
SECRETARY OF STATE I PUT WOMEN'S
RIGHTS AT THE CENTER OF OUR
FOREIGN POLICY AND I WENT TO 112
COUNTRIES FOR ALL OF YOU.
I RAISED IT IN EVERY COUNTRY.
I LOOKED ACROSS THE TABLE AT
DICTATORS AND SEXISTS -- YEAH, I
DID -- AND I RAISED IT WITH
EVERY ONE OF THEM.
SO IT WILL BE A HUGE ISSUE FOR
ME.
YOU KNOW, I ALSO RAISE GAY
RIGHTS.
I WENT TO GENEVA AND I MADE A
SPEECH ABOUT HOW GAY RIGHTS ARE
HUMAN RIGHTS BECAUSE THE PEOPLE
WHO ARE OFTEN THE MOST OWE
MISTREATED IN MANY COUNTRIES ARE
THE LGBT COMMUNITY.
HUMAN RIGHTS HAS TO BE AT THE
CENTER OF WHO WE ARE AS A NATION
AND WHAT I WILL DO AS PRESIDENT.
>> QUICK FOLLOW UP ON FOREIGN
POLICY.
PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS ANNOUNCED
HE'S GOING TO GO TO CUBA IN
MARCH.
WHAT HAS CUBA DONE TO EARN A
PRESIDENTIAL VISIT?
IT'S ONE THING TO OPEN
DIPLOMATIC TIES, BUT SINCE
DECEMBER THERE HAVE BEEN SOME
REGRESSION, PARTICULARLY ON SOME
HUMAN RIGHTS ISSUE.
IS A PRESIDENTIAL VISIT A STEP
TOO FAR?
WOULD A PRESIDENT CLINTON BE
GOING THIS QUICKLY REWARDING
CUBA WITH A PRESIDENTIAL VISIT
THIS QUICKLY?
>> I KNOW THAT THE PRESIDENT
INTENDS TO RAISE HUMAN RIGHTS
ISSUES.
HE WILL BE VERY OPEN ABOUT THAT,
I AM SURE, TALKING ABOUT THE
ONGOING ABUSES WITHIN CUBA THAT
ARE VISITED UPON WHO ARE SEEKING
FREEDOM, STANDING UP, SPEAKING
OUT.
I THINK HAVING THE PRESIDENT ON
CUBAN SOIL DELIVERING THAT
MESSAGE IS VERY POWERFUL AND
I'LL SAY TOO, CHUCK, I WAS
DETERMINED AS SECRETARY OF STATE
TO TRY TO GET AN OPENING TO
BURMA AND A LOT OF PEOPLE THAT
WILL NEVER HAPPEN, THE MILITARY
DICTATORSHIP WILL NEVER CHANGE
AND I SAID WE HAVE TO TRY.
SO I WENT AND I MADE THE CASE
FOR WHY IT WOULD BE BETTER FOR
THEM TO OPEN TO PURSUE DEMOCRACY
AND FREEDOM AND THEN I TOOK THE
PRESIDENT BACK WITH ME AND THE
PRESIDENT SPOKE OUT AND HE SPOKE
TO A BIG GROUP OF STUDENTS AND
SAID YOU DESERVE BETTER, SPEAK
OUT FOR IT, SPEAK UP FOR IT.
THE UNITED STATES WILL SUPPORT
YOU.
LOOK WHAT'S HAPPENED.
THERE WAS AN ELECTION.
THE PARTY WON, THE MILITARY IS
TURNING OVER POWER.
NOW, WE CAN'T PROMISE THAT IN
EVERYTHING, BUT IF WE DON'T TAKE
REASONABLE STEPS, WE NEGOTIATED
A LONG TIME TO TRY TO GET THE
OPENING TO CUBA, SO I THINK THE
PRESIDENT'S GOAL IS TO MAKE IT
CLEAR TO THE CUBAN PEOPLE WE'RE
WITH YOU TODAY, TOMORROW AND
INTO THE FUTURE.
WE KNOW YOU DESERVE A FUTURE OF
FREEDOM.
>> SOME PEOPLE WORRY THE
ADMINISTRATION HAS LOST LEVERAGE
ON THIS ISSUE OF HUMAN RIGHTS.
>> I THINK IT'S A DIFFERENT
SITUATION BECAUSE THERE'S SO
MUCH TRAFFIC NOW BETWEEN THE
UNITED STATES AND CUBA.
THERE'S SO MANY AMERICANS BOTH
CUBAN AMERICANS AND OTHER
AMERICANS COMING TO LOOK AT NEW
BUSINESSES, LOOKING TO MAKE
ALLIANCES WITH PEOPLE IN THEIR
PROFESSIONS OR SIMILAR INTERESTS
SO I THINK IT'S NOT JUST A
PRESIDENTIAL VISIT, IT IS A
PUNCTUATION POINT THAT MAKES
CLEAR THE UNITED STATES IS GOING
TO STAY WITH THIS, WE'RE GOING
TO KEEP PUSHING.
I DON'T THINK THE CASTROS CAN
LIVE FOREVER UNLESS THEY HAVE
FOUND SOME MAGIC WATER FUN TAKEN
SOMEWHERE.
WE NEED TO SAY WE'RE HERE, WHAT
ARE YOU GOING TO DO FOR YOUR
PEOPLE.
LOOK HOW FAR BEHIND YOU ARE.
THE ECONOMY IS IN CUBA IS
STUTTERING BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT
PART OF THE LARGER WORLD.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR BEING
WITH US TONIGHT.
>> OH MY GOSH, IT'S OVER.
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU.
>> WE'LL TRY TO GO -- WE WOULD
TRY TO GO A THIRD HOUR.
>> THANKS VERY MUCH.
RACHEL MADDOW TAKES THINGS OVER
RIGHT NOW.
THANK YOU NEVADA.
>>> THAT WAS SUPER FUN.