WE'RE LIVE IN OHIO.
THE DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES FOR
PRESIDENT ARE HERE.
>> AND THE VOTERS HAVE FEWER
THAN TWO DAYS TO MAKE UP THEIR
MINDS.
>> TONIGHT, THE DEMOCRATS ARE IN
OHIO ANSWERING DIRECTLY TO
VOTERS IN ONE OF THE NATION'S
KEY BATTLEGROUND STATES.
>> I WANT TO BE THE PRESIDENT
FOR THE STRUGGLING AND THE
STRIVING.
>> WE HAVE A LONG, LONG WAY TO
GO TO REBUILD THE AMERICAN
MIDDLE CLASS.
>> HILLARY CLINTON AND BERNIE
SANDERS SHARING THE SPOTLIGHT
AND THE SCRUTINY.
>> IT MATTERS WHAT YOU SAY WHEN
YOU RUN FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
>> PRESSURE IS MOUNTING AS THE
FIGHT FOR DELEGATES ENTERS A
CRUCIAL ROUND.
>> WE'RE GOING TO WIN HERE ON
MARCH 15th AND TOGETHER WE'RE
GOING TO TRANSFORM AMERICA.
>>> THIS IS A TOWN HALL EVENT.
A CHANCE FOR VOTERS TO HAVE
THEIR SAY.
>> WE HAVE FOCUSED ON ISSUES.
>> THIS IS A GREAT COUNTRY AND
WE CAN DO A LOT BETTER THAN
WE'RE DOING NOW.
>> THE DEMOCRATS ARE MAKING
THEIR PITCH.
VOTERS ARE MAKING THEIR CHOICE
AND OHIO HANGS IN THE BALANCE
RIGHT NOW.
>>> LIVE ON THE CAMPUS OF THE
OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY IN
COLUMBUS, THIS IS THE CNN TV ONE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL.
WE WANT TO WELCOME OUR VIEWERS
HERE IN THE UNITED STATES AND
AROUND THE WORLD AND OUR PARTNER
TV ONE AND TO LISTENERS OF THE
TV ONE NETWORK, I'M JAKE TAPPER.
ELECTIONS IN THE STATE IS ABOUT
TO PLAY A CRITICAL ROLL ON
TUESDAY WHEN VOTERS GO TO THE
POLLS HERE ALONG WITH FOUR OTHER
BIG STATES.
IN THIS AUDITORIUM WE HAVE FOUND
MANY OHIO VOTERS WHO ARE STILL
UNDECIDED.
AND BEFORE THEY MAKE UP THEIR
MINDS THEY WANT ANSWERS FROM
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS AND
FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE
HILLARY CLINTON.
AUDIENCE MEMBERS HAVE SUBMITTED
QUESTIONS TO US.
WE HAVE REVIEWED THEM TO MAKE
SURE THAT THEY DO NOT OVERLAP,
I'LL BE ASKING SOME QUESTIONS AS
WELL AS WELL AS MY FRIEND ROLAND
MARTIN OF TV ONE.
FIRST, LET'S WELCOME SENATOR
BERNIE SANDERS OF VERMONT.
>> SO SENATOR, LET'S START.
I HAVE A FEW QUESTIONS, SO DID
ROLAND, THEN WE'LL GET TO OHIO
VOTERS.
THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF EMOTION ON
THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL AND IN SOME
CASES UNFORTUNATELY THERE'S BEEN
SOME VIOLENCE.
DONALD TRUMP HAS BEEN ON THE
STUMP BLAMING YOUR SUPPORTERS
FOR SOME OF IT.
TAKE A LISTEN.
>> LOOK, IT'S A BERNIE PERSON.
IT'S A BERNIE -- HELLO, BERNIE.
BERNIE, GET YOUR PEOPLE IN LINE,
BERNIE.
CAN YOU IMAGINE BERNIE SAYING
THAT TRUMP SHOULD GET HIS PEOPLE
UNDER CONTROL AND THEY PUT IN
THESE PEOPLE?
AND BY THE WAY, OUR CROWDS ARE
SO MUCH BIGGER THAN BERNIE'S,
YOU WOULDN'T BELIEVE IT.
>> YOUR RESPONSE, SENATOR?
>> I HATE TO SAY THIS BECAUSE I
REALLY DON'T LIKE TO DISPARAGE
PUBLIC OFFICIALS, BUT DONALD
TRUMP IS A PATHOLOGICAL LIAR.
WE HAVE NEVER -- OUR CAMPAIGN
DOES NOT BELIEVE AND NEVER WILL
ENCOURAGE ANYBODY TO DISRUPT
ANYTHING.
WE HAVE MILLIONS OF SUPPORTERS,
AND PEOPLE DO WHAT THEY DO, AND
PEOPLE HAVE THE RIGHT TO
PROTEST.
I HAPPEN NOT TO BELIEVE THAT
PEOPLE SHOULD DISRUPT ANYBODY'S
MEETINGS, BUT LET ME SAY
SOMETHING ABOUT MR. TRUMP.
SOME OF YOU MAY HAVE READ JUST A
FEW HOURS AGO THAT MR. TRUMP
SAID THAT HE IS PREPARED TO PAY
FOR THE LEGAL COSTS OF AN
INDIVIDUAL WHO SUCKER PUNCHED
SOMEBODY AT A RECENT EVENT.
HE IS GOING TO PAY THE LEGAL
FEES OF SOMEBODY WHO COMMITTED A
TERRIBLE ACT OF VIOLENCE.
WHAT THAT MEANS IS THAT DONALD
TRUMP IS LITERALLY INCITING
VIOLENCE WITH HIS SUPPORTERS.
HE IS SAYING THAT IF YOU GO OUT
TO BEAT SOMEBODY UP, THAT IS
OKAY, I WILL PAY THE LEGAL FEES.
THAT IS AN OUTRAGE AND I WOULD
HOPE THAT MR. TRUMP TONES IT
DOWN BIG TIME AND TELLS HIS
SUPPORTERS THAT VIOLENCE IS NOT
ACCEPTABLE IN THE AMERICAN
POLITICAL PROCESS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
SO I INTERVIEWED SENATOR MARCO
RUBIO THIS MORNING, AND HE TOLD
ME THAT HE IS ALSO VERY
CONCERNED ABOUT THE TONE THAT
DONALD TRUMP HAS AT HIS RALLIES,
AND SENATOR RUBIO TOLD ME THAT
HE IS, QUOTE, VERY CONCERNED
ABOUT THE TONE TO THE DEGREE
THAT HE'S WORRIED THAT SOMEBODY
MIGHT ACTUALLY LOSE THEIR LIFE.
ARE YOU CONCERNED THAT WAY?
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, JAKE, YOU
HEARD THIS ONE INDIVIDUAL WHO
SUCKER PUNCHED SOMEBODY, AND IF
HE IS QUOTED CORRECTLY, WHAT HE
SAID, WELL, YOU KNOW, WHY DID
YOU PUNCH HIM UP?
WELL, HE MIGHT BE A TERRORIST,
AND NEXT TIME I MIGHT HAVE TO
KILL HIM.
I THINK THAT'S ROUGHLY THE
QUOTE.
>> THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT HE SAID.
>> THAT'S WHAT HE SAID.
AND THIS IS GUY THAT TRUMP IS
GOING TO BE PAYING LEGAL FEES
FOR?
WHAT THAT IS ESSENTIALLY SAYING,
MY FRIENDS, IS AN INCITEMENT TO
VIOLENCE.
YOU GO BEATING UP SOMEBODY, IT'S
OKAY.
WE'LL PAY THE LEGAL FEES.
THIS IS UNACCEPTABLE, AND I
THINK THAT SENATOR RUBIO HAS A
LEGITIMATE CONCERN.
WE GOT TO PUT AN END TO THIS.
TRUMP HAS TO GET ON THE TV AND
TELL HIS SUPPORTERS THAT
VIOLENCE IN THE POLITICAL
PROCESS IN AMERICA IS NOT
ACCEPTABLE, END OF DISCUSSION.
>> AND ONE SECOND, ROLAND,
I'M SORRY.
I WANT TO PLAY DEVIL'S ADVOCATE
FOR ONE SECOND ON THIS.
SOME OF YOUR SUPPORTERS IN
CHICAGO WERE ACTING VIOLENTLY AS
WELL, AND I HAVE TO SAY THAT THE
GUY WHO RUSHED THE STAGE
YESTERDAY AT DONALD TRUMP VOTED
FOR YOU.
NOW I KNOW THAT YOU ARE NOT
ENCOURAGING -- I KNOW YOU'RE NOT
ENCOURAGING THE VIOLENCE.
>> JAKE, MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
VOTED FOR ME.
IF I HAVE TO TAKE RESPONSIBILITY
FOR EVERYBODY WHO VOTED FOR ME,
IT WILL BE A VERY DIFFICULT
LIFE.
BUT LET ME REPEAT WHAT I SAID.
I HAVE NEVER AND I WILL NEVER
CONDONE VIOLENCE.
PEOPLE HAVE THE RIGHT TO
PROTEST.
THAT'S WHAT AMERICA IS ABOUT.
I'VE BEEN ON PICKET LINES MY
WHOLE LIFE.
BUT THAT'S VERY DIFFERENT FROM
GETTING INVOLVED IN VIOLENCE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU HAVE
TALKED A LOT ABOUT INCOME
INEQUALITY IN THIS CAMPAIGN.
REVEREND JESSE JACKSON SR. WHO
IS HERE HAS BEEN FIGHTING
SILICON VALLEY AND
OPENING UP THE DOORS FOR PEOPLE
OF COLOR, AND HOWEVER, POWER PAC
PLUS DID A STUDY SHOWING THAT
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY SPENT $514
MILLION ON VARIOUS CONSULTANTS,
AND MINORITIES GOT 1.7% OR
8 MILLION OF THAT.
AND HOW CAN THE PEOPLE TRUST
DEMOCRATS TO DO
SOMETHING ABOUT INCOME
INEQUALITY WHEN IT COMES TO
DOLLARS THEY PRACTICE INCOME
INEQUALITY?
>> THAT'S A VERY GOOD POINT.
LET ME SAY HELLO TO REVEREND
JACKSON.
AND I WAS WITH HIM YESTERDAY.
I AM PROUD TO SAY THAT WAY BACK
IN 1988 WHEN HE AND I WERE
YOUNGER AND HE RAN THE BRILLIANT
CAMPAIGN FORT PRESIDENT, AND I
AM PROUD TO SAY THAT I WAS ONE
OF THE FEW WHITE POLITICIANS AND
ELECTED OFFICIALS TO SUPPORT
JESSE JACKSON.
AND HE, IN FACT, WON THE STATE
OF VERMONT.
I'M PROUD OF THAT.
AND WHAT WE HAVE TO DO AS A
PARTY BUT AS A NATION MAKE SURE
THAT FEDERAL CONTRACTS AND MONEY
GOES TO THOSE PEOPLE WHO NEED IT
THE MOST.
ROLAND, LET ME TELL YOU WHAT I
THINK IS ONE OF THE GREAT CRISES
FACING THE COUNTRY WHICH GETS
LITTLE COVERAGE FROM THE MEDIA,
AND THAT IS YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT
IN THIS COUNTRY.
UNEMPLOYMENT AND UNDEREMPLOYMENT
IS OFF THE CHARTS.
FOR AFRICAN-AMERICAN KIDS, IT IS
51%.
>> MM-HMM.
>> I WANT AND I BELIEVE THAT THE
FOLKS MOST CAPABLE OF HELPING
LOWER THAT RATE ARE THE BLACK
BUSINESS COMMUNITY.
AND I THINK THAT WE SHOULD BE
VERY AGGRESSIVE IN TARGETING
FEDERAL CONTRACTS TO THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY, THE
LATINO COMMUNITY AND THOSE
COMMUNITIES THAT CAN HELP US THE
MOST DEAL WITH HIGHEST RATES OF
UNEMPLOYMENT.
I SHARE YOUR CONCERN.
IT'S A GOOD POINT.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, WOULD YOU
STAND UP.
WE'LL TAKE QUESTIONS FROM
AMERICAN VOTERS NOW.
THE FIRST QUESTION IS FROM
TARINA ALLEN.
IF SHE WOULD STAND UP.
THERE YOU ARE.
HER BROTHER WAS SHOT AND KILLED
BY A POLICE OFFICER LAST YEAR
AFTER A ROUTINE TRAFFIC STOP FOR
A MISSING LICENSE PLATE.
YOU MIGHT REMEMBER THIS TOOK
PLACE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
CINCINNATI.
HE WOULD HAVE TURNED 44
YESTERDAY.
SHE SAID SHE'S LEANING TOWARDS
SECRETARY CLINTON BUT SHE'S
STILL UNDECIDED.
THE FLOOR IS YOURS.
>> HI, SENATOR SANDERS.
THANK YOU FOR TAKING MY
QUESTION.
I JUST WANTED TO ASK AS
AMERICANS WE ARE -- IT'S
EXPECTED THAT WE CAN SPEAK OUT
AGAINST TERRORISTS, WE CAN SPEAK
OUT AGAINST MURDERERS, AND
KILLERS OF ALL FORMS, EXCEPT
WHEN THAT KILLER IS A POLICE
OFFICER.
YESTERDAY MY BROTHER WAS GOING
TO TURN 44 YEARS OLD.
AND LAST YEAR HE WAS SHOT BY A
POLICE OFFICER.
WE'VE BEEN ON A MISSION TO GET
SOME ACCOUNTABILITY OF THE
POLICE SYSTEMS.
WE WANTED TO KNOW -- IT'S BEEN
MY EXPERIENCE, UNFORTUNATELY,
THAT POLICE OFFICERS DO LIE.
THEY DO KILL UNJUSTLY.
THEY DO FALSIFY POLICE REPORTS.
HOW CAN WE -- AS PRESIDENT WHAT
WOULD YOU DO TO CREATE A ZERO
TOLERANCE POLICY FOR UNJUST
POLICE KILLINGS AND TO HELP TO
CREATE A SYSTEM OF
ACCOUNTABILITY THAT'S GREATER
THAN WHAT WE HAVE RIGHT NOW?
>> WELL, TERINA, FIRST OF ALL,
ON BEHALF OF MY WIFE AND MYSELF,
WE SEND YOU OUR CONDOLENCES FOR
YOUR TERRIBLE UNJUST LOSS.
WE HAVE SEEN IN OHIO AND ALL
OVER THIS COUNTRY UNARMED
PEOPLE, OFTEN AFRICAN-AMERICANS,
SHOT AND KILLED WHILE BEING
APPREHENDED BY POLICE OFFICERS.
THAT HAS GOT TO END, AND IT HAS
GOT TO END SOON.
SO LET ME JUST SAY A COUPLE
THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, ANY POLICE OFFICER
WHO BREAKS THE LAW, LIKE ANY
OTHER PUBLIC OFFICIAL, MUST BE
HELD ACCOUNTABLE.
PERIOD.
PEOPLE BREAK THE LAW, THEY MUST
BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NUMBER TWO, IF ELECTED PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, MY
DEPARTMENT OF JUSTICE WILL
INVESTIGATE EVERY KILLING OF AN
AMERICAN HELD IN POLICE CUSTODY
OR KILLED WHILE BEING
APPREHENDED.
AN AUTOMATIC DEPARTMENT OF
JUSTICE INVESTIGATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NUMBER THREE, WE NEED TO DEVELOP
THE CONCEPT OF A MODEL POLICE
DEPARTMENT.
AND A MODEL POLICE DEPARTMENT,
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CAN PLAY
A SIGNIFICANT ROLE ON THAT.
SO TO MAKE AND TO CREATE
TRAINING PROCEDURES SO THAT
POLICE OFFICERS UNDERSTAND THAT
THE USE OF LETHAL FORCE IS THE
LAST RESPONSE NOT THE FIRST
RESPONSE.
TOO OFTEN PEOPLE ARE SHOOTING,
AND THEN ASKING QUESTIONS LATER.
FURTHERMORE, WE NEED TO
DEMILITARIZE LOCAL POLICE
DEPARTMENTS AROUND THIS COUNTRY
SO THAT THEY DON'T LOOK LIKE
OCCUPYING ARMIES, AND WE NEED TO
MAKE POLICE DEPARTMENTS REFLECT
THE DIVERSITY OF THE COMMUNITIES
THEY ARE SERVING.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE TIRED,
BLACKS, WHITES, ALL OF US ARE
TIRED OF SEEING UNARMED PEOPLE
GETTING SHOT.
WE ARE TIRED, BY THE WAY, OF
SEEING MORE PEOPLE IN JAIL IN
AMERICA THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY
ON EARTH.
I PROMISE YOU THAT ADDRESSING
THIS ISSUE OF REAL CRIMINAL
JUSTICE REFORM AND ENDING
INSTITUTIONAL RACISM WILL BE AT
THE VERY TOP OF MY LIST OF
PRIORITIES.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
I WANT TO TURN NOW TO JOHN TERRY
WHO WORKS IN MANUFACTURING, AND
HE IS LEANING TOWARDS YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, SENATOR.
IT IS A ONCE IN A LIFETIME
OPPORTUNITY TO BE HERE.
WE ALL KNOW THAT THE AUTO
INDUSTRY IS BOOMING, BUT FOR
MYSELF AND THOUSANDS OF WORKERS
LIKE ME WHO MANUFACTURE PARTS
FOR THESE HUGE COMPANIES, OUR
PAYCHECKS ARE MORE COMPARABLE TO
FAST FOOD WAGES AS OPPOSED TO
BEING A PATHWAY TO LIKE THE
MIDDLE-CLASS.
SO AS PRESIDENT, WHAT WOULD YOU
DO NOT ONLY TO BRING UP WAGES,
BUT TO KEEP THESE VITAL JOBS IN
THE UNITED STATES?
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR THAT
VERY IMPORTANT QUESTION.
THERE ARE TWO ISSUES SURROUNDING
THE QUESTION THAT YOU HAVE ASKED
IF I MIGHT.
NUMBER ONE, YOU ARE LOOKING AT A
SENATOR AND FORMER CONGRESSMAN
WHO OPPOSED EVERY ONE OF THESE
DISASTROUS TRADE AGREEMENTS
WHICH HAVE COST AMERICAN WORKERS
MILLIONS OF JOBS.
I COULD SEE FROM DAY ONE THAT
THESE CORPORATELY WRITTEN TRADE
AGREEMENTS WERE DESIGNED TO
ALLOW CORPORATIONS TO SHUT DOWN
IN AMERICA, THROW PEOPLE OUT ON
THE STREET, GO TO MEXICO, GO TO
CHINA, PAY PEOPLE PEN ES AN HOUR
AND THEN BRING THOSE PRODUCTS
BACK INTO THIS COUNTRY.
ONE OF THE STRONG DIFFERENCES
BETWEEN SECRETARY CLINTON AND
MYSELF, SHE HAS SUPPORTED ALMOST
ALL OF THOSE TRADE AGREEMENTS I
HAVE VIGOROUSLY OPPOSED IT.
NOW YOU'RE RAISING ANOTHER ISSUE
WHICH GETS LITTLE ATTENTION, AND
THAT IS THE RACE TO THE BOTTOM.
AND THE GOOD NEWS IS THAT IN THE
RECENT YEARS WE HAVE BEEN SEEING
THE INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF
MANUFACTURING JOBS IN AMERICA,
AND THAT IS GOOD.
THE BAD NEWS IS THAT SOME OF THE
JOBS ARE NOW PAYING 50% OR 60%
OF WHAT THESE JOBS USED TO PAY.
AND THE REASON FOR THAT IS
CORPORATIONS ARE SAYING, OKAY,
WELL, WE WILL BRING BACK JOBS,
BUT YOU ARE GOING TO HAVE TO
TAKE A SIGNIFICANT PAY CUT, AND
IF YOU DO NOT, WE WILL SHIP YOUR
COMPANY'S JOBS OFF TO CHINA OR
VIETNAM.
ALL RIGHT.
I WILL NOT ONLY CONTINUE TO
OPPOSE TRADE THE AGREEMENTS LIKE
THE TPP WHICH ASKED US TO
COMPETE AGAINST PEOPLE IN
VIETNAM WHO MAKE 65 CENTS AN
HOUR MINIMUM WAGE, BUT WHAT WE
ARE GOING TO DO IS TO DEVELOP AN
ENTIRELY DIFFERENT PROCESS IN
TERMS OF TRADE.
TONIGHT ON CNN, THERE ARE GOING
TO BE 30-SECOND ADS FROM ALL OF
THE MAJOR CORPORATIONS, AND THEY
ARE GOING TO BE SAYING, BUY THIS
PRODUCT AND BUY THAT PRODUCT.
WELL, YOU KNOW WHAT, IF THEY
WANT US TO BUY THOSE PRODUCTS,
THE TIME IS LONG OVERDUE FOR
THEM TO MANUFACTURE THOSE
PRODUCTS HERE IN THE UNITED
STATES, NOT IN CHINA.
FURTHERMORE, FURTHERMORE, FOR
ALL WORKING PEOPLE, WE HAVE GOT
TO RECOGNIZE THAT THE $7.25/HOUR
MINIMUM WAGE IS A STARVATION
WAGE.
WE ARE GOING TO RAISE THAT
MINIMUM WAGE TO 15 BUCKS AN HOUR
SO THAT NOBODY IN AMERICA WORKS
40 HOURS, LIVES IN POVERTY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, SENATOR,
HOPE TO SEE SOME OF THOSE ADS ON
TV ONE, TOO.
AND NOW, RIGHT HERE, WAYNE
CARLSON WHO IS THE DEAN OF
UNDERGRADUATE STUDENTS HERE AT
OHIO STATE, AND HE SAYS HE IS
TORN BETWEEN YOU AND SECRETARY
CLINTON.
WAYNE?
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
ALLOWING ME TO BE HERE.
AS DEAN OF UNDERGRADUATES, I AM
VERY, VERY MUCH AWARE OF THE
IMPACT ON OUR STUDENTS OF
ESCALATING COSTS AND HIGHER
EDUCATION PARTICULARLY OUR
DISADVANTAGED STUDENTS.
I, MYSELF, AM A FIRST-GENERATION
LOW-INCOME STUDENT, AND I
FINANCED MY WAY ARE THROUGH
COLLEGE USING FEDERAL GRANTS AND
FORGIVABLE LOANS.
I KNOW, SENATOR, THAT YOU ARE
PROPOSING FREE COLLEGE FOR ALL.
I DON'T QUITE UNDERSTAND HOW
THAT'S POSSIBLE.
SENATOR, IS THERE ROOM FOR
COMPROMISE ON THIS ISSUE?
>> WELL, WAYNE, I AM NOT
PROPOSING -- AND VERY OFTEN IT
GETS MISUNDERSTOOD.
I AM NOT PROPOSING FREE COLLEGE
FOR ALL.
WHAT I AM PROPOSING IS FREE
TUITION AT PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES.
THAT'S WHAT I'M PROPOSING.
AND I AM ALSO PROPOSING TO
SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER THE
OUTRAGEOUS LEVEL OF STUDENT DEBT
THAT MILLIONS OF PEOPLE IN THE
COUNTRY ARE CURRENTLY CARRYING.
WHY AM I DOING THIS?
I AM DOING THIS BECAUSE TODAY,
IN MANY RESPECTS, THE COLLEGE
DEGREE IS THE EQUIVALENT OF WHAT
A HIGH SCHOOL DEGREE WAS 50
YEARS AGO.
THE WORLD HAS CHANGED.
THE ECONOMY HAS CHANGED.
PEOPLE NEED MORE EDUCATION.
THAT IS WHY I BELIEVE THAT WE
SHOULD MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES TUITION-FREE SO
THAT ANYBODY IN THIS COUNTRY WHO
HAS THE ABILITY, WHO HAS THE
QUALIFICATIONS WILL BE ABLE TO
GET A COLLEGE DEGREE, REGARDLESS
OF THE INCOME OF HIS OR HER
FAMILY.
AND LIKE YOU, I CAME FROM A
FAMILY THAT DIDN'T HAVE A LOT OF
MONEY, AND FIRST GENERATION TO
GO TO COLLEGE, BUT I WANT EVERY
KID IN THIS COUNTRY WHO IS IN
THE SIXTH GRADE OR THE FOURTH
GRADE TO UNDERSTAND THAT IF HE
OR SHE STUDIES HARD, DOES WELL,
THEY WILL BE ABLE TO GO TO
COLLEGE REGARDLESS OF THE INCOME
OF THEIR FAMILY.
AND WE ARE GOING TO PAY FOR
THAT.
AND I WILL TELL YOU HOW WE WILL
PAY FOR THIS.
I HAVE BEEN CRITICIZED, BECAUSE
IT IS AN EXPENSIVE PROPOSITION,
IT IS.
70 BILLION BUCKS A YEAR.
SOME OF YOU WILL REMEMBER THAT
BACK IN 2008 CONGRESS BAILED OUT
WALL STREET AFTER THEIR GREED
AND ILLEGAL BEHAVIOR NEARLY
DESTROYED OUR ECONOMY.
I BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD IMPOSE
A TAX ON WALL STREET
SPECULATION.
IF WE COULD BAIL OUT WALL
STREET, NOW IT IS WALL STREET'S
TIME TO HELP THE THE MIDDLE
CLASS OF THIS COUNTRY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I HAVE HEARD
FROM -- AND OBVIOUSLY AT TV ONE
WE TARGET AFRICAN-AMERICANS.
AND I HAVE HEARD FROM A NUMBER
OF HBCU GRADUATES WHO ARE VERY
CONCERNED ABOUT THE PLAN, AND WE
ARE AT OHIO STATE, BUT THERE ARE
TWO HBCUs IN THIS STATE.
WILBERFORCE AND CENTRAL STATE.
HOW WOULD YOU ENSURE THAT YOUR
PLAN WOULD NOT BE THE DEATH
KNELL OF HBCUs.
>> I AM 100% SUPPORTIVE.
BUT IF I REMEMBER HBCUs ARE
PUBLIC.
>> AND HALF ARE PRIVATE.
>> AND HALF ARE NOT, AND I
UNDERSTAND THAT FOR AS
RELATIVELY SMALL NUMBER OF
COLLEGES, THEY GRADUATE A HECK
OF A LOT OF AFRICAN-AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
>> 300,000 STUDENTS EVERY YEAR.
>> HUGE ROLE.
I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO
MAKE SURE -- AND WE'RE NOT DOING
IT NOW.
LET'S BE CLEAR.
I'VE TALKED TO MANY PRESIDENTS
AT BLACK COLLEGES.
AND THEY'RE STRUGGLING.
I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO
FULLY SUPPORT.
WE HAVE LEGISLATION IN THAT CAN
PROTECT NOT ONLY HBCUs BUT OTHER
NONPROFIT COLLEGES WHO BRING IN
A LOT OF LOW-INCOME STUDENTS.
THEY ARE HIGH ON MY AGENDA, AND
THEY SHOULD NOT FEEL THREATENED
BY THIS LEGISLATION.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I WANT YOU
TO MEET CHARLES NOBEL.
HE'S A PROGRAM MANAGER HERE AT
THE OHIO STATE UNIVERSITY.
HE SAYS HE'S STILL MAKING UP HIS
MIND ON WHO TO SUPPORT THIS
TUESDAY.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR, FOR
TAKING MY QUESTION.
I AM A DIRECTOR OF A PROGRAM
CALLED MY BROTHER'S KEEPER, AND
WE WORK WITH YOUNG BLACKMAILS
ALL BELOW THE POVERTY LINE.
THERE'S BEEN A LOT OF DEBATE AT
THE FEDERAL LEVEL RELATED TO
WHERE DO WE GO WITH TRADE.
IN THE LAST 15 YEARS
IN SOUTH SIDE OF COLUMBUS, WE
HAVE SEEN THOUSANDS OF JOBS GONE
DUE TO PLANT FORECLOSURE AND
SEEN ECONOMIC DISINVESTMENT,
RATES OF INFANT MORTALITY, RATES
OF CHILD POVERTY, RATES OF
EDUCATIONAL ATTAINMENT, SO ON
AND SO FORTH IN SOME AREAS OF
THE SOUTH SIDE ARE AS BAD AS
THEY ARE IN THIRD WORLD
COUNTRIES.
IF LELECTED WHAT WOULD YOUR
ADMINISTRATION GOING TO DO TO
ENSURE THAT INTERNATIONAL TRADE
DEALS DO MORE TO PROMOTE GROWTH
ON THE SOUTH SIDES AND AREAS
LIKE IT?
>> WELL, WHEN I TALK ABOUT THE
DISASTROUS TRADE AGREEMENTS --
AND WE HAVE LOST, SINCE 2001,
ALMOST 60,000 FACTORIES.
CAN YOU IMAGINE THAT?
60,000 FACTORIES, MILLIONS OF
GOOD-PAYING JOBS.
IF YOU GO TO THE DEPARTMENT
STORE, IT IS VERY HARD TO FIND
SOMETHING MANUFACTURED IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
WE NEED TO CHANGE THAT.
WHEN WE TALK ABOUT GROUPS OF
PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN HIT,
EVERYBODY HAS BEEN HIT.
BUT THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
COMMUNITY HAS ACTUALLY BEEN HIT
HARDER.
IF YOU ARE AN AFRICAN-AMERICAN
WORKER AND YOU WORK IN A FACTORY
AND YOU HAVE A UNION, YOU ARE
DOING PRETTY WELL.
BECAUSE YOU ARE MAKING
MIDDLE-CLASS WAGES, BUT IF YOU
LOSE THAT FACTORY, WHAT ARE YOU
DOING?
WORKING IN THE McDONALD'S, AND
WORKING FOR $9 OR $10 AN HOUR,
AND SO WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO
AND WE HAVE TO DO A NUMBER OF
THINGS ECONOMICALLY TO MY MIND.
NUMBER ONE, WE WILL DEVELOP AN
ENTIRELY NEW SET OF TRADE
POLICIES NOT WRITTEN BY
CORPORATE AMERICA FOR CORPORATE
AMERICA, ALL RIGHT.
WE ARE GOING TO WRITE TRADE
POLICIES THAT WORK FOR THE
WORKING PEOPLE OF THIS COUNTRY,
AND POOR PEOPLE ABROAD BUT NOT
JUST FOR THE MULTI NATIONAL
CORPORATIONS.
NUMBER TWO, AS PART OF THE
OVERALL ECONOMIC INVESTMENT
POLICY, AND WE HAVE TALKED ABOUT
THIS WITH JESSE JACKSON THE
OTHER DAY, AND WE HAVE TO TARGET
OUR ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT INTO
THOSE COMMUNITIES WHO ARE MOST
HARD PRESSED.
I KNOW WHAT IS GOING ON IN OHIO,
I WAS IN FLINT, MICHIGAN, A
COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO.
YOU CANNOT BELIEVE WHAT IS GOING
ON.
YOU TALK ABOUT A THIRD WORLD
COUNTRY.
YOU WOULD THINK IT WAS A FOURTH
WORLD COUNTRY.
AND HERE IS THE MAIN POINT THAT
THIS CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT.
PEOPLE DON'T KNOW IT.
WE ARE THE RICHEST COUNTRY IN
THE HISTORY OF THE WORLD.
PROBLEM IS THAT ALMOST ALL OF
THE NEW INCOME AND WEALTH IS
GOING TO THE TOP 1%.
PROBLEM IS WE HAVE THE WORST
DISTRIBUTION OF WEALTH OF ANY
MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH.
I HAVE SPENT MY LIFE TAKING ON
THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS AND THE
SPECIAL INTERESTS.
I WILL CONTINUE TO DO THAT, AND
WE ARE GOING TO CREATE THE
ECONOMY THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
US NOT JUST A FEW, AND WE ARE
GOING TO INVEST IN LOW INCOME
COMMUNITIES ALL OVER AMERICA.
WHAT IS GOING ON IN AREAS OF IN
COLUMBUS, AREAS ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY IS A NATIONAL DISGRACE.
TOGETHER, WE ARE GOING TO CHANGE
IT.
>> SENATOR, LET'S TALK ABOUT
TRADE MORE BROADLY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YES.
>> YOU WERE AND REMAIN A STRONG
OPPONENT OF NAFTA.
>> YES.
>> AND EXPORTS ARE A BIG PART OF
THE OHIO ECONOMY AND MORE THAN
HALF OF OHIO EXPORTS GO TO THE
TWO COUNTRIES AFFECTED BY NAFTA
OTHER THAN THE UNITED STATES,
CANADA AND MEXICO.
WHAT DO YOU TELL A SKEPTICAL
OHIOAN ABOUT HOW YOUR TRADE
POLICIES WON'T HURT THEM?
>> WELL, LOOK, JAKE.
WE LIVE IN A GLOBAL ECONOMY, AND
EVERYBODY UNDERSTANDS THAT TRADE
IS A POSITIVE THING.
NOBODY IS TALKING ABOUT BUILDING
A WALL AROUND THE UNITED STATES.
OF COURSE, WE ARE GOING TO
TRADE.
OH, I BEG YOUR PARDON, THERE IS
ONE GUY WHO IS TALKING ABOUT
BUILDING A WALL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
LET ME REPHRASE, NO RATIONAL
PERSON IS TALKING ABOUT BUILDING
A WALL.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
SO OF COURSE WE'RE GOING TO DO
TRADE.
BUT TRADE POLICIES HAVE GOT TO
BE POLICIES THAT WORK FOR THE
PEOPLE OF OUR COUNTRY.
I WILL WORK VERY HARD TO EXPAND
AGRICULTURAL EXPORTS, EXPAND
MANUFACTURING EXPORTS, BUT THEY
HAVE TO BE BASED AROUND A
PRINCIPLE NOT OF UNFETTERED FREE
TRADE WHERE THE AMERICAN WORKERS
ARE WORKING AGAINST PEOPLE
AROUND THE WORLD WHO MAKE
PENNIES AN HOUR WITH YOU FAIR
TRADE.
AND THAT'S THE TRADE POLICY.
>> STAY WITH US.
AND WE WILL BE RIGHT BACK WITH
MORE QUESTIONS.
YOU ARE WATCHING THE DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL TOWN HALL LIVE FROM
COLUMBUS, OHIO.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE OHIO
STATE UNIVERSITY IN COLUMBUS FOR
THIS DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL
DOWN HALL.
WE ARE HERE WITH SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS OF VERMONT.
LET'S GO TO OUR NEXT QUESTIONER
AND NEXT VOTER.
STEVE CAMINOTI WHO WORKS IN
PUBLIC RELATIONS.
HE SAYS THAT HE'S LEANING
TOWARDS SECRETARY CLINTON BUT
THERE IS STILL A CHANCE, SENATOR
SANDERS.
>> AND SENATOR SANDERS, WELCOME
TO COLUMBUS.
YOU HAVE MENTIONED THE TAX
POLICY WHICH WOULD TAX WALL
STREET, AND OBVIOUSLY, IT IS TAX
THE WEALTHIEST AMERICANS, BUT
ACCORDING TO THE TAX POLICY
CENTER, MIDDLE INCOME HOMEOWNERS
COULD ALSO SEE AN INCREASE IN
THE INCOME TAXES AND I THINK THE
NUMBER IS $4700 FOR WAGES THAT
HAVE BEEN STAGNANT FOR A
SHRINKING MIDDLE CLASS, WHAT'S
YOUR MESSAGE TO MIDDLE-INCOME
AMERICANS AND OHIOANS?
>> FIRST OF ALL, WE DISAGREE
WITH THAT ANALYSIS.
DIFFERENT GROUPS DO DIFFERENT
ANALYSES, AND OTHER GROUPS COME
UP WITH VERY DIFFERENT RESULTS.
AT A TIME WHEN THE TOP 0.1% OWNS
THE TOP 1% AND WHEN 58% OF ALL
NEW GENERATED INCOME GOES TO THE
TOP 1%.
WHEN MAJOR CORPORATIONS MAKE
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS A YEAR IN
PROFITS AND STASH THEIR MONEY IN
THE CAYMAN ISLANDS AND BERMUDA
AND END UP IN A GIVEN YEAR NOT
PAYING A NICKEL IN TAXES.
AND COMMUNITIES IN COLUMBUS AND
ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY ARE
FALLING APART, WHEN WE HAVE THE
HIGHEST RATE OF CHILDHOOD
POVERTY OF ALMOST ANY MAJOR
COUNTRY ON EARTH.
YOU KNOW WHAT I THINK?
I DO BELIEVE THAT THE WEALTHIEST
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY AND THE
LARGEST CORPORATIONS ARE GOING
TO HAVE TO START PAYING THEIR
FAIR SHARE OF TAXES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NUMBER TWO.
A LOT OF THE ANALYSES OF OUR
PROPOSALS, OUR TAX PROPOSALS
HAVE FORGOTTEN TO INCLUDE OUR
MEDICARE FOR ALL HEALTH CARE
PROGRAM.
AND WHAT MEDICARE FOR ALL WILL
DO IS PROVIDE HEALTH CARE TO
EVERY MAN, WOMAN AND CHILD
WITHOUT HAVING TO PAY PREMIUMS
TO THE INSURANCE COMPANIES AND
VERY SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER THE
COST OF PRESCRIPTION DRUGS.
I BELIEVE THAT IS THE DIRECTION
THAT WE SHOULD GO IN.
SO, TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION,
YES, I BELIEVE THAT THE
WEALTHIEST PEOPLE AND THE
LARGEST CORPORATIONS SHOULD BE
ASKED TO PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE.
WE ARE GOING TO PROTECT THE
MIDDLE-CLASS OF THIS COUNTRY,
AND WE ARE GOING TO ADDRESS
MASSIVE LEVELS OF INCOME AND
WEALTH INEQUALITY, AND THE
DISINVESTMENT THAT WE ARE SEEING
IN COMMUNITIES THROUGHOUT THIS
COUNTRY.
>> WELL, SENATOR --
[ APPLAUSE ]
THANK YOU, SINCE I HAVE A
BROTHER AND TWO SISTERS WHO ARE
TEACHERS AND ONE A TEACHER'S
AIDE, LET'S GO TO A TEACH PERF
WE HAVE CAITLIN DON WHO TEACHES
HERE AND SAW THE INEQUITIES IN
THE AMERICAN SCHOOL SYSTEM.
SHE SAYS SHE'S UNDECIDED.
SO YOU HAVE A SHOT.
GO FOR IT.
>> I WILL WORK FOR IT.
>> AND SO THANK YOU FOR TAKING
MY QUESTION.
AN ARTICLE WAS RELEASED IN THE
COLUMBUS DISPATCH FRIDAY
RELEASING THE TOP STUDENT GAINS
FROM AROUND THE STATE OF OHIO.
OF THESE ONE-THIRD OF THOSE
SCHOOLS PRODUCING THE RESULTS
WERE CHARTERS RIGHT HERE IN
COLUMBUS, OHIO.
SO, KNOWING THIS AND ALSO HAVING
SIMILAR NARRATIVES FROM ACROSS
THE COUNTRY, DO YOU THINK THAT
CHARTER SCHOOLS ARE A VIABLE WAY
TO EDUCATE CHILDREN IN
LOW-INCOME COMMUNITIES OR DO YOU
THINK THAT YOU WOULD CONTINUE AS
PRESIDENT GIVING MONEY TO
TRADITIONAL PUBLIC SCHOOLS?
>> I BELIEVE IN PUBLIC
EDUCATION, AND I BELIEVE IN
PUBLIC CHARTER SCHOOLS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I DO NOT BELIEVE IN PRIVATE --
PRIVATELY CONTROLLED CHARTER
SCHOOLS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I'LL TELL YOU WHAT ELSE I
BELIEVE.
I BELIEVE THAT WHEN WE TALK
ABOUT EDUCATION AS A NATION, WE
HAVE GOT TO MAKE EDUCATION NOT
JUST RHETORICALLY, BUT IN
REALITY ONE OF THE GREAT
PRIORITIES FACING OUR COUNTRY.
I GOT A LITTLE BIT TIRED OF
HEARING ABOUT ALL THE GREAT
FOOTBALL PLAYERS AND THE
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS A YEAR THEY
MAKE.
MAYBE WE SHOULD TALK ABOUT THE
GREAT TEACHERS IN THE COUNTRY
AND MAKE SURE THAT THEY CAN EARN
A GOOD WAGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND LET ME ALSO SAY, IF I CAN
BUILD ON YOUR QUESTION, YOU
KNOW, WHEN WE TALK ABOUT
NATIONAL PRIORITIES,
AND WHEN WE TALK ABOUT A
PROLIFERATION OF MILLIONAIRES
AND BILLIONAIRES WHILE HALF OF
THE KIDS IN PUBLIC SCHOOLS IN
AMERICA ARE ON FREE OR REDUCED
LUNCH, LET'S TALK ABOUT AN ISSUE
THAT NOBODY EVER TALKS ABOUT.
AND THAT THE DYSFUNCTIONAL CHILD
CARE SYSTEM WE HAVE IN AMERICA.
EVERY PSYCHOLOGIST WHO STUDIES
THE ISSUE KNOWS THAT ZERO
THROUGH FOUR ARE THE MOST
IMPORTANT YEARS FOR INTELLECTUAL
AND EMOTIONAL DEVELOPMENT, AND
YET WE HAVE CHILD CARE WORKERS
WHO ARE MAKING $9 OR $10 AN HOUR
WITHOUT ANY BENEFITS.
I INTEND TO DO EVERYTHING THAT I
CAN TO CREATE A FIRST-CLASS
NATIONAL CHILD CARE SYSTEM WITH
WELL PAID, WELL TRAINED TEACHERS
SO THAT THE ALL OF OUR LITTLE
KIDS GET A START IN LIFE THAT IS
WORTHY OF CHILDREN IN THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
>> SENATOR SANDERS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
I LISTENED TO YOUR ANSWER ABOUT
CHARTER SCHOOLS AND NOT
SUPPORTING PRIVATE CHARTERS.
>> YES.
>> BUT WE USE THE TAXPAYER
DOLLARS IN THE FORM OF GRANTS
FOR FOLKS TO GO TO PRIVATE
COLLEGES.
WE DID A POLL ON TVONE WITH
ROLANDMARTIN.COM AND NEARLY 80%
OF BLACK PARENTS SAID THEY
SUPPORT CHARTERS, THEY SUPPORT
VOUCHERS.
MANY DEMOCRATS DON'T.
EXPLAIN TO ME HOW WE CAN
SUPPORT TAX DOLLARS FOR
PRIVATE COLLEGES BUT WE DON'T
BELIEVE IN SCHOOL CHOICE FOR
FOLKS IN ELEMENTARY, MIDDLE AND
HIGH SCHOOL?
>> I THINK THERE IS A
DIFFERENCE.
>> AND THAT IS?
>> THE DIFFERENCE IS THAT RIGHT
NOW PUBLIC SCHOOLS ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY ARE BEING DEFUNDED.
AND MONEY IS LEAVING THE PUBLIC
SCHOOL SYSTEM.
AND YOU MAY WANT TO ARGUE MANY
WITH ME, AND IT'S A GOOD DEBATE,
BUT I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE THAT
PUBLIC SCHOOLS, THE IDEAS OF
NEIGHBORHOOD SCHOOLS, PEOPLE
FROM DIFFERENT ECONOMIC LEVELS,
RICH AND POOR AND MIDDLE CLASS
COMING TOGETHER, THAT'S ONE OF
THE REASONS THAT WE CREATED THE
KIND OF GREAT NATION THAT WE
HAVE.
SO, WE ARE GOING TO DO
EVERYTHING THAT WE CAN TO
SUPPORT PUBLIC EDUCATION, AND
SUPPORT EXPERIMENTATION IN
PUBLIC EDUCATION.
IN MY CITY OF BURLINGTON,
VERMONT, WE HAVE STARTED SOME
GREAT PUBLIC -- I DON'T KNOW
WHAT THEY'RE CALLED, CHARTER
SCHOOLS.
ONE IS INTO -- ONE IS -- WELL, I
FORGOT WHAT IT IS.
>> MAGNET SCHOOL?
>> YEAH, MAGNET TYPE SCHOOLS AND
THEY'RE DOING A GREAT JOB.
AND I WANT TO SEE THE
EXPERIMENTATION, BUT I DO NOT
WANT TO SEE THE MONEY LEAVE THE
PUBLIC SCHOOLS.
>> ALL RIGHT.
SENATOR SANDERS, I WANT YOU TO
MEET A DOCTOR FROM DUBLIN, OHIO,
WHO SAYS THAT HE IS UNDECIDED,
BUT LEANING TOWARDS SECRETARY
CLINTON.
DOCTOR?
>> WELCOME TO COLUMBUS.
I'M A SON OF IMMIGRANTS, AND
MY PARENTS, BOTH CITIZENS NOW
HAVE DONE VERY WELL IN THIS
GREAT COUNTRY.
AND SO HAVE I.
BUT AS A 1% ETHNIC AND RELIGIOUS
MINORITY WITNESSING THE RISE OF
DONALD TRUMP FOR THE FIRST TIME
MY FAMILY HAS START FEELING A
LITTLE UNCOMFORTABLE HERE.
AND FRANKLY, A LITTLE BIT
SCARED.
IF DONALD TRUMP SECURES THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINATION, I AM
GOING TO HAVE ONE MISSION
HEADING TO THE BALLOT BOX WHICH
IS TO KEEP HIM FROM TAKING
OFFICE.
WHICH DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE IS
GOING TO BE BETTER AT HELPING ME
DO THAT?
>> GOOD, GOOD.
>> SOMEONE WHO CANNOT JUST
CONDEMN HIM, WHICH IS EASY, BUT
DEFEAT HIM.
>> GOOD.
GOOD QUESTION.
>> AND, AND OTHER THAN THE USUAL
NEGATIVE RHETORIC AND ATTACK
ADS, NONE OF WHICH HAVE WORKED
SO FAR, WHAT ARE THREE SPECIFIC
POINTS OF YOUR ANTI-TRUMP GAME
PLAN?
>> OKAY.
FIRST OFF, THANK YOU MORE THE
QUESTION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU KNOW, A LOT OF CRITICISMS
ARE THROWN AT ME, AND THIS IS
NATURAL IN POLITICS, BUT ONE
THAT I RESENT IS THAT, WELL,
BERNIE, YOU ARE A NICE GUY, AND
I LIKE YOUR IDEAS, BUT YOU CAN'T
WIN THE GENERAL ELECTION.
SO LET ME DEAL WITH THAT.
TAKE A LOOK AT VIRTUALLY EVERY
NATIONAL POLL THAT HAS BEEN
DONE.
TAKE A LOOK AT THE NBC/"WALL
STREET JOURNAL" POLL OF TWO OR
THREE DAYS AGO.
BERNIE SANDERS WAS DEFEATING
DONALD TRUMP BY 18 POINTS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IN FACT, BY ALL OF -- IN
VIRTUALLY, NOT ALL BUT VIRTUALLY
ALL OF THOSE POLLS MY MARGIN
OVER TRUMP IS WIDER THAN
SECRETARY CLINTON'S.
IF YOU LOOK AT STATEWIDE POLLS,
AND THE POLLS DONE IN MICHIGAN A
WEEK OR TWO AGO, I WAS 19 POINTS
AHEAD OF TRUMP, AND IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, I THINK 19 POINTS AS
WELL.
SO FIRST POINT, I THINK THAT IF
YOU LOOK AT THE POLLING,
I AM THE STRONGEST DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATE TO BEAT DONALD TRUMP.
SECOND POINT IS REPUBLICANS WIN
WHEN THE VOTER TURNOUT IS LOW.
I THINK ANY OBJECTIVE
ASSESSMENT OF THE CURRENT
CAMPAIGN, AND WE HAVE JUST HAD A
RALLY HERE IN COLUMBUS A FEW
HOURS AGO, AND WE HAD 7,000
PEOPLE OUT, AND WE HAVE HAD
25,000 OR 28,000 PEOPLE OUT AT
THE RALLIES, AND ANY OBJECTIVE
ASSESSMENT OF THIS THIS CAMPAIGN
WILL SUGGEST THAT THE EXCITEMENT
AND THE ENERGY FOR LARGE VOTER
TURNOUTS IS WITH THE BERNIE
SANDERS' CAMPAIGN.
THIRD POINT TO ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION.
THE WAY THAT YOU BEAT TRUMP IS
TO EXPOSE HIM.
AND HE CAN BE EXPOSED AT MANY,
MANY LEVELS, AND NOT THE LEAST
OF WHICH, THIS IS A GUY WHO IS A
BILLIONAIRE BUT DOESN'T THINK WE
SHOULD RAISE THE MINIMUM WAGE
ABOVE $7.25 AN HOUR.
AND THIS IS A GUY WHO GOES ON
A REPUBLICAN DV DEBATE AND SAYS
WAGES IN AMERICA ARE TOO LOW.
TELL THAT TO THE PEOPLE IN OHIO
THAT WAGES ARE TOO LOW.
THIS IS A GUY WHO BELIEVES
IN DEFIANCE OF ALL SCIENCE THAT
CLIMATE CHANGE IS A HOAX.
AND THEN OF COURSE, ON TOP OF
ALL OF THAT IS THE ISSUE THAT
YOU RAISED, THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
ARE NOT GOING TO ELECT A
PRESIDENT WHO IS INSULTING
MEXICANS, MUSLIMS, WOMEN,
VETERANS -- INSULTING VIRTUALLY
EVERYBODY WHO IS NOT QUITE LIKE
DONALD TRUMP.
THANK GOD, MOST PEOPLE ARE NOT
QUITE LIKE DONALD TRUMP.
AND BY THE WAY --
[ APPLAUSE ]
BY THE WAY, JUST AS AN ADDITION,
I DON'T WANT ANYBODY HERE TO
FORGET THAT DONALD TRUMP WAS ONE
OF THE LEADERS OF THE SO-CALLED
BIRTHER MOVEMENT.
AND WHAT THAT MOVEMENT WAS ABOUT
WAS A VERY, VERY DEEP ATTACK ON
THE LEGITIMACY OF THE PRESIDENCY
OF BARACK OBAMA.
THAT WAS A REAL ASSAULT.
IT WASN'T SAYING I DISAGREE WITH
OBAMA.
THAT'S FINE.
WHAT HE WAS SAYING WAS THAT
BARACK OBAMA DOES NOT HAVE THE
RIGHT TO BE PRESIDENT.
HE WASN'T BORN IN AMERICA.
THAT IS AN INSULT NOT ONLY TO
THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY,
BUT IT IS AN INSULT TO EVERY ONE
OF US WHO VOTED AND SUPPORTED
BARACK OBAMA.
>> SENATOR, I WANT YOU TO MEET
CRYSTAL EARLY, WHO IS A MOTHER
AND AN ADVOCATE WHO HELPS PEOPLE
STRUGGLING WITH ADDICTION.
SHE SAID SHE IS SUPPORTING YOU
ON TUESDAY, BUT SHE HAS THIS
QUESTION.
>> HI.
I WAS ADDICTED TO HEROIN FOR
OVER 12 YEARS, AND TRYING TO
RAISE MY TWO SMALL CHILDREN, AND
OFTENTIMES TAKING MY YOUNGEST
WITH ME TO BUY HEROIN DAILY AND
IT BECAME MY MAIN GOAL EVERY
DAY.
I AM IN RECOVERY NOW, LUCKY NOT
TO BE IN PRISON.
AND WHAT MY QUESTION IS IS WHAT
YOU PLAN TO DO WITH THE FAILED
DRUG POLICY THAT TENDS TO WANT
TO INCARCERATE ADDICTS INSTEAD
OF REHABILITATE THEM?
>> THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IF YOU WERE AT THE RALLY WE
HELD JUST A FEW HOURS AGO, WHAT
YOU WOULD HAVE HEARD ME SAY, AND
WHAT I SAY ALL OF THE TIME IS
THAT TODAY IN AMERICA WE HAVE,
IN MY STATE, IN NEIGHBORING NEW
HAMPSHIRE AND ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY, A MASSIVE CRISIS IN
HEROIN ADDICTION AND OVERDOSING
AND OPIATE ADDICTION AS WELL.
WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO IS TO
FUNDAMENTALLY RETHINK THE
SO-CALLED WAR ON DRUGS WHICH HAS
BEEN A FAILURE.
WE HAVE GOT TO LOOK AT SUBSTANCE
ABUSE AND ADDICTION AS A HEALTH
ISSUE, NOT A CRIMINAL ISSUE.
LOCKING UP ADDICTS IS NOT GOING
TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND FRANKLY, FRANKLY, IN TERMS
OF THE BROADER ISSUES OF MENTAL
HEALTH IN THIS COUNTRY, WE ARE
FILING AND FAILING BADLY.
IT IS NOT ONLY THAT WE ARE NOT
PROVIDING THE TREATMENT THAT
ADDICTS AND ABUSERS NEED WHEN
THEY NEED IT, WE HAVE THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE WHO ARE WALKING THE
STREETS OF AMERICA TODAY, AND
YOU TALK ABOUT THE HORRIFIC MASS
KILLINGS, AND YOU HAVE PEOPLE
WALKING THE STREETS TODAY WHO
ARE SUICIDAL AND WHO ARE
HOMICIDAL AND THEY CALL UP MY
OFFICE OR THE SENATORS' OFFICES,
AND FAMILIES CANNOT FIND THE
TREATMENT THAT THOSE PEOPLE
NEED.
MENTAL HEALTH IS PART OF HEALTH
CARE.
WE NEED A REVOLUTION IN
PROVIDING MENTAL HEALTH
TREATMENT TO THE PEOPLE WHO NEED
IT IN THIS COUNTRY.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH, SENATOR.
WE WILL BE RIGHT BACK AFTER THIS
QUICK BREAK, AND WE WILL HAVE
MORE QUESTIONS FOR SENATOR
SANDERS.
>>> HEY, FOLKS, WELCOME BACK TO
THE CNN/TV ONE DEMOCRATIC
PRESIDENTIAL TOWN HALL IN THE
AUDITORIUM HERE AT COLUMBUS,
OHIO.
WE'RE HERE WITH SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS.
LET'S CONTINUE WITH OUR
QUESTIONS.
AND SO WE HAVE ANN MERCHER RIGHT
HERE.
SHE'S A CHEF.
SO IS MY BROTHER.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT'S UP WITH
THESE TIE-INS.
HE'S LEANING TOWARDS YOU.
SEE IF YOU CAN SEAL THE DEAL.
>> OKAY.
>> SENATOR, I AM OPENING UP A
SMALL INDEPENDENT RESTAURANT NOT
FAR FROM HERE THIS SUMMER.
WHILE A CITIZEN I'M 100% BEHIND
YOUR POPULIST MESSAGE BUT I HAVE
QUESTIONS AS AN ENTREPRENEUR.
WHAT WILL THE TAXES FOR SMALL
BUSINESS LOOK LIKE UNDER YOUR
ADMINISTRATION?
>> AFTER YOU ADD UP THE FACT
THAT YOU WILL NOT HAVE TO
PROVIDE HEALTH INSURANCE FOR
YOUR EMPLOYEES OR FOR YOURSELF,
YOU WILL BE A LOT BETTER OFF.
SMALL AND MEDIUM-SIZED AND LARGE
BUSINESSES IN THIS COUNTRY ARE
BEING CRIPPLED BY THE HUGE
AMOUNTS OF MONEY THAT THEY ARE
NOW SPENDING ON HEALTH CARE.
AND THE AMOUNT OF TIME THAT THEY
ARE SPENDING TRYING TO FIGURE
OUT WHAT TYPE OF HEALTH
INSURANCE PROGRAM WORKS FOR
THEIR EMPLOYEES.
I WANT YOU TO THINK ABOUT YOUR
BUSINESS AND HAVING HEALTH
INSURANCE FOR YOU AND YOUR
FAMILIES AND YOUR EMPLOYEES
WHICH IS PUBLICLY FUNDED WHICH
IS THE CASE IN EVERY OTHER MAJOR
COUNTRY ON EARTH.
WHAT WILL THAT DO FOR YOUR
BUSINESS, MAKE IT A LITTLE
EASIER?
SO TO BE HONEST, YOU WILL PAY A
LITTLE BIT MORE IN TAXES.
YOU WILL PAY A LITTLE BIT MORE
IN TAXES, BUT THE SAVINGS WILL
BE IN TOTAL MUCH GREATER BY THE
REDUCTION -- BY THE FACT THAT
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE TO PAY
PRIVATE HEALTH INSURANCE
PREMIUM.
YOU AND EVERY OTHER SMALL
BUSINESSMAN IN THIS COUNTRY WILL
BE BETTER OFF UNDER MY PLAN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND NOW, CONSIDERING THAT
BLACK WOMEN START BUSINESSES
AT A FASTER RATE THAN ANYBODY IN
THE COUNTRY, THAT'S GOOD NEWS.
AND NOW, WE GO TO MISTY JORDAN
FROM RADIO ONE HERE IN COLUMBUS,
OHIO, AND WE CALL THAT FAMILY.
>> GOOD EVENING.
I'M THRILLED TO BE HERE.
MY QUESTION FOR YOU IS WHAT WILL
YOU DO DIFFERENT THAN PRESIDENT
OBAMA TO MOVE YOUR AGENDA
FORWARD IF THERE'S NO CHANGE IN
CONGRESSIONAL POWER?
>> GOOD QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU.
>> AND FOR START, IF I BECOME
PRESIDENT, IT WILL MEAN THAT
THERE WILL BE A SIGNIFICANT
INCREASE IN THE VOTER TURNOUT.
IN EVERY CAUCUS AND PRIMARY THAT
WE HAVE WON, WE HAVE WON NINE SO
FAR, AND WE THINK THAT WE HAVE A
CHANCE TO WIN HERE IN OHIO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IN EVERY INSTANCE INCLUDING
MICHIGAN LAST WEEK THE TURNOUT
WAS GREAT.
SO WHAT WE ARE DOING IS TO
CREATING LARGE VOTER TURNOUTS.
IF THERE IS A LARGE VOTER
TURNOUT, THERE'S NO DOUBT IN MY
MIND THAT THE DEMOCRATS WILL
RECOVER THE UNITED STATES SENATE
AND GAIN SIGNIFICANT SEATS IN
THE HOUSE.
ALL RIGHT.
THAT'S NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO, AND MAYBE MORE
IMPORTANTLY, THE WHOLE PREMISE
OF MY CAMPAIGN -- YOU'RE SAYING
HOW DO WE GET THINGS DONE
REALLY.
THE PREMISE AND ESSENCE OF MY
CAMPAIGN IS THE BELIEF, WHICH I
KNOW TO BE TRUE, BECAUSE I WORK
IN WASHINGTON, D.C., THAT MOST
OF THE MEMBERS OF CONGRESS FEEL
THEMSELVES INDEBTED TO THEIR
LARGE CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTORS
RATHER THAN TO THE PEOPLE THEY
REPRESENT.
ON ALL OF THE ISSUES THAT I AM
FIGHTING FOR, RAISING THE
MINIMUM WAGE, HEALTH CARE FOR
ALL, MAKING PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES TUITION FREE, AND
PAY EQUITY FOR WOMEN, AND
DEALING WITH THE CLIMATE CHANGE,
AND BY THE WAY, WE DON'T TALK
ENOUGH ABOUT CLIMATE CHANGE.
THAT'S WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
WANT, BUT YOU HAVE REPUBLICANS
WHO ARE MOVING IN THE OPPOSITE
DIRECTION.
WHAT I HAVE SAID OVER AND OVER
AGAIN, NO PRESIDENT, NOT BERNIE
SANDERS OR ANYBODY ELSE CAN DO
IT ALONE.
WALL STREET IS TOO POWERFUL.
CORPORATE AMERICA IS TOO
POWERFUL, AND LARGE CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTORS.
THE ONLY WAY WE REALLY TRANSFORM
THIS COUNTRY, AND THAT IS THE
HISTORY OF THE WORKERS MOVEMENT
AND UNIONS, THE HISTORY OF THE
CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT, THE
HISTORY OF THE WOMEN'S MOVEMENT,
THE HISTORY OF THE GAY MOVEMENT
IS WHEN PEOPLE STAND UP BY THE
MILLIONS AND FIGHT BACK AND TELL
CONGRESS THEY'RE GOING TO HAVE
TO REPRESENT ALL OF US NOT JUST
THE 1%.
WE DO THAT, WE'LL HAVE A
PROGRESSIVE AGENDA.
>> ALL RIGHT.
FOLKS, THE FINAL QUESTION
QUESTION FOR BERNIE SANDERS.
AFTER THIS SHORT BREAK.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE OHIO
STATE UNIVERSITY IN COLUMBUS.
WE ARE TALKING WITH VERMONT
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
SENATOR SANDERS, AS YOU KNOW IN
THESE TOWN HALLS TOWARDS THE END
OF THEM, WE LIKE TO ASK SOME
QUESTIONS SO THE AUDIENCE CAN
GET TO KNOW YOU A LITTLE BIT
BETTER.
YOU ARE STILL RELATIVELY NEW ON
THE NATIONAL SCENE, AND ONE
QUESTION THAT I THINK THAT
PEOPLE MIGHT BE INTERESTED IN
HEARING IS THAT WE ALL KNOW THAT
YOU ARE VERY CLOSE WITH YOUR
WIFE JANE AND YOUR FAMILY, BUT
WHO ARE YOUR FRIENDS?
IF YOU GOT NATIONALS TICKETS IN
WASHINGTON ONE DAY AND SAY JANE
WAS OUT OF TOWN, WHO WOULD YOU
INVITE?
>> WELL, WE HAVE SOME CLOSE
FRIENDS, MANY WHO WORK WITH ME
IN MY OFFICE WHO I HAVE KNOWN
FOR YEARS.
MY CAMPAIGN MANAGER IS SOMEBODY
WHO STARTED WORKING FOR ME WHEN
HE WAS 18 YEARS OF AGE.
DOING A GREAT JOB RUNNING THIS
CAMPAIGN.
SO THE PEOPLE THAT I WORK WITH
ARE OFTEN MY CLOSEST FRIENDS,
AND BACK IN BURLINGTON, I HAVE
SOME VERY DEAR FRIENDS WHO I
HAVE BEEN CLOSE TO FOR 30 OR 40
YEARS.
>> AS YOU KNOW, WASHINGTON WORKS
WELL WHEN PEOPLE IN WASHINGTON
FROM BOTH SIDES OF THE AISLE
KNOW EACH OTHER, WORK WELL
TOGETHER.
WHO IS THE PERSON WHO IS CLOSEST
TO YOU WITH WHOM YOU DISAGREE
THE MOST ON POLITICS?
>> REPUBLICAN WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT?
YOU SEE, THE IRONY HERE -- AND
THIS IS NOT EVEN FUNNY.
IF I TOLD YOU THE REPUBLICANS
THAT I LIKED THE MOST, IT WOULD
PROBABLY RUIN HIS POLITICAL
CAREER.
>> DO IT!
>> THERE IS A 30-SECOND AD,
SANDERS SAID HE LIKES THIS
PERSON, AND HE IS FINISHED.
>> WHO IS IT?
>> I'LL GIVE YOU AN EXAMPLE.
ONE OF THE MOST CONSERVATIVE
MEMBERS OF THE SENATE IS A
FELLOW NAMED JIM INHOFE FROM
OKLAHOMA.
AND JIM IS A CLIMATE CHANGE
DENIGHER.
HE'S A DECENT GUY AND I LIKE
HIM.
AND YOU FIND THAT.
YOU FIND THE FACT THAT JUST
BECAUSE YOU HAVE VERY
SIGNIFICANT POLITICAL
DIFFERENCES DOESN'T MEAN TO SAY
THAT YOU CANNOT DEVELOP
FRIENDSHIPS WITH GOOD PEOPLE.
>> AND LASTLY, SENATOR, THIS IS
AN ENORMOUS UNDERTAKING THAT YOU
ARE IN THE MIDDLE OF RIGHT NOW.
HAS THIS EXPERIENCE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT CHANGED YOU, AND IF
SO, HOW HAS IT CHANGED YOU?
>> HOW HAS IT CHANGED ME?
GO.
YES, IT HAS PROFOUNDLY CHANGED
ME.
I COME FROM A SMALL STATE, AND I
LOVE MY STATE SO MUCH, AND I'M
SO PROUD TO REPRESENT VERMONT IN
THE SENATE.
BUT WHEN YOU GO AROUND THE
COUNTRY, YOU MEET SO MANY
EXTRAORDINARY PEOPLE.
ALMOST AT EVERY RALLY THAT WE
DO, WE USUALLY DO WHAT WE CALL A
CLUTCH, WHERE WE BRING LOCAL
PEOPLE TOGETHER.
YOU MEET PEOPLE FROM THE LATINO
COMMUNITY AND YOU HEAR THEIR
EXPERIENCES.
I REMEMBER IN PHOENIX TALKING TO
A YOUNG TEENAGED GIRLS WITH
TEARS, LITERALLY TEARS ROLLING
DOWN HER EYES FEARFUL ABOUT
SOMEBODY IN HER FAMILY BEING
DEPORTED.
SOMEBODY FROM HER FAMILY BEING
DEPORTED, AND THAT MAKES YOU
FIGHT THAT MUCH MORE FOR REAL
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
WE MEET WITH PEOPLE FROM THE
NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITY,
EXTRAORDINARY PEOPLE WHOM WE
HAVE TREATED SO SHABBILY OVER
THE YEAR, AND YOU LEARN ABOUT
THEIR CULTURE, AND THE ONE
REGRET I HAVE, AND IT IS THE
NATURE OF THE CAMPAIGNS IS THAT
YOU DON'T HAVE THE TIME TO SPEND
WITH PEOPLE AND GO AROUND THE
STATE.
YOU KNOW, YOU GO IN THERE AND
GIVE A SPEECH AND YOU GO TO THE
HOTEL AND YOU'RE OFF FOR FIVE
SPEECHES THE NEXT DAY.
BUT I HAVE MET EXTRAORDINARY
PEOPLE, AND I HAVE SEEN SO MANY
YOUNG PEOPLE WHO ARE OPTIMISTIC
ABOUT THE FUTURE OF THIS
COUNTRY AND ARE PREPARED TO
FIGHT TO MAKE SURE THAT THIS
COUNTRY BECOMES ALL THAT IT CAN
BECOME.
ALL OF THAT IS EXTREMELY
GRATIFYING TO ME, AND AT THE END
OF THE DAY, WHEN YOU LOOK
AROUND, WE ARE SO PROUD TO BE
AMERICANS, WE ARE SO PROUD OF
WHAT WE HAVE ACCOMPLISHED, BUT
WE KNOW WE STILL HAVE A LONG WAY
TO GO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU SO
MUCH.
LET'S GIVE A HAND TO SENATOR
SANDERS.
THANK YOU SO MUCH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW, PLEASE WELCOME SECRETARY OF
STATE HILLARY CLINTON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HI.
HOW ARE YOU?
GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> PLEASE HAVE A SEAT.
>> THANKS FOR COMING TO OUR
PARTY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SO, WELCOME, AND THANK YOU
FOR BEING HERE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> I UNDERSTAND THAT YOU WERE
JUST SPEAKING TO THE OHIO
DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
>> RIGHT.
>> AND YOU HAD A FEW CHOICE
WORDS ABOUT THE REPUBLICAN
FRONTRUNNER.
>> I DID.
>> A COUPLE.
>> SPECIFICALLY ABOUT THE
VIOLENCE AT HIS RALLIES AND SOME
OF THE COMMENTS, AND WE TALKED
ABOUT THAT WITH SENATOR SANDERS.
WHAT ARE YOUR CONCERNS?
>> WELL, I THINK THAT ALL
AMERICANS SHOULD BE CONCERNED.
IT IS CLEAR THAT DONALD TRUMP IS
RUNNING A VERY CYNICAL CAMPAIGN
PITTING GROUPS OF AMERICANS
AGAINST ONE ANOTHER.
HE IS TRAFFICKING IN HATE AND
FEAR.
HE IS PLAYING TO OUR WORST
INSTINCTS RATHER THAN OUR ANGELS
OF OUR BETTER NATURE.
HE ACTUALLY INCITES VIOLENCE IN
THE WAY THAT HE URGES HIS
AUDIENCE ON.
YOU KNOW, TALKING ABOUT PUNCHING
PEOPLE, OFFERING TO PAY LEGAL
BILLS, AND THEN ON THE
SPECIFICS, YOU KNOW, WE KNOW
THAT HE HAS BEEN INCREDIBLY
BIGOTED TOWARDS SO MANY GROUPS.
HE TALKS ABOUT DEPORTING 11, 12
MILLION IMMIGRANTS.
WE'RE A NATION BUILT ON
IMMIGRANTS.
HE TALKS ABOUT PREVENTING
MUSLIMS FROM COMING INTO OUR
COUNTRY.
WE BELIEVE IN RELIGIOUS FREEDOM.
THERE'S JUST SO MUCH OF WHAT
HE'S DOING THAT I THINK WE ALL
HAVE TO REJECT BECAUSE IT IS SO
AT ODDS WITH OUR VALUES.
YOU DON'T MAKE AMERICA GREAT BY
TEARING DOWN EVERYTHING THAT
MADE AMERICA GREAT.
AND SO LET'S STAND UP AND WITH
ONE VOICE REJECT THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SO DONALD TRUMP, TO PLAY
DEVIL'S ADVOCATE, HE SAYS IT IS
SUPPORTERS OF SENATOR SANDERS
AND SUPPORTERS OF YOURS WHO CAME
TO CHICAGO AND SHUT DOWN HIS
RALLY WITH VIOLENCE.
OBVIOUSLY, WHEN WE ALL LOOKED AT
THE HORRIFIC PICTURES FROM THAT
NIGHT, IT WAS NOT EASY TO
DISCERN THAT ONE SIDE WAS WRONG
AND THE THE OTHER SIDE WAS RIGHT
OR WHAT WAS GOING ON, THERE WERE
A LOT OF PEOPLE FIGHTING.
DO YOU THINK THAT THERE ARE
DEMOCRATS WHO ALSO NEED TO BE
CAUTIONED VIOLENCE IS NOT THE
WAY TO GO HERE?
>> WELL, LET'S START WITH WHAT I
THINK IS THE TRUTH.
DONALD TRUMP IS RESPONSIBLE FOR
WHAT HAPPENS AT HIS EVENTS.
HE IS THE PERSON WHO --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- HAS FOR MONTHS NOW BEEN NOT
JUST INCITING VIOLENCE, BUT
APPLAUDING VIOLENCE.
THE IMAGES OF THE, YOU KNOW,
YOUNG AFRICAN-AMERICAN PROTESTER
BEING ATTACKED TOTALLY WITHOUT
ANY PROVOCATION WHATSOEVER, AND
HAVING DONALD TRUMP SAY HE WOULD
PAY THE LEGAL BILLS OF THE
ATTACKER, SO CLEARLY PEOPLE WHO
ENGAGE IN PROTEST SHOULD FOLLOW
CIVIL DISOBEDIENCE PRINCIPLES
AND SHOULD BE PEACEFUL, SHOULD
BE NONVIOLENT, BUT I DO THINK
THAT AS I SAID THE OTHER DAY
WHAT TRUMP HAS DONE IS LIKE A
CASE OF POLITICAL ARSON.
YOU KNOW, HE HAS LIT THE FIRE
AND THEN HE THROWS HIS HANDS UP,
AND CLAIMS THAT HE SHOULDN'T BE
HELD RESPONSIBLE, AND HE SHOULD
BE HELD RESPONSIBLE.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, YESTERDAY
YOU WERE IN ST. LOUIS, AND YOU
TALKED ABOUT CARPENTERS AND THE
REBUILDING OF THE COUNTRY, THE
FOLKS WHO BUILT THIS NATION.
>> RIGHT.
>> BOTH YOU AND SENATOR SANDERS
HAVE SIGNIFICANT UNION SUPPORT,
AND YET MANY OF THE TRADE UNIONS
THAT WE TALK ABOUT WHO BUILT THE
COUNTRY, THEY'VE LOCKED OUT
BLACK FOLKS AND MINORITIES FOR
DECADES.
WOULD YOU EVEN RIGHT NOW AND
EVEN AS PRESIDENT CALL A MEETING
WITH THE TRADE UNIONS AND SAY
IT'S TIME FOR YOU TO OPEN UP
THOSE DOORS AND BRING IN MORE
AFRICAN-AMERICANS, MORE
HISPANICS AND OTHERS, BECAUSE
THOSE ARE HIGH-PAYING JOBS AND
IF WE KEEP SAYING REBUILD
AMERICA WITH THE HUGE
INFRASTRUCTURE AND BUILD OF
DOLLARS, THEY'RE THE ONES WHO
ARE GOING TO DO IT AND BLACK
FOLKS AND OTHERS ARE GOING TO BE
LEFT ON THE OUTSIDE LOOKING IN.
>> ROLAND, I CERTAINLY AGREE,
AND HAVE BEEN AN ADVOCATE FOR
OPENING UP UNIONS, BUSINESSES,
ACADEMIC INSTITUTIONS, EVERY
INSTITUTION IN OUR COUNTRY, AND
IT IS FOR ME A SPECIAL
COMMITMENT THAT WE WOULD OPEN UP
APPRENTICESHIPS FOR THE FULL
DIVERSITY OF OUR COUNTRY.
>> AND I DON'T MEAN ANY
DISRESPECT, BUT THE
APPRENTICESHIPS ARE THE FRONT
JOBS.
I'M TALKING ABOUT THE PEOPLE WHO
ARE ALREADY TRAINED AND CAN DO
THE JOB.
THAT IS THE EARLY FOLKS.
BUT I'M TALKING  INGING  ING AB
SKILLED FOLKS RIGHT NOW.
>> WE SHOULD DO THE WHOLE GAMUT.
I'VE BEEN IN A NUMBER OF
TRAINING FACILITIES AND AT LEAST
DURING MY VISITS, AND THIS GOES
BACK TO MY TIME IN THE SENATE,
THERE'S A VERY DIVERSE
REPRESENTATION.
NOW, WE DO NEED TO WORK MUCH
MORE DILIGENTLY TO OPEN UP ALL
OF THE TRADES, ALL OF THE
BUSINESSES, AND YOU WILL
CERTAINLY SEE ME PUSHING THAT,
AND THERE IS GOING TO BE SO MUCH
WORK IF I HAVE MY WAY, IF I'M SO
FORTUNATE TO BE PRESIDENT THAT
WE ARE GOING TO NEED A MUCH
BIGGER WORKFORCE TO DO
INFRASTRUCTURE, ADVANCED
MANUFACTURING, CLEAN ENERGY
JOBS, AND IT WOULD BE
COUNTERPRODUCTIVE AS WELL AS
WRONG TO KEEP ANYBODY OUT.
SO I HAVE A TAX CREDIT TO EXPAND
APPRENTICESHIP PROGRAMS BECAUSE
YOU'RE RIGHT, WE HAVE TO FOCUS
ON THOSE WHO ALREADY HAVE THE
SKILLS, BUT WE'RE GOING TO NEED
A BIG PIPELINE.
AND I CAME FROM A VERY
INTERESTING MEETING I HAD IN
MERION, OHIO BEFORE COMING HERE.
AND I TALKED TO SOME PEOPLE WHO
HAVE BEEN RUNNING SOME GREAT
TECH PROGRAMS.
I KNOW THAT SENATOR BROWN IS
SUPPORTING SOMETHING CALLED RAM
TECH, AND IT IS REALLY FOCUSED
ON MAKING THE CASE, AND I NEED
YOUR HELP IN THE MEDIA TO MAKE
THE CASE, THERE ARE VERY MANY
GOOD JOBS IN THE TRADES, BUT A
LOT OF PEOPLE ARE NOT REALLY
ENCOURAGED TO GO THAT DIRECTION.
>> WE DO IT ON TVONE.
>> PLEASE DO IT.
>> YES.
>> BECAUSE RIGHT NOW IN OHIO I
WAS TOLD THERE ARE 60,000 JOBS
AVAILABLE FOR SKILLED WORK IN
THE TRADES AND THESE ARE JOBS
THAT GO 40, 50, 60 THOUSAND TO
START.
AND I MET A YOUNG WOMAN WELDER
IN MERION WHO -- SHE GOT INTO
THE PROGRAM, GOT HER
CERTIFICATION IN WELDING, AND
SHE'S, YOU KNOW, ALREADY MOVED
FROM $14 AN HOUR TO $19 AN HOUR
WITH MORE INCREASES IN SIGHT.
SO WE'VE GOT TO OPEN UP THE
TRADES BUT WE ALSO HAVE TO
ENCOURAGE MORE PEOPLE TO THINK
ABOUT THOSE AS AN OCCUPATION
PROFESSION.
>> LET'S MEET SOME MORE VOTERS
IF YOU COULD.
MADAM SECRETARY, IF YOU'D WALK
UP HERE.
>> OKAY.
>> I WANT TO INTRODUCE TO YOU
THOMAS KELLING.
HE IS A STEELWORKER AND HE SAYS
HE'S STILL UNDECIDED.
>> HI.
HOW ARE YOU?
?
HI.
THANK YOU.
NICE TO SEE YOU.
I'M A 47-YEAR-OLD -- EXCUSE ME.
I'M A 47-YEAR-OLD LAID-OFF STEEL
WORKER FROM LORRAINE, OHIO.
I HAVE A WIFE, THREE KIDS TWO,
CARS AND A HOUSE.
THERE ARE THOUSANDS OF STEEL
WORKERS THAT ARE GETTING READY
TO LOSE EVERYTHING BECAUSE OF
THE ILLEGAL DUMPING OF FOREIGN
STEEL.
>> RIGHT.
>> THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CAME
OUT AND HELPED THE AUTO INDUSTRY
BY GIVING OUT OR GIVING THEM
LOANS SO THEY CAN KEEP RUNNING,
AND THEY ALSO HELPED OUT THE
BANKING SYSTEMS.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS DO YOU
THINK OR DO YOU BELIEVE THAT IT
IS POSSIBLE FOR THE GOVERNMENT
TO DO THE SAME FOR THE STEEL
INDUSTRY, AND IF NOT, WHY?
THANK YOU.
>> HOW LONG HAVE YOU BEEN LAID
OFF?
>> SINCE NOVEMBER, BUT I HAVE
FRIENDS THAT HAVE BEEN OUT SINCE
MARCH OF 2015.
>> WELL, I JUST FINISHED
SPEAKING ABOUT THIS AT THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY DINNER.
AND I THINK THAT NUMBER ONE, WE
HAVE TO TAKE MUCH MORE
AGGRESSIVE ACTION TO STOP THE
DUMPING.
I BELIEVE THAT THE DUMPING IS
ILLEGAL, AND THAT WE HAVE TO
SUMMON UP THE POLITICAL AND THE
LEGAL ARGUMENTS TO TAKE IT ON.
AND THIS IS NOT NEW FOR ME.
I FOUGHT FOR OUR STEEL COMPANIES
AND WORKERS IN NEW YORK WHEN I
WAS A SENATOR, AND I TESTIFIED
BEFORE THE INTERNATIONAL TRADE
COMMISSION, AND THIS IS
SOMETHING THAT I KNOW
CONGRESSMAN BEATTY AND SENATOR
BROWN AND I ALL AGREE ON THAT
YOU SHOULDN'T HAVE TO BE A
BUSINESS OR UNION OR WORKER TO
BRING THESE KINDS OF THE UNFAIR
TRADE PRACTICES TO A LEGAL
FORUM.
I WANT THE GOVERNMENT TO DO IT.
I WANT THE UNITED STATES
GOVERNMENT TO STAND UP FOR STEEL
AND STAND UP FOR THE COMPANIES
AND THE WORKERS.
AND --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- I ALSO HAVE FOR THE FIRST
TIME EVER A TRADE PROSECUTOR WHO
WOULD REPORT DIRECTLY TO THE
PRESIDENT, AND MORE
INVESTIGATORS SO THAT WE DON'T
WAIT UNTIL THE DAMAGE IS DONE,
WE TRY TO GET IN EARLY TO
PREVENT IT, AND THEN MAKE IT
POSSIBLE FOR THERE TO BE SOME
KIND OF RECOVERY.
I HAPPEN TO THINK A STEEL
INDUSTRY IS IN AMERICA'S
NATIONAL SECURITY INTEREST AS
WELL AS OUR ECONOMIC INTEREST,
AND SO WHAT I WILL TELL YOU --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- IS THAT IN ADDITION TO
ENFORCING LAWS AND TRYING TO
REALLY GO AFTER THE MAJOR RULE
BREAKER IN THE GLOBAL ECONOMY,
NAMELY CHINA, WE HAVE TO LOOK AT
HOW WE KEEP A STEEL INDUSTRY
GOING.
STANDING HERE TONIGHT, I CAN'T
TELL YOU EXACTLY WHAT THAT WOULD
LOOK LIKE, BUT I CAN PLEDGE TO
YOU THAT I'M COMMITTED TO
KEEPING A STEEL INDUSTRY AND
STEEL WORKERS WORKING IN OHIO
AND AMERICA.
>> MADAM SECRETARY, LET'S BRING
IN ANNE VALENTINE WHO IS A TRIAL
LAWYER AND SHE SAID IF SHE HAD
TO CHOOSE RIGHT NOW, SHE WOULD
CHOOSE YOU, BUT SHE IS STILL
TORN, AND SHE HAS A QUESTION.
>> GREAT.
>> GOOD EVENING, SENATOR
CLINTON.
THANK YOU FOR TAKING MY
QUESTION.
ONE OF MY CONCERNS FOR THE NEW
PRESIDENT IS THE PROSPECT OF YET
ANOTHER WAR.
I HAVE NEPHEWS AND A GODSON VERY
DEAR TO ME, AND MY QUESTION IS
THIS.
IN A RECENT "NEW YORK TIMES"
MAGAZINE ARTICLE FOR WHICH YOU
WERE INTERVIEWED, IT WAS SAID
ABOUT YOU THAT GIVEN A CHOICE
BETWEEN ACTION AND INACTION
YOU'D RATHER BE CAUGHT TRYING.
DOES THAT MEAN THAT WE ARE
DESTINED FOR MORE CONFLICT UNDER
YOUR WATCH?
>> NO.
NO, AND I DON'T THINK IT IS AN
EITHER/OR KIND OF QUESTION.
I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE TO USE
EVERY TOOL AT OUR DISPOSAL, OUR
DIPLOMACY, OUR DEVELOPMENT AND
OUR STRONG CULTURAL INFLUENCE
AROUND THE WORLD AS WELL AS
DEFENSE.
AND I THINK IN THE WORLD IN
WHICH WE ARE LIVING TODAY, IT IS
REALLY IMPORTANT FOR THE
PRESIDENT TO BUILD COALITIONS,
TO SUPPORT OUR FRIENDS, OUR
PARTNERS AND OUR ALLIES TO BE
ABLE TO TAKE ON CHALLENGES THAT
CONFRONT THEM.
OBVIOUSLY, FORCE SHOULD ALWAYS
BE A LAST RESORT, NOT A FIRST
CHOICE.
I WILL GIVE YOU A QUICK EXAMPLE.
YOU KNOW, WHEN PRESIDENT OBAMA
WENT INTO OFFICE AND I BECAME
THE SECRETARY OF STATE, THE
IRANIANS HAD MASTERED THE
NUCLEAR FUEL CYCLE.
THEY HAD BUILT COVERT FUEL
FACILITIES, THEY HAD STOCKED
THEM WITH CENTRIFUGES.
ALL OF THAT HAPPENED WHILE
GEORGE W. BUSH WAS PRESIDENT.
AND WE HAD DONE THE SANCTIONS
AND EVERYTHING THAT WE COULD
THINK OF AS THE UNITED STATES
GOVERNMENT AND CONGRESS, BUT IT
HADN'T STOMD THEM.
AND THERE WERE A LOT OF OTHER
COUNTRIES IN THE REGION WHO SAID
THEY WOULD TAKE MILITARY ACTION
IF NECESSARY.
SO I LED THE EFFORT TO IMPOSE
SANCTIONS ON IRAN, TO REALLY
BRING THEM TO THE NEGOTIATING
TABLE.
THE NEGOTIATIONS STARTED UNDER
MY WATCH, ABLY CONCLUDED UNDER
SECRETARY KERRY, TO PUT A LID ON
THE IRANIAN NUCLEAR WEAPONS
PROGRAM.
THAT IS MY PREFERENCE, SMART
POWER USING OUR INTELLIGENCE,
OUR DIPLOMATIC EFFORTS,
EVERYTHING THAT WE CAN BRING TO
BEAR, BUT LEADING THE REST OF
THE WORLD AND NOT GOING OFF AND
DOING IT OUR OWN TO TRY TO END
CONFLICTS WHERE WE CAN, TO
PREVENT THEM WHERE WE CAN, AND
IF YOU HAVE A SITUATION LIKE WE
DO CURRENTLY IN SYRIA AND IRAQ,
PROVIDE SUPPORT AS WE ARE DOING
FOR OTHERS TO CARRY THE CONFLICT
FORWARD THROUGH MILITARY ACTION.
SO THAT IS IN A KIND OF CAPSULE
HOW I SEE WHAT THE NEXT
PRESIDENT SHOULD DO.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON --
[ APPLAUSE ]
SINCE 1976, WE HAVE EXECUTED
1,414 PEOPLE IN THE COUNTRY, AND
SINCE 1973, 156 WHO WERE
CONVICTED HAVE BEEN EXONERATED
FROM THE DEATH ROW.
THIS GENTLEMAN HERE IS ONE OF
THEM.
THIS IS RICKY JACKSON,
WRONGFULLY CONVICTED OF MURDER
IN 1975.
HE SPENT 39 YEARS IN PRISON.
HE IS UNDECIDED.
RICKY, WHAT IS YOUR QUESTION?
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
THANK YOU FOR TAKING MY
QUESTION.
AS STATED, I DID SPEND 39 YEARS
OF MY LIFE IN PRISON FOR A CRIME
OF MURDER I DIDN'T COMMIT.
AND IT WAS ONLY THROUGH HEROIC
EFFORTS OF THE OHIO INNOCENCE
PROJECT AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
CINCINNATI THAT I WAS ULTIMATELY
EXONERATED AND AM ABLE TO STAND
BEFORE YOU TODAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THANK YOU.
SENATOR, I SPENT SOME -- SOME OF
THOSE YEARS ON DEATH ROW, AND --
EXCUSE ME.
I'M SORRY.
>> IT'S OKAY, BROTHER.
>> I CAME PERILOUSLY CLOSE TO MY
OWN EXECUTION, AND IN LIGHT OF
THAT, WHAT I HAVE JUST SHARED
WITH YOU AND IN LIGHT OF THE
FACT THAT THERE ARE -- THERE ARE
DOCUMENTED CASES OF INNOCENT
PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN EXECUTED IN
OUR COUNTRY, I WOULD LIKE TO
KNOW HOW CAN YOU STILL TAKE YOUR
STANCE ON THE DEATH PENALTY IN
LIGHT OF WHAT WE KNOW RIGHT NOW?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU KNOW, THIS IS SUCH A
PROFOUNDLY DIFFICULT QUESTION
AND WHAT I HAVE SAID AND WHAT I
CONTINUE TO BELIEVE IS THAT THE
STATES HAVE PROVEN THEMSELVES
INCAPABLE OF CARRYING OUT FAIR
TRIALS THAT GIVE ANY DEFENDANT
ALL OF THE RIGHTS THAT A
DEFENDANT SHOULD HAVE, ALL THE
SUPPORT THAT THE DEFENDANT'S
LAWYER SHOULD HAVE, AND I SAID
I WOULD BREATHE A SIGH OF RELIEF
IF EITHER THE SUPREME COURT OR
THE STATES THEMSELVES BEGAN TO
ELIMINATE THE DEATH PENALTY.
WHERE I END UP IS THIS, AND
MAYBE IT'S A DISTINCTION THAT IS
HARD TO SUPPORT, BUT AT THIS
POINT GIVEN THE CHALLENGES WE
FACE FROM TERRORIST ACTIVITIES
PRIMARILY IN OUR COUNTRY THAT
END UP UNDER FEDERAL
JURISDICTION FOR VERY LIMITED
PURPOSES, I THINK IT CAN STILL
BE HELD IN RESERVE FOR THOSE.
AND THE KIND OF CRIMES I'M
THINKING OF ARE THE BOMBING IN
OKLAHOMA CITY WHERE AN AMERICAN
TERRORIST BLEW UP THE GOVERNMENT
BUILDING, KILLING AS I RECALL
158 AMERICANS, INCLUDING A
NUMBER OF CHILDREN WHO WERE IN
THE PRESCHOOL PROGRAM.
THE PLOTTERS AND THE PEOPLE WHO
CARRIED OUT THE ATTACKS ON 9/11,
BUT A VERY LIMITED USE OF IT IN
CASES WHERE THERE HAS BEEN
HORRIFIC MASS KILLINGS.
THAT'S REALLY THE EXCEPTION THAT
I STILL AM STRUGGLING WITH, AND
THAT WOULD ONLY BE IN THE
FEDERAL SYSTEM.
BUT WHAT HAPPENED TO YOU WAS A
TRAVESTY, AND I JUST CAN'T EVEN
IMAGINE WHAT YOU WENT THROUGH
AND HOW TERRIBLE THOSE DAYS AND
NIGHTS MUST HAVE BEEN FOR ALL OF
THOSE YEARS, AND I KNOW THAT ALL
OF US ARE SO REGRETFUL THAT YOU
OR ANY PERSON HAS TO GO THROUGH
WHAT YOU DID, AND I HOPE THAT
NOW THAT YOU ARE STANDING HERE
BEFORE US THAT YOU WILL HAVE
WHATEVER PATH IN LIFE YOU CHOOSE
GOING FORWARD AND THAT YOU WILL
GET THE SUPPORT THAT YOU DESERVE
TO HAVE.
>> AND I HAVE TO ASK RICKY --
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> IS THAT ANSWER SATISFACTORY
FOR YOU?
>> YES.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> THANK YOU, SIR.
>> ALL RIGHT.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE MORE
QUESTIONS FROM THE AUDIENCE FOR
THE FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE
HILLARY CLINTON AFTER THIS SHORT
BREAK.
STAY WITH US.
>>> WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE IN OHIO WITH HILLARY
CLINTON AT OUR TOWN HALL
MEETING.
LET'S CONTINUE.
MADAM SECRETARY, I WANT YOU TO
MEET TERESA O'DONNELL.
SHE IS AN OFFICE COORDINATOR
FROM POWELL, OHIO, AND SHE SAYS
THAT SHE IS LEANING IN YOUR
FAVOR, BUT SHE HAS NOT YET MADE
A FIRM AND COMPLETE DECISION.
>> HELLO.
I VOTED FOR OBAMA, AND THEN MY
HEALTH INSURANCE SKYROCKETED
FROM $490 A MONTH TO $1,080 A
MONTH FOR A FAMILY OF FOUR.
I KNOW THAT OBAMA TOLD US THAT
WE WOULD BE PAYING A LITTLE
MORE, BUT DOUBLING, OVER
DOUBLING MY HEALTH INSURANCE
COST HAS NOT BEEN A LITTLE MORE.
IT HAS BEEN DIFFICULT TO COME UP
WITH THAT KIND OF PAYMENT EVERY
MONTH.
I WOULD LIKE TO VOTE DEMOCRATIC,
BUT IT'S COST ME A LOT OF MONEY,
AND I'M JUST WONDERING IF
DEMOCRATIC -- DEMOCRATS REALLY
REALIZE HOW DIFFICULT IT HAS
BEEN ON WORKING CLASS AMERICANS
TO FINANCE OBAMACARE.
>> WOW, THANK YOU FOR ASKING ME
THAT.
BECAUSE -- MAY I ASK YOU, BEFORE
WERE YOU BUYING YOUR FAMILY
HEALTH INSURANCE IN THE
INDIVIDUAL FAMILY MARKET?
WERE YOU GETTING IT THROUGH AN
EMPLOYER?
>> PURCHASING IT PRIVATELY
BECAUSE WE BOTH HAD BOUTS OF
UNEMPLOYMENT.
>> SO YOU WERE GOING TO A BROKER
AND --
>> YES.
>> -- BUYING A HEALTH INSURANCE
POLICY.
>> MM-HMM.
>> AND IN EFFECT, IT NEARLY
TRIPLED AFTER YOU WENT ONTO THE
EXCHANGE AND BOUGHT A POLICY
UNDER THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT,
IS THAT RIGHT?
>> WE COULD NOT DO THAT.
IT WAS MUCH MORE EXPENSIVE THAN
JUST PURCHASING PRIVATE
INSURANCE FROM THE INSURANCE
COMPANY.
>> SO YOU ARE STILL BUYING THE
PRIVATE INSURANCE DIRECTLY?
>> YES.
>> OKAY.
WELL, FIRST OF ALL, LET ME SAY
I WANT VERY MUCH TO GET THE
COSTS DOWN, AND THAT IS GOING TO
BE MY MISSION, BECAUSE I DO
THINK THAT FOR MANY, MANY
PEOPLE, BUT THERE ARE EXCEPTIONS
LIKE WHAT YOU ARE TELLING ME,
HAVING THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT
HAS REDUCED COSTS, HAS CREATED A
REAL GUARANTEE OF INSURANCE,
BECAUSE IF YOU'D HAD A
PRE-EXISTING CONDITION UNDER THE
OLD SYSTEM, YOU WOULDN'T HAVE
GOTTEN AFFORDABLE INSURANCE, SO
IT'S DONE A LOT OF REALLY GOOD
THINGS, BUT IT HAS BECOME
INCREASINGLY CLEAR THAT WE ARE
GOING TO HAVE TO GET THE COSTS
DOWN, AND WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO
SEE HAPPEN FOR YOU AND YOUR
FAMILY IS THAT IF WE CAN GET THE
CO-PAYS DOWN, THE DEDUCTIBLES
DOWN, GET THE PRESCRIPTION DRUG
COSTS UNDER CONTROL, THAT YOU
WOULD FIND AN AFFORDABLE PLAN ON
YOUR EXCHANGE.
AND ONE THING THAT I WOULD LIKE
YOU TO DO, AND I'M NOT SAYING
IT'S GOING TO MAKE A DIFFERENCE,
BUT I WOULD LIKE YOU TO JUST GO
SHOPPING ON THAT EXCHANGE.
AS I UNDERSTAND IT, OHIO HAS THE
FEDERAL EXCHANGE -- IS THAT
RIGHT, JOYCE?
BECAUSE THEY DID NOT SET UP A
STATE EXCHANGE, SO YOU HAVE THE
FEDERAL EXCHANGE, AND TO GO ON
AND KEEP LOOKING TO SEE WHAT THE
PRICES ARE, BECAUSE WE HAVE TO
GET MORE COMPETITION BACK INTO
THE INSURANCE MARKET.
ONE THING THAT I WANT TO WORK ON
WITH MY FRIENDS FROM CONGRESS
WHO ARE HERE IS WE'VE GOT THE
GET MORE NONPROFITS THAT ARE
CAPABLE OF SELLING INSURANCE
BACK INTO THE INSURANCE MARKET.
YOU KNOW, BLUE CROSS AND BLUE
SHIELD USED TO BE NONPROFITS.
AND THEN THEY TRANSFERRED
THEMSELVES INTO FOR-PROFIT
COMPANIES.
THERE WAS SOME EFFORT MADE UNDER
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT TO GET
SOME COMPETITION FROM NONPROFIT
INSTITUTIONS.
SOME OF THEM WORKED AND A LOT OF
THEM DIDN'T.
I WANT TO KNOW WHAT WE CAN DO,
BECAUSE IF IF YOU COULD GET A
RANGE OF INSURERS, SOME OF WHOM
WERE FOR NONPROFIT COMPANY, THAT
WOULD LOWER THE COSTS, AND SO
THERE IS A NUMBER OF THINGS THEY
I AM LOOKING AT.
WHAT I WANT TO ASSURE YOU AND
YOUR FAMILY OF IS THAT I WILL DO
EVERYTHING I CAN AS PRESIDENT
WORKING WITH MEMBERS OF CONGRESS
WHERE NECESSARY TO TRY TO GET
THE COSTS DOWN.
BUT I DO WANT YOU TO KEEP
SHOPPING, BECAUSE WHAT YOU'RE
TELLING ME IS MUCH HIGHER THAN
WHAT I HEAR FROM OTHER FAMILIES,
AND SO I WANT TO BE SURE THAT IF
THERE'S A BETTER OPTION FOR YOU
YOU'RE GOING TO BE ABLE TO TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF IT AND THEN I WANT
TO WORK AS HARD AS I CAN TO KEEP
COSTS DOWN FOR EVERYBODY.
AND THAT INCLUDES PRESCRIPTION
DRUG COSTS WHICH ARE
SKYROCKETING AND INCREASING
COSTS FOR EVERYTHING ELSE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ALL RIGHT.
TO GAYLE SAUNDERS WHO IS A SHOT
CALLER, BIG BALLER, AND OWNER OF
HER OWN P.R. FIRM, AND SHE IS
LEANING YOUR WAY AND SEE IF YOU
CAN PULL HER OVER THE FINISH
LINE.
OKAY.
GO AHEAD.
>> GOOD EVENING, SECRETARY
CLINTON.
THANK YOU FOR TAKING MY
QUESTION.
I BELIEVE THAT THE NUMBER OF
PRISONS BUILT IN THIS COUNTRY IS
ABSOLUTELY SHAMEFUL.
AND WE KNOW THAT BLACK AND BROWN
PEOPLE ARE DISPROPORTIONATELY
REPRESENTED IN A SYSTEM THAT IN
ONE INSTANCE ALLOWS FOR AN
AFFLUENZA DEFENSE, AND IN OTHER
INSTANCES REALLY MAKES TOUGHER
PENALTIES ON PEOPLE BECAUSE THEY
LIVE IN A PARTICULAR ZIP CODE.
>> RIGHT.
>> SO MY QUESTION QUESTION OF
YOU, SECRETARY CLINTON, AS
PRESIDENT WHAT WILL YOU DO TO
ADDRESS THIS SYSTEM TO MAKE IT
MORE FAIR AND BALANCED AND
ADDRESS A SYSTEM THAT MANY ARE
CALLING MODERN DAY SLAVERY.
>> WELL, YOUR DESCRIPTION OF THE
PROBLEM IS ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
THE VERY FIRST SPEECH I GAVE IN
THIS CAMPAIGN WAS ABOUT CRIMINAL
JUSTICE AND INCARCERATION
REFORM.
SO THERE ARE A NUMBER OF THINGS
THAT I HAVE LAID OUT.
I WANT TO JUST GIVE YOU A SORT
OF OVERVIEW.
BUT PLEASE GO TO MY WEBSITE,
HILLARYCLINTON.COM, THAT LAYS
OUT MY COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH.
1 IN 3 AFRICAN-AMERICAN MEN, IF
THE TRENDS CONTINUE THAT WE SEE
TODAY CONTINUE, WILL SPEND SOME
TIME IN JAIL OR PRISON.
THAT IS ABSOLUTELY UNACCEPTABLE.
THERE IS NO JUSTIFICATION FOR
IT.
THERE IS NO EXCUSE FOR IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I HAVE BEEN GOING AROUND
SPEAKING OUT THAT AN
AFRICAN-AMERICAN YOUNG MAN IS
MORE LIKELY TO BE ARRESTED,
CHARGED, CONVICTED AND
INCARCERATED FOR DOING THE
EXACTLY SAME THING AS A WHITE
MAN, WHO IS NOT.
AND WHAT THAT MEANS IS THAT WE
HAVE TO BE HONEST WITH
OURSELVES, WE HAVE SYSTEMIC
RACISM THAT IS REALLY AT WORK
INSIDE THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
AND WE'VE GOT TO BE WILLING TO
STAND UP --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- AND QUESTION THESE INEQUITIES
AND THEN GO ABOUT THE BUSINESS
OF RIDDING THEM.
WE NEED TO DIVERT MANY MORE
PEOPLE OUT OF THE JAIL AND
PRISON SYSTEM INTO DIVERSION
PROGRAMS, JOB PROGRAMS, SKILLS
PROGRAMS.
WHERE WE ARE DOING THIS,
ALTHOUGH IT IS ON TOO SMALL A
SCALE, IT WORKS.
AND WE NEED TO HAVE MUCH MORE IN
THE WAY OF TREATMENT AND HELP
FOR PEOPLE WHO HAVE ADDICTIONS,
WHO HAVE MENTAL HEALTH ISSUES,
SO THAT THEY CAN BE HELPED, NOT
INCARCERATED.
WE NEED TO END PRIVATE PRISONS.
THEY ARE A SHAMEFUL BLOT ON OUR
PRISON SYSTEM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND IF WE CAN ELIMINATE THE
SCHOOL-TO-PRISON PIPELINE AND
SUBSTITUTE A CRADLE-TO-COLLEGE
PIPELINE THAT STARTS WITH EARLY
EDUCATION, AND STARTS WITH MORE
HELP EARLIER ON, THEN WE CAN
BEGIN CLOSING THE PRISON, AND I
GUESS THAT THE FINAL THING THAT
I WOULD SAY ABOUT THIS OVERVIEW
IS THAT I REALLY BELIEVE STATES
HAVE GOT TO STOP BUILDING
PRISONS AND START INVESTING IN
EDUCATION.
ELEMENTARY, SECONDARY AND HIGHER
>> JAKE, JAKE, JAKE -- SORRY.
JUST IF I CAN.
SHOULD THE DEMOCRATS STOP TAKING
MONEY FROM PRIVATE PRISONS?
SHOULD PEOPLE, SHOULD DEMOCRATS
STOP TAKING THE MONEY FROM
PRIVATE PRISONS?
>> THE ANSWER IS YES.
YES.
THAT CERTAINLY IS WHAT MY
CAMPAIGN DECIDED.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT AN ISSUE
THAT OF A LOT OF CONCERN HERE IN
OHIO, FRACKING.
FRACKING IS A TECHNIQUE FOR OIL
AND GAS FUELING THAT IS LEADING
TO A SIGNIFICANT INCREASE IN
AMERICAN PRODUCTION.
IT'S ALSO RAISED CONCERNS ABOUT
HEALTH AND SAFETY RISKS.
THERE ARE ALMOST 20,000 FRACKING
JOBS HERE IN OHIO.
THE INDUSTRY BRINGS IN ABOUT
TO-20 MILLION FOR THE STATE EACH
YEAR.
AND LET'S BRING IN CHRISTINE
HUGHS WHO IS AN OWNER OF A
RESTAURANT FROM ATHENS, OHIO.
SHE'S AN ANTI-FRACKING ACTIVIST.
SHE SAID SHEZ UN'S UNDECIDED.
SHE HAS A QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> ATHENS IS BEAUTIFUL.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I DEPEND
ON THE SMALL FARMS IN OHIO FOR
MY PRESENTER, AND MANY FARMERS
HAVE BEEN HARMED BY THE FRACKING
INDUSTRY.
OHIO ALLOWS FRACKING, PIPELINES
AND INJECTION WELLS ON AND
AROUND EVEN ORGANIC FARMS.
AT THE DEBATE IN FLINT, MICHIGAN
YOU SAID YOU WOULDN'T ALLOW
FRACKING IN COMMUNITIES THAT
DIDN'T WANT IT.
BUT OHIO DOESN'T ALLOW LOCAL
FRACKING BANS.
AS PRESIDENT WILL YOU LET
FARMERS AND COMMUNITIES SAY NO
TO FRACKING AND FULLY SUPPORT A
CLEAN ENERGY FUTURE?
>> YOU KNOW, AS I SAID IN THE
DEBATE WHEN ASKED THIS, BECAUSE
SO MUCH OF WHAT GOVERNS FRACKING
RIGHT NOW IS WITHIN STATE AND
LOCAL CONTROL, AND THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT I THINK THAT IT HAS
AN IMPORTANT ROLE TO PLAY
INCLUDING ADVOCATING FOR WHAT
YOU SAID THAT I HAD PUT FORWARD
WHICH IS TO GIVE LOCAL
COMMUNITIES THE SAY OVER IT.
I ALSO SAID THIS.
WE NEED MUCH MORE SCIENTIFIC
RESEARCH, BUT HERE'S WHAT WE
KNOW.
WE KNOW THAT METHANE RELEASES
ARE BAD.
THEY ARE BAD FOR THE
ENVIRONMENT.
THEY ARE BAD FOR GREENHOUSE GAS
EMISSIONS.
WE KNOW THAT IF WATER IS
CONTAMINATED, THAT'S BAD, AND WE
CAN'T ALLOW THAT TO GO FORWARD.
WE KNOW THAT THERE IS A LOOPHOLE
IN THE LAW THAT I DISAGREE WITH
THAT PERMITS THE FRACKING
COMPANIES TO NOT HAVE TO
DISCLOSE THE CHEMICALS THAT THEY
ARE USING IN FRACKING.
WE DESERVE TO KNOW.
I THINK WE HAVE A RIGHT TO KNOW.
WE DESERVE TO KNOW, AND WE HAVE
A RIGHT TO KNOW.
SO I AM GOING TO PUSH VERY TOUGH
RULES.
NOW I HAVE TO FIGURE OUT WHAT I
CAN DO ON THE FEDERAL LEVEL AS
OPPOSED TO WHAT WE ARE GOING TO
HAVE TO WORK ON AT THE STATE
LEVEL.
OKLAHOMA WHICH IS AS YOU KNOW
HAS BEEN VERY PRO FRACKING HAS
SUFFERED FROM TREMORS AND LITTLE
EARTHQUAKES AROUND THE STATE.
AND THERE IS GROWING SCIENTIFIC
EVIDENCE THAT FRACKING IS
CONNECTED TO, AND I DON'T WANT
TO SAY CAUSE, BECAUSE THE
SCIENTISTS HAVE NOT REACHED
THAT.
BUT CERTAINLY CONNECTED TO THESE
TREMORS.
SO NOW EVEN OKLAHOMA IS SAYING
HEY, WAIT A MINUTE, WE'D BETTER
STOP AND TAKE A HARD LOOK AT
THIS.
SO I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN AS
PRESIDENT TO SET THE RULES, TO
SET THE REGULATIONS, TO TRY TO
FIGURE OUT HOW TO INFLUENCE
STATES.
I'M NOT SURE GIVEN THE PRESENT
POLITICAL MAKEUP WE COULD PASS A
FEDERAL LAW TO END FRACKING, BUT
WE SURE CAN TRY TO REGULATE IT
VERY EFFECTIVELY UNDER THE RULES
WE ALREADY HAVE THAT GIVE US
FEDERAL JURISDICTION OVER SOME
OF THESE CHEMICALS AND RELEASES.
SO THAT'S WHAT I'M GOING TO TRY
TO DO.
AND YOU KNOW, I KNOW THAT OTHERS
SAY, WELL, WE'RE GOING TO BAN
IT.
I JUST WANT TO TELL YOU I'M
GOING TO DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO
REGULATE IT AND TO TRY TO LIMIT
IT.
NO PRESIDENT CAN STAND UP BEFORE
YOU AND SAY I'M GOING TO BAN IT.
WE HAVE TOO MANY LAYERS OF LAW
THAT WE HAVE TO WORK THROUGH AND
REGULATION WE'VE GOT TO DEAL
WITH, AND THAT'S WHAT I'M TRYING
TO SAY VERY CLEAR LY.
YOU KNOW, I DON'T WANT TO MAKE A
PROMISE I CAN'T KEEP.
I WANT TO TELL YOU WHAT I THINK
I CAN DO AS PRESIDENT TO BE YOUR
ALLY IN TRYING TO STOP THAT AT
THE LOCAL LEVEL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I WANT TO
BRING BACK SOMEBODY WHO ASKED A
QUESTION OF BERNIE SANDERS
EARLIER, AND WE WILL LET HIM ASK
YOU AS WELL.
IT IS A DR. AMET, A RADIOLOGIST
FROM DUBLIN, OHIO, AND HE IS
ALSO THE POET LAUREATE OF OHIO,
>> MY GOODNESS.
>> DOCTOR, IF YOU WANT TO ASK
YOUR QUESTION AGAIN.
>> WOW.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, WELCOME TO
COLUMBUS.
THANK YOU FOR ENTERTAINING THIS
QUESTION.
I THINK WE'RE ALL INTERESTED TO
COMPARE YOUR RESPONSE GIVEN BY
SENATOR SANDERS JUST A FEW
MOMENTS AGO.
LONG STORY SHORT, I'M A SON OF
IMMIGRANTS, AND MY PARENTS ARE
BOTH CITIZENS NOW AND THEY'VE
BOTH DONE VERY WELL FOR
THEMSELVES IN THIS GREAT
COUNTRY.
AND SO HAVE I.
BUT AS A 1% ETHNIC AND RELIGIOUS
MINORITY WITNESSING THE RISE OF
DONALD TRUMP FOR THE FIRST TIME
MY FAMILY HAS STARTED FEELING A
LITTLE UNCOMFORTABLE HERE
AND TO BE HONEST A LITTLE
SCARED.
IF DONALD TRUMP SECURES THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINATION, I AM
GOING TO HAVE ONE MISSION
HEADING TO THE BALLOT BOX, WHICH
IS TO KEEP HIM OUT OF OFFICE.
SO MY QUESTION TO YOU IS WHICH
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE IS GOING TO
BE BEST AT HELPING ME DO THAT?
NOT JUST OFFERING THE EASY
CONDEMNATIONS BUT ACTUALLY BEING
ABLE TO DEFEAT HIM.
LEAVING ASIDE NEGATIVE RHETORIC
AND ATTACK ADS, NONE OF WHICH
HAVE WORKED SO FAR, CAN YOU
SHARE WITH US THREE SPECIFIC
POINTS OF YOUR ANTI-TRUMP GAME
PLAN.
>> OKAY.
DOCTOR, WELL, LET ME GIVE YOU A
LITTLE MORE CONTEXT.
WHERE WE ARE BEFORE EVERYBODY
VOTES ON TUESDAY, I'M THE ONLY
CANDIDATE WHO'S GOTTEN MORE
VOTES THAN TRUMP.
I HAVE 600,000 MORE VOTES THAN
DONALD TRUMP.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I AM BUILDING A BROAD-BASED
INCLUSIVE CAMPAIGN THAT I THINK
IS THE BEST WAY TO DEFEAT HIM BY
CONVINCING PEOPLE THAT THIS
REALLY IS THE HIGHEST STAKES
ELECTION THEY'VE EVER BEEN
INVOLVED IN AND THAT THEY'VE GOT
TO, WHETHER THEY'VE EVER VOTED
BEFORE OR NOT, TO COME OUT AND
VOTE AGAINST DONALD TRUMP AND
FOR ME.
AND BECAUSE I DO HAVE MORE VOTES
THAN EVERYBODY, ANYBODY, I
BELIEVE THAT I'M DEVELOPING THE
BASE THAT IS GOING TO GIVE ME
THE CHANCE TO DO THAT.
SECONDLY, YOU KNOW, ONE OF MY
ADVANTAGES IF I AM SO FORTUNATE
ENOUGH TO BE THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINEE IS THAT THE REPUBLICANS
HAVE BEEN AFTER ME FOR 25
YEARS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- AND THERE ISN'T ANYTHING THEY
HAVEN'T ALREADY SAID ABOUT ME,
AND IN THE COURSE OF DEALING
WITH ALL OF THIS INCOMING FIRE
FROM THEM, I HAVE DEVELOPED A
PRETTY THICK SKIN.
I AM NOT NEW TO THE NATIONAL
ARENA, AND I THINK THAT WHOEVER
GOES UP AGAINST DONALD TRUMP
BETTER BE READY, AND I FEEL I AM
THE BEST PREPARED AND READY
CANDIDATE TO TAKE HIM ON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
FINALLY, I REALLY BELIEVE THAT
THERE ARE GOING TO BE A LOT OF
ARGUMENTS TO MAKE AGAINST HIM
THAT WE CAN LOOK FORWARD TO, AND
I'M NOT GOING TO SPILL THE BEANS
RIGHT NOW.
BUT SUFFICE IT TO SAY THAT THERE
ARE MANY ARGUMENTS THAT WE CAN
USE AGAINST HIM.
BUT ONE ARGUMENT THAT I AM
UNIQUELY QUALIFIED TO BRING,
BECAUSE OF MY SERVICE AS
SECRETARY OF STATE IS WHAT HIS
PRESIDENCY WOULD MEAN TO OUR
COUNTRY AND OUR STANDING IN THE
WORLD.
I AM ALREADY RECEIVING MESSAGES
FROM LEADERS, I'M HAVING FOREIGN
LEADERS ASK IF THEY CAN ENDORSE
ME TO STOP DONALD TRUMP, AND I
SAY NO, THIS IS UP TO AMERICANS,
THANK YOU VERY MUCH, BUT I GET
WHAT YOU'RE SAYING.
>> YOU'RE NOT GOING TO TELL US
WHO?
>> WELL, SOME HAVE DONE IT
PUBLICLY, ACTUALLY.
THE ITALIAN PRIME MINISTER FOR
EXAMPLE.
>> HOW ABOUT THE ONES THAT HAVE
DONE IT PRIVATELY?
>> NO, JAKE.
WE'RE HOLDING THAT IN RESERVE,
TOO.
BUT, YOU KNOW, A LOT OF TIMES
FOREIGN POLICY DOES NOT PLAY AS
BIG OF A ROLE AS I THINK THAT IT
SHOULD, AND THE WONDERFUL
QUESTION THAT THE WOMAN ASKED ME
BEFORE ABOUT THE USE OF MILITARY
FORCE AND HOW YOU MAKE THOSE
TOUGH DECISIONS, AND YOU KNOW,
ONLY THE HARD CHOICES COME TO
THE PRESIDENT.
IF THEY ARE NOT REALLY HARD,
SOMEBODY ALONG THE WAY HAS A
CHANCE TO, YOU KNOW, MAKE A
DECISION.
SO WHEN YOU END UP IN THE
SITUATION ROOM ON A SERIOUS
FOREIGN POLICY ISSUE LIKE I WAS
THERE WITH THE SMALL GROUP
ADVISING THE PRESIDENT WHETHER
OR NOT TO GO AFTER BIN LADEN, IT
TAKES INCREDIBLE SERIOUSNESS,
DILIGENCE, JUDGMENT, A
TEMPERAMENT THAT IS NOT GOING TO
BE PUSHED ONE WAY OR ANOTHER
DEPENDING UPON WHO SAID WHAT TO
YOU TODAY.
AND I BELIEVE THAT I WILL HAVE
AN OPPORTUNITY TO REALLY FOCUS
IN ON HOW DANGEROUS A DONALD
TRUMP PRESIDENCY WOULD BE FOR
OUR STANDING, FOR OUR SAFETY,
FOR THE PEACE OF THE WORLD, AND
I THINK THAT WE CAN BE
SUCCESSFUL DOING THAT.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A VERY
QUICK BREAK.
WE HAVE MORE QUESTIONS FROM OUR
AUDIENCE FOR SECRETARY CLINTON.
YOU ARE WATCHING THE CNN/TVONE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL FROM COLUMBUS, OHIO.
STAY WITH US.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> ALL RIGHT.
FOLKS, WELCOME BACK TO THE OHIO
STATE UNIVERSITY.
LET'S GO BACK TO OUR AUDIENCE.
WE HAVE A TOWN HALL HERE IN
BETWEEN THE SECRETARY TAKING
SELFIES.
ALL RIGHT.
LET'S GO RIGHT HERE TO MISS
RASHIDA JOHNSON, A SOCIAL
ORGANIZER IN EQUALITY, OHIO AND
SHE SAYS THAT SHE'S STILL
UNDECIDED SO YOU HAVE A SHOT.
>> THANK YOU, ROLAND.
AND GOOD EVENING, SECRETARY
CLINTON.
MY QUESTION IS ON MARCH 4th, I
REGRET TO INFORM YOU THIS, BUT
THERE WERE TWO SEPARATE
SHOOTINGS INVOLVING FOUR
CHILDREN.
THE FIRST INCIDENT INVOLVED A
7-YEAR-OLD BOY BEING KILLED, HIS
5-YEAR-OLD BROTHER AND
4-YEAR-OLD SISTER WERE ALSO
WOUNDED.
THIS INCIDENT WAS A GANG-RELATED
RETALIATION SHOOTING.
THE SECOND INCIDENT WAS A
5-YEAR-OLD BOY BEING SHOT WHILE
HE ACTUALLY LAY ASLEEP IN BED.
AND HE'S STILL IN THE HOSPITAL
AS WE SPEAK.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS, AS
PRESIDENT, WHAT PROGRAMS WOULD
YOU IMPLEMENT IN
POVERTY-STRICKEN COMMUNITIES IN
THIS COUNTRY IN AN EFFORT TO
DECREASE THIS TYPE OF VIOLENCE?
>> YOU KNOW, I WANT -- I WANT
EVERYBODY TO KNOW WHAT YOU KNOW,
WHICH IS THAT ON AVERAGE 90
PEOPLE A DAY ARE KILLED BY GUNS
IN OUR COUNTRY.
THAT IS 33,000 PEOPLE A YEAR.
AND A SHOCKING NUMBER OF THOSE
KILLED AND INJURED ARE CHILDREN.
SOME OF THEM INTENTIONALLY, AND
SOME OF THEM ACCIDENTALLY.
SO HERE'S WHAT I BELIEVE WITH
ALL OF MY HEART, BECAUSE I THINK
WE ARE IN A CRISIS WHEN IT COMES
TO GUN VIOLENCE.
IT IS TRULY AN EPIDEMIC.
AND THERE IS NO DOUBT IN MY MIND
THAT WE'VE GOT TO DO MORE TO GET
COMMON SENSE GUN SAFETY REFORMS
ENACTED IN AMERICA.
SO I'M NOT SAYING WHAT I PROPOSE
WILL SOLVE EVERYTHING, BUT I
BELIEVE, AND THERE IS EVIDENCE
FOR THIS, THAT FAILING TO DO
ANYTHING, WHICH IS WHAT WE ARE
DOING RIGHT NOW, WILL ONLY LEAD
TO MORE TERRIBLE LOSS OF LIFE.
SO WE DO NEED COMPREHENSIVE
BACKGROUND CHECKS, AND WE NEED
TO CLOSE THESE LOOPHOLES.
THE SO-CALLED GUN SHOW LOOPHOLE.
THE UNLINED LOOPHOLE.
WHAT'S NOW CALLED THE CHARLESTON
LOOPHOLE.
A LOT OF THE GUNS THAT ARE USED
FOR THE KIND OF RANDOM GUN
VIOLENCE THAT WE SEE TOO MUCH OF
IN SO MANY COMMUNITIES ARE
OBTAINED ILLEGALLY.
THEY ARE OBTAINED FROM SELLERS
WHO DON'T REALLY CARE WHERE THE
GUNS END UP OR WHAT THEY'RE USED
FOR.
AND WE'VE GOT TO CRACK DOWN ON
THE MAKERS AND SELLERS OF GUNS.
THEY SHOULD BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE
FOR THE USE OF THEIR PRODUCTS
AND EXERCISE MORE CARE AS TO HOW
THEY END UP IN THE HANDS OF THE
PEOPLE WHO USE THEM.
WE HAVE TO END WITH THIS
TERRIBLE LAW THAT WAS PASSED
WHEN I WAS IN THE SENATE.
I VOTED AGAINST IT AND MY
OPPONENT VOTED FOR IT, WHICH
GAVE IMMUNITY FROM LIABILITY TO
GUN MAKERS AND SELLERS.
RIGHT NOW THE PARENTS OF THE
SANDY HOOK VICTIMS ARE TRYING TO
SUE THE GUN MAKER AND SELLER.
AS MUCH AS ANYTHING TO TRY TO DO
WHATEVER THEY CAN TO TURN THEIR
GRIEF INTO ACTION AND PREVENT
OTHER FAMILIES FROM EXPERIENCING
THE HORROR OF WHAT THEY WENT
THROUGH.
WE HAVE WITH US TONIGHT SOME OF
THE MOTHERS OF THE MOVEMENT,
MOTHERS WHO HAVE LOST THEIR
CHILDREN TO VIOLENCE, TO POLICE
VIOLENCE AND TO SENSELESS GUN
VIOLENCE.
AND I'VE GOTTEN TO KNOW AND JUST
ADMIRE THESE WOMEN SO MUCH, AND
WHEN YOU HEAR THEIR STORIES OR
WHEN YOU HEAR THE STORIES LIKE
YOU JUST TOLD US ABOUT CHILDREN
BEING KILLED, YOU JUST CRY OUT
AND SAY, WHAT ARE WE DOING AS A
COUNTRY?
AND I BELIEVE WHAT I AM
PROPOSING IS COMMON SENSE.
I AGREE WITH WHAT THE PRESIDENT
IS TRYING TO DO.
AND THE OBSTACLE IS THE GUN
LOBBY.
AND THE GUN LOBBY EXISTS FOR THE
PURPOSE OF SCARING AND
INTIMIDATING PEOPLE INTO DOING
WHAT THEY WANT DONE.
SO WE'VE GOT TO FIGURE OUT HOW
WE COME TOGETHER TO TRY TO TAKE
THIS ON.
AND, YOU KNOW, MAYBE I'VE
JUST -- I'VE JUST MET TOO MANY
FAMILIES NOW WHO HAVE LOST LOVED
ONES TO GUN VIOLENCE.
AND SOME OF THE BIG MASS
SHOOTINGS LITERALLY FROM
COLUMBINE TO SANDY HOOK TO
AURORA IN COLORADO, JUST THE
LIST GOES ON.
THE NINE VICTIMS IN MOTHER
EMMANUEL MURDERED BY A YOUNG MAN
THEY WELCOMED INTO THEIR BIBLE
STUDY AND HE WAS SO DRIVEN BY
HATRED AND RACISM HE SAT THERE,
LISTENED TO THE SCRIPTURE AND
THEN PULLED OUT THE GUN.
HE SHOULD NOT HAVE BEEN ABLE TO
GET EXCEPT FOR ONE OF THE
LOOPHOLES AND MURDERED THOSE
NINE FAITHFUL PEOPLE.
I'M GOING TO TAKE THEM ON.
I DON'T KNOW HOW MUCH WE CAN GET
DONE, BUT I AM SICK AND TIRED OF
THESE MURDERS AND KILLINGS AND
RANDOM HORRIBLE INCIDENTS OF GUN
VIOLENCE.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I NEED TO
PICK UP ON SOMETHING SHE SAID.
SHE MENTIONED POVERTY.
WHEN WE THINK ABOUT POVERTY IN
THIS COUNTRY, BASED UPON WHAT
MEDIA DOES, PEOPLE THINK THE
FACE OF POVERTY IS
AFRICAN-AMERICAN.
THERE ARE A LOT OF BROKE WHITE
FOLKS IN AMERICA.
>> 100% RIGHT.
>> BROKE IS BROKE.
>> THAT'S RIGHT.
>> MAKE THE CASE TO POOR WHITES
WHO LIVE IN TENNESSEE,
MISSISSIPPI, ALABAMA WHO VOTE
REPUBLICAN WHY THEY SHOULD VOTE
FOR YOU BASED UPON ECONOMIC
POLICIES VERSUS VOTING FOR A
REPUBLICAN.
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I WAS
HAPPY TO CARRY THOSE STATES YOU
MENTIONED, AND I CARRIED THE
WHITE VOTE IN THOSE STATES, TOO.
THAT VOTED DEMOCRATIC.
I DON'T WANT TO GET CARRIED AWAY
HERE.
LOOK, WE HAVE SERIOUS ECONOMIC
PROBLEMS IN MANY PARTS OF OUR
COUNTRY.
AND ROLAND'S ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
INSTEAD OF DIVIDING PEOPLE THE
WAY DONALD TRUMP DOES, LET'S
REUNITE AROUND POLICIES THAT
WILL BRING JOBS AND
OPPORTUNITIES TO ALL THESE
UNDERSERVED POOR COMMUNITIES.
SO FOR EXAMPLE, I'M THE ONLY
CANDIDATE WHICH HAS A POLICY
ABOUT HOW TO BRING ECONOMIC
OPPORTUNITY USING CLEAN
RENEWABLE ENERGY AS THE KEY INTO
COAL COUNTRY.
BECAUSE WE'RE GOING TO PUT A LOT
OF COAL MINERS AND COAL
COMPANIES OUT OF BUSINESS.
RIGHT, TIM?
AND WE'RE GOING TO MAKE IT CLEAR
THAT WE DON'T WANT TO FORGET
THOSE PEOPLE.
THOSE PEOPLE LABORED IN THOSE
MINES FOR GENERATIONS, LOSING
THEIR HEALTH, OFTEN LOSING THEIR
LIVES TO TURN ON OUR LIGHTS AND
POWER OUR FACTORIES.
NOW WE'VE GOT TO MOVE AWAY FROM
COAL AND ALL THE OTHER FOSSIL
FUELS, BUT I DON'T WANT TO MOVE
AWAY FROM THE PEOPLE WHO DID THE
BEST THEY COULD TO PRODUCE THE
ENERGY THAT WE RELIED ON.
SO WHETHER IT'S COAL COUNTRY OR
INDIAN COUNTRY OR POOR URBAN
AREAS, THERE IS A LOT OF POVERTY
IN AMERICA.
WE HAVE GONE BACKWARDS.
WE WERE MOVING IN THE RIGHT
DIRECTION.
IN THE '90s MORE PEOPLE WERE
LIFTED OUT OF POVERTY AT ANY
TIME IN RECENT HISTORY BECAUSE
OF THE TERRIBLE ECONOMIC
POLICIES OF THE BUSH
ADMINISTRATION.
PRESIDENT OBAMA WAS LEFT WITH
THE WORST FINANCIAL CRISIS SINCE
THE GREAT DEPRESSION, AND PEOPLE
FELL BACK INTO POVERTY BECAUSE
THEY LOST JOBS, THEY LOST HOMES,
THEY LOST OPPORTUNITIES AND
HOPE.
SO I AM PASSIONATE ABOUT THIS,
WHICH IS WHY I HAVE PUT FORWARD
SPECIFIC PLANS ABOUT HOW WE
INCENTIVIZE MORE JOBS, MORE
INVESTMENT IN POOR COMMUNITIES
AND PUT PEOPLE TO WORK.
>> GOT TO GO TO A COMMERCIAL.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
FINAL QUESTION WITH SECRETARY
HILLARY CLINTON AFTER THIS SHORT
BREAK.
>>> WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE HERE WITH SECRETARY
HILLARY CLINTON FOR SOME FINAL
QUESTIONS AS THE VOTERS OF THE
STATE GET TO KNOW YOU.
THEY'VE PROBABLY KNOWN YOU FOR A
WHILE NOW, BUT THERE ARE SOME
QUESTIONS.
YOU SAID AT THE DEBATE EARLIER
THIS WEEK THAT YOU'RE NOT A
NATURAL POLITICIAN LIKE YOUR
HUSBAND OR PRESIDENT OBAMA.
YOU HAVE TO DO JUST THE BEST
THAT YOU CAN.
WHAT DO YOU MEAN BY THAT?
WHAT DO YOU WISH YOU WERE BETTER
AT AS A POLITICIAN?
>> I GUESS WHAT I REALLY MEAN BY
THAT IS THAT A LOT OF THE -- A
LOT OF THE WORK THAT GOES INTO A
CAMPAIGN AND A LOT OF THE, YOU
KNOW, DEMANDS THAT YOU ARE FACED
WITH IN A CAMPAIGN I THINK ARE
CHALLENGING.
AND I HAVE WORKED AT IT, TRIED
TO GET BETTER AT IT, BUT I'M
MUCH BETTER WHEN I ACTUALLY HAVE
A JOB TO DO RATHER THAN TRYING
TO GET THE JOB.
YOU KNOW?
I DON'T WANT TO BE HIRED TO
BE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- A CONSTANT CANDIDATE.
I WANT TO BE HIRED TO BE THE
PRESIDENT BECAUSE I THINK THAT
I, AT THIS MOMENT IN OUR
COUNTRY'S HISTORY, BRING THE
COMBINATION OF SKILLS AND
UNDERSTANDING AND EXPERIENCE
THAT CAN REALLY BE PUT TO WORK
IMMEDIATELY TO DO ALL PARTS OF
THE JOB.
BUT YOU KNOW, LOOK, I WATCHED MY
HUSBAND CAMPAIGN.
I WATCHED PRESIDENT OBAMA
CAMPAIGN.
IT IS POETRY.
I MEAN, IT IS JUST -- I MEAN, I
GET CARRIED AWAY AND I'VE SEEN
THEM A MILLION TIMES.
YOU KNOW?
I GO, OH, MY GOSH, YOU KNOW?
BOTH OF THEM.
THAT'S NOT NECESSARILY MY FORTE,
BUT I THINK WHAT I HAVE ALWAYS
BEEN ABLE TO DO IS TO REALLY
PRODUCE RESULTS IN EVERY JOB
THAT I'VE HAD.
YOU KNOW, ONE OF THE FUNNY
THINGS, JAKE, AND IT GOES BACK
TO THE QUESTION THE DOCTOR
ASKED, I HAVE A WHOLE ARCHIVE OF
NICE THINGS REPUBLICANS HAVE
SAID ABOUT ME INCLUDING DONALD
TRUMP AND IT'S ABOUT WORKING
WITH ME.
IT'S ABOUT COMING TOGETHER TO
FIND COMMON GROUND.
AND SO WHEN I START RUNNING FOR
SOMETHING, YOU KNOW, THEY
IMMEDIATELY START ATTACKING ME,
BUT THE WORK, YOU KNOW, WHETHER
IT'S SENATOR, SECRETARY OF STATE
OR EVEN FIRST LADY, I REALLY
LOVE THE WORK.
I LOVE TRYING TO HELP PEOPLE.
I WAS RAISED TO BELIEVE YOU DO
ALL THE GOOD YOU CAN TO ALL THE
PEOPLE YOU CAN FOR AS LONG AS
YOU CAN.
AND THAT IS HOW I FEEL I AM
REALLY TRYING TO APPROACH, YOU
KNOW, RUNNING FOR AND HOPEFULLY
BEING ELECTED PRESIDENT.
>> THAT'S ALL THE TIME WE HAVE,
MADAM SECRETARY.
THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> THANK YOU.
>> APPRECIATE IT.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
>> OUR THANKS TO THE CANDIDATES
AND MEMBERS OF THE AUDIENCE FOR
THE GREAT, GREAT QUESTIONS.
THANKS ALSO TO THE OHIO STATE
UNIVERSITY AND ROLAND MARTIN OF
TVONE.
>> FOLKS, TUNE IN TOMORROW ON TV
ONE, 7:00 TO 9:00 A.M., I'LL
HAVE A TWO-HOUR SPECIAL, NEWS
ONE NOW FROM THE CAMPUS OF OHIO
STATE WHERE WE'RE GOING TO BRING
THE FUNK TV ONE STYLE.
>> JUST TWO DAYS FROM NOW
ANOTHER SUPER TUESDAY WITH FIVE
STATES INCLUDING THIS ONE
HOLDING PRIMARIES.
WE'LL HAVE ALL-DAY COVERAGE ON
CNN.
RIGHT NOW THE BRAND-NEW CNN
SERIES ABOUT GREAT PRESIDENTIAL
RACES.
>> VOTE, VOTE, VOTE!