>>> IT'S DEBATE NIGHT FOR THE
REPUBLICANS AND WE'RE JUST
MOMENTS AWAY FROM THE MAIN
EVENT.
>> RIGHT NOW THE ROAD TO THE
WHITE HOUSE LEADS STRAIGHT
THROUGH LAS VEGAS.
AND THE RACE IS TAKING A
CRITICAL TURN WITH TERROR FEARS
FRONT AND CENTER.
>> WE ARE AT WAR WITH TERRORISTS
AND WE WILL WIN THAT WAR.
>> IF YOU GO AND JOIN ISIS,
YOU'RE SIGNING YOUR DEATH
WARRANT.
>> I DON'T CARE.
>> TONIGHT, THE TOP REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES IN A PRIMETIME DEBATE
IN A CAMPAIGN JOLTED BY THE
ATTACKS IN SAN BERNARDINO AND
PARIS.
>> ISIS HAS RAISED ITS UGLY
HEAD, AGAIN.
>> DONALD TRUMP STILL ON TOP
GOING TO NEW LENGTHS TO SHOW
HE'D BE TOUGH ON TERROR.
>> A TOTAL AND COMPLETE SHUTDOWN
OF MUSLIMS ENTERING THE UNITED
STATES.
WE HAVE NO CHOICE.
>> TED CRUZ AND MARCO RUBIO.
TO BE THE GOP'S CHOICE IF THE
FRONTRUNNER FALLS.
>> WE'RE SEEING THE EVIL OFAT
HOME.
>> BEN CARSON TRYING TO BOUNCE
BACK.
WARNING THAT AMERICA CAN'T FIGHT
A POLITICALLY CORRECT WAR
AGAINST ISIS.
>> YOU STRANGLE THEM.
ANYTHING THAT LOOKS LIKE A
MILITARY VEHICLE, IT'S GONE.
>> JEB BUSH AND CHRIS CHRISTIE
ZEROING IN ON NATIONAL SECURITY.
ARGUING THAT EXPERIENCE MATTERS
IN DANGEROUS TIMES.
>> WE'RE IN THE MIDST OF THE
NEXT WORLD WAR.
>> IT'S NOT ABOUT THE BIG
PERSONALITIES ON THE STAGE.
IT'S ABOUT LEADERSHIP.
>> THE REST OF THE FIELD LOOKING
FOR A BREAKOUT MOMENT.
SLAMMING PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
POLICIES AND USING THEM AGAINST
HILLARY CLINTON.
>> MRS. CLINTON IS ACCOUNTABLE
FOR WHAT IS GOING ON WITH ISIS
AS PRESIDENT OBAMA.
>> WE WATCH DEMOCRATS SO MANY
CRAZY IDEAS.
>> WE'VE COME TO TAKE OUR
COUNTRY BACK.
>> NOW THE STAGE IS SET FOR THE
FINAL REPUBLICAN DEBATE THIS
YEAR.
>> THIS IS NOT A GAME OF RISK.
>> WE ARE DEALING WITH PEOPLE
WHO HAVE A THIRST FOR INNOCENT
BLOOD.
>> WE'RE GOING TO BOMB THE YOU
KNOW WHAT OUT OF THEM.
>> THE FIRST REAL VOTES ARE JUST
WEEKS AWAY.
>> PEOPLE ARE STARTING TO PAY
ATTENTION AND GETTING CLOSER TO
MAKE A DECISION.
>> WE CAN'T AFFORD TO BE SO
NICE, FOLKS.
>> AND AMERICA'S SECURITY IS AT
STAKE.
>>> WELCOME TO THE CNN FACEBOOK
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
HERE AT THE VENETIAN LAS VEGAS.
WE HAVE A VERY ENTHUSIASTIC
AUDIENCE.
EVERYONE IS HERE AND THEY'RE
LOOKING FORWARD TO A SERIOUS AND
SPIRITED DISCUSSION ABOUT THE
SECURITY OF THIS NATION.
I'M WOLF BLITZER, YOUR MODERATOR
TONIGHT.
THIS DEBATE IS AIRING ON CNN
NETWORKS HERE IN THE UNITED
STATES AND AROUND THE WORLD AND
ON THE SALEM RADIO NETWORK.
THE NINE LEADING CANDIDATES.
THEY ARE HERE.
LET'S WELCOME THEM RIGHT NOW.
SENATOR RAND PAUL OF KENTUCKY.
NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR, CHRIS
CHRISTIE.
FORMER FLORIDA GOVERNOR, JEB
BUSH.
SENATOR TED CRUZ OF TEXAS.
BUSINESSMAN AND REAL ESTATE
DEVELOPER, DONALD TRUMP.
RETIRED NEURO SURGEON, DR. BEN
CARSON.
SENATOR MARCO RUBIO OF FLORIDA.
FORMER HEWLETT-PACKARD CEO CARLY
FIORINA.
AND OHIO GOVERNOR, JOHN KASICH.
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, WELCOME
THESE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES FOR
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
THIS IS THE FINAL REPUBLICAN
DEBATE BEFORE THE ELECTION YEAR
BEGINS.
AND WE'RE TAKING A MOMENT FOR
THE PHOTOGRAPHS OF THE
CANDIDATES TOGETHER ON THIS
STAGE.
NOW, EVERYONE, PLEASE RISE FOR
THE NATIONAL ANTHEM SUNG BY ALA
BROWN.
O SAY, CAN YOU SEE
BY THE DAWN'S EARLY LIGHT
WHAT SO PROUDLY WE HAILED
AT THE TWILIGHT'S
LAST GLEAMING?
WHOSE BROAD STRIPES
AND BRIGHT STARS
THROUGH THE PERILOUS FIGHT
O'ER THE RAMPARTS
WE WATCHED
WERE SO GALLANTLY
STREAMING?
AND THE ROCKETS'
RED GLARE
THE BOMBS BURSTING
IN AIR
GAVE PROOF
THROUGH THE NIGHT
THAT OUR FLAG
WAS STILL THERE
OH, SAY, DOES THAT
STAR-SPANGLED BANNER
YET WAVE
O'ER THE LAND
OF THE FREE
AND THE HOME
OF THE BRAVE?
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>>> I KNOW EVERYONE IS EAGER TO
GET STARTED.
SO, CANDIDATES, PLEASE TAKE YOUR
PLACES WHILE I EXPLAIN THE
GROUND RULES FOR TONIGHT.
AS MODERATOR, I'LL GUIDE THE
DISCUSSION AND I'LL BE JOINED IN
THE QUESTIONING BY SALEM RADIO
NETWORK TALK SHOW HOST HUGH
HEWITT AND CNN POLITICAL DANA
BASH.
WE ASK NATIONWIDE TO SHARE THEIR
QUESTIONS FOR THE CANDIDATES.
WE TEAMED UP WITH FACEBACK TO
SEND A CAMPAIGN CAMPER ACROSS
THE COUNTRY OVER THE PAST
SEVERAL WEEKS.
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE STEPPED
INSIDE AND RECORD ED STEPPED
INSIDE AND RECORDED THEIR
QUESTIONS.
MILLIONS MORE WEIGHED IN ON
FACEBOOK.
CANDIDATES, I WILL TRY TO MAKE
SURE EACH OF YOU GET YOUR FAIR
SHARE OF QUESTIONS.
YOU'LL HAVE 1:15 TO ANSWER AND
30 SECONDS FOR FFOLLOW-UPS AND
REBUTLES.
I'LL GIVE YOU TIME TO RESPOND IF
YOU'RE SINGLED OUT FOR
CRITICISM.
OUR VIEWERS SHOULD KNOW WE HAVE
TIMING LIGHTS THAT ARE VISIBLE
TO THE CANDIDATES TO WARN THEM
WHEN THEIR TIME IS UP.
AND AS THE CANDIDATES'
REQUESTED, A BELL WILL SOUND
LIKE THIS.
WE KNOW YOU ARE ALL EAGER TO
JUMP IN AND DEBATE THESE
IMPORTANT ISSUES.
SO, PLEASE, WAIT UNTIL YOU'RE
CALLED ON.
THESE NINE REPUBLICANS ARE
POSITIONED ON STAGE BASED ON
THEIR RANKING IN THE RECENT
POLLS, SO, LET'S BEGIN RIGHT
NOW.
I'D LIKE TO INVITE EACH
CANDIDATE TO INTRODUCE HIMSELF
OR HERSELF TO OUR AUDIENCE.
YOU'LL HAVE ONE MINUTE.
FIRST TO YOU, SENATOR PAUL.
>> THE QUESTION IS, HOW DAWE
KDO
WE KEEP AMERICA SAFE?
THE QUESTION IS, WHAT DOES HE
MEAN BY THAT?
LIKE THEY DO IN NORTH KOREA?
LIKE THEY DO IN CHINA?
RUBIO SAYS WE SHOULD COLLECT ALL
AMERICANS' RECORDS ALL OF THE
TIME.
THE CONSTITUTION SAYS OTHERWISE.
I THINK THEY'RE BOTH WRONG.
I THINK WE DEFEAT TERRORISM BY
SHOWING THEM THAT WE DO NOT FEAR
THEM.
I THINK IF WE BAN CERTAIN
RELIGIONS, IF WE SENSOR THE
INTERNET, I THINK THAT AT THAT
POINT THE TERRORISTS WILL HAVE
WON.
REGIME CHANGE HASN'T WON.
TOPPLING SECULAR DICTATORS IN
THE MIDDLE EAST HAS ONLY LED TO
CHAOS AND THE RISE OF RADICAL
ISLAM.
I THINK IF WE WANT TO DEFEAT
TERRORISM, I THINK IF WE TRULY
ARE SINCERE ABOUT DEFEATING
TERRORISM, WE NEED TO QUIT
ARMING THE ALLIES OF ISIS.
IF WE WANT TO DEFEAT TERRORISM,
THE BOOTS ON THE GROUND.
THE BOOTS ON THE GROUND NEED TO
BE ARAB BOOTS ON THE GROUND.
AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF I WILL DO
WHATEVER IT TAKES TO DEFEND
AMERICA.
BUT IN DEFENDING AMERICA, WE
CANNOT LOSE WHAT AMERICA STANDS
FOR.
TODAY IS THE BILL OF RIGHTS
ANNIVERSARY.
I HOPE WE WILL REMEMBER THAT AND
CHERISH THAT IN THE FIGHT ON
TERRORISM.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
GOVERNOR KASICH.
>> THANK YOU, WOLF.
JUST LAST WEEKEND A FRIEND ASKED
ONE OF MY DAUGHTERS, DO YOU LIKE
POLITICS?
AND MY DAUGHTER SAID, NO, I
DON'T.
AND THE REASON I DON'T LIKE IT
IS BECAUSE THERE'S TOO MUCH
FIGHTING.
TOO MUCH YELLING.
IT'S SO LOUD I DON'T LIKE IT.
I TURNED TO MY FRIEND AND I
SAID, YOU KNOW.
SHE'S REALLY ON TO SOMETHING.
WHEN WE THINK ABOUT OUR COUNTRY
AND THE BIG ISSUES, WOLF, THAT
WE FACE IN THIS COUNTRY.
CREATING JOBS, MAKING SURE
PEOPLE CAN KEEP THEIR JOBS.
THE NEED FOR RISING WAGES.
WHETHER OUR CHILDREN WHEN THEY
GRADUATE FROM COLLEGE CAN FIND A
JOB.
PROTECTING THE HOMELAND.
DESTROYING ISIS.
REBUILDING DEFENSE.
THESE ARE ALL THE THINGS THAT WE
NEED TO FOCUS ON BUT WE'LL NEVER
GET THERE IF WE'RE DIVIDED.
WE'LL NEVER GET THERE IF
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS JUST
FIGHT WITH ONE ANOTHER.
FRANKLY, WE ARE REPUBLICANS AND
THEY ARE DEMOCRATS.
BUT BEFORE ALL OF THAT, WE'RE
AMERICANS.
AND I BELIEVE WE NEED TO UNIFY
IN SO MANY WAYS TO REBUILD OUR
COUNTRY TO STRENGTHEN OUR
COUNTRY TO REBUILD OUR DEFENSE
AND FOR AMERICA TO SECURE ITS
PLACE IN THE WORLD FOR US.
FOR OUR CHILDREN.
AND FOR THE NEXT GENERATION.
THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> THANK YOU, WOLF.
AMERICA HAS BEEN BETRAYED.
WE'VE BEEN BETRAYED BY THE
LEADERSHIP THAT BARACK OBAMA AND
HILLARY CLINTON HAVE PROVIDED TO
THIS COUNTRY OVER THE LAST
NUMBER OF YEARS.
THINK ABOUT JUST WHAT'S HAPPENED
TODAY.
THE SECOND LARGEST SCHOOL
DISTRICT IN AMERICA IN LOS
ANGELES CLOSED BASED ON A
THREAT.
THINK ABOUT THE EFFECT THAT THAT
IS GOING TO HAVE ON THOSE
CHILDREN.
WHEN THEY GO BACK TO SCHOOL
TOMORROW WONDERING, FILLED WITH
ANXIETY ABOUT WHETHER THEY'RE
REALLY GOING TO BE SAFE.
THINK ABOUT THE MOTHERS WHO WILL
TAKE THOSE CHILDREN TOMORROW
MORNING TO THE BUS STOP.
WONDERING WHETHER THEIR CHILDREN
WILL ARRIVE BACK ON THAT BUS
SAFE AND SOUND.
THINK ABOUT THE FATHERS OF LOS
ANGELES WHO TOMORROW WILL HEAD
OFF TO WORK AND WONDER ABOUT THE
SAFETY OF THEIR WIVES AND THEIR
CHILDREN.
WHAT IS BARACK OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON DONE TO THIS COUNTRY
THAT THE MOST BASIC
RESPONSIBILITY OF AN
ADMINISTRATION IS TO PROTECT THE
SAFETY AND SECURITY OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
I WILL TELL YOU THIS.
I'M A FORMER FEDERAL PROSECUTOR.
I FOUGHT TERRORISTS AND WON.
WHEN WE GET BACK IN THE WHITE
HOUSE, WE WILL FIGHT TERRORISTS
AND WIN, AGAIN.
AND AMERICA WILL BE SAFE.
>> MS. FIORINA.
>> LIKE ALL OF YOU.
I'M ANGRY.
I'M ANGRY AT WHAT'S HAPPENING TO
OUR NATION.
T
AS CITIZENS, IT'S TIME TO TAKE
OUR COUNTRY BACK.
INSULTS WON'T TAKE IT BACK.
POLITICAL RHETORIC THAT PROMISES
A LOT AND DELIVERS LITTLE WON'T
TAKE IT BACK.
ALL OF OUR PROBLEMS CAN BE
SOLVED.
ALL OF OUR WOUNDS CAN BE HEALED
BY A TESTED LEADER WHO IS
WILLING TO FIGHT FOR THE
CHARACTER OF OUR NATION.
I HAVE BEEN TESTED.
I HAVE BEATEN BREAST CANCER.
I HAVE BURIED A CHILD.
I STARTED AS A SECRETARY.
I FOUGHT MY WAY TO THE TOP OF
CORPORATE AMERICA WHILE BEING
CALLED EVERY B-WORD IN THE BOOK.
I FOUGHT MY WAY INTO THIS
ELECTION.
AND ON OTO THIS DEBATE STAGE
WHILE ALL THE POLITICAL INSIDERS
AND THE PUNDITS TOLD ME IT
COULDN'T BE DONE.
I'VE BEEN TOLD NO ALL MY LIFE.
AND ALL MY LIFE I'VE REFUSED TO
ACCEPT NO AS AN ANSWER.
CITIZENS, IT IS TIME TO TAKE OUR
COUNTRY BACK FROM THE POLITICAL
CLASS.
FROM THE MEDIA.
FROM THE LIBERAL ELITES.
IT CAN BE DONE.
IT MUST BE DONE.
JOIN ME AND WE WILL GET IT DONE.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH.
>> OUR FREEDOM IS UNDER ATTACK.
OUR ECONOMY IS UNDER WATER.
THE LEADING DEMOCRAT IS UNDER
INVESTIGATION.
AND AMERICA IS UNDER THE GUN TO
LEAD THE FREE WORLD TO PROTECT
OUR CIVILIZED WAY OF LIFE.
SERIOUS TIMES REQUIRES STRONG
LEADERSHIP.
THAT'S WHAT IS AT STAKE RIGHT
NOW.
REGARDING NATIONAL SECURITY.
WE NEED TO REBUILD OUR MILITARY,
TO DESTROY ISIS BEFORE IT
DESTROYS US.
REGARDING ECONOMIC SECURITY, WE
NEED TO TAKE POWER AND MONEY
AWAY FROM WASHINGTON, D.C., AND
EMPOWER AMERICAN FAMILIES SO
THAT THEY CAN RISE UP, AGAIN.
LOOK, AMERICA STILL IS AN
EXCEPTIONAL COUNTRY.
WE LOVE TO LEAD.
AND WE LOVE TO WIN.
AND WE DO IT WHEN WE TAKE ON ANY
CHALLENGE AND WHEN WE TAKE ON,
WE SUPPORT OUR FRIENDS.
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL KEEP YOU IN
OUR COUNTRY SAFE, SECURE AND
FREE.
THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> THANK YOU, WOLF.
IT'S REALLY AMAZING TO BE BACK
IN LAS VEGAS.
I SPENT SIX YEARS HERE AS A
CHILD GROWING UP.
NOT FAR FROM WHERE WE STAND
TONIGHT I SAT ON THE PORCH AND
LISTENED TO MY GRANDFATHER.
ONE THING MY GRANDFATHER
INSTILLED IN ME IS I WAS REALLY
BLESSED BECAUSE I WAS A SIT
WHEREIN OF THE GREATEST COUNTRY
OF ALL MANKIND.
BUT PEOPLE WHO WANTED AMERICA TO
BE MORE LIKE THE REST OF THE
WORLD.
IN 2008, ONE OF THEM WAS ELECTED
PRESIDENT OF THIS COUNTRY AND
THE RESULT HAS BEEN A DISASTER.
TODAY YOU HAVE MILLIONS OF
AMERICANS THAT FEEL LEFT OUT AND
OUT OF PLACE IN THEIR OWN
COUNTRY.
STRUGGLING TO LIVE PAYCHECK TO
PAYCHECK AND CALLED BIGOTS
BECAUSE THEY HOLD ON TO
TRADITIONAL VALUES.
AROUND THE WORLD, AMERICA'S
INFLUENCE HAS DECLINED WHILE
THIS PRESIDENT HAS DESTROYED OUR
MILITARY, OUR ALLIES NO LONGER
TRUST US AND OUR ADVERSARIES NO
LONGER RESPECT US.
THAT'S WHY THIS ELECTION IS SO
IMPORTANT.
THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT AND THAT'S WHY I'M
GOING TO ASK YOU FOR YOUR VOTE
TONIGHT.
IF YOU ELECT ME PRESIDENT, WE
WILL HAVE A PRESIDENT THAT
BELIEVES AMERICA IS THE GREATEST
COUNTRY IN THE WORLD AND WE WILL
HAVE PRA PRESIDENT THAT ACTS LI
ITIT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> THANK YOU, WOLF.
AMERICA IS AT WAR.
OUR ENEMY IS NOT VIOLENT
EXTREMISM.
IT IS NOT SOME UNNAMED BELEVANT
FORCE.
IT IS RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORIST.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO IS
UNWILLING TO OTHER ITS NAME.
THE MEN AND WOMEN ON THIS STAGE,
EVERY ONE OF US, IS BETTER
PREPARED TO KEEP THIS NATION
SAFE THAN IS BARACK OBAMA OR
HILLARY CLINTON.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO
UNDERSTANDS THE FIRST OBLIGATION
OF THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF IS TO
KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
IF I AM ELECTED PRESIDENT, WE
WILL HUNT DOWN AND KILL THE
TERRORISTS.
WE WILL UTTERLY DESTROY ISIS.
WE WILL STOP THE TERRORIST
ATTACKS BEFORE THEY OCCUR
BECAUSE WE WILL NOT BE PRISONERS
TO POLITICAL CORRECTNESS.
RATHER WE WILL SPEAK THE TRUTH.
BORDER SECURITY IS NATIONAL
SECURITY AND WE WILL NOT BE
ADMITTING JIHADISTS AS REFUGEES.
WE WILL KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
>> DR. CARSON.
>> THANK YOU, WOLF.
PLEASE JOIN ME FOR A MOMENT OF
SILENCE A
SIL
SILENCE AND REMEMBRANCE OF THE
SAN BERNARDINO VICTIMS.
THANK YOU.
YOU KNOW, OUR COUNTRY SINCE ITS
INCEPTION HAS BEEN AT WAR.
EVERY 15 OR 20 YEARS.
BUT THE WAR THAT WE ARE FIGHTING
NOW AGAINST RADICAL ISLAMIST
JI
JIHA
JIHADISTS IS ONE WE MUST WIN.
AS A NEURO SURGEON I HAD TO FACE
LIFE AND DEATH SITUATION.
I HAD TO COME UP WITH THE RIGHT
DIAGNOSIS AND RIGHT PLAN AND
EXECUTE THAT PLAN FREQUENTLY
WITH OTHER COLLEAGUES.
RIGHT NOW, THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA IS THE PATIENT.
AND THE PATIENT IS IN CRITICAL
CONDITION AND WILL NOT BE CURED
BY POLITICAL CORRECTNESS AND
WILL NOT BE CURED BY TUMIDITY.
AND I AM ASKING THE CONGRESS,
WHICH REPRESENTS THE PEOPLE, TO
DECLARE A WAR ON ISIS.
SO THAT WE CAN BEGIN THE PROCESS
OF EXCISING THAT CANDIDCER AND
BRING PEACE AND PROSPERITY BACK
TO AMERICA.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> THANK YOU.
I BEGAN THIS JOURNEY SIX MONTHS
AGO.
MY TOTAL FOCUS WAS ON BUILDING
UP OUR MILITARY, BUILDING UP OUR
STRENGTH.
BUILDING UP OUR BORDERS.
MAKING SURE THAT CHINA, JAPAN,
MEXICO BOTH AT THE BORDER AND IN
TRADE NO LONGER TAKES ADVANTAGE
OF OUR COUNTRY.
CERTAINLY WOULD NEVER HAVE MADE
THAT HORRIBLE, DISGUSTING,
ABSOLUTELY INCOMPETENT DEAL WITH
IRAN WHERE THEY GET $150
BILLION.
THEY'RE A TERRORIST NATION.
BUT I BEGAN IT TALKING ABOUT
OTHER THINGS.
AND THOSE THINGS ARE THINGS THAT
I'M VERY GOOD AT AND MAYBE
THAT'S WHY I'M CENTER STAGE.
PEOPLE SAW IT.
PEOPLE LIKED IT.
PEOPLE RESPECTED IT.
A MONTH AGO THINGS CHANGED.
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM CAME
INTO EFFECT EVEN MORE SO THAN IT
HAS BEEN IN THE PAST.
PEOPLE LIKE WHAT I SAY.
PEOPLE RESPECT WHAT I SAY.
AND WE'VE OPENED UP A VERY BIG
DISCUSSION THAT NEEDED TO BE
OPENED UP.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU.
SINCE YOU LAST DEBATED,
AMERICANS HAVE WITNESSED TERROR
ATTACKS IN PARIS AND SAN
BERNARDINO.
THE FBI DIRECTOR SAYS THE
COUNTRY NOW FACES THE GREATEST
TERROR THREAT SINCE 9/11.
YOU ALL HAVE DIFFERENT
APPROACHES TO KEEPING THE
COUNTRY SAFE.
AND THAT WILL BE THE FOCUS OF
TONIGHT'S DEBATE.
MR. TRUMP, AS YOU MENTIONED IN
YOUR OPENING STATEMENT, PART OF
YOUR STRATEGY IS TO FOCUS IN ON
AMERICA'S BORDERS.
TO KEEP THE COUNTRY SAFE, YOU
SAY YOU WANT TO TEMPORARILY BAN
NONAMERICAN MUSLIMS FROM COMING
TO THE UNITED STATES.
BAN REFUGEES FLEEING ISIS FROM
COMING HERE.
DEPORT 11 MILLION PEOPLE AND
WALL OFF AMERICA'S SOUTHERN
BORDER.
IS THE BEST WAY TO MAKE AMERICA
GREAT AGAIN TO ISOLATE IT FROM
MUCH OF THE REST OF THE WORLD?
>> WE ARE NOT TALKING ABOUT
ISOLATION.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT SECURITY.
WE'RE NOT TALKING ABOUT
RELIGION.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT SECURITY.
OUR COUNTRY IS OUT OF CONTROL.
PEOPLE ARE POURING ACROSS THE
SOUTHERN BORDER.
I WILL BUILD A WALL.
IT WILL BE A GREAT WALL.
PEOPLE WILL NOT COME IN UNLESS
THEY COME IN LEGALLY.
DRUGS WILL NOT COME THROUGH THAT
WALL.
AS FAR AS OTHER PEOPLE INTO
MIGRATION WHERE THEY'RE GOING,
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE
HAVING CELL PHONES WITH ISIS
FLAGS ON THEM.
I DON'T THINK SO, WOLF.
THEY'RE NOT COMING TO THIS
COUNTRY.
AND IF I'M PRESIDENT AND IF
OBAMA HAS BROUGHT SOME TO THIS
COUNTRY, THEY ARE LEAVING.
THEY'RE GOING.
THEY'RE GONE.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH.
YOU CALLED MR. TRUMP UNHINGED
WHEN HE PROPOSED BANNING
NONAMERICAN MUSLIMS FROM THE
UNITED STATES.
WHY IS THAT UNHINGED?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, WE NEED
TO DESTROY ISIS IN THE
CALIPHATE.
THAT SHOULD BE OUR OBJECTIVE.
THE REFUGEE ISSUE WILL BE SOLVED
IF WE DESTROY ISIS THERE.
WE CHNEED TO EMBED OUR FORCES, R
TROOPS INSIDE THE IRAQI
MILITARY.
WE NEED TO ARM DIRECTLY THE
KURDS AND ALL OF THAT HAS TO BE
DONE IN CONCERT WITH THE ARAB
NATIONS.
IF WE'RE GOING TO BAN ALL
MUSLIMS, HOW ARE WE GOING TO GET
THEM TO BE PART OF A COALITION
TO DESTROY ISIS?
THE KURDS ARE OUR STRONGEST
ALLIES.
THEY'RE MUSLIM.
LOOK, THIS IS NOT A SERIOUS
PROPOSAL.
IN FACT, IT WILL PUSH THE MUSLIM
WORLD, THE ARAB WORLD AWAY FROM
US AT A TIME WHEN WE NEED TO
REENGAGE WITH THEM TO BE ABLE TO
CREATE A STRATEGY TO DESTROY
ISIS.
SO, DONALD, YOU KNOW, IS GREAT
AT THE ONE LINERS.
BUT HE'S A CHAOS CANDIDATE.
AND HE'D BE A CHAOS PRESIDENT.
HE WOULD NOT BE THE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF WE NEED TO KEEP OUR
COUNTRY SAFE.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> JEB DOESN'T REALLY BELIEVE
I'M UNHINGED.
HE SAID THAT VERY SIMPLY BECAUSE
HE HAS FAILED IN THIS CAMPAIGN.
IT'S BEEN A TOTAL DISASTER.
NOBODY CARES.
AND, FRANKLY, I'M THE MOST SOLID
PERSON UP HERE.
I BUILT A TREMENDOUS COMPANY AND
ALL I WANT TO DO IS MAKE AMERICA
GREAT, AGAIN.
I DON'T WANT OUR COUNTRY TO BE
TAKEN AWAY FROM US AND THAT'S
WHAT'S HAPPENING.
THE POLICIES THAT WE'VE SUFFERED
UNDER OTHER PRESIDENTS HAVE BEEN
A DISASTER FOR OUR COUNTRY.
WE WANT TO MAKE AMERICA GREAT
AGAIN.
AND, JEB, IN ALL FAIRNESS, HE
DOESN'T BELIEVE THAT.
>> LOOK, HE MENTIONED ME.
I CAN TALK.
THIS IS THE PROBLEM.
BANNING ALL MUSLIMS WILL MAKE IT
HARDER FOR US TO DO EXACTLY WHAT
WE NEED TO DO.
WHICH IS TO DESTROY ISIS.
WE NEED A STRATEGY.
WE NEED TO GET THE LAWYERS OF
THE BACK OF THE WAR FIGHTERS.
RIGHT NOW UNDER PRESIDENT OBAMA
WE'VE CREATED THIS STANDARD THAT
IS SO HIGH THAT IT'S IMPOSSIBLE
TO BE SUCCESS FUL IN FIGHTING
ISIS.
WE NEED TO ENGAGE WITH THE ARAB
WORLD TO MAKE THIS HAPPEN.
IT IS NOT A SERIOUS PROPOSAL TO
SAY THAT TO THE PEOPLE THAT
YOU'RE ASKING TO SUPPORT, FOR
THEIR SUPPORT THAT THEY CAN'T
EVEN COME TO THE COUNTRY TO EVEN
ENGAGE IN A DIALOGUE WITH US.
THAT'S NOT A SERIOUS PROPOSAL.
WE NEED A SERIOUS LEADER TO DEAL
WITH THIS.
I BELIEVE I'M THAT GUY.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
I'M GOING TO GO TO SENATOR
RUBIO, AGAIN, HIS THOUGHTS.
YOU HAVE SAID THAT BANNING
MUSLIMS IS UNCONSTITUTIONAL.
BUT ACCORDING TO A RECENT ABC
NEWS/"WASHINGTON POST" POLL A
MAJORITY OF AMERICANS SUPPORT
MR. TRUMP'S IDEA.
>> THIS PRESIDENT HASN'T KEPT US
SAFE.
WE HAD AN ATTACK IN SAN
BERNARDINO AND WE WERE PAYING
ATTENTION TO THE MOST IMPORTANT
ISSUE WE HAD IN THIS COUNTRY
SINCE 9/11 AND ALL THIS TALK
ABOUT THE PROPOSAL THAT ISN'T
GOING TO HAPPEN.
WE MUST DEAL WITH THIS THREAT OF
RADICAL ISLAMISTS, ESPECIALLY
FROM ISIS.
THE MOST SOPHISTICATED TERROR
GROUP THAT HAS THREATENED THE
WORLD OR THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
THEY'RE ACTIVELY RECRUITING
AMERICANS.
BORN AND RAISED IN THIS COUNTRY,
HE WAS A HEALTH INSPECTOR.
HAD A NEWBORN CHILD AND LEFT ALL
THAT BEHIND TO KILL 14 PEOPLE.
WE ALSO UNDERSTAND THAT THIS IS
A GROUP THAT IS GROWING IN ITS
GOVERNANCE OF TERRITORY.
NOT JUST IRAQ AND SYRIA.
THEY ARE NOW A PREDOMINANT GROUP
IN LIBYA.
BEGINNING TO POP UP IN
AFGHANISTAN AND INCREASINGLY
INVOLVED IN ATTACKS IN YEMEN AND
JORDAN IN ITS SIGHTS.
THIS GROUP NEEDS TO BE
CONFRONTED AND THE PRESIDENT HAS
LEFT US UNSAFE.
HE SPOKE THE OTHER NIGHT TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE TO REASSURE US.
I WISH HE HADN'T SPOKEN AT ALL.
HE MADE THINGS WORSE BECAUSE
WHAT HE BASICALLY SAID WAS WE'RE
GOING TO KEEP DOING WHAT WE'RE
DOING NOW AND WHAT WE ARE DOING
NOW IS NOT WORKING.
>> HUGH HEWITT, YOU HAVE A
QUESTION.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU'VE SAID YOU
DISAGREE WITH MR. TRUMP'S
POLICY.
I DON'T WANT TO CAGE MATCH, BUT
REPUBLICAN PRIMARY VOTERS
DESERVE TO KNOW.
WITH THE KIND OF SPECIFICITY
THAT YOU DELIVERED IN YOUR NINE
SUPREME COURT ARGUMENTS HOW YOU
DISAGREE WITH MR. TRUMP.
WOULD YOU SPELL THAT OUT WITH
US?
>> WELL, LISTEN, HUGH, EVERYONE
UNDERSTANDS WHY DONALD HAS
SUGGESTED WHAT HE HAS.
WE'RE LOOKING AT A PRESIDENT
WHO'S ENGAGED IN THIS DOUBLE
SPEAK.
WHERE HE DOESN'T CALL RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM BY ITS NAME.
INDEED, HE GIVES A SPEECH AFTER
THE SAN BERNARDINO ATTACK WHERE
HIS APPROACH IS TO TRY TO GO
AFTER THE CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS
OF LAW ABIDING CITIZENS, RATHER
THAN TO KEEP US SAFE.
EVEN WORSE, PRESIDENT OBAMA AND
HILLARY CLINTON ARE PROPOSING
BRINGING TENS OF THOUSANDS OF
SYRIAN REFUGEES TO THIS COUNTRY
WHEN THE HEAD OF THE FBI HAS
TOLD CONGRESS THEY CANNOT VET
THOSE REFUGEES.
I UNDERSTAND WHY DONALD MADE
THAT PROPOSAL. INTRODUCED IN TH
WHAT MY LEGISLATION WOULD DO IS
SUSPEND ALL REFUGEES FOR THREE
YEARS FROM COUNTRIES WHERE ISIS
OR AL QAEDA CONTROLS SUBSTANTIAL
TERRITORY.
>> SO, YOU'RE SAYING YOU
DISAGREE BECAUSE HE'S TOO BROAD
AND YOU HAVE MORE NARROWER
FOCUS.
WHY DO YOU DISAGREE WITH HIM?
>> I'M REMINDED OF WHAT FDR'S
GRANDFATHER SAID.
HE SAID ALL HORSE THIEVES ARE
DEMOCRATS.
BUT NOT ALL DEMOCRATS ARE HORSE
THIEVES.
IN THIS INSTANCE, THERE ARE
MILLIONS OF PEACEFUL MUSLIMS
ACROSS THE WORLD IN COUNTRIES
LIKE INDIA WHERE THERE IS NOT
THE PROBLEMS WE ARE SEEING IN
NATIONS THAT ARE CONTROLLED.
HAVE TERRITORY CONTROLLED BY AL
QAEDA OR ISIS AND WE SHOULD
DIRECT AT THE PROBLEM, FOCUS ON
THE PROBLEM AND DEFEAT RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
IT'S NOT A WAR ON A FAITH.
IT'S A WAR ON A POLITICAL
IDEOLOGY THAT SEEKS TO MURDER
US.
>> CARLY FIORINA, THIS IS THE
CHRISTMAS DINNER DEBATE.
THIS WILL BE THE DEBATE THAT
AMERICANS TALK ABOUT AT
CHRISTMAS.
THUS FAR IN THE FIRST TEN
MINUTES, WE HAVEN'T HEARD A LOT
ABOUT RONALD REAGAN'S SITTING ON
A HILL.
BUT HEARD A LOT OF KEEPING
AMERICANS SAFE AND EVERYONE ELSE
OUT.
IS THIS WHAT YOU WANT THE PARTY
TO STAND FOR?
>> WHAT I THINK WE NEED TO STAND
FOR ARE SOLUTIONS.
I OFFER MYSELF AS A LEADER TO
THE PEOPLE OF THIS COUNTRY
BECAUSE I THINK THEY'RE LOOKING
FOR SOLUTIONS.
NOT LAWYERS ARGUING OVER LAWS.
OR ENTERTAINERS THROWING OUT
SOUND BITES THAT DRAW MEDIA
ATTENTION.
WE NEED TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM.
TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM, WE NEED TO
DO SOMETHING HERE AT HOME.
AND SOMETHING OVER THERE IN
THEIR CALIPHATE.
WE NEED TO DENY THEM TERRITORY.
HERE AT HOME WE NEED TO DO TWO
FUNDAMENTAL THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, WE NEED TO RECOGNIZE
THAT TECHNOLOGY HAS MOVED ON.
THE PATRIOT ACT WAS SIGNED IN
2001, ROUGHLY.
THE iPHONE WAS INVENTED IN 2007.
THE iPAD WAS INVENTED IN 2011.
SNAPCHAT AND TWITTER AND ALL THE
REST OF IT HAVE BEEN AROUND JUST
FOR SEVERAL YEARS.
TECHNOLOGY HAS MOVED ON AND THE
TERRORISTS HAVE MOVED ON WITH
IT.
LET ME TELL YOU A STORY.
SOON AFTER 9/11 I GOT A PHONE
CALL FROM THE NSA.
THEY NEEDED HELP.
I GAVE THEM HELP.
I STOPPED A TRUCK LOAD OF
EQUIPMENT AND I HAD IT TURNED
AROUND.
IT WAS ESCORTED BY THE NSA INTO
HEADQUARTERS.
WE NEED THE PRIVATE SECTOR'S
HELP BECAUSE GOVERNMENT IS NOT
INOVATING.
TECHNOLOGY IS RUNNING AHEAD BY
LEAPS AND BOUND.
THE PRIVATE SECTOR WILL HELP,
JUST AS I HELPED AFTER 9/11.
THEY MUST BE ENGAGED AND THEY
MUST BE ASKED.
I WILL ASK THEM.
I KNOW THEM.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, AMERICANS
ARE CLEARLY MORE AFRAID TODAY
THAN AT ANY TIME SINCE 9/11.
AS YOU MENTIONED IN YOUR OPENING
STATEMENT TODAY IN LOS ANGELES,
650 SCHOOL CHILDREN DIDN'T GO TO
650,000 SCHOOL CHILDREN DIDN'T
GO TO SCHOOL BECAUSE OF AN
E-MAIL THREAT.
THIS, TWO WEEKS AFTER AN ATTACK
KILLED 14 PEOPLE IN SAN
BERNARDINO.
IS THIS THE NEW NORMAL?
AND, IF SO, WHAT STEPS WOULD YOU
TAKE AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES TO ENSURE THAT FEAR DOES
NOT PARALYZE AMERICA?
>> WOLF, UNFORTUNATELY, IT'S THE
NEW NORMAL UNDER BARACK OBAMA
AND HILLARY CLINTON.
THE FACT IS THAT IF YOU LISTEN
TO HILLARY CLINTON THE OTHER
DAY, WHAT SHE SAID TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE WAS, THAT'S
REGARDS TO ISIS.
MY STRATEGY WOULD BE JUST ABOUT
THE SAME AS THE PRESIDENT'S.
JUST ABOUT THE SAME AS THE
PRESIDENT'S.
WE HAVE PEOPLE ACROSS THIS
COUNTRY WHO ARE SCARED TO DEATH.
BECAUSE I COULD TELL YOU THIS,
AS A FORMER FEDERAL PROSECUTOR,
IF A CENTER FOR THE
DEVELOPMENTALLY DISABLED AND SAN
BERNARDINO, CALIFORNIA, IS NOW A
TARGET FOR TERRORISTS, THAT
MEANS EVERYWHERE IN AMERICA IS A
TARGET FOR THESE TERRORISTS.
NOW, I SPENT SEVEN YEARS OF MY
LIFE IN THE IMMEDIATE AFTERMATH
OF SEPTEMBER 11th DOING THIS
WORK.
WORKING WITH THE PATRIOT ACT.
WORKING WITH OUR LAW
ENFORCEMENT.
WORKING WITH THE SURVEILLANCE
COMMUNITY TO MAKE SURE THAT WE
KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
WHAT WE NEED TO DO, WOLF, IS
RESTORE THOSE TOOLS THAT HAVE
BEEN TAKEN AWAY BY THE PRESIDENT
AND OTHERS.
RESTORE THOSE TOOLS TO THE NSA
AND LAW ENFORCEMENT COMMUNITY.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHAT
ACTIACTION
A
AND WE NEED A PRESIDENT AND A
CABINET THAT UNDERSTANDS THAT
THE FIRST AND MOST IMPORTANT
PRIORITY AS THE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES IS TO PROTECT THE
SAFETY AND SECURITY OF AMERICANS
AS SOMEONE WHO HAS DONE IT, I
WILL MAKE SURE IT GETS DONE,
AGAIN.
>> THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR KASICH.
ONE OF THE KILLERS IN SAN
BERNARDINO WAS AN AMERICAN WHO
WAS NOT ON ANYONE'S WATCH LIST.
HOW ARE YOU GOING TO FIND THAT
RADICALIZED PERSON AND STOP
ANOTHER SUCH ATTACK?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, WOLF, I
SAID LAST FEBRUARY THAT WE
NEEDED TO HAVE PEOPLE ON THE
GROUND, TROOPS ON THE GROUND IN
A COALITION SIMILAR TO WHAT WE
HAD IN THE FIRST GULF WAR.
I REMEMBER WHEN THE EGYPTIAN
AMBASSADOR TO THE UNITED STATES
STOOD IN THE ROSE GARDEN AND
PLEDGED ARAB COMMITMENT TO
REMOVING SADDAM HUSSEIN FROM
KUWAIT.
BEFORE WE CAME OUT HERE TONIGHT,
I AM TOLD THAT THE SAUDIS
ORGANIZED 34 COUNTRIES WHO WANT
TO JOIN IN THE BATTLE AGAINST
TERRORISM.
FIRST AND FOREMOST, WE NEED TO
GO AND DESTROY ISIS AND WE NEED
TO DO THIS WITH OUR ARAB FRIENDS
AND OUR FRIENDS IN EUROPE.
WHEN I SEE THEY HAVE A CLIMATE
CONFERENCE OVER IN PARIS, THEY
SHOULD HAVE BEEN TALKING ABOUT
DESTROYING ISIS BECAUSE THEY ARE
INVOLVED IN VIRTUALLY EVERY
COUNTRY, YOU KNOW, ACROSS THIS
WORLD.
NOW, YOU DESTROY ISIS IN A
COALITION AND YOU GET JOINT
INTELLIGENCE WITH OUR EUROPEAN
FRIENDS AND THEN HERE AT HOME,
THERE ARE THINGS CALLED THE
JOINT TERRORISM TASK FORCE.
HEADED BY THE FBI AND MADE UP OF
LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT, INCLUDING
STATE POLICE.
THEY NEED THE TOOLS AND THE
TOOLS INVOLVE ENCRYPTION WHERE
WE CANNOT HEAR WHAT THEY'RE EVEN
PLANNING.
WHEN WE SEE RED FLAGS, A MOTHER,
A FATHER, A NEIGHBOR THAT SAYS
WE HAVE A PROBLEM WE HAVE TO
GIVE LAW ENFORCEMENT TO LISTEN
TO STOP THESE TERRORIST ATTACKS
BEFORE THEY OCCUR.
PAY ME NOW OR PAY ME A LOT MORE
LATER.
THIS IS THE DIRECTION WE NEED TO
GO.
>> THANK YOU.
DANA BASH, YOU HAVE THE NEXT
QUESTION.
>> HOW TO BALANCE SURVEILLANCE
WITH PRIVACY AND KEEPING
AMERICANS SAFE.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU VOTED FOR A
BILL THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA SIGNED
INTO LAW JUST THIS PAST JUNE
THAT MADE IT HARDER FOR THE
GOVERNMENT TO ACCESS AMERICANS'
PHONE RECORDS.
IN LIGHT OF THE SAN BERNARDINO
ATTACK, WAS YOUR VOTE A MISTAKE?
>> WELL, DANA, THE PREMISE OF
YOUR QUESTION IS NOT ACCURATE.
I'M VERY PROUD TO HAVE JOINED
WITH CONSERVATIVES IN BOTH THE
SENATE AND THE HOUSE TO REFORM
HOW WE TARGET BAD GUYS.
AND WHAT THE USA FREEDOM ACT DID
IT DID TWO THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, IT ENDED THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT'S BULK COLLECTION OF
PHONE MEDA DATA OF MILLIONS OF
LAW-ABIDING CITIZENS.
NUMBER TWO IN THE SECOND HALF
THAT IS CRITICAL.
IT STRENGTHENED THE TOOLS OF
NATIONAL SECURITY AND LAW
ENFORCEMENT TO GO AFTER
TERRORISTS.
IT GAVE US GREATER TOOLS AND WE
ARE SEEING THOSE TOOLS WORK
RIGHT NOW IN SAN BERNARDINO.
IN PARTICULAR, WHAT IT DID IS
THE PRIOR PROGRAM ONLY COVERED A
RELATIVELY NARROW SLICE OF PHONE
CALLS.
WHEN YOU HAD A TERRORIST, YOU
COULD ONLY SEARCH A RELATIVELY
NARROW SLICE OF NUMBERS,
PRIMARILY LANDLINES.
THE USA FREEDOM ACT EXPANDS THAT
SO WE HAVE THE PHONES THAT
TERRORISTS ARE LIKELY TO USE AND
THE FOCUS OF LAW ENFORCEMENT IS
ON TARGETING THE BAD GUYS.
YOU KNOW, THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION KEEPS GETTING
WRONG IS WHENEVER ANYTHING BAD
HAPPENS THEY FOCUS ON
LAW-ABIDING CITIZENS INSTEAD OF
FOCUSING ON THE BAD GUYS.
WE NEED TO FOCUS ON RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISTS AND WE NEED
TO STOP THEM BEFORE THEY CARRY
OUT ACTS OF TERROR.
>> BIPARTISAN SUPPORT FOR THAT.
BUT YOU VOTED AGAINST IT.
SO, IS SENATOR CRUZ WRONG?
>> HE IS AND SO ARE THOSE WHO
VOTED FOR IT.
SOME THAT VOTED FOR IT BECAUSE
THEY WANTED TO KEEP IT ALIVE AND
THEY WERE AFRAID THE WHOLE
PROGRAM WOULD EXPIRE.
HERE'S THE WORLD WE LIVE IN.
AI RADICAL JIHADIST GROUP AND
RADICALIZE AMERICAN CITIZENS AND
ITS INABILITY TO EXPLOIT
LOOPHOLES IN OUR ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM AND CAPTURE
TO HOLD TERRITORY IN THE MIDDLE
EAST AND MULTIPLE COUNTRIES.
THIS IS NOT JUST THE MOST
CAPABLE, BUT THE MOST
SOPHISTICATED TERROR THREAT WE
HAVE EVER FACED.
WE ARE NOW AT A TIME WHEN WE
NEED MORE TOOLS AND NOT LESS
TOOLS.
THAT WAS A VALUABLE TOOL THAT WE
NO LONGER HAVE AT OUR DISPOSAL.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> I WOULD NOTE THAT MARCO KNOWS
WHAT
WHAT HE'S SAYING, THEY ARE
SAYING THE SAME THING.
THEY ARE KNOWINGLY FALSE AND
ATTACKS LIKE BARACK OBAMA AND
THE REASON IS SIMPLE.
WHAT HE KNOWS IS THAT THE OLD
PROGRAM COVERED 20 TO 30% OF
PHONE NUMBERS TO SEARCH FOR
TERRORISTS.
THE NEW PROGRAM COVERS NEARLY
100%.
THAT GIVES US GREATER ABILITY TO
STOP ACTS OF TERRORISM AND HE
KNOWS THAT IS THE CASE.
>> SENATOR --
>> LET ME BE VERY CAREFUL WHEN
ANSWERING THIS.
I DON'T THINK NATIONAL
TELEVISION IN FRONT OF 15
MILLION PEOPLE IS THE PLACE TO
DISCUSS PERSONAL INFORMATION.
THERE IS NOTHING WE ARE ALLOWED
TO DO UNDER THIS BILL THAT WE
COULD NOT DO BEFORE.
THIS BILL DID, HOWEVER, TAKE
AWAY A VALUABLE TOOL THAT
ALLOWED THE NATIONAL SECURITY
AGENCY AND OTHER INTELLIGENCE
AGENCIES TO QUICKLY AND RAPIDLY
ACCESS PHONE RECORDS AND MATCH
THEM UP WITH OTHER PHONE RECORDS
TO SEE WHO TERRORISTS HAVE BEEN
CALLING.
BECAUSE I PROMISE YOU THE NEXT
TIME THERE IS AN ATTACK ON THIS
COUNTRY, THE FIRST THING PEOPLE
ARE GOING TO WANT TO KNOW IS,
WHY DIDN'T WE KNOW ABOUT IT AND
WHY DIDN'T WE STOP IT?
THE ANSWER BETTER NOT BE WE
DIDN'T HAVE ACCESS TO
INFORMATION TO IDENTIFY THESE
KILLERS BEFORE THEY ATTACK.
>> SENATOR PAUL, I KNOW THIS
IS -- THIS HAS BEEN A VERY BIG
ISSUE FOR YOU.
YOU HEAR MANY OF YOUR COLLEAGUES
ARE CALLING FOR INCREASED
SURVEILLANCE BY LAW ENFORCEMENT.
YOU CALL THAT HOGWASH.
WHY IS THAT HOGWASH?
>> YOU KNOW, I THINK MARCO GETS
IT COMPLETELY WRONG.
WE ARE NOT ANY SAFER THROUGH THE
COLLECTION OF ALL AMERICANS'
RECORDS.
IN FACT, I THINK WE'RE LESS
SAFE.
WE GET SO DISTRACTED BY ALL THE
INFORMATION, WE'RE NOT SPENDING
ENOUGH TIME GETTING SPECIFIC
INFORMATION ON TERRORISTS.
THE OTHER THING IS, THE ONE
THING THAT MIGHT HAVE STOPPED
SAN BERNARDINO AND MIGHT HAVE
STOPPED 9/11, STRICTER CONTROLS
ON THOSE WHO CAME HERE.
MARCO HAS OPPOSED INCREASED
SECURITY BORDER SECURITY FOR
THOSE WHO COME TO OUR COUNTRY.
ON HIS GANG OF EIGHT BILL, HE
WOULD HAVE LEGALIZED IMMIGRATION
AND HE DID NOT AND HE
STEADFASTLY OPPOSED ANY NEW
BORDER SECURITY FOR REFUGEES OR
STUDENTS.
LAST WEEK, I INTRODUCED ANOTHER
BILL SAYING WE NEED MORE
SECURITY.
WE NEED MORE SCRUTINY.
ONCE AGAIN, MARCO OPPOSED THIS.
SO, MARCO CAN'T HAVE IT BOTH
WAYS.
HE THINKS HE WANTS TO BE THIS,
OH O, I'M GREAT AND STRONG ON
NATIONAL DEFENSE.
BUT HE'S THE WEAKEST OF ALL THE
CANDIDATES ON IMMIGRATION.
HE IS THE ONE FOR AN OPEN BORDER
THAT IS LEAVING US DEFENSELESS.
IF WE WANT TO DEFEND THE
COUNTRY, WE HAVE TO DEFEND
AGAINST THOSE COMING IN AND
MARCO HASAALLEGIANCE
THAN HE DOES TO CONSERVE POLICY.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> I WANT TO THANK RAND FOR
ANOTHER 30 SECONDS BECAUSE,
NUMBER ONE, WHAT HE'S POINTING
TO IS A BILL LAST WEEK THAT
AMENDMENT THAT HE VOTED FOR THAT
ONLY TEN PEOPLE VOTED FOR.
YOU KNOW WHY?
BECAUSE IT'S NOT FOCUSED ON
TERRORISTS.
SOMEONE FROM TAIWAN WOULD NOT
HAVE BEEN ABLE TO COME HERE AS A
TOURIST.
THIS MEDA DATA PROGRAM IS
ACTUALLY MORE STRICT THAN WHAT A
REGULAR LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCY
HAS NOW.
IF A REGULAR LAW ENFORCEMENT
AGENCY WANTS YOUR PHONE RECORDS,
ALL THEY HAVE TO DO IS ISSUE A
SUBPOENA.
NOT ABLE TO QUICKLY GATHER
RECORDS AND LOOK AT THEM TO SEE
WHO THESE TERRORISTS ARE
CALLING.
AND THE TERRORISTS THAT ATTACKED
US IN SAN BERNARDINO WAS AN
AMERICAN I BET WE WISH WE HAD
ACCESS TO FIVE YEARS OF HIS
RECORDS TO SEE WHO HE WAS
WORKING WITH.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, I'LL COME
TO YOU IN A MINUTE.
GO AHEAD, SENATOR PAUL.
>> CAN I RESPOND?
>> GO AHEAD, PLEASE.
>> MARCO STILL MISUNDERSTANDS
THE IMMIGRATION ISSUE.
WHAT I PUT FORWARD WAS AN
AMENDMENT FROM HIGH-RISK
TERRORIST COUNTRIES BUT WOULD
HAVE STARTED IT UP BUT WANTED TO
GO THROUGH GLOBAL ENTRY WHICH IS
A PROGRAM WHERE WE DO BACKGROUND
CHECKS.
EVERY TERRORIST ATTACK WE HAD
SINCE 9/11 HAS BEEN LEGAL
IMMIGRATION.
MARCO WANTS TO EXPAND THAT.
I WANT MORE RULES, MORE SCRUTINY
AND TO DEFEND THE COUNTRY YOU
HAVE TO DEFEND THE BORDER.
>> SENATOR, WE'RE GOING TO TALK
ABOUT IMMIGRATION IN A WHILE.
BUT GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, JUST
LISTENING TO THIS, LISTENING TO
THIS, YOU HEARD SENATOR PAUL,
SENATOR CRUZ TALK ABOUT HOW
IMPORTANT IT IS TO PROTECT
AMERICANS' PRIVACY, EVEN IN A
TIME OF GRAVE DANGER.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH THAT?
>> LISTEN, I WANT TO TALK TO THE
AUDIENCE AT HOME FOR A SECOND.
IF YOUR EYES ARE GLAZING OVER
LIKE MINE THIS IS WHAT IT IS
LIKE TO BE ON THE FLOOR OF THE
UNITED STATES SENATE.
ENDLESS DEBATES ABOUT HOW MANY
ANGELS ON THE HEAD OF A PIN FROM
A PERSON WHO NEVER HAD TO MAKE A
CONSEQ
CONSEQUENCEAL DECISION.
HOW TO PULL FORWARD OR PULL
BACK.
WHETHER YOU USE CERTAIN
ACTIONABLE INTELLIGENCE OR
WHETHER NOT TO.
THEY DEBATE ABOUT THIS BILL AND
THE SUBCOMMITTEE AND NOBODY IN
AMERICA CARES ABOUT THAT.
WHAT THEY CARE ABOUT.
ARE WE GOING TO HAVE A PRESIDENT
WHO KNOWS WHAT THEY'RE DOING TO
MAKE THESE DECISIONS?
FOR THE SEVEN YEARS AFTERWARDS
NEW JERSEY WAS THREATENED LIKE
NO OTHER REGION IN THIS COUNTRY
AND WHAT WE DID IS WE TOOK
ACTIONS WITHIN THE CONSTITUTION
TO MAKE SURE THAT LAW
ENFORCEMENT HAD ALL THE
INFORMATION THEY NEEDED.
WE PROSECUTED TWO OF THE BIGGEST
TERRORISM CASES IN THE WORLD AND
STOPPED FT. DIX FROM BEING
ATTACKED FROM SIX RADICALIZED
MUSLIMS FROM A MOSQUE IN NEW
JERSEY BECAUSE WE WORK WOULD THE
MUSLIM AMERICAN COMMUNITY TO GET
INTELLIGENCE.
WE USED THE PATRIOT ACT TO GET
OTHER INTELLIGENCE.
THIS IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
HAVING BEEN A FEDERAL PROSECUTOR
AND ACTUALLY DOING SOMETHING AND
JUST SPENDING YOUR LIFE AS 1 OF
100 DEBATING IT.
LET'S TALK ABOUT HOW WE DO THIS
AND NOT EACH BILL WHICH THESE
GUYS LIKE MORE.
PEOPLE DON'T CARE ABOUT THAT.
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU.
DR. CARSON.
YOU'RE IN FAVOR OF MONITORING
MOSQUES AND SCHOOLS WHERE THERE
IS ANTI-AMERICAN SENTIMENT.
WHAT DO YOU CONSIDER
ANTI-AMERICAN?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, LET ME
JUST COMPLAIN A LITTLE BIT.
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME I HAVE
SPOKEN AND SEVERAL PEOPLE HAVE
HAD MULTIPLE QUESTIONS.
SO, PLEASE TRY TO PAY ATTENTION
TO THAT.
NOW, AS FAR AS MONITORING IS
CONCERNED, WHAT MY POINT IS, WE
NEED TO MAKE SURE THAT ANY
PLACE.
I DON'T CARE WHETHER IT'S A
MOSQUE, A SCHOOL, A
SUPERINTENDENT, YOU KNOW, A
THEATER.
IT DOESN'T MATTER.
IF THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE
GETTING THERE, ENGAGING IN
RADICALIZING ACTIVITIES, THEN WE
NEED TO BE SUSPICIOUS OF IT.
WE HAVE TO GET RID OF ALL THIS
STUFF AND PEOPLE ARE WORRIED
ABOUT SOMEBODY'S GOING TO SAY
THAT I'M ISLAMAPHOBIC OR WHAT
HAVE YOU.
THIS IS CRAZINESS.
WE ARE AT WAR.
THAT'S WHY I ASK CONGRESS, GO
AHEAD AND DECLARE THE WAR.
WE NEED TO BE ON A WAR FOOTING.
WE NEED TO UNDERSTAND THAT OUR
NATION IS IN GRAVE DANGER.
YOU KNOW, WHAT THE MUSLIM
BROTHERHOOD SAID AND THE
EXPLANATORY MEMORANDUM THAT WAS
DISCOVERED DURING THE HOLYLAND
FOUNDATION TRIAL IS THAT THEY
WILL TAKE ADVANTAGE OF OUR PC
ATTITUDE TO GET US.
WE HAVE TO BE BETTER THAN THIS.
WE HAVE TO BE SMARTER THAN THEY
ARE.
>> DR. CARSON, WHO WAS RIGHT IN
THAT LITTLE DEBATE WE JUST HEARD
BETWEEN SENATOR RUBIO AND
SENATOR PAUL?
>> I THINK YOU HAVE TO ASK THEM
ABOUT THAT.
I DON'T WANT TO GET IN BETWEEN
THEM.
LET THEM FIGHT.
>> WOLF, THESE --
>> HOLD ON ONE SECOND.
WE HAVE A LOT MORE TO COME AND
EVERYONE WILL HAVE THEIR FULL
OPPORTUNITIES.
GOVERNOR BUSH, SIX DAYS AFTER
9/11, YOUR BROTHER VISITED A
MOSQUE AND SAID, "ISLAM IS
PEACE."
THE CONVERSATION TONIGHT IS
ABOUT BANNING MUSLIMS AND
SURVEILLANCE OF MOSQUES.
ARE PRESIDENT BUSH'S WORDS STILL
RELEVANT IN TODAY'S REPUBLICAN
PARTY?
>> THEY ARE RELEVANT, IF WE WANT
TO DESTROY ISIS.
IF WE WANT TO DESTROY RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
WE CAN'T DISASSOCIATE OURSELVES
FROM PEACE-LOVING MUSLIMS.
IF WE EXPECT TO DO THIS ON OUR
OWN, WE WILL FAIL.
IF WE DO IT IN UNISON WITH
PEOPLE WHO ARE ALSO AT RISK AND
THREATENED BY ISLAMIC RADICAL
TERRORISM, WE'LL BE FAR MORE
SUCCESSFUL.
LOOK, THE FBI HAS THE TOOLS
NECESSARY TO MONITOR UNAMERICAN
ACTIVITIES IN OUR COUNTRY.
IT GOES ON.
WE SHOULDN'T BE TALKING ABOUT
IT.
TO BE HONEST WITH YOU, OUT IN
THE PUBLIC.
THEY HAVE THOSE CAPABILITIES AND
WE SHOULD BE SURE WE GIVE THE
FBI AND NSA AND INTELLIGENCE
COMMUNITIES ALL THE RESOURCES
THEY NEED TO KEEP US SAFE.
BUT THE MAIN THING WE SHOULD BE
FOCUSED ON IS A STRATEGY TO
DESTROY ISIS.
I LAID OUT A PLAN AT THE REAGAN
LIBRARY BEFORE THE TRAGEDY OF
PAIRS AND BEFORE SAN BERNARDINO
TO DO JUST THAT.
IT REQUIRES LEADERSHIP.
IT'S NOT FILING ONMENDAN AMENDMD
CALLING IT SUCCESS.
DEVELOPING A STRATEGY AND
FUNDING IT AND MAKING SURE WE
HAVE A MILITARY THAT IS SECOND
TO NONE AND DOING THE JOB AND
MAKING SURE THAT WE DESTROY ISIS
THERE.
THAT'S HOW YOU KEEP AMERICA
SAFE.
>> MS. FIORINA, AS YOU POINTED
OUT, YOU WERE A CEO IN SILICON
VALLEY ON 9/11.
COMPANIES THERE SAY THEY WON'T
HELP THE FBI CRACK ENCRYPTED
FROM ISIS.
SHOULD THEY BE FORCED TO?
>> LISTENING TO THIS
CONVERSATION, LET ME JUST SAY,
WE HAVE A LOT OF ARGUMENT ABOUT
LAWS, BUT NONE OF IT SOLVES THE
PROBLEM.
LET'S EXAMINE WHAT HAPPENED.
WHY DID WE MISS THE TSARNAEV
BROTHERS?
WHY DID WE MISS THE SAN
BERNARDINO COUPLE?
IT WASN'T BECAUSE WE HAD STOPPED
COLLECTING DATA.
IT WAS BECAUSE I THINK AS
SOMEONE WHO COMES FROM THE
TECHNOLOGY WORLD, WE WERE USING
THE WRONG ALGORITHMS.
THE GOVERNMENT IS WILLFULLY
BEHIND THE TECHNOLOGY CURVE.
BUT SECONDLY, THE BUREAUCRATIC
PROCESSIES THAT HAVE BEEN IN
PLACE SINCE 9/11 ARE INADEQUATE,
AS WELL.
WHAT DO WE NOW KNOW THAT DHS
VETS PEOPLE BY GOING INTO
DATABASES OF KNOWN OR SUSCPECTE
TERRORISTS.
ISIS IS RECRUITING PEOPLE WHO
ARE NOT IN THOSE DATABASES.
SO, OF COURSE, WE'RE GOING TO
MISS THEM.
THEN WE NOW LEARN THAT DHS SAYS,
NO, WE CAN'T CHECK THEIR SOCIAL
MEDIA.
EVERY PARENT IN AMERICA IS
CHECKING SOCIAL MEDIA AND EVERY
EMPLOYER IS, AS WELL.
THE GOVERNMENT CAN'T DO IT?
THE BUREAUCRATIC PROCEDURES ARE
SO FAR BEHIND.
OUR GOVERNMENT HAS BECOME
INCOMPETENT, UNRESPONSIVE,
CORRUPT.
THAT INCOMPETENCE AND LACK OF
ACCOUNTABILITY IS NOW DANGEROUS.
IT IS WHY WE NEED A DIFFERENT
KIND OF LEADERSHIP IN THE WHITE
HOUSE THAT UNDERSTANDS HOW TO
GET BUREAUCRACIES COMPETENT,
AGAIN.
>> BUT MY QUESTION WAS, SHOULD
THESE SILICON VALLEY COMPANIES
BE FORCED TO COOPERATE WITH THE
FBI?
>> THEY DO NOT NEED TO BE
FORCED.
THEY NEED TO BE ASKED.
TO BRING THE BEST AND BRIGHTEST.
THE MOST RECENT TECHNOLOGY TO
THE TABLE.
I WAS ASKED AS A CEO.
I COMPLIED HAPPILY AND THEY
WILL, AS WELL.
BUT THEY HAVE NOT BEEN ASKED.
THAT'S WHY IT COST BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS TO BUILD AN OBAMA
WEBSITE THAT FAILED.
BECAUSE THE PRIVATE SECTOR
WASN'T ASKED.
>> MR. TRUMP.
YOU RECENTLY SUGGESTED CLOSING
THAT INTERNET UP.
THOSE WERE YOUR WORDS AS A WAY
TO STOP ISIS FROM RECRUITING
ONLINE.
ARE YOU REFERRING TO CLOSING
DOWN ACTUAL PORTIONS OF THE
INTERNET?
SOME SAY THAT WOULD PUT THE U.S.
IN LINE WITH CHINA AND NORTH
KOREA.
>> WELL, LOOK, THIS IS SO EASY
TO ANSWER.
ISIS IS RECRUITING THROUGH THE
INTERNET.
ISIS IS USING THE INTERNET
BETTER THAN WE ARE USING THE
INTERNET AND IT WAS OUR IDEA.
WHAT I WANTED TO DO IS I WANTED
TO GET OUR BRILLIANT PEOPLE FROM
SILICON VALLEY AND OTHER PLACES
AND FIGURE OUT A WAY THAT ISIS
CANNOT DO WHAT THEY'RE DOING.
YOU TALKED FREEDOM OF SPEECH.
YOU TALKED FREEDOM OF ANYTHING
YOU WANT.
I DON'T WANT THEM USING OUR
INTERNET TO TAKE OUR YOUNG
IMPRESSIONABLE YOUTH AND
WATCHING THE MEDIA TALKING ABOUT
HOW THEY'RE MASTERMINDS.
THESE ARE MASTERMINDS.
THEY SHOULDN'T BE USING THE WORD
MASTERMIND.
THESE ARE THUGS AND TERRIBLE
PEOPLE IN ISIS.
NOT MASTERMINDS.
WE HAVE TO CHANGE IT FROM EVERY
STANDPOINT.
WE SHOULD BE USING OUR BRILLIANT
PEOPLE.
OUR MOST BRILLIANT MIND TO
FIGURE A WAY THAT ISIS CANNOT
USE THE INTERNET.
AND THEN ON SECOND, WE SHOULD BE
ABLE TO PENETRATE THE INTERNET
AND FIND OUT EXACTLY WHERE ISIS
IS AND EVERYTHING ABOUT ISIS.
WE CAN DO THAT IF WE USE OUR
GOOD PEOPLE.
>> LET ME FOLLOW UP, MR. TRUMP.
SO, ARE YOU OPEN TO CLOSING
PARTS OF THE INTERNET?
>> I WOULD CERTAINLY BE OPEN TO
CLOSING AREAS WHERE WE ARE AT
WAR WITH SOMEBODY.
I SURE AS HELL DON'T WANT TO LET
PEOPLE THAT WANT TO KILL US AND
KILL OUR NATION USE OUR
INTERNET.
YES, SIR.
I AM.
>> THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR KASICH, IS SHUTTING
DOWN ANY PART OF THE INTERNET A
GOOD IDEA?
>> NO.
I DON'T THINK IT IS.
I WANT TO GO BACK TO TWO OTHER
ISSUES.
ONE IS THE DATA.
WE KNOW WE HAVE TO HOLD THIS
DATA FOR A LONGER PERIOD OF
TIME.
AND, YOU KNOW, IN A LOT OF WAYS,
CHRIS IS RIGHT.
WHAT A PRESIDENT HAS TO DO IS
STAKE A POSITION.
WE DON'T WANT TO ERR ON THE SIDE
OF HAVING LESS.
WE WANT TO ERR ON THE SIDE OF
HAVING MORE.
THAT'S GOOD FOR OUR FAMILIES.
IN ADDITION TO THAT, WOLF, THERE
IS A BIG PROBLEM.
IT'S CALLED ENCRYPTION.
AND THE PEOPLE IN SAN BERNARDINO
WERE COMMUNICATING WITH PEOPLE
WHO THE FBI HAD BEEN WATCHING
BUT BECAUSE THEIR PHONE WAS
INC
ENC
ENCRYPTED.
BECAUSE THE INTELLIGENCE
OFFICIALS COULD NOT SEE WHO THEY
WERE TALKING TO, IT WAS LOST.
WE HAVE TO SOLVE THE ENCRYPTION
PROBLEM.
IT IS NOT EASY.
A PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, AGAIN, HAS TO BRING
PEOPLE TOGETHER.
HAVE A POSITION.
WE NEED TO BE ABLE TO PENETRATE
THESE PEOPLE WHEN THEY ARE
INVOLVED IN THESE PLOTS AND
THESE PLANS AND WE HAVE TO GIVE
THE LOCAL AUTHORITIES THE
ABILITY TO PENETRATE THAN
DISRUPT.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO.
ENCRYPTION IS A MAJOR PROBLEM
AND CONGRESS HAS GOT TO DEAL
WITH THIS AND SO DOES THE
PRESIDENT TO KEEP US SAFE.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> THE FIGHT AGAINST RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISTS AND ISIS HAS
BEEN CALLED THE WAR OF OUR TIME.
LET'S TALK ABOUT HOW EACH OF YOU
AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF WOULD
FIGHT THIS WAR AND WIN IT.
SENATOR CRUZ.
YOU HAVE SAID YOU WOULD "CARPET
BOMB ISIS INTO OBLIVION TESTING
WHETHER OR NOT SAND CAN GLOW IN
THE DARK."
DOES THAT MEAN LEVELING THE ISIS
CAPITAL WHERE THERE ARE HUNDREDS
AND THOUSANDS OF CIVILIANS?
>> WHAT IT MEANS IS USING
OVERWHELMING AIR POWER TO
UTTERLY AND COMPLETELY DESTROY
ISIS.
TO PUT THINGS IN PERSPECTIVE.
IN THE FIRST PERSIAN GULF WAR WE
LAUNCHED ROUGHLY 1,100 AIR
ATTACKS A DAY.
WE CARPET BOMBED THEM FOR 37
DAYS.
SATURATION BOMBING AFTER WHICH
OUR TROOPS WENT IN AND MOPPED UP
WHAT WAS LEFT OF THE IRAQI ARMY.
RIGHT NOW OBAMA IS LAUNCHING
BETWEEN 15 AND 30 AIR ATTACKS A
DAY.
WE NEED TO USE OVERWHELMING AIR
POWER AND WE NEED TO BE ARMING
THE KURDS AND WE NEED TO BE
FIGHTING AND KILLING ISIS WHERE
THEY ARE.
LET ME GO BACK TO THE EARLIER
DISCUSSION A MINUTE AGO.
IT IS NOT A LACK OF CONFIDENCE
THAT IS PREVENTING THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION FROM STOPPING
THESE ATTACKS.
IT IS POLITICAL CORRECTNESS.
WE DIDN'T MONITOR THE FACEBOOK
POSTING OF THE FEMALE SAN
BERNARDINO TERRORIST BECAUSE THE
OBAMA DHS THOUGHT IT WOULD BE
INAPPROPRIATE SHE MADE A PUBLIC
CALL TO JIHAD AND THEY DIDN'T
TARGET IT.
THE TSARNAEV BROTHERS.
THE ELDER BROTHER MADE A PUBLIC
CALL TO JIHAD AND THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION DIDN'T TARGET IT.
ASSAD COMMUNICATED WITH A CLERIC
WAGING JIHAD AGAINST HIS FELLOW
SOLDIERS.
THE PROBLEM IS BECAUSE OF
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS, THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION, LIKE A LOT OF
FOLKS HERE, WANT TO SEARCH EVERY
ONE'S CELL PHONES AND E-MAILS
AND NOT FOCUS ON THE BAD GUYS
AND POLITICAL CORRECTNESS IS
KILLING PEOPLE.
>> THANK YOU.
TO BE CLEAR, SENATOR CRUZ, WOULD
YOU CARPET BOMB RAQUA WHERE
THERE ARE A LOT OF CIVILIANS?
YES OR NO.
>> YOU WOULD CARPET BOMB WHERE
ISIS IS.
THE LOCATION OF THE TROOPS.
YOU USE AIR POWER DIRECTED.
BUT THE OBJECT ISN'T TO LEVEL A
CITY, THE OBJECT IS TO KILL THE
ISIS TERRORISTS.
TO MAKE IT, LISTEN, ISIS IS
GAINING STRENGTH BECAUSE THE
PERCEPTION IS THAT THEY'RE
WINNING.
AND PRESIDENT OBAMA FUELS THAT
PERCEPTION.
THAT WILL CHANGE WHEN MILITANTS
ACROSS THE GLOBE SEE THAT WHEN
YOU JOIN ISIS THAT YOU ARE
GIVING UP YOUR LIFE.
YOU ARE SIGNING YOUR DEATH
WARRANT AND WE NEED A PRESIDENT
WHO IS FOCUSED ON DEFEATING
EVERY SINGLE ISIS TERRORIST AND
PROTECTING THE HOMELAND WHICH
SHOULD BE THE FIRST PRIORITY.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
SENATOR RUBIO.
YOU HAVE BEEN CRITICAL OF
SENATOR CRUZ'S STRATEGY.
HIS VOTING RECORD DOESN'T MATCH
HIS RHETORIC.
WHY?
>> WELL, LET ME BEGIN BY SAYING
WE HAVE TO UNDERSTAND WHO ISIS
IS.
ISIS IS A RADICAL SUNNI GROUP.
AIR STRIKES ARE A KEY COMPONENT,
BUT THEY MUST BE DEFEATED ON THE
GROUND FORCE AND THAT MUST BE
MADE OF SUNNI ARABS THEMSELVES.
SUNNI ARABS THAT CONFRONT THEM
MILITARILY.
WE WILL HAVE TO EMBED ADDITIONAL
AMERICAN SPECIAL OPERATORS
ALONGSIDE THEM TO HELP THEM WITH
TRAINING AND HELP THEM CONDUCT
SPECIAL MISSIONS AND HELP
IMPROVE THE AIR STRIKES.
THE AIR STRIKES ARE IMPORTANT.
BUT WE NEED TO HAVE AN AIR FORCE
CAPABLE OF IT AND BECAUSE OF THE
BUDGET CUTS WE ARE FACING IN
THIS COUNTRY, WE ARE GOING TO BE
LEFT WITH THE OLDEST AND THE
SMALLEST AIR FORCE WE HAVE EVER
HAD.
WE HAVE TO REVERSE THOSE CUTS.
IN ADDITION TO THE CUTS TO OUR
NAVY AND IN ADDITION TO THE CUTS
TO OUR ARMY, AS WELL.
BEYOND THAT WE MUST WIN THE
INFORMATION WAR AGAINST ISIS.
EVERY WAR WE HAVE EVER BEEN
INVOLVED IN HAS HAD A PROPAGANDA
OF INFORMATIONAL ASPECT TO IT.
ISIS IS WINNING THE PROPAGANDA
WAR AND RECRUITING PEOPLE,
INCLUDING AMERICANS, TO JOIN
THEM.
WE HAVE TO SHOW WHAT LIFE IS
REALLY LIKE IN ISIS TERRITORY
AND WE HAVE TO SHOW THEM WHY
ISIS IS NOT INVINCIBLE BY GOING
OUT AND CONDUCTING THESE ATTACKS
AND PUBLICIZING THEM TO THOSE
WHO THEY RECRUIT.
>> I ASK THE QUESTION, SENATOR,
BECAUSE YOU SAID THIS.
YOU SAID HE, REFERRING TO
SENATOR CRUZ, VOTED AGAINST THE
DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT EVERY
YEAR THAT IT CAME UP AND I
ASSUME THAT IF HE VOTED AGAINST
IT, HE WOULD VETO IT AS
PRESIDENT.
THAT'S THE BILL THAT FUNDS OUR
TROOPS.
>> THAT IS ACCURATE.
THREE TIMES HE VOTED AGAINST THE
DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT.
WHICH IS A BILL THAT FUNDS THE
TROOPS.
IT ALSO, BY THE WAY, FUNDS THE
IRON DOME AND OTHER IMPORTANT
PROGRAMS.
I HAVE TO ASSUME YOU VOTE
AGAINST IT IT IN THE SENATE, YOU
WOULD ALSO VETO IT AS PRESIDENT.
HE HAS ALSO SUPPORTED, BY THE
WAY, A BUDGET THAT IS CALLED A
CONTAINMENT BUDGET.
IT IS A BUDGET THAT WOULD
RADICALLY REDUCE THE AMOUNT OF
MONEY YOU SPEND ON OUR MILITARY.
YOU CAN'T CARPET BOMB ISIS.
IF WE CONTINUE THOSE CUTS THAT
WE'RE DOING NOW, NOT TO MENTION
ADDITIONAL CUTS.
WE'LL LEFT WITH THE SMALLEST AND
OLDEST AIR FORCE THIS COUNTRY
HAS EVER HAD AND THAT LEAVES US
LESS SAFE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> YOU KNOW, MARCO HAS CONTINUED
THESE ATTACKS AND THEY KNOW IT'S
NOT TRUE.
IT IS TRUE THAT I VOTED AGAINST
THE NATIONAL DEFENSE
AUTHORIZATION ACT BECAUSE WHEN I
CAMPAIGNED IN TEXAS I TOLD
VOTERS IN TEXAS THAT I WOULD
OPPOSE THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
HAVING THE AUTHORITY TO DETAIN
U.S. CITIZENS PERMANENTLY WITH
NO DUE PROCESS.
I HAVE REPEATEDLY SUPPORTED AN
EFFORT TO TAKE THAT OUT OF THAT
BILL AND I HONORED THAT CAMPAIGN
COMMITMENT.
BUT MORE BROADLY, YOU KNOW, THE
NOTION MARCO IS SUGGESTING THAT
SOMEHOW HE ALSO HAS TOSSED MORE
THAN A FEW INSULTS THIS DR
DIRECTION.
LET'S BE ABSOLUTELY CLEAR.
ISIS AND RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM WILL FACE NO MORE
DETERMINED FOE THAN I WILL BE.
WE WILL OTUTTERLY DESTROY THEM
DESTROYING THE BAD GUYS.
ONE OF THE PROBLEMS WITH MARCO'S
FOREIGN POLICY IS HE IS FAR TOO
OFTEN SUPPORTED HILLARY CLINTON
AND BARACK OBAMA UNDERMINING
GOVERNMENTS IN THE MIDDLE EAST
THAT HAVE HELPED RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISTS.
WE NEED TO FOCUS ON KILLING THE
BAD GUYS, NOT GETTING STUCK IN
MIDDLE EASTERN CIVIL WARS THAT
DON'T KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> THREE POINTS OF DISTINCTION.
THE FIRST IS, IF YOU'RE AN
AMERICAN CITIZEN AND YOU DECIDE
TO JOIN UP WITH ISIS.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO READ YOU YOUR
MIRRANDA RIGHTS.
NUMBER TWO, WE DO NEED OUR
DEFENSE CAPABILITIES.
IT IS A FACT THAT THE CUTS WE
ARE FACING TODAY AND THE CUTS
THAT SENATOR CRUZ WOULD HAVE
SUPPORTED WOULD LEAVE US WITH AN
EVEN SMALLER AIR FORCE AND A
SMALLER NAVY THAN THE ONE WE ARE
GOING TO BE LEFT WITH.
THE FINAL POINT I WOULD MAKE IS
HILLARY CLINTON AND BARACK OBAMA
STRATEGY IS TO LEAD FROM BEHIND.
IT SOUNDS LIKE WHAT HE IS
OUTLINING IS NOT TO LEAD AT ALL.
WE CANNOT CONTINUE TO OUTSOURCE
FOREIGN POLICY.
WE MUST LEAD.
AND THE MOST POWERFUL NATION IN
THE WORLD.
WE NEED TO BEGIN TO ACT LIKE IT,
AGAIN.
>> MUCH MORE ON THIS, BUT I WANT
TO MOVE NOW BACK TO MR. TRUMP.
>> LOOK, THIS LEGISLATION/.
>> HOLD ON.
HOLD ON.
WE HAVE A LOT.
WE HAVE A LOT TO DISCUSS.
I WANT TO MOVE TO MR. TRUMP
RIGHT NOW.
WE HAVE A QUESTION ON THIS WAR
AGAINST ISIS AND HOW YOU WOULD
FIGHT AND WIN THIS WAR.
HERE'S THE QUESTION FROM
FACEBOOK.
LISTEN TO THIS.
>> I'M JOSH JACOB FROM GEORGIA
TECH.
RECENTLY DONALD TRUMP MENTIONED
WE MUST KILL THE FAMILY OF ISIS
MEMBERS.
BETWEEN CIVILIANS AND
COMBATANTS.
MY QUESTION IS, HOW WOULD
INTENTIONALLY KILLING INNOCENT
CIVILIANS SET US APART FROM
ISIS?
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> WE HAVE TO BE MUCH TOUGHER
AND MUCH STRONGER THAN WE'VE
BEEN.
WE HAVE PEOPLE THAT KNOW WHAT IS
GOING ON.
YOU LOOK AT THE ATTACK IN
CALIFORNIA THE OTHER DAY.
NUMEROUS PEOPLE, INCLUDING THE
MOTHER THAT KNEW WHAT WAS GOING
ON.
THEY SAW A PIPE BOMB SITTING ALL
OVER THE FLOOR.
THEY SAW AMMUNITION ALL OVER THE
PLACE.
THEY KNEW EXACTLY WHAT WAS GOING
ON.
WHEN YOU HAD THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER GO.
PEOPLE WERE PUT INTO PLANES THAT
WERE FRIENDS, FAMILY,
GIRLFRIENDS AND THEY WERE PUT ON
PLANES AND THEY KNEW WHAT WAS
GOING ON.
THEY WENT HOME AND WANTED TO
WATCH THEIR BOYFRIENDS ON
TELEVISION.
I WOULD BE VERY, VERY FIRM WITH
FAMILIES.
FRANKLY, THAT WILL MAKE PEOPLE
THINK BECAUSE THEY MAY NOT CARE
MUCH ABOUT THEIR LIVES.
BUT THEY DO CARE, BELIEVE IT OR
NOT, ABOUT THEIR FAMILIES'
LIVES.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH.
>> THIS IS ANOTHER EXAMPLE OF
THE LACK OF SERIOUSNESS.
LOOK, THIS IS, THIS IS TROUBLING
BECAUSE WE'RE AT WAR.
THEY'VE DECLARED WAR ON US AND
WE NEED TO HAVE A SERIOUS
STRATEGY TO DESTROY ISIS.
BUT THE IDEA THAT THAT IS A
SOLUTION TO THIS IS JUST IS JUST
CRAZY.
IT MAKES NO SENSE TO SUGGEST
THIS.
LOOK, TWO MONTHS AGO DONALD
TRUMP SAID THAT ISIS WAS NOT OUR
FIGHT.
JUST TWO MONTHS AGO.
HE SAID THAT HILLARY CLINTON
WOULD BE A GREAT NEGOTIATOR WITH
IRAN.
AND HE GETS HIS FOREIGN POLICY
EXPERIENCE FROM THE SHOWS.
THAT IS NOT A SERIOUS KIND OF
CANDIDATE.
WE NEED SOMEONE THAT THINKS THIS
THROUGH.
THAT CAN LEAD OUR COUNTRY TO
SAFETY AND SECURITY.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> LOOK, THE PROBLEM IS WE NEED
TOUGHNESS.
HONESTLY.
I THINK JEB IS A VERY NICE
PERSON.
HE'S A VERY NICE PERSON, BUT WE
NEED TOUGH PEOPLE AND WE NEED
TOUGHNESS AND WE NEED
INTELLIGENCE AND WE NEED TOUGH.
JEB SAID WHEN THEY COME ACROSS
THE SOUTHERN BORDER THEY COME AS
AN ACT OF LOVE.
>> YOU SAID ON SEPTEMBER 30th
THAT ISIS WAS NOT A FACTOR.
>> ARE YOU TALKING OR AM I
TALKING?
YOU CAN GO BACK.
YOU INTERRUPTED ME.
ARE YOU GOING TO APOLOGIZE, JEB.
NO.
AM I ALLOWED TO FINISH?
EXCUSE ME, AM I ALLOWED TO
FINISH?
>> GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, PLEASE.
ONE AT A TIME.
>> LOOK, LOOK, LOOK.
WE NEED A TOUGHNESS.
WE NEED STRENGTH.
WE'RE NOT RESPECTED, YOU KNOW,
AS A NATION ANY MORE.
WE DON'T HAVE THAT LEVEL OF
RESPECT THAT WE NEED.
AND IF WE DON'T GET IT BACK
FAST, WE'RE JUST GOING TO GO
WEAKER, WEAKER AND JUST
DISINTEGRATE.
AND WE CAN'T ALLOW THAT TO
HAPPEN.
WE NEED STRENGTH.
WE DON'T HAVE IT.
WHEN JEB COMES OUT AND HE TALKS
ABOUT THE BORDER AND I SAW IT
AND I WAS WITNESS TO IT AND SO
WAS EVERYONE ELSE AND I WAS
STANDING THERE, THEY COME ACROSS
AS AN ACT OF LOVE.
HE'S SAYING THE SAME THING RIGHT
NOW WITH RADICAL ISLAM.
AND WE CAN'T HAVE THAT IN OUR
COUNTRY.
IT JUST WON'T WORK.
WE NEED STRENGTH.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH.
>> DONALD, YOU'RE NOT GOING TO
BE ABLE TO INSULT YOUR WAY TO
THE PRESIDENCY.
THAT'S NOT GOING TO HAPPEN.
AND I DO HAVE THE STRENGTH.
LEADERSHIP, LEADERSHIP IS NOT,
LEADERSHIP IS NOT ABOUT
ATTACKING PEOPLE AND DISC
DISCOURAGING PEOPLE.
LEADERSHIP IS ABOUT CREATING A
SERIOUS STRATEGY TO DEAL WITH
THE THREAT OF OUR TIME.
I LAID OUT THAT STRATEGY BEFORE
THE ATTACKS IN PARIS AND BEFORE
THE ATTACKS IN SAN BERNARDINO.
AND IT IT IS THE WAY FORWARD.
WE NEED TO INCREASE OUR MILITARY
SPENDING.
WE NEED TO DEAL WITH THE NO-FLY
ZONE IN SYRIA AND BUILDING A
MILITARY THAT IS SECOND TO NONE.
>> WITH JEB'S ATTITUDE, WE WILL
NEVER BE GREAT AGAIN.
THAT I CAN TELL YOU.
WE WILL NEVER BE GREAT, AGAIN.
>> HUGH HEWITT AND DANA BASH.
GO AHEAD WITH THE NEXT QUESTION.
>> DR. CARSON, YOU MENTIONED IN
YOUR OPENING REMARKS THAT YOU'RE
A PEDIATRIC NEUROLOGIST --
>> NEUROSURGEON.
>> PEOPLE ARE INSPIRED BY YOUR
LIFE STORY, YOUR KINDNESS AND
EVANGELICAL CORE SUPPORT.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT RUTHLESS
THINGS TONIGHT.
CARPET BOMBING, TOUGHNESS, WAR.
PEOPLE WONDER, COULD YOU DO
THAT?
COULD YOU ORDER AIR STRIKES THAT
WOULD KILL INNOCENT CHILDREN BY
NOT THE SCORES, BUT THE HUNDREDS
AND THOUSANDS?
COULD YOU WAGE WAR AS A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF?
>> INTERESTINGLY ENOUGH, YOU
SHOULD SEE THE EYES OF SOME OF
THOSE CHILDREN.
THEY DON'T LIKE ME VERY MUCH AT
THAT POINT.
BUT LATER ON, THEY LOVE ME.
SOMETIMES YOU, I SOUND LIKE HIM.
LATER ON THEY REALLY REALIZE
WHAT'S GOING ON AND BY THE SAME
TOKEN, YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO
LOOK AT THE BIG PICTURE.
AND UNDERSTAND THAT IT'S
ACTUALLY MERCIFUL IF YOU GO
AHEAD AND FINISH THE JOB RATHER
THAN DEATH BY 1,000 --
>> SO YOU ARE OKAY WITH THE
DEATHS OF THOUSANDS OF INNOCENT
CHILDREN AND CIVILIAN?
I
>> YOU GOT IT.
>> THAT IS WHAT WAR.
CAN YOU BE AS RUTHLESS AS
CHURCHILL WAS.
>> RUTHLESS IS NOT NECESSARILY
THE WORD I WOULD USE BUT TOUGH,
RESOLUTE, UNDERSTANDING WHAT THE
PROBLEMS ARE AND UNDERSTANDING
THAT THE JOB OF THE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES IS TO PROTECT
THE PEOPLE OF THIS COUNTRY AND
TO DO WHAT IS NECESSARY IN ORDER
TO GET IT DONE.
>> SENATOR PAUL.
YOU SAID ISIS GREW STRONGER
BECAUSE OF THE HAWKS IN YOUR
PARTY.
DO YOU REALLY THINK THAT
REPUBLICANS HAVE FUELED THE RISE
OF ISIS?
>> I THINK THAT BY ARMING THE
ALLIES OF ISIS THE ISLAMIC
REBELS AGAINST ASSAD THAT WE
MADE THAT SPACE BIGGER FOR ISIS
TO GROW.
I THINK THOSE THAT WANTED REGIME
CHANGE HAVE MADE A MISTAKE.
WHEN WE TOPPLED GADHAFI IN
LIBYA, I THINK THAT WAS A
MISTAKE.
I THINK ISIS GREW STRONGER AND
WE HAD A FAILED STATE AND MORE
AT RISK.
I WOULD LIKE TO ALSO GO BACK TO
ANOTHER QUESTION.
WHICH IS, IS DONALD TRUMP A
SERIOUS CANDIDATE.
THE REASON I ASK THIS IS, IF YOU
ARE GOING TO CLOSE THE INTERNET,
REALIZE AMERICA WHAT THAT
ENTAILS.
THAT ENTAILS GETTING RID OF THE
FIRST AMENDMENT.
OKAY.
NO SMALL FEAT.
IF YOU ARE GOING TO KILL THE
FAMILIES OF TERRORISTS, REALIZE
THAT THERE IS SOMETHING CALLED
THE GENEVA CONVENTION WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO PULL OUT OF.
IT WOULD DEFY EVERY NORM THAT IS
AMERICA.
SO, WHEN YOU ASK YOURSELF
WHOEVER YOU ARE THAT THINK
YOU'RE GOING TO SUPPORT DONALD
TRUMP.
THINK, DO YOU BELIEVE IN THE
CONSTITUTION?
ARE YOU GOING TO CHANGE THE
>> SO, THEY COULD KILL US, BUT
WE CAN'T KILL THEM?
THAT'S WHAT YOU'RE SAYING.
AS FAR AS THE INTERNET IS
CONCERNED.
WE'RE NOT TALKING ABOUT CLOSING
THE INTERNET.
I'M TALKING ABOUT PARTS OF
SYRIA, PARTS OF IRAQ.
WHERE ISIS IS.
SPOTTING IT IT.
NOW, YOU COULD CLOSE IT.
WHAT I LIKE EVEN BETTER THAN
THAT IS GETTING OUR SMARTEST AND
GETTING OUR BEST TO INFILTRATE
THEIR INTERNET.
SO, THAT WE KNOW EXACTLY WHERE
THEY'RE GOING.
EXACTLY WHERE THEY'RE GOING TO
BE.
I LIKE THAT BETTER.
BUT, WE HAVE TO -- WHO WOULD BE.
I JUST CAN'T IMAGINE SOMEBODY
BOOING.
THESE ARE PEOPLE THAT WANT TO
KILL US, FOLKS.
AND YOU'RE OBJECTING TO US
INFILTRATING THEIR
CONVERSATIONS?
I DON'T THINK SO.
>> SENATOR PAUL.
>> SENATOR PAUL, I WANT TO GO
BACK TO MY INITIAL QUESTION
WHICH IS, YOU SAYING THAT ISIS
GREW STRONGER BECAUSE OF YOUR
PARTY AND DO YOU THINK YOUR OWN
PARTY, THE PEOPLE WHO YOU'RE
DESCRIBING ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR
THE RISE OF ISIS?
>> I THINK THAT IF YOU BELIEVE
IN REGIME CHANGE, YOU'RE
MISTAKEN.
IN 2013, WE PUT 600 TONS OF
WEAPONS.
US, SAUDI ARABIA AND KUTAR INTO
THE WAR AGAINST ASSAD.
BY PUSHING ASSAD BACK WE DID
CREATE A SAFE SPACE.
WE HAD PEOPLE COMING INTO OUR
FOREIGN RELATIONS COMMITTEE AND
SAYING WE NEED TO ARM THE ALLIES
OF AL QAEDA.
THEY'RE STILL SAYING THIS.
IT IS A CRAZY NOTION.
THIS IS THE BIGGEST DEBATE WE
SHOULD BE HAVING TONIGHT IS
REGIME CHANGE A GOOD IDEA.
HAS IT BEEN A GOOD IDEA?
THERE ARE STILL PEOPLE.
THE MAJORITY ON THE STAGE.
THEY WANT TO TOPPLE ASSAD.
AND THEN THERE WILL BE CHAOS AND
I THINK ISIS WILL BE IN CHARGE.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, WOULD YOU
LIKE TO RESPOND TO SENATOR PAUL?
>> YEAH, LET ME JUST SUGGEST TO
EVERYBODY.
AND I HEAR, LAST FEBRUARY I SAID
WE NEEDED TO HAVE PEOPLE ON THE
GROUND AND A COALITION WITH
EUROPE AND OUR ALLIES.
THIS IS NOT GOING TO GET DONE
JUST BY WORKING WITH THE SUNNIS.
AND IT IS NOT GOING TO GET DONE
IF WE JUST EMBED A FEW PEOPLE.
WE HAVE TO GO MASSIVELY LIKE WE
DID IN THE FIRST GULF WAR WHERE
WE DESTROYED SADDAM'S ABILITY TO
TAKE KUWAIT.
WE NEED TO HAVE A COALITION THAT
WILL STAND FOR NOTHING LESS THAN
THE TOTAL DESTRUCTION OF ISIS
AND WE HAVE TO BE THE LEADER.
WE CAN'T WAIT FOR ANYBODY ELSE.
I SERVED ON THE ARMED SERVICES
COMMITTEE FOR 18 YEARS AND WE
MUST LEAD OR THE JOB WON'T GET
DONE, UNFORTUNATELY, FOR OUR
COUNTRY.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
LET'S CONTINUE THIS
CONVERSATION.
THIS IS A CRITICALLY IMPORTANT
ISSUE.
>> I HOPE AT SOME POINT YOU'RE
GOING TO ASK ME MY STRATEGY FOR
DEFEATING ISIS.
>> WE HAVE A LOT OF TIME.
I WANT TO GET SENATOR RUBIO
RIGHT NOW.
ONE OF THE ASPECTS OF YOUR
STRATEGY.
THE ONLY WAY TO DEFEAT ISIS WITH
GROUND FORCES MADE UP PRIMARILY
OF ARAB FORCES.
THOSE NATIONS HAVE CONDUCTED
LESS THAN 5% OF THE AIR STRIKES
AND ACTUALLY NONE SINCE AUGUST.
WHAT MAKES YOU THINK THEY ARE
WILLING TO FIGHT ON THE GROUND
IF THEY'RE NOT EVEN WILLING TO
FIGHT FROM THE AIR?
>> THEY MOST CERTAINLY WILL HAVE
TO BE WORKED ON TO PROVIDE MORE
THAN WHAT THEY'RE DOING NOW.
ONE MAJOR REASON WHY THEY ARE
NOT A BROADER PART OF THE
COALITION.
THEY HAVE LOST COMPLETE TRUST
AND CONFIDENCE IN THIS
PRESIDENT.
THIS PRESIDENT CUT A DEAL WITH
OUR MORTAL ENEMY THE SHIA IN
IRAN.
THIS IS THE REASON WHY THEY NO
LONGER TRUST THIS PRESIDENT AND
WILLING TO WORK ALONGSIDE THEM.
THEY HAVE AS MUCH INVESTED IN
THIS THAN US OR MORE SO.
THE KING OF JORDAN THEY WANT TO
DETHRONE.
THEY WANT TO GO INTO EGYPT.
LIKE THE WAY THEY'VE GONE INTO
LIBYA.
ON ANOTHER POINT WE NEED TO TALK
ABOUT.
ASSAD IS ONE OF THE REASONS WHY
ISIS EXISTS TO BEGIN WITH.
HE HAS BEEN SO BRUTAL TOWARDS
THE SUNNI WITHIN SYRIA THAT HE
CREATED THE SPACE THAT LED FOR
THE PEOPLE OF SYRIA THEM SELVES
TO STAND UP AND OVERTHROW HIM.
THAT LED TO THE CHAOS TO GROW
MORE POWERFUL.
NO ALTERNATIVE GROUPS ON THE
GROUND TO BE EMPOWERED LEAVING
ISIS THE PRIME OPERATING SPACE
THEY NEEDED.
>> STAND BY.
MS. FIORINA.
THE FORMER DEFENSE SECRETARY BOB
KATE SAYS THE CHANCES OF GETTING
SUNNI ARAB FORCES ON THE GROUND
TO GET THE JOB DONE.
HIS WORDS, CHANCES VERY REMOTE.
WHAT'S YOUR STRATEGY?
>> WELL, FIRST, I'LL JUST POINT
OUT THAT TALKING TOUGH IS NOT
THE SAME AS BEING STRONG.
TO WAGE WAR, WE NEED A COMMANDER
IN CHIEF WHO MADE TOUGH CALLS IN
TOUGH TIMES AND STOOD UP TO BE
ACCOUNTABLE OVER AND OVER.
NOT FIRST-TERM SENATORS WHO
NEVER MADE AN EXECUTIVE DECISION
IN THEIR LIFE.
ONE OF THE THINGS I WOULD
IMMEDIATELY DO IN ADDITION TO
DEFEATING THEM HERE AT HOME IS
BRING BACK THE WARRIOR CLASS.
PET
PETRAEUS, McCHRYSTAL, MADS,
KEEN, FLYNN.
EVERY SINGLE ONE OF THESE
GENERALS I KNOW, EVERY ONE WAS
RETIRED EARLY BECAUSE THEY TOLD
PRESIDENT OBAMA THINGS THAT HE
DIDN'T WANT TO HEAR.
WE MUST HAVE SUNNI ARABS
INVOLVED IN THIS COALITION.
WE MUST COMMIT LEADERSHIP,
STRENGTH, SUPPORT AND RESOLVE.
I WILL JUST ADD THAT MARGARET
THATCHER ONCE SAID IF YOU WANT
SOMETHING TALKED ABOUT.
ASK A MAN.
IF YOU WANT SOMETHING DONE, ASK
A WOMAN.
>> THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, WHAT IS YOUR
STRATEGY?
>> WOLF, YOU SIT UP HERE AND YOU
LISTEN TO THIS STUFF AND YOU
THINK THAT SO MANY OF THESE
PEOPLE HAVE HAD SO MUCH TO DO IN
THIS NATIONAL DEBATE.
THEY TALK LIKE THEY WERE
BYSTANDERS.
YOU KNOW, WE TALK ABOUT OUR
MILITARY BEING DEGRADED OVER
TIME AND, YET, WE'VE HAD FOLKS
ON THE STAGE THAT HAVE BEEN A
PART OF CONGRESS WHO HAVE
PARTICIPATED IN SEQUESTER.
WHO PARTICIPATED IN THE
DEGRADING OF THIS MILITARY OVER
TIME.
AND THAT'S WHY I THINK PEOPLE
GET SO FRUSTRATED WITH
WASHINGTON, D.C., NOW.
THAT'S WHY THEY'RE SO ANGRY WITH
THE ELECTORATE SO ANGRY WITH
EVERYBODY WHO IS INVOLVED IN
GOVERNMENT WASHINGTON, D.C.
BECAUSE IF YOU LISTEN TO THE
FOLKS UP HERE, YOU WOULD THINK
THAT THEY'RE NOT EVEN THERE.
THEY HAD NOTHING TO DO WITH
THIS.
THIS IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
BEING A GOVERNOR AND BEING IN
THE LEGISLATURE.
BECAUSE WHEN SOMETHING DOESN'T
WORK IN NEW JERSEY, THEY LOOK AT
ME.
SAY WHY DIDN'T YOU GET DONE.
WHY DIDN'T YOU
SO GET IT DONE?
THE PRESIDENT NEEDS TO BE A
FORCE THAT IS TRUSTED IN THE
WORLD.
AND ON THIS I AGREE WITH MARCO.
YOU KNOW, THIS PRESIDENT'S NOT
TRUSTED.
IF YOU'RE THE KING OF JORDAN OR
IN THE ROYAL FAMILY IN SAUDI
ARABIA AND HE'S MADE THIS DEAL
WITH I RAN TO GIVE THEM MONEY TO
WAGE A WAR AND TRY TO EXTEND
THEIR EMPIRE IN THE MIDDLE EAST,
WHY WOULD YOU WANT TO DO IT NOW?
BUT WHEN I STAND ACROSS FROM
KING HUSSAIN OF JORDAN YOU HAVE
A FRIEND WHO WILL STABBED WITH
YOU TO FIGHT THIS FIGHT.
>> DR. CARSON, WHAT IS YOUR
STRANGE IN -- STRATEGY?
>> I HAVE BEEN TALKING ABOUT
THIS FOR OVER A YEAR.
WE HAVE TO DESTROY THEIR
CALIPHATE.
THAT GIVES THEM LEGITIMACY TO GO
AHEAD WITH THE GLOBAL JIHAD.
WE HAVE TO TAKE THEIR ENERGY
BECAUSE THEY ARE -- ISIS IS THE
RICHEST TERRORIST ORGANIZATION
THERE IS, TAKE THEIR OIL AND
SHUT DOWN THEIR MECHANISMS BY
WHICH THEY CAN DISPERSE MONEY.
AND THEY ARE ABLE TO PAY THEM,
AND THAT MAKES A DIFFERENCE.
AS FAR AS THE COMMAND CENTERS
ARE CONCERNED IN RAQQAH AND
MOSUL, CUT THOSE OFF THE SAME
KIND OF THING WE DID WITH
SINJAR, WORKING WITH THE
EMBEDDED FORCES WITH THE KURDS,
SHUT OFF THE SUPPLY ROUTES AND
FOLLOW WITH OUR AIR FORCE TO
TAKE THEM OVER.
THOSE ARE THINGS THAT WORK.
BUT ALSO, YOU KNOW, THIS WHOLE
CONCEPT OF BOOTS ON THE GROUND,
YOU KNOW WE'VE GOT A PHOBIA OF
BOOTS ON THE GROUND.
IF OUR MILITARY EXPERTS WANT
BOOTS ON THE GROUND THERE SHOULD
BE BOOTS ON THE GROUND.
AND THERE WILL BE BOOTS ON THE
GROUND AND THEY WILL BE THEIR
BOOTS AND THEY'LL BE OVER HERE
IF WE DON'T STAND OUR GROUND.
>>> STAND BY, WE'RE ONLY JUST
BEGINNING.
WHICH CANDIDATES WANT TO MOVE
U.S. FOREIGN POLICY IN A
DRAMATIC NEW DIRECTION?
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
FACEBOOK REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE AT THE VENETIAN, LAS
VEGAS.
THE WAR AGAINST ISIS WILL POSE
MANY CHALLENGES FOR THE NEXT
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF.
THE LAST TWO PRESIDENTS PURSUED
A POLICY THAT PROMOTED TOMLING
DICTATORS TO SUPPORT DEMOCRATIC.
SENATOR CRUZ YOU SAID THAT THE
WORLD WOULD BE SAFER IF SADDAM
HUSSEIN WAS IN IRAQ AND HOSNI
MUBARAK RULED EGYPT.
WOULD YOU PRESERVE DICTATORSHIPS
RATHER THAN PROMOTING DEMOCRACY
IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
>> IF I BELIEVE AN AMERICA FIRST
FOREIGN POLICY THAT PRESIDENT
OBAMA AND HILLARY CLINTON AND
MORE THAN A NEW REPUBLICANS HAVE
GOTTEN DISTRACTED FROM THE
CENTRAL FOCUS OF KEEPING THIS
COUNTRY SAFE.
SO LET'S GO BACK TO THE
BEGINNING OF THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION WHEN HILLARY
CLINTON AND PRESIDENT OBAMA LET
NATO IN TOPPLING THE GOVERNMENT
IN LIBYA.
A NUMBER OF REPUBLICANS
SUPPORTED THEM, THE RESULT OF
THAT -- AND WE WERE TOLD THEN
THERE WERE THESE MODERATE REBELS
THAT WOULD TAKE OVER.
THE RESULT IS THAT LIBYA IS NOW
A TERRORIST WAR ZONE RUN BY
JIHADISTS.
MOVE TO EGYPT.
ONCE AGAIN THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION TOPPLED MUBARAK
WHO HAD BEEN A RELIABLE ALLY OF
THE UNITED STATES AND ISRAEL AND
IN ITS PLACE MORSI AND THE
MUSLIM BROTHERHOOD CAME IN, A
TERRORIST ORGANIZATION.
AND WE NEED TO LEARN FROM
HISTORY, THESE SAME LEADERS,
OBAMA, CLINTON AND FAR TOO MANY
REPUBLICANS WANT TO TOPPLE
ASSAD.
ASSAD IS A BAD MAN.
GADDAFI IS A BAD MAN.
BUT THEY WERE ASSISTING US AT
LEAST GADDAFI AND MUBARAK IN
FIGHTING TERRORISTS.
AND IF WE TOPPLE ASSAD, ISIS
WILL TAKE OVER SYRIA AND IT WILL
WORSEN NATIONAL SECURITY
INTERESTS.
AND THE APPROACH INSET OF A
DEMOCRACY PROMOTER WE OUGHT TO
HUNT DOWN THE ENEMIES AND KILL
ISIS RATHER THAN CREATING
OPPORTUNITIES FOR ISIS TO
CONTROL NEW COUNTRIES.
>>> SENATOR RUBIO, ISIS IS
CLEARLY GROWING IN TURKEY.
SENATOR CRUZ SAYS YOU HAVEN'T
LEARNED YOUR LESSON DO.
YOU HAVE ANY REGRETS FOR
SUPPORTING PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
INTERVENTION IN LIBYA?
>> THE REVOLT AGAINST GADDAFI
WAS STARTED BY THE LIBYAN
PEOPLE.
AND I ARGUED WE NEEDED TO GET
INVOLVED BECAUSE HE WAS GOING TO
GO ONE WAY OR THE OTHER AND THE
LONGER THE CIVILIAN WAR
TOOKINGS, THE MORE MA MILITIAS
WOULD BE FORMED.
AS FAR AS MOE MAR GADDAFI, HE IS
THE MAN WHO KILLED THE AMERICANS
OVER LOCKERBIE, SCOTLAND AND
KILLED MARINES.
AND YOU KNOW WHY HE COOPERATED
ON THE NUCLEAR PROGRAM?
BECAUSE WE GOT RID OF SADDAM
HUSSEIN.
WE WILL IS TO WORK WITH LESS
THAN IDEAL GOVERNMENTS.
THE GOVERNMENT IN SAUDI ARABIA
IS NOT A DEMOCRACY BUT WE HAVE
TO WORK WITH THEM.
THE GOVERNMENT IN JORDAN IS NOT
PERFECT BUT WE HAVE TO WORK WITH
THEM.
BUT ASSAD, WHO GEM GET IEDs INTO
IRAQ IF THEY GO, I WILL NOT SHED
A TEAR.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> IT'S MORE THAN NOT SHEDDING A
TEAR IT'S ACTIVELY GETTING
INVOLVED TO TOPPLE A GOVERNMENT
AND WE KEEP HEARING FROM
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON AND WASHINGTON
REPUBLICANS THAT THEY ARE
SEARCHING FOR MYTH CALL MODERATE
REBELS.
IT'S LIKE A PURPLE UNICORN.
THEY DON'T EXIST.
THEY END UP BEING JIHADISTS.
AND PRIME MINISTER NETTANYAHU HS
SAID -- AT THE SAME TIME, PRIME
MINISTER NETANYAHU DOESN'T WANT
TO SEE SYRIA GOVERNED BY ISIS
AND WE NEED TO FOCUS ON AMERICAN
INTERESTS NOD -- EVERYBODY STAND
BY FOR A MOMENT.
GOVERNOR KASICH GO AHEAD.
>> ASSAD WITH ALIGNED WITH IRAN
AND RUSSIA.
WE WANT TO PREVENT IRAN BEING
ABLE TO EXTEND A SHIA CRESCENT
ACROSS THE MIDDLE EAST.
THERE ARE MODERATES IN SYRIA WHO
WE SHOULD BE SUPPORTING.
I DON'T SUPPORT A CIVIL WAR OR
WANT TO BE POLICEMAN OF THE
WORLD BUT WE CAN'T BACK OFF OF
THIS.
AND THE SAUDIS HAVE AGREED TO
PUT TOGETHER A COALITION INSIDE
SYRIA TO STABILIZE THAT COUNTRY.
HE MUST GO.
WOULD BE A BLOW TO IRAN AND
RUSSIA.
>> MR. TRUMP, ARE AMERICANS
SAFER WITH DICTATORS RUNNING THE
WORLD IN THE MIDDLE EAST?
>> IN MY OPINION --
>> GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP.
>> WE HAVE SPENT $4 TRILLION
TRYING TO TOPPLE VARIOUS PEOPLE
THAT FRANKLY IF THEY WERE THERE
AND IF WE COULD HAVE SPENT THAT
$4 TRILLION IN THE UNITED STATES
TO FIX OUR ROADS, OUR BRIDGES
AND ALL OF THE OTHER PROBLEMS,
OUR AIRPORTS AND ALL THE OTHER
PROBLEMS WE HAVE WE WOULD HAVE
BEEN A LOT BETTER OFF I CAN TELL
YOU THAT RIGHT NOW.
WE HAVE DONE A TREMENDOUS
DISSERVICE NOT ONLY TO THE
MIDDLE EAST BUT TO HUMANITY, THE
PEOPLE THAT HAVE BEEN KILLED,
THE PEOPLE THAT HAVE BEEN WIPED
AWAY AND FOR WHAT?
IT'S NOT LIKE WE HAD VICTORY.
IT'S A MESS.
THE MIDDLE EAST IS TOTALLY
DESTABILIZED, A TOTAL AND
COMPLETE MESS.
I WISH WE HAD THE $4 TRILLION OR
$5 TRILLION.
I WISH IT WERE SPENT RIGHT HERE
IN THE UNITED STATES ON SCHOOLS,
HOSPITALS, ROADS, AIRPORTS AND
EVERYTHING ELSE THAT ARE ALL
FALLING APART.
>> THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT PRESIDENT
OBAMA HAS SAID I'M AMAZED TO
HEAR THAT FROM A REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.
BUT LET'S START WITH WHO GOT IT
WRONG, WHO REALLY GOT IT WRONG.
HILLARY CLINTON HAS GOTTEN EVERY
FOREIGN POLICY CHALLENGE WRONG.
THE RESET BUTTON WITH VLADIMIR
PUTIN.
SHE CALLED BASHAR AL ASSAD A
POSITIVE REFORMER AND OPENED AN
EMBASSY AND LATER SAID OVER AND
OVER AND OVER, BASHAR AL ASSAD
MUST GO ALTHOUGH SHE WAS NOT
PREPARED TO DO ANYTHING ABOUT
IT.
HILLARY CLINTON WAS ALL FOR
TOPPLING MOE MAR GADDAFI AND
DIDN'T LISTEN TO HER OWN PEOPLE
ON THE GROUND.
AND SHE LIED ABOUT THE TERRORIST
ATTACK IN BENGHAZI.
>> THERE IS NOTHING TO RESPOND
TO.
PEOPLE FEEL DIFFERENTLY.
BENGHAZI WAS A DISASTER BECAUSE
OF LIBYA EVERYTHING FELL INTO
PLACE.
IT COULD NOT HAVE BEEN WORSE.
WHAT DO WE HAVE NOW?
WE HAVE SPENT $3 TRILLION AND
PROBABLY MUCH MORE.
THOUSANDS AND THOUSANDS OF
LIVES, WE HAVE NOTHING.
WOUNDED WARRIORS ALL OVER THE
PLACE, WHO I LOVE, WE HAVE
NOTHING FOR IT.
BEN SAID, CORRECTLY, THIS IS NOT
A KNOCK.
THIS IS ONE OF THE FINEST MEN.
BUT I HAVE BEEN TALKING ABOUT
OIL FOR THREE YEARS.
I'VE BEEN SAYING TAKE THE OIL.
TAKE THE OIL.
I DIDN'T JUST SAY BOMB IT, TAKE
IT AND USE IT AND DISTRIBUTE IT
SO THE WOUNDE WARRIORS AND
PEOPLE.
I HAVE BEEN SAYING THIS NOW FOR
MANY YEARS.
NOW ALL OF A SUDDEN EVERYONE
SAYING TAKE THE OIL.
I HAVE BEEN SAYING IT FOR YEARS.
>> DR. CARSON, IS THE MIDDLE
EAST BETTER OFF WITH DICTATORS?
>> NO ONE IS EVER BETTER OFF
WITH DICTATORS.
BUT THERE COMES A TIME WHEN
YOU'RE ON AN AIRPLANE, THEY
ALWAYS SAY, IN CASE OF AN
EMERGENCY, OXYGEN MASKS WILL
DROP DOWN PUT YOURS ON FIRST AND
ADMINISTRATOR HELP TO YOUR
NEIGHBOR.
WE NEED OXYGEN RIGHT NOW AND
NEED TO THINK ABOUT THE NEEDS OF
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE BEFORE WE GO
AND TRY TO SOLVE EVERYBODY
ELSE'S PROBLEMS.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, THE
MIDDLE EAST HAS BEEN IN TURMOIL
FOR THOUSANDS OF YEARS.
FOR US TO THINK THAT WE'RE GOING
TO GO IN THERE AND FIX THAT WITH
A COUPLE OF LITTLE BOMBS AND A
FEW DECLARATIONS IS RELATIVELY
FOOLISH.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH?
>> I THINK WE ARE --
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, HERE IS THE
QUESTION, YOU SAID GETTING RID
OF SADDAM HUSSEIN WAS A PRETTY
GOOD DEAL.
IN LIGHT OF WHAT IS HAPPENED IN
IRAQ DO YOU STILL FEEL THAT WAY?
>> I DO.
AND THE LESSON LEARNED IS WE
HAVE TO HAVE A STRATEGY TO GET
IN AND A STRATEGY TO GET OUT
WHICH MEANS YOU CREATE A STABLE
SITUATION.
PRESIDENT OBAMA DOES NOT BELIEVE
AMERICAN'S LEADERSHIP IN THE
WORLD IS A FORCE FOR GOOD.
HE DOES NOT BELIEVE THAT OUR
STRENGTH IS A PLACE WHERE
SECURITY CAN TAKE PLACE.
HE LEADS FROM BEHIND.
HE CREATES AN ENVIRONMENT THAT
NOW WE'RE CREATING THE MOST
UNSTABLE SITUATION WE'VE HAD
SINCE THE WORLD WAR II ERA.
THE FOCUS OUGHT TO BE THAT
HILLARY CLINTON WANTS TO DOUBLE
DOWN ON A FAILED FOREIGN POLICY.
WE NEED TO BE UNITED TO BEAT
THAT.
WE'LL BE IN A PLACE FAR LESS
SECURE THAN IT USED TO BE.
>> SENATOR PAUL, WAS GETTING RID
OF SADDAM HUSSEIN A GOOD DEAL?
>> WHETHER OR NOT REGIME CHANGE
IS A GOOD IDEA OR A BAD IDEA.
I DON'T THINK BECAUSE IT WAS A
BAD IDEA THAT HUSSAIN WAS
NECESSARILY A GOOD IDEA.
THERE IS VARIATIONS OF EVIL ON
BOTH SIDES OF THE WAR.
WHAT WE HAVE TO DECIDE IS
WHETHER OR NOT REGIME CHANGE IS
A GOOD IDEA.
IT'S WHAT THE NEOCONSERVATIVES
HAVE WANTED AND WHAT THE VAST
MAJORITY OF THOSE ON THE STAGE
WANT.
THEY WANT REGIME CHANGE IN
SYRIA, THEY WANTED IT IN IRAQ
AND LIB YEAH.
IT HAS NOT WORKED.
YOU GET CHAOS AND YOU HAVE SEEN
REPEATLY THE THE RISE OF RADICAL
ISLAM.
SO WE GET THIS PROFESSION OF
THEY WANT TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT
TERRORISM AND YET THEY'RE THE
PROBLEM BECAUSE THEY ALLOW
TERRORISM TO ARISE OUT OF THAT
CHAOS.
>> THE WOLF --
>> HOLD ON.
HOLD ON.
>> IS ASKING THE WRONG
QUESTIONS.
WE SHOULD BE DEFEATING --
>> WAIT YOUR TURN.
WE HAVE TWO HOURS.
WE'LL HAVE PLENTY OF TIME.
>> THE FOCUS SHOULD BE ON
DEFEATING OUR ENEMIES --
>> IRAN, IRAN HAS DECLARED WAR
ON US.
>> SENATOR, PLEASE.
>> FIGHTING RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISMS.
>> THESE ARE THE RULES YOU ALL
AGREED TO.
HUGH GO AHEAD WITH YOUR
QUESTION.
>> MR. TRUMP, WE ARE TALKING
ABOUT THE MOST IMPORTANT THING.
YOU ARE OKAY WITH MR. AL ASSAD
STAYING IN POWER BUT YOU ARE IN
FAVOR OF WINNING.
IF HE STAYS IN POWER, IRAN IS
WINNING, HEZBOLLAH IS WINNING.
THEY ARE WINNING EVERYWHERE.
IF THEY ARE WINNING HOW CAN WE
BE WINNING?
>> I THINK AL ASSAD IS A BAD
GUY.
A LOT OF PEOPLE KILLED.
WE ARE BACKING PEOPLE WE HAVE NO
IDEA WHO THEY ARE.
THE REBELS, WE HAVE NO IDEA.
A LOT OF PEOPLE THINK THAT THEY
ARE ISIS.
WE HAVE TO DO ONE THING AT A
TIME.
WE CAN'T BE FIGHTING ISIS AND
FIGHTING AL ASSAD, AL ASSAD IS
FIGHTING ISIS, RUSSIA IS
FIGHTING ISIS AND IRAN IS
FIGHTING ISIS.
WE HAVE TO DO ONE THING AT A
TIME.
LINDSEY GRAHAM SAID I HAVE BEEN
HER TEN YEARS.
BUT HE WILL BE THERE ANOTHER 50.
HE WON'T BE ABLE TO SOLVE THE
PROBLEM.
WE HAVE TO GET RID OF ISIS
FIRST.
THEN WE START THINKING ABOUT IT.
BUT WE CAN'T FIGHT AL ASSAD AND
WHEN YOU FIGHT AL ASSAD YOU ARE
FIGHTING RUSSIA AND A LOT OF
DIFFERENT GROUPS.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, IS HE
RIGHT?
BECAUSE IF WE STEP BACK, IRAN
GOES NUCLEAR.
IS DONALD TRUMP RIGHT?
>> I THINK WE HAVE TO FOCUS ON
WHAT THE PRIORITIES ARE.
AND WHAT I'VE ALWAYS SAID THAT
THE PRESIDENT HAS SET UP AN
AWFUL SITUATION THROUGH HIS DEAL
WITH IRAN.
BECAUSE WHAT HIS DEAL WITH IRAN
HAS DONE IS EMPOWER THEM AND
ENRICH THEM.
AND THAT'S THE WAY ISIS HAS BEEN
CREATED AND FORMED HERE.
ISIS IS CREATED AND FORMED
BECAUSE OF THE ABUSE THAT AL
ASSAD AND HIS IRANIAN SPONSORS
HAVE RAINED DOWN ON THE SUNNIS
IN SYRIA.
WHEN WE EMPOWER IRAN THAT'S WHY
THIS PRESIDENT -- AND WHEN
HILLARY CLINTON SAYS HER THEORY
AGAINST ISIS WILL BE JUST ABOUT
THE SAME AS THE PRESIDENT.
THEN GET READY FOR MORE UNREST
AND MORE MURDER AND MORE
VIOLENCE IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
WE NEED TO FOCUS OUR ATTENTION
ON IRAN.
IF YOU MISS IRAN YOU ARE NOT
GOING TO GET ISIS.
THE TWO ARE CONNECTED BECAUSE
ONE CAUSES THE OTHER.
>> SENATOR PAUL, LET ME ASK YOU
HEARD GOVERNOR KASICH SAY AL
ASSAD MUST GO.
DO YOU AGREE?
>> I THINK IT'S A MISTAKE.
REGIME CHANGE IN SYRIA -- I HAVE
BEEN SAYING THIS FOR SEVERAL
YEARS NOW.
IN 2013 I SAID YOU ARE GIVING
ARMS TO RADICAL JIHADISTS?
THAT'S CRAZY.
BUT YOU WILL BE BACK FIGHTING
YOUR OWN WEAPONS.
HAD AL ASSAD BEEN BOMBED TWO
YEARS AGO, ISIS WOULD HAVE BEEN
IN CHARGE OF ALL OF SYRIA NOW.
WE NEED A REALISTIC FOREIGN
POLICY INSTEAD OF A UTOPIAN ONE.
THEY ARE NOT GOING TO LOVE US.
>> THE FOREIGN POLICY, YOU HAVE
TO KNOW HOW TO PICK AND CHOOSE.
THERE'S NO WAY IF SADDAM HAD NOT
HAD WEAPONS OF MASS DESTRUCTION
I WOULD HAVE GONE.
I DON'T BELIEVE THAT THE U.S.
SHOULD BE INVOLVED DIRECTLY IN
CIVIL WARS.
I OPPOSED THE U.S. INVOLVEMENT
IN LEBANON.
THERE IS A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
IRAQ, WHERE YOU HAVE SUNNI, SHIA
AND KURDS PUT TOGETHER AFTER THE
FIRST WORLD WAR BY THE WESTERN
POWERS.
IT DOESN'T WORK.
IT NEEDS TO BREAK UP INTO THREE
PARTS.
AND FINALLY IN REGARD TO SYRIA,
UNDERSTAND THAT AL ASSAD IS AN
ALLY OF IRAN.
AND IT IS TIME WE PUNCHED THE
RUSSIANS IN THE NOSE.
WE NEED TO STAND UP AGAINST
THEM.
NOT JUST THERE BUT ALSO IN
EASTERN EUROPE WHERE THEY
THREATEN SOME OF OUR MOST
PRECIOUS ALLIES.
>>> MY NAME IS ASHLEY, MS.
FIORINA YOU SAID YOU WOULD NOT
COMMUNICATE WITH VLADIMIR PUTIN
BECAUSE YOU WOULD BE COMING FROM
A SIDE OF WEAKNESS.
>> U.S. AND RUSSIAN WAR PLANES
ARE FLYING OVER SYRIA RIGHT NOW.
IS THIS A GOOD TIME FOR THE
UNITED STATES NOT TO TALK TO
PUTIN?
>> I DIDN'T SAY I WOULD CUT OFF
ALL COMMUNICATION WITH PUTIN.
AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES NOW IS NOT THE TIME TO
TALK WITH HIM.
REAGAN WALKED AWAY AT REYKJAVIK.
THERE IS A TIME AND A PLACE FOR
TALK AND A TIME AND A PLACE FOR
ACTION.
ER VLADIMIR PUTIN RESPECTS
STRENGTH.
HE LIED TO OUR PRESIDENT'S FACE.
WE NEED TO SPEAK TO HIM FROM A
POSITION OF STRENGTH.
SO AS COMMANDER-IN-CHIEFLY iWILL
NOT SPEAK TO HIM UNTIL WE SET UP
THAT NO-FLY ZONE, UNTIL WE HAVE
GATHERED OUR SUNNI ARAB ALLIES.
AND WE THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA ARE GOING TO CUT OFF THE
MONEY FLOW WHICH WE CAN DO AND
DON'T NEED PERMISSION OR
COLLABORATION TO DO AND I WILL
NOT SPEAK TO HIM PERSONALLY
UNTIL WE HAVE REBUILT THE SIXTH
FLEET AND THE MISSILE DEFENSE
PROGRAM AND CONDUCTED MILITARY
EXERCISES IN THE BALTIC STATES.
AND LET US REMEMBER ONE OTHER
THING, HILLARY CLINTON AND
BARACK OBAMA ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR
THE GROWTH OF ISIS BECAUSE THEY
WITHDREW FROM IRAQ IN 2011.
IT'S NOT THESE PEOPLE UP HERE.
IT'S HILLARY CLINTON.
>> THANK YOU MS. FIORINA.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE IF THE U.S.
IMPOSED A NO-FLY ZONE OVER SYRIA
AND A RUSSIAN PLANE ENCROACHED
THAT NO-FLY ZONE WOULD YOU BE
WILLING TO SHOOT DOWN THE PLANE
AND RISK WAR WITH RUSSIA?
>> I WOULD DO IT.
A NO-FLY ZONE MEANS NO-FLY ZONE.
THAT'S WHAT IT MEANS.
I HAVE THIS PLAIN LANGUAGE HANG
UP.
BUT I WOULD NOT TALK TO VLADIMIR
PUTIN.
I WOULD TALK TO VLADIMIR PUTIN A
LOT.
I WOULD SAY TO HIM, LISTEN, MR.
PRESIDENT, THERE IS A NO-FLY
ZONE IN SYRIA AND IT APPLIES TO
YOU.
AND WE WOULD SHOOT DOWN THE
PRESIDENTS, IF THEY THOUGHT THAT
THIS PRESIDENT IS THE SAME
FECKLESS WEAKLING THAT THE
PRESIDENT WE HAVE IN THE OVAL
OFFICE IS RIGHT NOW.
>> SENATOR PAUL?
I WANT YOU TO RESPOND TO WHAT WE
HEARD FROM GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, IF
THERE WAS A NO-FLY ZONE, YOU
SAID THAT POTENTIALLY COULD LEAD
TO WORLD WAR 3, WHY?
>> IF YOU ARE IN FAVOR OF WORLD
WAR III, YOU HAVE YOUR
CANDIDATE.
HERE'S THE THING.
MY GOODNESS, WHAT WE WANT IN A
LEADER IS SOMEONE WITH JUDGMENT
NOT SOMEONE SO RECKLESS AS TO
STAND ON THE STAGE SAYING YES,
I'M GOING TO SHOOT DOWN RUSSIAN
PLANES.
RUSSIA FLIES IN THAT AIR SPACE.
IT MAY OR MAY NOT BE IN LOVE
WITH THE FACT THAT THEY ARE
THERE.
BUT THEY WERE INIT SITED BY IRAQ
AND SYRIA TO FLY IN THAT AIR
SPACE.
IF WE ANNOUNCE A NO-FLY ZONE
IT'S A RECIPE FOR DISASTER AND
WORLD WAR III.
WE NEED TO CONFRONT RUSSIA FROM
A POSITION OF STRENGTH BUT NOT
FROM A POINT OF RECKLESSNESS
THAT WOULD LEAD TO WAR.
THIS IS SOMETHING -- THIS TYPE
OF JUDGMENT IS HAVING THAT KIND
OF JUDGMENT WHO YOU WOULD
APPOINT AND CONDUCT AFFAIRS THAT
IS IMPORTANT.
WHEN WE THINK ABOUT THE JUDGMENT
OF SOMEONE WHO MIGHT WANT WORLD
WAR III WE MIGHT THINK ABOUT
SOMEONE WHO WOULD SHUT DOWN A
BRIDGE BECAUSE THEY DON'T LIKE
THEIR FRIENDS.
I THINK WE NEED TO BE VERY
CAREFUL ABOUT THAT.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE?
>> WHAT RECKLESS IS IS CALLING
AL ASSAD A REFORMER AND ALLOWING
RUSSIA TO COME INTO CRIMEA AND
UKRAINE AND INVITING RUSSIA INTO
SYRIA TO TEAM WITH IRAN AND THE
RECKLESS PEOPLE ARE THE FOLKS IN
THE WHITE HOUSE RIGHT NOW,
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON ARE THE RECKLESS PEOPLE
AND IF YOU THINK THAT A NO-FLY
ZONE IS A RECKLESS POLICY YOU'RE
WELCOME TO YOUR OPINION, BUT HOW
IS IT WORKING SO FAR AS WE HAVE
250,000 SYRIANS MURDERED AND
MILLIONS RUNNING AROUND THE
WORLD RUNNING FOR THEIR LIVES.
WE NEED TO TRY SOMETHING ELSE
AND THAT IS NOT RECKLESS.
>> HUGH?
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, YOU SAID THAT
MR. TRUMP IS NOT QUALIFIED TO
DEAL WITH VLADIMIR PUTIN.
WHY ARE YOU BETTER QUALIFIED
THAN MR. TRUMP?
>> FIRST OF ALL.
I KNOW WHAT I DON'T KNOW.
I WOULD SEEK OUT, AS I HAVE, THE
BEST ADVICE THAT EXISTS.
I WON'T GET MY INFORMATION FROM
THE SHOWS.
I DON'T KNOW IF THAT IS SATURDAY
MORNING OR SUNDAY MORNING.
I DON'T KNOW WHICH ONE.
I WILL SEEK OUT THE BEST ADVICE
AND CREATE A STRATEGY AND PUSH
SUEDE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WHAT
THE ROLE OF AMERICA SHOULD BE.
I'VE LAID OUT A POLICY OF
REBUILDING THE MILITARY.
ALL OF THE TALK WE ARE SEEING
HERE, MOST OF WHICH I AGREE ON,
FRANKLY REQUIRES A MUCH STRONGER
MILITARY.
WE HAVE A LACK OF READINESS THAT
IS SCARY.
WE HAVE PLANES THAT HARRY TRUMAN
INAUGURATED, THE B-52.
THE NAVY HAS BEEN GUTTED AND
DECIMATED.
THE READINESS OF THE MARINES IS
WAY DOWN.
THE ARMED FORCES RADIO IS HERE
LISTENING TODAY.
IF I'M PRESIDENT I'LL BE A
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF NOT AN
AGITATOR OR DIVIDER IN CHIEF.
I WILL LEAD WITH THE COUNTRY IN
A WAY THAT WILL CREATE GREAT
SECURITY AND GREATER SAFETY.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> I THINK IT'S VERY SAD THAT
CNN LEADS JEB BUSH DOWN A ROAD
BY STARTING ALL THE QUESTIONS
MR. TRUMP THIS, MR. TRUMP THAT,
I THINK IT'S VERY SAD.
AND FRANKLY I WATCHED THE FIRST
DEBATE AND THE FIRST LONG NUMBER
OF QUESTIONS WERE MR. TRUMP SAID
THIS, SAID THAT.
THESE POORS -- ALTHOUGH,
SANTORUM, GOOD GUY.
GOVERNOR HUCKABEE GOOD GUY.
BUT IN ORDER TO GET RATINGS, I
GUESS.
>> MR. TRUMP I WAS ON CNN LAST
NIGHT --
>> I THINK IT'S VERY
UNPROFESSIONAL.
>> IT'S NOT CNN.
IT'S AMERICA'S WATCHING YOU.
>> OKAY, FINE.
>> I WAS -- I WAS MENTIONED SO I
CAN BRING UP SOMETHING, IF YOU
THINK THIS IS TOUGH AND YOU ARE
NOT BEING TREATED FAIRLY.
IMAGINE WHAT IT WILL BE LIKE
DEALING WITH PUTIN OR PRESIDENT
XI OR THE ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
>> YOU'RE A TOUGH GUY, JEB.
I KNOW.
>> YOU'RE NEVER GOING TO BE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
BY INSULTING YOUR WAY.
>> I'M AT 42.
SO FAR I'M DOING BETTER.
YOU STARTED OVER HERE AND MOVING
OVER FURTHER AN FURTHER.
>> THIS DOES NOT DO A THING TO
SOLVE THE PROBLEM.
>> HUGH, GO AHEAD.
>> IT SOUNDS MORE AND MORE WHAT
MY DAUGHTER SAID THAT I SAID IN
THE BEGINNING ALL THE FIGHTING
AND ARGUING IS NOT ADVANCING US.
IT IS NOT THE WAY WE'RE GOING TO
STRENGTHEN OUR COUNTRY.
WE WILL STRENGTHEN OUR COUNTRY
WHEN WE COME TOGETHER.
YOU HAVE RAND PAUL AND TED CRUZ
AND MARCO AND A LOT OF PEOPLE
WHO HAVE STUDIED THESE ISSUES.
YOU KNOW WHAT A LEADER DOES?
A LEADER HAS A SOUND PROGRAM,
HAS A GOOD POLICY AND THEN
BRINGS PEOPLE TOGETHER TO SOLVE
PROBLEMS.
GUESS WHAT?
BOTH IN CONGRESS AND IN
BALANCING THE BUDGET IN AN OHIO
FIXING THE ECONOMY AND WE TALK
ABOUT THE FENCE, THE FIRST THING
WE BETTER GET GOING IS
STRENGTHEN OUR ECONOMY, BECAUSE
IF WE DON'T HAVE A STRONG
ECONOMY, WE CAN'T PAY FOR ALL OF
THIS.
AND THE WORLD WANTS US TO BE
ABLE TO FUNCTION FROM STRENGTH,
BELIEVE IT OR NOT.
GET OUR ECONOMY GOING, GET THESE
PEOPLE TOGETHER IN A ROOM.
WE CAN FIX THIS, LADIES AND
GENTLEMEN.
WE DON'T HAVE TO FIGHT ALL THE
TIME.
IT CAN BE DONE AND WE WILL BE
GREAT.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> THANK YOU, HUGH.
>> DR. CARSON,
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF QUESTION.
YOU HAVE BEEN THE HEAD OF
NEUROSURGERY BUT DOES THAT
PREPARE YOU TO COMMAND TROOPS
FROM DJIBOUTI AND JAPAN AND
AFGHANISTAN TO IRAQ TO BE IN
CHARGE OF THE MEN AND WOMEN IN
THE ARMED SERVICES LISTENING
TONIGHT?
>> YOU KNOW, THERE IS A FALSE
NARRATIVE THAT ONLY THE
POLITICAL CLASS HAS THE WISDOM
AND THE ABILITY TO BE
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF.
BUT IF YOU GO BACK AND YOU STUDY
THE DESIGN OF OUR COUNTRY, IT'S
REALLY DESIGNED FOR THE CITIZEN
STATESMAN.
AND WE NEED TO BE TALKING ABOUT
WHERE DOES YOUR EXPERIENCE COME
FROM?
YOU KNOW, AND I'VE HAD A LOT OF
EXPERIENCE BUILDING THINGS.
ORGANIZING THINGS, YOU KNOW, A
NATIONAL SCHOLARSHIP PROGRAM.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT YOU'LL
NOTICE IF YOU LOOK THROUGH MY
LIFE IS I DON'T DO A LOT OF
TALKING.
I DO A LOT OF DOING.
AND REALLY, IT SAYS MORE ABOUT A
PERSON THAN HOW MUCH THEY TALK.
AND SOME PEOPLE SAY YOU'RE WEAK
BECAUSE YOU KNOW YOU'RE NOT LOUD
AND YOU'RE NOT BOISTEROUS AND
YOU'RE NOT RUDE.
BUT THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS,
LOOK AND SEE WHAT I'VE DONE.
AND THAT SPEAKS VOLUMES ABOUT
STRENGTH.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
WE'VE BEEN TALKING TONIGHT ABOUT
PROGRAMS AND POLICY PROPOSALS
THAT YOU ALL HAVE TO KEEP
AMERICANS SAFE AND IT'S A BIG
DISCUSSION ON THE CAMPAIGN
TRAIL.
ALSO ABOUT BORDER SECURITY AND
IMMIGRATION.
SO LET'S TALK ABOUT IMMIGRATION.
SENATOR RUBIO.
Y
YOKO -- YOU CO AUTHORED A BILL
THAT SUPPORTED A PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP TO IMMIGRANTS.
DO YOU STILL SUPPORT THAT PATH
TO CITIZENSHIP?
>> MY FAMILY ARE IMMIGRANTS.
MY WIFE'S FAMILY ARE IMMIGRANTS.
ALL OF MY NEIGHBORS ARE
IMMIGRANTS.
I SEE EVERY ASPECT OF THIS
PROBLEM.
THE GOOD, THE BAD, AND THE UGLY.
IN 2013 WE LEARNED THAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE DON'T TRUST THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO ENFORCE
IMMIGRATION LAWS AND WE WILL NOT
BE ABLE TO DO ANYTHING ON
IMMIGRATION UNTIL WE PROVE TO
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE THAT
IMMIGRATION IS UNDER CONTROL.
WE KNOW WHAT IT TAKES TO DO.
THAT IT TAKES 20,000 ADDITIONAL
BORDER AGENTS AND COMPLETING 700
MILES OF FENCING.
IT TAKES A MANDATORY VERIFY
SYSTEM AND ENTRY/EXIT SYSTEM.
AFTER WE HAVE DONE THAT, THE
SECOND THING WE HAVE TO DO IS
REFORM AND MODERNIZE THE LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM.
AFTER WE HAVE DONE THOSE TWO
THINGS THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WILL
BE REASONABLE WITH WHAT DO YOU
DO WITH SOMEONE WHO HAS BEEN IN
THIS COUNTRY FOR TEN OR 12 YEARS
AND HAVE TO GO UNDER A
BACKGROUND CHECK, PAY A FINE AND
PAY TAXES AND GIVEN A WORK
PERMIT.
BUT YOU CAN'T GET TO THAT THIRD
STEP UNTIL YOU HAVE DONE THE
OTHER TWO THINGS AND THAT WAS
THE LESSON WE LEARNED IN 2013.
THERE IS NO TRUST THAT THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WILL ENFORCE
THE LAW.
THEY WILL NOT SUPPORT YOU UNTIL
YOU SEE IT DONE FIRST.
>> YOU DESCRIBED A LONG PATH BUT
DOES IT END AT CITIZENSHIP?
>> I AM PERSONALLY OPEN AFTER
ALL THAT HAS HAPPENED AND AFTER
TEN YEARS IN PROBATIONARY
STATUS, TIE AM OPEN TO A GREEN
CARD.
YOU CAN'T BEGIN THAT PROCESS
UNTIL YOU PROVE TO PEOPLE NOT
JUST PASS A LAW THAT SAYS YOU
WILL BRING ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION
YOU SHOULD CONTROL YOU HAVE TO
PROVE IT IS WORKING.
THAT IS THE LESSON OF 2013.
AND IT IS MORE TRUE TODAY, AFTER
A MIGRATORY CRISIS WITH MIGRANTS
COMING OVER AFTER ALL THE
EXECUTIVE ORDERS, MORE THAN EVER
WE NEED TO PROVE THAT ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION IS YOU SHOULD
CONTROL.
>>> THANK YOU, SENATOR, SENATOR
CRUZ ON THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL,
SENATOR RUBIO HAS SAID HIS
IMMIG
IMMIGRATION PLAN IS NOT THAT
DIFFERENT FROM YOUS.
IS THAT TRUE?
>> I THINK THAT ANYONE WHO
WATCHED THE BATTLE THAT WE HAD.
THERE WAS A TIME FOR CHOOSING
WHERE REAGAN PUT IT WHERE THERE
WAS A BATTLE OVER AMNESTY AND
SOME CHOSE TO STAND WITH
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND SUPPORT A
MASSIVE AMNESTY PLAN.
OTHERS CHOSE TO STAND WITH JEFF
SESSIONS AND THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
AND SECURE THE BORDER.
THIS ISSUE IS DIRECTLY CONNECTED
TO WHAT WE'VE BEEN TALKING
ABOUT.
THE FRONT LINE WITH ISIS ISN'T
JUST IN IRAQ AND SYRIA, IT'S IN
KENNEDY AIRPORT AND THE RIO
GRANDE.
BORDER SECURITY IS NATIONAL
SECURITY.
AND ONE OF THE MOST TROUBLING
ASPECTS OF THE RUBIO-SCHUMER
GANG OF EIGHT BILL IS IT GAVE
PRESIDENT OBAMA BLANKET
AUTHORITY TO ADMIT REFUGEES.
WE HAVE SEEN WHAT HAPPENED IN
SAN BERNARDINO WHEN YOU ARE
LETTING PEOPLE IN AND THE FBI
CAN'T VET THEM, IT PUTS AMERICAN
CITIZENS AT RISK.
I TELL YOU IF I'M ELECTED
PRESIDENT, WE WILL SECURE THE
BORDER.
WE WILL TRIPLE THE BORDER
PATROL.
WE WILL BUILD A WALL THAT WORKS
AND I'LL GET DONALD TRUMP TO PAY
FOR IT.
>> I'LL BUILD IT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, PLEASE.
>> IN 2013 WE HAD NEVER FACED A
CRISIS LIKE THE SYRIAN REFUGEE
CRISIS NOW.
AS FAR AS TED'S RECORD I'M
PUZZLED BY HIS ATTACK ON THIS
ISSUE.
YOU SUPPORT LEGALIZING PEOPLE
WHO ARE IN THIS COUNTRY
ILLEGALLY AND SUPPORTED A 500%
INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF H 1 V
VISAS AND SUPPORTS DOUBLING THE
NUMBER OF GREEN CARDS.
I THINK WHAT IS IMPORTANT FOR US
TO UNDERSTAND IS THERE IS A WAY
FORWARD ON THIS ISSUE.
AND WHEN I'M PRESIDENT I WILL DO
IT.
IT WILL BEGIN BY BRINGING
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION UNDER
CONTROL AND PROVING IT TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> I UNDERSTAND THAT MARCO WANTS
TO RAISE CONFUSION.
IT IS NOT ACCURATE WHAT HE SAID
THAT I SUPPORTED LEGALIZATION.
I LED THE FIGHT AGAINST HIS
LEGALIZATION AND AMNESTY BILL.
THERE WAS ONE COMMENTATOR THAT
PUT IT THIS WAY, FOR MARCO TO
SUGGEST OUR RECORD IS THE SAME
IS LIKE SUGGESTING THAT THE
FIREMAN AND THE ARSONIST HAVE
THE SAME PLAN BECAUSE THEY WERE
AT THE SAME FIRE.
I WAS FIGHTING TO SECURE THE
BORDER.
AND ON CAMPAIGN TRAILS,
CANDIDATES ALL THE TIME MAKE
PROMISES.
MARCO SAID HE LEARNED THAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE DIDN'T TRUST THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
HE CAMPAIGNED IN FLORIDA
PROMISING --
>> HE CAMPAIGNED TO --
>> LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, THIS IS
WHY THE AMERICAN -- STAND BY,
SENATOR CRUZ CAN YOU ANSWER
THAT --
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> I HAVE NEVER --
>> DO YOU RULE IT OUT?
>> I HAVE NEVER SUPPORTED
LEGALIZATION AND DO NOT INTEND
TO SUPPORT LEGALIZATION.
>> THIS IS WHY THE NATION IS FED
UP WITH THE --
>> ONE AT A TIME, PLEASE.
>> MS. FIORINA, PLEASE WAIT YOUR
TURN.
>> YOU HAVEN'T GOTTEN TO ME.
THIS IS WHY --
>> WHAT YOU DO -- IS YOU ENFORCE
THE LAW.
I'VE LAID OUT A VERY, VERY
DETAILED IMMIGRATION PLAN ON MY
WEBSITE, IT'S 11 PAGES, EXISTING
FEDERAL LAW AND IN PARTICULAR
THE QUESTION OF WHAT TO DO WITH
PEOPLE WHO ARE HERE NOW, YOU
ENFORCE THE LAW.
THAT MEANS YOU STOP THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION'S POLICY OF
RELEASING CRIMINAL ILLEGAL
ALIENS.
YOU KNOW HOW MANY ILLEGAL ALIENS
GEORGE W. BUSH DEPORTED?
10 MILLION.
WE CAN ENFORCE THE LAWS AND IF
WE SECURE THE BORDER THAT SOLVES
THE PROBLEM.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU LIKE TO SAY
THAT YOU RESTARTED THIS
CONVERSATION.
AND THE CAMPAIGN.
>> I THINK I DID.
>> WHO DO YOU SIDE WITH IN THIS?
SENATOR RUBIO OR CRUZ?
>> I HAVE A HARD LINE POSITION,
WE HAVE A COUNTRY OR WE DON'T
HAVE A COUNTRY.
PEOPLE WHO HAVE COME INTO OUR
COUNTRY THEY HAVE TO GO AND COME
BACK THROUGH A LEGAL PROCESS.
WALLS HAVE TO WORK, JUST SPEAK
TO THE FOLKS IN ISRAEL, WALLS
WORK, IF THEY ARE PROPERLY
CONSTRUCTED.
I KNOW HOW TO BUILD.
BUT I FEEL A VERY, VERY STRONG
BIND AND I'M BOUND TO THIS
COUNTRY.
WE EITHER HAVE A BORDER OR WE
DON'T.
PEOPLE CAN COME INTO THE COUNTRY
AND WE WELCOME PEOPLE TO COME IN
BUT THEY HAVE TO COME IN
LEGALLY.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, LISTENING TO
THIS, DO YOU THINK THIS IS THE
TONE, THIS IMMIGRATION DEBATE?
THAT REPUBLICANS NEED TO TAKE TO
WIN BACK HISPANICS INTO YOUR
PARTY ESPECIALLY STATES LIKE
NEVADA THAT HAS A PRETTY LARGE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY.
>> IT ISN'T BUT IT'S AN
IMPORTANT SUBJECT TO TALK ABOUT
FOR SURE AND PEOPLE HAVE GOOD
IDEAS ON.
THIS WE NEED TO SECURE THE
BORDER.
COMING HERE LEGALLY NEEDS TO BE
EASIER THAN COMING HERE
ILLEGALLY.
WE HAVE A NATIONAL SECURITY
CONSIDERATION, AN EPIDEMIC OF
HEROIN OVERDOSES IN ALL SORPTS
OF PLACES BECAUSE OF THE EASE OF
BRINGING HEROIN IN.
WE HAVE TO SECURE THE BORDER.
IT'S A SERIOUS UNDERTAKING AND
WE NEED MORE FENCING AND WE DO
NEED TO USE TECHNOLOGY AND
BORDER CONTROL AND WE NEED TO
HAVE COOPERATION WITH LOCAL LAW
ENFORCEMENT.
THERE ARE 800,000 COPS ON THE
BEAT.
THEY SHOULD BE THE EYES AND EARS
FOR THE THREAT AGAINST TERROR AS
WELL AS FOR IMMIGRATION.
THIS IS A SERIOUS CHALLENGE.
IF WE CAN GET IT RIGHT YEAH,
WE'LL START WINNING VOTES AGAIN.
THE REAL PROBLEM ISN'T ANYONE ON
THIS STAGE.
THE REAL PROBLEM IS BARACK OBAMA
HAS DONE NOTHING.
CONGRESS HAS FUNDED THESE
PROGRAMS OF BUILDING THE FENCING
AND HE HASN'T DONE IT.
HE WANTS TO MAINTAIN IT AS A
WEDGE ISSUE.
REPUBLICANS NEED TO FIX IT.
WHEN WE DO WE'LL BE BETTER OFF.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU VERY
MUCH.
DR. CARSON, YOU RECENTLY VISITED
A REFUGEE CAMP IN JORDAN AND YOU
DEEMED IT REALLY QUITE NICE
SAYING THAT THE PEOPLE THERE
DIDN'T WANT TO COME TO THE
UNITED STATES.
DO YOU THINK THE CAMPS ARE A
LOCK-TERM SOLUTION TO THE
PROBLEM OF SYRIAN REFUGEES?
>> IT WAS VERY INTERESTING TO
HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO TALK TO
THE SYRIANS THEMSELVES.
I ASKED WHAT DO YOU WANT?
WHAT IS YOUR SUPREME DESIRE?
THEIR DESIRE WAS TO BE SETTLED
BACK IN YOUR OWN COUNTRY.
I SAID WHAT CAN AMERICANS DO?
THEY SAID SUPPORT THE EFFORTS OF
THOSE WHO ARE TRYING TO PROVIDE
SAFETY FOR US.
INCLUDING THE JORDANIANS.
OF COURSE THEY HAD A NEW
HOSPITAL, FOR INSTANCE, THAT WAS
UNSTAFFED BECAUSE THERE WASN'T
ENOUGH MONEY TO DO IT.
BUT HERE'S WHAT IS REALLY NEAT
IF YOU GO INTO THE PROVINCE IN
NORTHEASTERN SYRIA, THAT IS AN
AREA AS BIG AS LEBANON
CONTROLLED BY THE KURDS, THE
CHRISTIANS AND THE MODERATE
SUNNIS AND THERE ARE AIRSTRIPS
AND HOTELS, YOU COULD SETTLE A
LOT OF PEOPLE THERE.
ALL WE WOULD HAVE TO DO IS BE
WILLING TO PROVIDE THEM WITH
DEFENSIVE WEAPONRY.
AND WE SEEM TO WITH AFRAID TO
GIVE THE KURDS WEAPONRY.
WE LIKE TO SEND IT THROUGH
BAGHDAD AND THEY GET A TENTH OF
IT.
AND IF WE WOULD SUPPORT THEM WE
HAVE A PERFECT IDEAL THERE WE
DON'T NEED TO SET THIS UP AS WE
EITHER TAKE A BUNCH OF REFUGEES
WHO WILL BE INFILTRATED WITH
TERRORISTS, I GUARANTEE YOU, TO
NOT WOULD BE TERRORIST
MALPRACTICE AND WE HAVE TO
CHOOSE THE RIGHT CHOICE.
>> SENATOR PAUL YOU OPPOSE
LETTING SYRIAN REFUGEES INTO THE
UNITED STATES.
THE UNITED STATES HAS ACCEPTED
2,000 SYRIAN REFUGEES INCLUDING
13 LIVING IN LAS VEGAS RIGHT
NOW.
WOULD YOU SEND THEM BACK?
WHAT WOULD YOU DO WITH THESE
PEOPLE?
>> I THINK WE NEED TO SET THE
RECORD STRAIGHT ON THIS.
I THINK MARCO MISSPOKE ABOUT THE
BILL.
ON THE GANG OF EIGHT BILL THERE
WAS NO EMPHASIS ON SCRUTINY OR
SAFETY FOR REFUGEES.
TWO IRAQI REFUGEES CAME TO MY
TOWN.
THEIR FINGERPRINTS WERE ON A
BOMB IN A DATABASE.
WE GOT THEM ON FOOD STAMPS AND
BEGAN TO PROVIDE FOR THEM BUT
DIDN'T HAVE ADEQUATE SECURITY.
ON MARCO'S BILL WE HAD AN
OPPORTUNITY.
THERE WAS A CONSERVATIVE
CONSENSUS FOR AN AMENDMENT I PUT
FORWARD CALLED TRUST BY VERIFY
WHICH WOULD HAVE STRENGTHENED
BORDER SECURITY AND MARCO WAS
MORE SYMPATHETIC TO THE
PRESIDENT THAN CONSERVATIVE
PRINCIPLES.
IF HE WANTS TO RUN AS A NATIONAL
DEFENSE CONSERVATIVE HE HAS TO
EXPLAIN WHY HE HAS NOT STEPPED
UP TO SUPPORT BORDER SECURITY
IT.
>> AS HE HAS JUST ADMITTED THE
REASON WHY THEY WERE ALLOWED IN
IS THEY MESSED UP ON USING THE
DATABASE.
THEY DID NOT RUN THE WALL AS IT
EXISTS NOW.
IT'S NOT THAT AMERICA DOESN'T
WANT TO ACCEPT REFUGEES WE MAY
NOT BE ABLE TO.
THIS IS AN ISSUE WE HAVE TO BE
100% RIGHT ON.
IF WE ALLOW 900,000 IN BUT ONE
WHO IS AN ISIS KILLER.
WE GET ONE PERSON WRONG AND WE
HAVE A SERIOUS PROBLEM.
THERE IS NOT A SINGLE PERSON IN
THE NATIONAL DEFENSE APPARATUS
OF THE COUNTRY THAT CAN
GUARANTEE YOU WILL BE 100%
RIGHT.
>> SENATOR PAUL YOU DIDN'T
ANSWER THE QUESTION ABOUT THE
2,000 SYRIAN REFUGEES ALREADY
HERE IN THE UNITED STATES.
WILL YOU SEND THEM BACK OR LET
THEM STAY?
>> MY BILL WOULD ONLY BE FOR
GOING FORWARD.
I HAVE NOT TAKEN A POSITION ON
SENDING ANYONE HOME.
BUT WE HAVE A LOT OF PROBLEMS IN
OUR COUNTRY AND ONE OF THE
THINGS THAT WE DO, CHARITY IS
ABOUT GIVING YOUR OWN MONEY, NOT
GIVING SOMEONE ELSE'S MONEY TO
PUT EVERYONE ON GOVERNMENT
HOUSING AND FOOD STAMPS IS A
MISTAKE.
TO GIVE OF YOUR OWN MONEY.
MY CHURCH HAS HELPED PEOPLE THAT
HAVE COME FROM BOSNIA, THAT IS A
GOOD THING.
BUT WE SHOULD NOT JUST TAKE CARE
OF THE WORLD'S REFUGEES.
NO ONE IN THE MIDDLE EAST IS
DOING ANYTHING, SAUDI ARABIA
YEAH, QATAR, KUWAIT.
THEY NEED TO STEP UP.
>> WE HAVE ANOTHER QUESTION FROM
FACEBOOK.
LET'S LISTEN.
>> MY NAME IS CARLA HERNANDEZ
FROM THE UNITED STATES OF TEXAS
AT AUSTIN AND MY QUESTION IS
DIRECTED TO ALL THE CANDIDATES
IF THE BIBLE CLEARLY STATES THAT
WE NEED TO EMBRACE THOSE IN NEED
AND NOT FEAR, HOW CAN WE JUSTIFY
NOT ACCEPTING REFUGEES?
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE YOU SAY
THERE SHOULD BE A PAUSE IN
ALLOWING NEW REFUGEES COMING
INTO THE UNITED STATES INCLUDING
AR FANS UNDER THE AGE OF 5.
>> THE FIRST JOB OF THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
IS TO PROTECT YOUR AND YOUR
SECURITY AND THE SECURITY AND
SAFETY OF YOUR FAMILY.
AND THIS DEBATE STOPS WITH ME IN
THE DISCUSSIONS WITH THE FBI
DIRECTOR.
NOW, LISTEN, I'M A FORMER
FEDERAL PROSECUTE I KNOW JIM
COMEY.
WE WORKED TOGETHER.
WHEN HE GETS UP BEFORE CONGRESS
AND SAYS WE CANNOT EFFECTIVELY
VET THESE PEOPLE, FOR ME AS MT.
THAT IS THE END OF THE
CONVERSATION.
WE HAVE TO PUT AMERICA'S
SECURITY FIRST.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, WE ON THE
STAGE NEED TO OPEN OUR EARS.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE NOT
WHISPERING TO US.
THEY ARE SCREAMING TO US THAT
IT'S OUR JOB TO MAKE THIS
GOVERNMENT WORK.
IT'S SO DYSFUNCTIONAL.
IT'S SO INEFFECTIVE.
IT'S SO INEFECT YUL.
AND IT WAS WIDOWS AND ORPHANS BY
THE WAY AND WE NOW KNOW THAT
WOMEN CAN COMMIT HEINOUS ACTS
AGAINST HUMANITY JUST THE SAME
AS MEN CAN DO IT.
WHEN THE FBI DIRECTOR TELLS ME
THAT HE CAN VET THOSE PEOPLE,
THEN WE'LL CONSIDER IT AND NOT A
MOMENT BEFORE BECAUSE YOUR
SAFETY AND SECURITY IS MOST
IMPORTANT TO ME.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> YOU YOU YOU NEW YORK CITY
OBVIOUSLY, AS PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES WE HAVE TO KEEP
THE PEOPLE SAFE.
THAT'S THE FIRST AND FOREMOST.
AS GOVERNOR OF OHIO I HAVE AN
OBLIGATION TO KEEP THE 11.5
MILLION PEOPLE IN OHIO SAFE.
WE HAVE BEEN ABLE TO MAKE -- WE
MADE ONE AGAINST A PERSON WHO
WAS FAVORABLE TO ISIS LIVING IN
AKRON.
BUT WILL IT ME TELL YOU WHAT IS
INTERESTING ABOUT THE
ADMINISTRATION.
WE HAD CENTRAL AMERICAN MINERS
PLAY -- PLACED IN OHIO.
SOME OF THEM MAY HAVE BEEN HUMAN
TRAFFICKED.
WHEN THE ADMINISTRATION TELLS ME
WE HAVE A GREAT VETTING PROCESS,
THEY SENT THE MINERS TO US, THE
SCHOOLS WERE DISRUPTED.
WE DIDN'T KNOW WHERE THEY WERE,
AND BAD THINGS HAPPENED TO THEM
AND NOW THEY TELL ME WE OUGHT TO
ADMIT THE SYRIAN REFUGEES.
PEOPLE ACCUSE ME OF HAVING TOO
BIG OF A HEART.
BUT I ALSO HAVE TO SAY I MUST
KEEP THE PEOPLE OF MY STATE
SAFE.
SO WE TAKE A PAUSE.
>> THERE IS MUCH MORE COMING UP.
COMING UP, WHAT OTHER GLOBAL HOT
SPOTS AWAIT THE NEXT PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES.
.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
FACEBOOK REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE.
WE'RE HERE AT THE VENETIAN LAS
VEGAS.
WE HAVE BEEN FOCUSING ON THE
MIDDLE EAST BUT LET'S TURN TO
WORLD THREATS YOU WILL
POTENTIALLY FACE AS
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF.
CANDIDATES HERE HAVE CALLED THE
NORTH KOREAN LEADER UNSTABLE.
HE NOW SAYS HE HAS A HYDROGEN
BOMB.
WHAT WOULD YOU DO ABOUT KIM
JONG-UN?
>> HE IS A DANGEROUS MAN.
AND REPUBLICAN AND DEMOCRAT
ADMINISTRATIONS HAVE BEEN
INEFFECTIVE DEALING WITH HIM.
WE NEED CHINA AS PART OF THE
STRATEGY.
CHINA IS A RISING ADVERSARY.
WE HAVE TO PUSH BACK ON CHINA.
THEY, TOO, RECOGNIZE ONE THING,
STRENGTH AND THEIR OWN ECONOMIC
INTEREST.
I KNOW THAT IN ORD TO GET CHINA
TO COOPERATE WITH US WE MUST
FIRST RETALIATE AGAINST THEIR
CYBERATTACKS SO THEY KNOW WE'RE
SERIOUS.
WE HAVE TO PUSH BACK ON THEIR
DESIRE TO CONTROL THE TRADE
ROUTE THROUGH THE SOUTH CHINA
SEA.
WE CANNOT LET THEM CONTROL THE
DISPUTED ISLANDS AND WE MUST
WORK WITH THE AGES, THE SKRAENS,
THE JAPANESE AND THE PHILIPPINES
TO CONTAIN CHINA AND WE MUST ASK
FOR THEIR HELP AND SUPPORT WITH
NORTH KOREAN.
CHINA IS CONCERNED ABOUT KIM
JONG-UN AS WE ARE.
>> DR. CARSON?
WHAT WOULD YOU DO ABOUT KIM
JONG-UN?
>> I DO BELIEVE HE IS UNSTABLE
AND CHINA HAS MORE INFLUENCE
WITH HIM THAN WE DO.
BUT WE ALSO RECOGNIZE THAT NORTH
KOREA IS IN SEVERE FINANCIAL
STRAITS AND THEY HAVE DECIDED TO
USE THEIR RESOURCES TO BUILD
THEIR MILITARY THAN TO FEED
THEIR PEOPLE AND TAKE CARE OF
THE HUMANITARIAN
RESPONSIBILITIES THAT WE HAVE.
WE CAN CAPITALIZE ON.
THAT WE CAN USE THAT TO KEEP
PUTIN CONTAINED.
HE IS A ONE-HORSE SHOW, ENERGY.
AND WE HAVE AN ABUNDANCE OF
ENERGY BUT WE HAVE OR KAYIC
ENERGY EXPOOR STATION RULES.
WE NEED TO GET RID OF THOSE AND
MAKE EUROPE DEPENDENT ON US FOR
ENERGY, PUT HIM BACK IN HIS
LITTLE BOX WHERE HE BELONGS.
AND WE NEED TO DO A LOT OF OTHER
THINGS WITH THE RESOURCES THAT
WE HAVE.
SO THAT ECONOMIC POWER WORKS
JUST AS WELL AS MILITARY POWER,
PERHAPS BETTER.
THE MILITARY NEEDS TO BE
UPGRADED.
YOU LOOK AT THE OHIO GLASS
SUBMARINES, THE MINUTEMAN 3
MISSILES, THE B-52 BOMBERS, YOU
KNOW, IF WE DON'T GET THE
MILITARY RIGHT NOTHING ELSE
MATTERS.
>> DANA AND HUGH YOU HAVE
QUESTIONS.
>> IF YOU SAID IF CHINA LAUNCHES
A CYBERATTACK ON THE U.S. THEY
WILL SEE CYBERWARFARE LIKE THEY
HAVE NEVER SEEN BEFORE.
WHAT WOULD THAT LOOK LIKE?
>> WE HAVE ONE OF THE GREAT
ADVANTAGES OF AMERICA BEING THE
OPEN SOCIETY THAT WE ARE.
WE ARE NOT HIDING THINGS FROM
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE BUT CHINA IS
CONDUCTING BUSINESS IN A WAY
THAT HIDES THINGS FROM THEIR
PEOPLE.
IF THEY WANT TO ATTACK ALL THE
PERSONNEL RECORDS IN THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT WHICH THEY HAVE DONE
AND THEY HAVE MY SOCIAL SECURITY
NUMBER AND FINGERPRINTS AS WELL
AS OTHER FOLKS ON THIS STAGE.
THEY NEED TO BE FOUGHT BACK ON.
AND WE NEED TO GO WITH THE
THINGS THEY ARE MOST SENSITIVE
AND EMBARRASSING TO THEM THAT
THEY ARE HIDING AND GET THAT
INFORMATION AND PUT IT OUT IN
PUBLIC AND LET THE CHINESE
PEOPLE DIGEST HOW CORRUPT THE
GOVERNMENT IS AND HOW THEY ARE
ENRICHING OLIGARCHS ALL
THROUGHOUT CHINA.
AND THIS PRESIDENT HAS SEEN
PERSONNEL RECORDS OF PEOPLE WHO
HAVE SACRIFICED FOR THE AMERICAN
AND FOR THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
STOLEN BY THE CHINESE AND DONE
NOTHING IN RETURN.
THIS IS WHY I SAID AT THE
BEGINNING THAT THIS
ADMINISTRATION, BARACK OBAMA AND
HILLARY CLINTON HAVE BETRAYED
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
IT HAS LED TO PUTIN IN THE
MIDDLE EAST AND EASTERN EUROPE
AND SIGNIFICANT PROBLEMS IN THE
MIDDLE EAST AS WELL.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, WHAT YOU JUST
HEARD FROM GOVERNOR CHRISTIE,
ARE YOU CONCERNED THAT COULD
ESCALATE WITH CHINA AND THEY
COULD RETALIATE AND AS THE NSA
HAS SAID, ATTACK THE U.S. AND
MAYBE ITS POWER GRID WHICH IS
CHINESE HAVE THE CAPABILITY TO
DO?
>> I AGREE WITH CHRIS.
HILLARY CLINTON'S USING A
PRIVATE SERVER FOR WHERE
CLASSIFIED INFORMATION GOES BY.
THIS IS A SERIOUS
ADMINISTRATION?
THE PRESIDENT RECEIVES AN
INSPECTOR GENERAL'S REPORT THAT
THE OFFICE OF PERSONNEL
MANAGEMENT COULD BE HACKED INTO,
23 MILLION FILES HAVE -- ARE IN
THE HANDS OF THE CHINESE,
ALLEGEDLY, INCLUDING BY THE WAY,
MEMBERS OF THE PRESS IT TURNS
OUT LAST WEEK.
SO NOW YOU CAN HAVE A FEEL FOR
WHAT IT IS LIKE TO SEE THIS TYPE
OF ATTACK.
THIS IS SOMETHING WE HAVE TO
HAVE THE BEST DEFENSIVE
CAPABILITIES AND COORDINATE OUR
EFFORTS WITH THE PRIVATE SECTOR
AND OFFENSIVELY WE NEED TO HAVE
CAPABILITIES SECOND TO NONE.
WE NEED TO CREATE A SITUATION
WHERE THEY KNOW THAT THERE WILL
BE ADVERSE IMPACTS IF THEY
CONTINUE TO DO WHAT THEY'RE
DOING.
THEY WILL RESPECT A UNITED
STATES THAT IS SERIOUS ABOUT
PROTECTING OUR INFRASTRUCTURE.
IF WE DON'T DO IT WE WILL
CONTINUE TO SEE WHAT IS
HAPPENING.
THE RUSSIANS AND ROGUE ACTORS,
INCLUDING ISIS, THIS IS A
SERIOUS PART OF THE 21st CENTURY
SECURITY CHALLENGE THAT WE FACE.
>> MR. TRUMP -- DR. CARSON JUST
REFERENCED THE SINGLE MOST
IMPORTANT JOB OF THE PRESIDENT,
THE COMMAND AND CARE AND CONTROL
OF THE MILITARY FORCES.
THE TRY YARD, THE MISSILES AND
SUBMARINES ARE AGING OUT.
IT'S AN EXECUTIVE ORDER.
WHAT IS YOUR PRIORITY?
>> I THINK WE NEED SOMEONE WE
CAN TRUST WHO IS TOTAL
RESPONSIBILITY WHO KNOWS WHAT HE
OR SHE IS DOING THAT IS SO
POWERFUL AND SO IMPORTANT.
AND ONE OF THE THINGS THAT I'M
FRANKLY MOST PROUD OF IS THAT IN
2003, 2004, I WAS AGAINST GOING
INTO IRAQ BECAUSE YOU ARE GOING
TO DESTABILIZE THE MIDDLE EAST.
I CALLED IT VERY STRONGLY AND IT
WAS VERY IMPORTANT.
BUT WE HAVE TO BE EXTREMELY
VIGILANT AND CAREFUL WHEN IT
COMES TO NUCLEAR.
NUCLEAR CHANGES THE WHOLE BALL
GAME.
I WOULD HAVE SAID GET OUT OF
SYRIA.
IF WE DIDN'T HAVE THE POWER OF
WEAPONRY TODAY, THE POWER IS SO
MASSIVE THAT WE CAN'T JUST LEAVE
AREAS THAT 50 YEARS AGO WE
WOULDN'T CARE, IT WAS HAND TO
HAND COMBAT.
THE BIGGEST PROBLEM THIS WORLD
HAS TOO IS NOT PRESIDENT OBAMA
WITH GLOBAL WARMING WHICH IS
INCONCEIVABLE, THIS IS WHAT HE'S
SAYING.
THE BIGGEST PROBLEM WE HAVE
TODAY IS NUCLEAR PROLIFERATION
ANDING ARE SOME MANIAC, HAVING
SOME MADMAN GO OUT AND GET A
NUCLEAR WEAPON.
IN MY OPINION, THAT IS THE
SINGLE BIGGEST PROBLEM THAT OUR
COUNTRY FACES RIGHT NOW.
>> OF THE THREE LEGS OF THE TRY
Y
TRIAD DO YOU HAVE A --
>> IT'S IMPORTANT.
>> MAYBE A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE
NOT HEARD THAT TERMINOLOGY, IT'S
THE ABILITY OF THE UNITED STATES
TO CONDUCT NUCLEAR ATTACKS USING
AIRPLANES, FROM THE GROUND AND
FROM OUR NUCLEAR SUBS.
ALL THREE ARE CRITICAL.
IT GIVES US THE ABILITY AT
DETERRENCE.
SOME ARE MORE CRITICAL THAN
OTHERS.
THE OHIO CLASS SUBMARINE NEEDS
TO BE MODERNIZED.
THE B-52 AS SOMEONE POINTED OUT
IS AN OUTDATED MODEL THAT WAS
FLOWN BY THE GRANDPARENTS OF THE
PEOPLE FLYING IT NOW.
AND WE NEED AN UPGRADE ON THE
SILO-LAUNCHED MISSILES.
>> SOME OF YOU HAVE QUESTIONED
WHETHER YOUR OPPONENTS HAVE THE
RIGHT TEMPERAMENT TO BE IN
CONTROL OF THE NUCLEAR CODES.
DANA YOU HAVE A QUESTION ON
THIS.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU SAID THIS
WEEKEND THAT SENATOR CRUZ IS NOT
QUALIFIED TO BE PRESIDENT
BECAUSE HE DOES NOT HAVE THE
RIGHT TEMPERAMENT AND ACTED LIKE
A MANIAC.
BUT LAST MONTH YOU SAID YOU WERE
OPEN TO NAMING SENATOR CRUZ AS
YOUR RUNNING MATE.
>> I DID.
>> I HAVE GOTTEN TO KNOW HIM
OVER THE LAST THREE OR FOUR
DAYS, HE HAS A WONDERFUL
TEMPERAMENT.
HE'S JUST FINE.
DON'T WORRY ABOUT IT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
YOU HAVE NOT BEEN WILLING TO
ATTACK MR. TRUMP IN PUBLIC.
BUT YOU --
>> YOU BETTER NOT ATTACK.
>> BUT YOU QUESTIONED HIS
JUDGMENT IN HAVING CONTROL OF
MARK'S NUCLEAR ARSENAL.
WHY ARE YOU WILLING TO SAY
THINGS IN PRIVATE AND NOT IN
PUBLIC.
>> I SAID THAT THE JUDGMENT THAT
EVERY VOTER IS MAKING OF EVERY
ONE OF US UP HERE IS WHO HAS THE
EXPERIENCE, WHO HAS THE VISION,
WHO HAS THE JUDGMENT TO BE
CHANDLER
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF.
THAT IS A STANDARD I'M HELD TO.
AND IN THE COURSE OF THIS
DISCUSSION ABOUT OUR FOREIGN
POLICY THREATS IT ILLUSTRATES
THE NEED FOR CLARITY OF FOCUS.
MY DAUGHTERS, CAROLINE AND
KATHERINE CAME TONIGHT.
THEY ARE 7 AND 5.
YOU THINK ABOUT THE LOS ANGELES
SCHOOLS CANCELLING THEIR SCHOOLS
TODAY.
AND EVERY PARENT IS WONDERING
HOW DO WE KEEP OUR KIDS SAFE?
WE NEED A COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF
THAT DID WHAT REAGAN DID.
HE SET OUT A STRATEGY TO DEFEAT
COMMUNISM.
ONE OF THE THINGS WE'VE SEEN
HERE IS HOW EASY IT IS FOR
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON TO BE DISTRACTED FROM
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO STANDS
UP AND SAYS WE WILL DEFEAT ISIS
AND SAYS THE GREATEST
NATIONAL --
>> A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE SEEN --
>> A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE SEEN
THESE COMMENTS YOU MADE IN
PRIVATE.
WHAT YOU ARE SAYING IS THAT YOU
DO BELIEVE THAT MR. TRUMP HAS
THE JUDGMENT TO BE
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF?
>> THAT IS A JUDGMENT FOR EVERY
VOTER TO MAKE.
BUT ALL NINE OF THE PEOPLE HERE
WOULD MAKE AN INFINITELY BETTER
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF THAN BARACK
OBAMA OR HILLARY CLINTON.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> AND THERE IS A REAL DANGER,
DANA WHEN PEOPLE GET DISTRACTED.
>> THANK YOU --
>> I'M ANSWERING THE QUESTION.
THERE IS A DANGER WHEN PEOPLE
ARE DISTRACTED BY PERIPHERAL
QUESTIONS AND MILITARY CONFLICT.
WE NEED TO FOCUS ON DEFEATING
JIHADISM, ISIS AND IRAN HAVE
DECLARED WAR ON AMERICA AND WE
NEED A COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF WHO
WILL DO EVERYTHING NECESSARY TO
KEEP OUR CHILDREN SAFE AND I
WILL DO EVERYTHING --
>> WE ARE A MONTH AND A HALF
AWAY FROM THE FIRST REAL TEST
WHO WILL BE THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL NOMINEE.
HUGH?
>> MY LISTENERS ARE WORRIED THAT
HILLARY CLINTON IS GOING TO WIN
BECAUSE YOU WILL RUN AS AN
INDEPENDENT.
WILL YOU ASSURE THE PEOPLE THAT
YOU WILL RUN AS A REPUBLICAN?
>> I REALLY AM.
>> DR. CARSON?
--
>> CAN I JUST FINISH?
>> PLEASE.
>> I'VE GAINED GREAT RESPECT FOR
THE REPUBLICAN LEADERSHIP.
I'VE GAINED GREAT RESPECT FOR
MANY -- IN DIFFERENT FORMS FOR
THE PEOPLE ON THE DIAS.
I HAVE GREAT RESPECT FOR THE
PEOPLE I HAVE MET IN THIS
PROCESS.
BUT I WILL TELL YOU, I AM
TOTALLY COMMITTED TO THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY.
I FEEL VERY HONORED TO BE THE
FRONT RUNNER.
AND I THINK I'LL DO VERY WELL IF
I'M CHOSEN IF I'M SO FORTUNATE
TO BE CHOSEN.
POLLS HAVE COME OUT RECENTLY
THAT SAY I WILL BEAT HILLARY.
>> DR. CARSON, MR. TRUMP JUST
COMMITTED TO STAY THE DISTANCE
REGARDLESS OF THE RESULT.
HOW ABOUT YOU?
>> THE STATEMENT THAT I WOULD
LEAVE THE PARTY WAS CONTINGENT
UPON WHETHER IN FACT THE PARTY
ACTS LIKE THEY HAVE IN THE PAST
WITH A LOT OF SUBTERFUGE.
AND I HAVE BEEN ASSURED THAT THE
WASHINGTON POST WRITER HAD IT
ALL WRONG AND THEY WILL NOT BE
ENGAGING IN ANYTHING TO THWART
THE WILL OF THE PEOPLE.
THAT'S WHY I GOT INTO THIS RACE
AS A MEMBER OF WE THE PEOPLE TO
BRING BACK HONESTY TO THE
PROCESS.
>> WHEN WE COME BACK, EVERYONE
WILL HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO
EXPLAIN WHY THIS PARTICULAR
CANDIDATE, EACH OF YOU ON THE
STAGE, BELIEVES HE OR SHE SHOULD
BE THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
NOMINEE.
>>> IT'S TIME FOR CLOSING
STATEMENTS.
SENATOR PAUL?
>> THE GREATEST THREAT TO
NATIONAL SECURITY IS OUR DEBT.
WE BORROW A MILLION DOLLARS A
MINUTE AND WHOSE FAULT IS IT IN
YOU HAVE THOSE ON THE RIGHT WHO
SAP WE WON'T SPEND ANYTHING ON
THE MILITARY AND THE SAME ON THE
LEFT WHO SAY THE SAME FOR
DOMESTIC WELFARE.
BUT THERE IS AN UNHOLY ALLIANCE
AND WE WE SPEND MORE MONEY ON
EVERYTHING.
WE ARE NOT STRONGER IF WE GO
FURTHER INTO DEBT.
WE ARE NOT PROJECTING POWER FROM
BANKRUPTCY COURT.
THERE IS NO GREATER THREAT THAN
OUR DEBT AND I'M WILLING TO HOLD
THE LINE ON ALL SPENDING.
I HOPE YOU WILL CONSIDER ME IN
THE ELECTION.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> NO REPUBLICAN HAS EVER BEEN
ELECTED PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES WITHOUT WINNING OHIO.
LET ME GIVE YOU A TIP ON HOW TO
WIN OHIO, IT'S REFORM, IT'S
HOPE, IT'S GROWTH, IT'S
OPPORTUNITY, AND IT'S SECURITY.
THE PEOPLE OF OHIO ARE THE
PEOPLE OF AMERICA.
THE PEOPLE OF AMERICA ARE
REFLECTED IN OHIO.
OUR MESSAGE HAS TO BE BIG.
AND BOLD, AND POSITIVE AND
CONNECT, NOT JUST WITH PEOPLE'S
HEADS BUT ALSO CONNECT WITH
THEIR HEARTS.
IF WE DO IT, WE WILL BEAT
HILLARY CLINTON AND WE WILL RUN
THE WHITE HOUSE AND WE WILL FIX
AMERICA.
>>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE?
>> I WAS NAMED CHIEF FEDERAL
PROSECUTOR OF NEW JERSEY AND ON
SEPTEMBER 11st 2001, I LOST
TOUCH WITH MY RELATIVES AND
PRAYING THEY WERE ALIVE.
THEY WERE SENT HOME.
MANY OF OUR FRIENDS AND OTHERS
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD LOST THEIR
LIVES THAT DAY.
TERRORISM, RADICAL JIHADIST
TERRORISM IS NOT THEORETICAL TO
ME.
IT'S REAL.
FOR SEVEN YEARS I SPENT MY LIFE
PROTECTING OUR COUNTRY AGAINST
ANOTHER ONE OF THOSE ATTACKS.
YOU WON'T WORRY WHEN I'M
PRESIDENT WHETHER IT CAN BE
DONE.
I HAVE ALREADY DONE IT.
IF YOU GIVE ME THE CHANCE AND
GIVE ME YOUR VOTE I WILL PROTECT
AMERICA FROM THE WARS BROUGHT TO
OUR DOORSTEP.
>> MISS FIORINA?
>> I, TOO, REMEMBER SEPTEMBER
11th.
I REMEMBER IMMEDIATELY PUTTING
INTO PLACE SECURITY PROCEDURES
ALL THROUGHOUT OUR COUNTRY THAT
DID BUSINESS IN 170 COUNTRIES
WHERE WE THOUGHT CORPORATE
INTERESTS WOULD BE ATTACKED
NEXT.
TO TAKE OUR COUNTRY BACK, TO
KEEP OUR NATION SAFE, WE HAVE TO
BEGIN BY BEATING HILLARY
CLINTON.
WE NEED TO UNIFY OUR PARTY.
WE NEED TO BE BETTER THAN OUR
GOVERNMENT WHICH 75% OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE NOW THINK IS
CORRUPT AND INCOMPETENT.
WE NEED TO BE BETTER THAN OUR
POLITICS.
WE HAVE 80% OF THE PEOPLE WHO
THIV WE HAVE A PROFESSIONAL
POLITICAL CLASS.
WE NEED TO UNIFY OUR PARTY.
WE NEED A CONSERVATIVE IN THE
WHITE HOUSE AND WE NEED TO BEAT
HILLARY CLINTON TO TAKE OUR
COUNTRY BACK AND KEEP OUR NATION
SAFE.
I CAN.
I AM.
AND TOGETHER, IF YOU JOIN ME, WE
WILL TAKE OUR COUNTRY BACK.
>>> GOVERNOR BUSH?
>> ASK YOURSELF, WHICH CANDIDATE
WILL KEEP YOU AND OUR COUNTRY
SAFER, STRONGER, AND FREER?
HILLARY CLINTON HAS ALIGNED
HERSELF WITH BARACK OBAMA ON
ISIS, IRAN, AND THE ECONOMY.
IT'S AN ALLIANCE DOOMED TO FAIL.
MY PLANS WILL FORTIFY OUR
NATIONAL AND ECONOMIC SECURITY.
AND MY RECORD AS GOVERNOR WILL
GIVE YOU A SENSE I DON'T MAKE
FALSE PROMISES.
I DELIVER REAL RESULTS.
FOR AMERICA TO BE SAFE AND SOUND
I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> AS WE NEAR THE ENOF THE YEAR
WE ENTER ONE OF THE MOST
IMPORTANT ELECTIONS IN A
GENERATION.
WHAT IS AT STAKE IS NOT JUST WHO
IS IN CHARGE BUT OUR IDENTITY AS
A PEOPLE AND A NATION.
FOR OVER 200 YEARS THIS IS A
UNIQUE PLACE WHERE ANYONE FROM
ANYWHERE CAN ACHIEVE ANYTHING.
AND MILLIONS OF AMERICANS FEEL
LIKE THEY ARE BEING LEFT BEHIND
INSECURE IN THEIR FUTURE AND
UNSAFE IN THE FACE OF TERRORISM.
THIS IS ABOUT ELECTING A
PRESIDENT SO THAT THE AMERICAN
DREAM CAN EXPAND AND REACH MORE
PEOPLE AND CHANGE MORE LIVES
THAN EVER BEFORE AND REBUILD OUR
MILITARY SO WE CAN REMAIN THE
STRONGEST NATION ON EARTH.
I ASK FOR YOUR VOTE.
IF YOU DO THIS, WE WILL REBUILD
THIS COUNTRY AND USHER IN THE
GREATEST ERA IN THE HISTORY OF
THIS GREAT LAND.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> JUDGMENT.
STRENGTH.
CLARITY AND TRUST.
BARACK OBAMA AS SAID HE DOESN'T
BELIEVE IN AMERICAN LEADERSHIP
OR AMERICA WINNING, HE IS WRONG.
AMERICA CAN WIN AGAIN AND WE
WILL WIN AGAIN.
RONALD REAGAN REIGNITED THE
AMERICAN ECONOMY, REBUILT THE
MILITARY AND I WILL DO THE SAME.
UNLEASHING SMALL BUSINESSES AND
REBUILDING THE MILITARY.
OUR STRATEGY IS SIMPLE.
WE WIN, THEY LOSE.
WE'VE DONE IT BEFORE.
AND WE CAN DO IT AGAIN.
>> DR. CARSON?
>> I HAVE BEEN FORTUNATE ENOUGH
TO TRAVEL TO 58 DIFFERENT
COUNTRIES.
AND I THANK GOD EVERY DAY I WAS
BORN IN THIS COUNTRY, THE MOST
EXCEPTIONAL COUNTRY THAT THE
WORLD HAS EVER KNOWN.
AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE THAT WE
PRESERVE THAT EXCEPTIONALISM FOR
THE NEXT-GENERATION.
MY MOTHER TOLD ME IF I WORK HARD
AND I BELIEVED IN THE AMERICAN
PRINCIPLES AND I BELIEVED IN GOD
ANYTHING IS POSSIBLE.
I BELIEVE THAT IS TRUE.
THAT'S WHY I'M NOT ANXIOUS TO
GIVE AWAY AMERICAN PRINCIPLES
FOR THE SAKE OF POLITICAL
CORRECTNESS.
>> OUR COUNTRY DOESN'T WIN
ANYWHERE.
WE DON'T WIN ON TRADE.
WE DON'T WIN ON THE MILITARY.
WE CAN'T DEFEAT ISIS.
WE'RE NOT TAKING CARE OF OUR
GREAT PEOPLE, THE VETERANS,
WE'RE NOT TAKING CARE OF THEM.
WE HAVE TO CHANGE OUR WHOLE WAY,
OUR HEALTH CARE SYSTEM IS A
DISASTER.
IT'S GOING TO IMPLODE IN 2017.
IT DOESN'T WORK.
NOTHING WORKS IN OUR COUNTRY.
IF I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT WE WILL
WIN AGAIN.
WE WILL WIN A LOT AND WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE A GREAT, GREAT
COUNTRY, GREATER THAN EVER
BEFORE.
THANK YOU.
>> THANKS TO ALL THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES.
THAT DOES IT FOR THIS REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
ON BEHALF OF EVERYONE AT CNN AND
THE VENETIAN, LAS VEGAS.
WE WANT TO WISH EVERYONE A VERY
MERRY CHRISTMAS, HAPPY HOLIDAYS
ESPECIALLY TO THE SOLDIERS,
SAILORS, AIRMEN AND MARINE
PROTECTING US AROUND THE WORLD