>>> GOOD EVENING.
TONIGHT LIVE HERE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA, DEMOCRATS WILL GET A
CHANCE TO SEE THEIR CANDIDATES
IN A DIFFERENT WAY.
FACE-TO-FACE WITH THE VOTERS,
MEN AND WOMEN LIVING WITH REAL
PROBLEMS THAT DEMAND REAL
SOLUTIONS.
SO LET'S SEE IF SENATOR BERNIE
SANDER AND SECRETARHILLARY CLIN
>>> TONIGHT THE DEMOCRATS TURN
TO FACE VOTERS BEFORE THEIR
FIRST CHANCE TO WIN IN THE
SOUTH.
>> SOUTH CAROLINA HAS THE
OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE AMERICAN
HISTORY.
>> THE FIGHT GOES ON, THE FUTURE
THAT WE WANT IS WITHIN OUR
GRASP.
>> BERNIE SANDERS, VICTOR IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, PROMISING VICTORY IN
NOVEMBER.
>> YOU HAVE A CANDIDATE WHO WILL
BEAT DONALD TRUMP, YOU'RE
LOOKING AT THAT CANDIDATES.
>> HILLARY CLINTON, IOWA WINNER,
NEVADA WINNER, TALKING
COMMITMENT.
>> I AM GOING TO FIGHT FOR YOU,
BECAUSE WE'VE GOT TO KNOCK DOWN
EVERY BARRIER THAT IS HOLDING
AMERICANS BACK.
>> TWO CANDIDATES CONNECTING
WITH THE VOTERS BEFORE DECIDING
WHO WILL GET THE MOST IMPORTANT
JOB IN THIS COUNTRY.
>> I JUST LOVE ANSWERING
QUESTIONS AND MAKING CLEAR WHERE
I STAND.
>> THIS IS A BRILLIANT AUDIENCE,
WITH PEOPLE THIS SMART, WE CAN'T
LOSE.
>> THIS IS A CNN DEMOCRATIC TOWN
HALL EVENT, A CHANCE FOR VOTERS
TO GET ANSWERS, BEFORE A PRIMARY
THAT CAN MAKE OTHER BREAK A
CAMPAIGN.
SOUTH CAROLINA IS CHOOSING, THE
DEMOCRATS ARE IN THE SPOTLIGHT,
AND THEY'RE TALKING TO VOTERS
RIGHT NOW.
¶
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> HELLO FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF
SOUTH CAROLINA, SCHOOL OF LAW
HERE IN THE STATE CAPITAL OF
COLUMBIA.
WE'RE SIMULCASTING LIVE ON CNN,
CNN ENESPANOL, ALSO ON THE ARMED
FORCES NETWORK AND CNN'S
SIRIUS/XM CHANNEL 116.
SO WELCOME TO ALL OF YOU.
ANDERSON COOPER WAS HERE LAST
WEEK WITH THE REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES.
TONIGHT IT IS THE DEMOCRATS'
TURN.
VOTERS ARE IN CONTROL, SOME
UNDECIDED, SOME NOT.
ALL WITH SOMEBODY TO SAY OR TO
ASK TO SENATOR SANDERS OR
SECRETARY CLINTON.
THEY CAME UP WITH THE QUESTIONS.
WE REVIEWED THEM TO MAKE SURE
THE QUESTIONS DON'T OVERLAP.
WHEN I SAY THEM, THE VOTERS CAME
UP WITH THE QUESTIONS.
BE CLEAR ON THAT.
I'M GOING TO ASK A FEW AS WELL.
TONIGHT AS ALWAYS, IT REALLY IS
ABOUT YOU, THE VOTERS.
NOW, SENATOR SANDERS ASKED TO GO
FIRST.
SECRETARY CLINTON WAS FINE WITH
THAT, SO LET'S GET AFTER IT.
JOINING US RIGHT NOW IS THE U.S.
SENATOR FROM VERMONT, BERNIE
SANDERS.
>>> IS THE CHAIR GOOD?
>> PRETTY GOOD.
THE TIE GOOD?
YOU LIKE IT?
>> VERY NICE.
>> SO A LOT OF PEOPLE THOUGHT
YOU WOULD NOT BE SITTING WHERE
YOU ARE RIGHT NOW, BUT HERE WE
ARE, THREE CONTESTS IN.
YOU AND SECRETARY CLINTON
SEPARATED BY ONE DELEGATE, THE
SAME NUMBER PLEDGED.
YOU'RE IN THIS THING.
WHAT DOES IT MEAN TO YOU TO BE
HERE TONIGHT?
>> WELL, IT IS KIND OF
MIND-BLOWING THE PROGRESS WE
HAVE MADE OVER THE LAST NINE
MONTHS.
YOU AND I HAVE BEEN CHATTING FOR
A LONG TIME.
WHEN I BEGAN WE WERE 3% IN THE
POLLS.
TO BE HONEST, MOST PEOPLE
CONSIDERED US A FRINGE CAMPAIGN,
NEVER GOING TO GO ANY PLACE.
TODAY IN THE NATIONAL POLLS WE
HAVE CLOSED THE GAP TO SINGLE
DIGITS, ACTUALLY ONE POLL HAD US
AHEAD.
IN IOWA, I WAS 50 POINTS DOWN,
WE HAD A VIRTUAL TIE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, 30 POINTS DOWN, WE
WON.
IN NEVADA, WE WERE WAY WAY DOWN,
CAME WITHIN FIVE POINTS.
SOUTH CAROLINA, WE STARTED HERE
7%, 8% IN THE POLLS.
WE HAVE NARROWED THAT.
I THINK WHAT IT MEANS TO ME IS
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE
RESPONDING TO OUR MESSAGE THAT
WE HAVE A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM, IN WHICH
BILLIONAIRES TODAY ARE BUYING
ELECTIONS AND UNDERMINING
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY.
WE HAVE A RIGGED ECONOMY IN
WHICH THE ORDINARY PEOPLE ARE
WORKING LONGER HOURS FOR LOWER
WAGES, ALMOST ALL NEW INCOME AND
WEALTH GOING TO THE TOP 1%, AND
WE HAVE A BROKEN CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM IN WHICH WE HAVE
MORE PEOPLE IN JAIL TODAY THAN
ANY OTHER COUNTRY ON EARTH,
LARGELY AFRICAN-AMERICAN AND
LARGELY LATINO.
WHAT IT MEANS TO ME AND WHY OUR
CAMPAIGN HAS BEEN DOING SO WELL,
I THINK PEOPLE ARE SAYING ENOUGH
WITH ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS AND
ESTABLISHMENT DMIKS.
WE NEED A POLITICAL REVOLUTION
IN WHICH MILLIONS COME TOGETHER
AND SAY YOU KNOW WHAT?
ALL OUR GOVERNMENT BELONGS TO
ALL OF US.
YOU'RE SENSITIVE IS YOU HAVE
CO-OPTED THE CNN COUNTDOWN
CLOCK.
I'M NOT HERE TO COME AFTER IT,
BUT JUST AS YESTERDAY SAID, IT'S
BEEN 17 DAYS, 16 HOURS, AND 32
MINUTES SINCE SHE SAID SHE WOULD
LOOK INTO -- CLINTON SAYS SHE
WILL DO THAT WHEN OTHER
CANDIDATES RELEASE THEIR
TRANSCRIPTS.
I KNOW YOU'RE SAYING I DON'T
TALK TO THE BASICS I DON'T HAVE
ANY, BUT YOU HAVE DONE SPEECHES
THAT WERE PAID BEFORE IF --
>> THAT'S NOT A PROBLEM.
LOOK, I HAVE NOT HAD A PAID
SPEECH, IT'S AGAINST THE LAW TO
GET PAID SPEECHES.
I HAVE GIVEN SOME SPEECHES, THE
MONEY WAS DONATED TO SPEECHES.
WAY WAY BACK I GOT A FEW
DOLLARS.
BUT WHAT SECRETARY CLINTON SAID,
I WILL DO IT IF OTHER PEOPLE
WILL DO IT.
I AM HAPPY TO RELEASE ALL OF MY
PAGES TO WALL STREET.
HERE IT IS, CHRIS -- THERE AIN'T
NONE.
I DON'T DO THAT.
I DON'T GET -- I DON'T GET
SPEAKER'S FEAES FROM GOLDMAN
SACHS.
IT'S NOT THERE.
I'M HAPPY TO RELEASE THEM.
IT WON'T BE SHOCKING TO ANYBODY.
>>> I KNOW IT'S BEEN A WHILE
AGO, BUT REPORTED IN 1974 --
>> THAT'S A WHILE AGO.
>> -- YOU SAID THE CIA IS A
DANGEROUS INSTITUTION THAT'S GOT
TO GO.
YOU WENT ON TO SAY IT WAS
ACCOUNTABLE TO NO ONE EXCEPT
RIGHT-WING LUNATICS TO PROP UP
FASCIST DICTATORSHIPS.
DO YOU STAND BY THOSE COMMENTS?
>> THAT WAS 40 YEARS AGO.
SINCE THEN I'VE SERVED AS MARE
YOR OF THE CITY OF BURLINGTON.
16 YEARS IN THE HOUSE AND NINE
YEARS IN THE UNITED STATES
SENATE, BUT LET ME TELL YOU
THIS.
I DO HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT PAST
ACTIVITIES OF THE CIA.
CIA WAS INVOLVED IN THE
OVERTHROW OF A GENTLEMAN NAMED
MOHAMMED MOZADEK WAY BACK WHEN
IN IRAN, OVERTHREW HIM ON BEHALF
OF BRITISH OIL.
YOU KNOW WHAT HAPPENED?
THAT LED TO THE IRANIAN
REVOLUTION AND WE ARE WHERE WE
ARE TODAY.
THE CIA WAS INVOLVED IN THE
OVERTHROW OF SALVADOR ALLENDE, A
DEMOCRAT ECWHO WON AN ELECTION,
THE CIA OVERTHREW HIM.
SO I HAVE PROBLEMS WITH SOME
PARTS OF OUR HISTORY WHICH
CONTINUES, BY THE WAY TO THE
PRESENT.
>> BUT THE INSTITUTION ITSELF?
>> THE CIA PLAYS AN IMPORTANT
ROLE.
HAVE THEY DONE THINGS THAT THEY
SHOULD NOT HAVE DONE ON BEHALF
OF THE UNITED STATES GO.
?
ABSOLUTELY.
>> OKAY.
NOW, IN THE HEADLINES, TODAY THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION RELEASED
ITS PLAN FOR CLOSING GUANTANAMO.
YOU SAID THIS IS A GOOD PLAN.
PART OF THE PLAN INVOLVES THE
NAVAL BRIG HERE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA, IN CHARLESTON THAT ONE
DAY COULD HOUSE DETAINEES.
I'M SURE THERE IS CONCERN IN THE
AUDIENCE TONIGHT ABOUT SOME OF
THE WORST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD
BEING IN THEIR BACKYARD.
WHY IS THAT OKAY?
>> WHAT IS OKAY IS, LOOK, WE
LOOK LIKE HYPOCRITES AND FOOLS
TO THE ENTIRE WORLD.
WHAT WE HAVE DONE IS LOCKED UP
PEOPLE IN A WAY THAT IS CAUSING
ALL KINDS OF REPERCUSSIONS
AROUND THE WORLD.
PEOPLE SAY YOU'RE A DEMOCRATIC
SOCIETY, WE HAVE LOCKED PEOPLE
UP IN AN ISLAND.
I THINK THAT HAS HURT US ALL
OVER THE WORLD.
OBVIOUSLY IF P PEOPLE ARE
TERRORISTS, THEY NEED TO BE
CONFINED, AND WE NEED TO MAKE
SURE THEY STAY IN JAIL UNTIL
WHATEVER HAPPENS.
BUT I THINK THE PRESIDENT IS
RIGHT.
I THINK WE SHOULD SHUT DOWN
GUANTANAMO.
I THINK IN THE LONG RUN IT WILL
HELP US SIGNIFICANTLY.
>> ARE YOU READY TO TALK TO THE
VOTERS?
>> THAT'S WHY I'M IN SOUTH
CAROLINA.
>> I KNOW, YOU DIDN'T COME HERE
BECAUSE OF ME.
>> SYLVIA JOHNSON, ONE OF THE --
SHE SAYS SHE IS UNDECIDED.
SYLVIA, THANK YOU FOR BEING
HERE.
WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION FOR THE
SENATOR?
>> GOOD EVENING.
SO GLAD TO BE HERE.
MY QUESTION IS, DO YOU THINK AN
INDIVIDUAL WHO LEGALLY PURCHASED
A GUN SHOULD BE ALLOWED TO CARRY
IT OPENLY IN A PUBLIC ARENA?
SUCH AS PLACES OF WORSHIP,
SCHOOLS IS PUBLIC PLACES?
AND IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, WOULD
YOU CHANGE THE GUN-FREE SCHOOL
ZONE ACT BY ALLOWING STAFF,
TEACHERS AND AT MARCH TORS TO
CARRY AGAINST IN ORDER TO DEFEND
THE STUDENTS AND THEMSELVES?
>> TO BEGIN WITH, LET ME JUST
SAY THIS.
I HAVE A D-MINUS VOTING RECORD
FROM THE NRA.
I PROBABLY LOST AN ELECTION WAY
BACK IN 1988 BECAUSE I SAID THAT
I DIDN'T THINK IT WAS PROPER IN
THIS COUNTRY THAT MILITARY-STYLE
ASSAULT WEAPONS BE SOLD.
NOW, THE ISSUES THAT YOU RAISE
ARE OFTEN SIGNIFICANTLY STATE
ISSUES.
IF I WAS THE GOVERNOR OF A
STATE, WOULD I BE SUPPORTIVE OF
PEOPLE TAKING GUNS INTO HOUSES
OF WORSHIP?
NO, I WOULD NOT.
THAT'S NOT SOMETHING THAT I AM
COMFORTABLE WITH, BUT THAT'S A
DECISION BEING MADE BY THE
STATE.
WHAT I WILL TELL YOU, AT THE
FEDERAL LEVEL, IS THAT WE HAVE
GOT TO DO EVERYTHING WE CAN TO
EXPAND AND IMPROVE THE INSTANT
BACKGROUND CHECK.
OUR GOAL MUST BE TO MAKE SURE
THAT PEOPLE WHO SHOULD NOT HAVE
WEAPONS, GUNS, DO NOT HAVE GUNS.
THAT MEANS PEOPLE OF CRIMINAL
BACKGROUNDS, PEOPLE WHO ARE
MENTALLY UNSTABLE.
WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH THE STRAW
MAN PROVISION RIGHT NOW WHICH
ALLOWS PEOPLE TO LEGALLY BUY
GUNS, AND THEN SELL THEM TO
CRIMINALS.
I'LL TELL YOU WHAT ELSE WE HAVE
TO DO.
WE NEED A REVOLUTION IN MENTAL
HEALTH IN THIS COUNTRY.
A LOT OF PEOPLE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- LET US BE HONEST AND
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT MANY THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE WALKING THE STREETS OF
AMERICA TODAY WHO ARE SUICIDAL
AND/OR HOMICIDAL.
THEY NEED TREATMENT WHEN THEY
NEED TREATMENT, NOW MONTHS FROM
NOW.
BUT BOTTOM LINE, ALL OF US ARE
SHOCKED AND DISGUSTED BY THE
KINDS OF MASS KILLINGS THAT WE
SAW IN THAT CHURCH AND WHAT
HAPPENED TO REVEREND PINCKNEY,
AND WE'VE GOT TO DO EVERYTHING
WE CAN.
WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID MONTHS
AGO I THINK CAPTURES IT.
THE PRESIDENT SAID, LOOK, THIS
IS A DIFFICULT PROBLEM.
NOBODY HERE CAN GUARANTEE YOU
THAT TERRIBLE THINGS DON'T
HAPPEN, BUT JUST BECAUSE IT IS A
HARD PROBLEM DOES NOT MEAN TO
SAY WE SHOULD NOT DO EVERYTHING
WE CAN TO TRY TO END THEY MASS
KILLINGS.
>>> ANOTHER QUESTION -- SYLVIA,
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>>> VIV VIDAL.
HE'S A STUDENT, THE FIRST MEMBER
OF HIS FAMILY TO GO TO COLLEGE.
HE SAYS HE IS LEANING TOWARDS
OF.
WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION, YOUNG MAN?
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I AM A
STUDENT HERE IN COLUMBIA, SOUTH
CAROLINA.
I'M FROM A RURAL AREA, RAISED IN
A SINGLE 46 PARENT HOME.
I ATTEND A HISTORICALLY BLACK
COLLEGE HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA.
MY QUESTION IS YOU HAVE A PLAN
TO MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGE FREE.
SO WHERE DOES HISTORICALLY BLACK
COLLEGES, PRIVATE HISTORIC BLACK
COLLEGES FALL UNDER THIS PLAN?
>> GREAT QUESTION, AND
CONGRATULATIONS ON WHAT YOU HAVE
ACCOMPLISHED.
YOU KNOW, I
GREW UP IN A FAMILY WHEN MY DAD
CAME FROM POLAND WITHOUT ANY
MONEY.
HE WAS A HIGH SCHOOL DROPOUT, MY
MOTHER WAS A DROPOUT, SO I WAS
PROUD THAT THEY SENT MY BROTHER
AND ME TO COLLEGE.
I BELIEVE HIS TURKEYLY BLACK
COLLEGES PLAYED A VERY IMPORTANT
ROLE.
YOU'RE QUITE RIGHT.
WHAT I BELIEVE IS IN THE YEAR
2016, WHEN WE TALK ABOUT PUBLIC
EDUCATION, WE SHOULD MAKE SURE
THAT PUBLIC COLLEGES ARE TUITION
FREE.
EVERYONE IN THE COUNTRY WHO HAS
THE ABILITY AND DESIRE CAN GET A
COLLEGE EDUCATION, BUT IN
ADDITION TO THAT, WE MUST
SUSTAIN AND STRENGTHEN THE
HISTORICALLY BLACK COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES WHO DO A PHENOMENAL
JOB TODAY EDUCATING A
SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF
AFRICAN-AMERICANS.
YOU HAVE MY WORD THAT WE WILL
NOT SUSTAIN BUT SUBSTANTIAL
INCREASE FUNDING FOR THE
HISTORICALLY BLACK COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES.
THEY ARE UNDER TODAY A LOT OF
FINANCIAL PRESSURE, AND ONE OF
THE REASONS THEY ARE UNDER
FINANCIAL PRESSURE IS THEY DO
THE RIGHT THING.
THEY WELCOME KIDS INTO THOSE
COLLEGES THAT HARVARD AND YALE
MIGHT NOT NECESSARILY WELCOME.
SOME OF THOSE KIDS ARE
STRUGGLING.
SOME OF THOSE KIDS MAY DROP OUT,
BUT THAT'S THE RIGHT THING TO
DO, AND THOSE COLLEGES DESERVE
VERY STRONG SUPPORT.
YOU HAVE MY WORD A SANDERS
ADMINISTRATION WOULD PROVIDE
THAT SUPPORT.
>>> WHILE WE'RE ON THE TOPIC OF
THINGS YOU COULD DO IN YOUR
ADMINISTRATION THAT WOULD HELPED
THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY,
SPEAK TO WHAT REMAINS A SIZABLE
GAP.
WE LOOK AT THE NEVADA ENTRANCE
POLLS, AS YOU WELL KNOW,
SENATORS, AMONG BLACK POLLS TESS
76-22.
WHY DO YOU BELIEVE YOUR MESSAGE
IS NOT RESONATING AS WELL THERE
IF.
>> WELL, CHRIS, YOU KNOW, WHEN
WE STARTED IN SOUTH CAROLINA, MY
MESSAGE WASN'T RESONATING WITH
ANYBODY.
NOBODY KNEW WHO I WAS.
I'M RUNNING AGAINST A CANDIDATE
WHO'S ONE OF THE BEST-KNOWN
PEOPLE IN THE WORLD, A
CANDIDATES WHO RAN HERE A VERY
STRONG CAMPAIGN IN 2008, WHO
KNOWS A LOT OF PEOPLE.
SO WE STARTED WITH NO SUPPORT.
OUR SUPPORT HAS GROWN AND IT HAS
GROWN IN THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
COMMUNITY.
WHAT I BELIEVE TO THE DEGREE WE
CAN GET OUR MESSAGE OUT AND THE
MESSAGE IS THAT WE HAVE A
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM, WHICH
IS BROKEN, THAT THERE ARE
SOMETHING VERY WRONG WHEN
AFRICAN-AMERICANS IN SOUTH
CAROLINA AND AROUND THE COUNTRY
GET NERVOUS ABOUT WALKING DOWN
THE STREET OR GOING INTO THEIR
CAR AND BEING STOPPED BY A
POLICE OFFICERS, THAT SHOULD NOT
BE HAPPENING IN AMERICA NOW WHEN
WE HAVE IDEAS ABOUT HOW TO DEAL
WITH THAT, WHEN AFRICA
AFRICAN-AMERICANS HEAR MY POINT
OF VIEW THAT WHEN YOUTH
UNEMPLOYMENT IN THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN DMUNT FOR HIGH
SCHOOL GRADUATES IS 51% -- 51%
UNEMPLOYED OR UNDEREMPLOYED, WE
HAVE A PLAN TO INVEST IN JOBS
AND EDUCATION, NOT JAILS AND
INCARCERATION.
WE HAVE VERY SPECIFIC IDEAS
ABOUT HOW THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT, YOU KNOW, LOCAL
POLICE DEPARTMENTS ARE RUN BY
MUNICIPALITIES, FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT CAN PLAY A MAJOR ROLE
IN ENDING THE MILL TARIZATION OF
SO MANY OF OUR LOCAL POLICE
DEPARTMENTS.
THEY LOOK LIKE OCCUPYING ARMS,
AND WE'LL MAKE THE POLICE
DEPARTMENTS LOOK LIKE THE
DIVERSITY OF THE COMMUNITIES
THEY ARE SERVING.
THERE'S A LOT TO BE DONE.
>>> LET'S LOOK TO YOUR RIGHT.
IT'S A QUESTION ABOUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING WITH THE SUPREME
COURT.
HE'S AN ATTORNEY AND THE PAST
PRESIDENT OF THE SOUTH CAROLINA
TRIAL LAWYERS ASSOCIATION.
>> GOOD TO MEET YOU.
>> HE SAID HE SUPPORTS SECRETARY
CLINTON.
>> I'M NOT GOING TO PICK ON YOU
ABOUT THAT.
SENATOR, WELCOME TO SOUTH
CAROLINA, AND WELCOME TO MY ALMA
MATER, THE UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH
CAROLINA.
WITH THE PASSING RECENTLY OF
JUSTICE SCALIA, THE ISSUE OF
APPOINTMENTS TO THE JUSTICE IN
THE SUPREME COURT IN MY OPINION
HAS RISEN TO THE TOP OF THIS
ELECTION.
WE ALL KNOW THE SUPREME COURT
ELECTED A PRESIDENT IN 2001 AND
LOOK WHAT HAPPENED.
>> I KNOW THAT, YOU KNOW THAT,
PROBABLY SOME PEOPLE WOULD
DISAGREE.
>> I HAVE GOOD FRIENDS OF MINE
THAT WOULD VEHEMENTLY DISAGREE,
BUT THAT'S OKAY.
WE'RE ALL FRIENDS.
JUST SPEAKING OF THE POLICE
CASES, TWO CASES YESTERDAY
REGARDING STOPPING WAS ARGUED
BEFORE THE SUPREME COURT.
EIGHT JUSTICES, IT WILL PROBABLY
END UP A 4-4.
SO THESE ISSUES AND OTHER
PROFOUND ISSUES WILL BE COMING
UP.
JUST TODAY SENATOR GRASSLEY
ADVISED CHAIRMAN OF THE SENATE
JUDICIARY COMMITTEE ADVISED
SENATOR McCONNELL THERE WOULD BE
NO HEARINGS ON ANY PRESIDENTIALE
NOMINEE.
NO VOTE ON ANY PRESIDENTIAL
NOMINEE, SO WE WILL CONTINUE FOR
AT LEAST ANOTHER YEAR WITH EIGHT
JUSTICES.
>> COUNSEL, IS THERE A QUESTION
IN THERE?
>> IT'S COMING.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES WILL APPOINT JUSTICE
SCALIA'S SUCCESSOR.
WITH THAT IN MIND, PAST JUSTICES
OF THE SUPREME COURT, NOT
PRESENT BUT PAST, WHICH PAST
JUSTICES DO YOU ADMIRE THE MOST?
AND WHY?
>> BEFORE I GET TO YOUR
QUESTION, I'M NOT SO SURE THAT
YOU'RE RIGHT.
I HEAR WHAT McCONNELL HAS TO SAY
AND I HEAR WHAT CHUCK GRASSLEY
HAS TO SAY, BUT LET ME SAY THIS.
WE HAVE BEEN DEALING IN THE LAST
SEVEN YEARS WITH AN
UNPRECEDENTED LEVEL OF
OBSTRUCTIONISM AGAINST PRESIDENT
OBAMA.
LITERALLY IT TURNS OUT ON THE
DAY THAT OBAMA YAW INAUGURATED
REPUBLICANS CAME TOGETHER AND
SAID WHAT WILL THEY DO?
THEY CAME TO THE CONCLUSION THAT
OBSTRUCT, OBSTRUCT, OBSTRUCT,
MAKE IT AS DIFFERENT AS WE
WOULD.
I'VE BEEN AT THE PRESIDENT'S
SIDE TIME AND TIME AGAIN TO GET
A STIMULUS BILL THROUGH,
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, ET CETERA,
ET CETERA, ET CETERA.
BUT WHAT YOU ARE SEEING TODAY IN
THIS SUPREME COURT SITUATION IS
NOTHING MORE THAN THE CONTINUOUS
AND UNPRECEDENTED OBSTRUCTIONISM
THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS GONE
THROUGH.
AND THIS -- AND THIS IS ON TOP
OF THIS BIRTHER ISSUE, WHICH WE
HEAR FROM DONALD TRUMP AND
OTHERS, THE RACIST EFFORT TO TRY
TO DE-LEGITIMATIZE THE PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES.
CAN YOU IMAGINE THAT?
TO SAY HE'S NOT REALLY THE
PRESIDENT.
HE WASN'T BORN IN THE UNITED
STATES, WHICH IS NONSENSE.
IT'S A FUNNY THINK ON THAT
ISSUE.
MY DAD CAME FROM POLAND.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
GUESS WHAT?
NOBODY HAS ASKED FOR MY BIRTH
CERTIFICATE.
MAYBE IT'S THE COLOR OF MY SKIN.
I DON'T KNOW.
>> SENATOR --
>> TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION,
THURGOOD MARSHALL WAS A DAMNED
GOOD SUPREME COURT JUSTICE.
>> ALSO BROOKLYN?
>> I WAS BORN AND MOVED INTO A
3 1/2-ROOM RENT-CONTROLLED
APARTMENT IN BROOKLYN.
>> AND YOU WERE TALKING ABOUT
THOSE WHO WERE BIG VOICES IN THE
BIRTHER MOVEMENT.
DO YOUABLY TRUMP WAS MOTIVATED
BY RACISM?
>> I'M NOT A PSYCHOANALYST, AND
BOY WOULD A PSYCHOANALYST HAVE
AN INTERESTING TIME WITH
DONALD TRUMP.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT THIS IS WHAT I WILL SAY, AND
TRUMP IS CLEARLY NOT THE ONLY
PERSON INVOLVED IN THIS.
THERE WAS AN EFFORT TO TRY TO
DELEGITIMATIZE THE PRESIDENT.
YOU CAN DISAGREE WITH OBAMA ALL
UNFORTUNATE, BUT TO SAY THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
WHO WON AN ELECTION FAIR AND
SQUARE WAS NOT A LEGITIMATE
PRESIDENT REALLY UNDERMINES WHAT
WE ARE AS A NATION.
SO I THINK WHAT THAT WAS -- THAT
WAS -- I'M NOT GOING TO SUPPLY
TO TRUMP, BUT DO I THINK AT
LEAST IN SOME PARTS OF THAT
REPUBLICAN BASE THERE IS RACE
INVOLVED IN THAT?
ABSOLUTELY.
>> ANOTHER QUESTION.
CLINT FLEMING SPENT 40 YEARS IN
THE BANKING INDUSTRY, AND IS NOW
IN A TAX PREPARATION COMPANY.
HE SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED.
WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION?
>> LET ME WORK ON THIS GUY.
>> THE QUESTION, SENATOR, IT
APPEARS TO ME THAT A LOT OF YOUR
EFFORTS ARE IN SOCIAL PROGRAMS
OF SOCIAL ISSUES.
MY QUESTION, WITH THE MOOD OF
THIS UNITED STATES, HOW ARE YOU
GOING TO CONVINCE THE VOTERS YOU
CAN MAKE A DIFFERENCE AS RELATES
TO SOCIAL ISSUES, FREE
EDUCATION.
THERE'S SEVERAL STATES OUT THERE
WHERE WE PROVIDE MINIMUM
EDUCATION.
SO THE QUESTION IS, HOW ARE YOU
GOING TO -- FROM A BANGER'S
STANDPOINT, WHERE IS THE MONEY
GOING TO COME FROM?
>> OKAY, THANKS, CLENTE, FOR THE
QUESTIONED.
I FIND IT FUNNY -- NOT SO FUNNY,
BUT I FIND IT INTERESTING THAT
OVER THE LAST 30 YEARS, CLENTE,
THERE'S BEEN A MASSIVE TRANSFER
OF WEALTH FROM THE MIDDLE CLASS
AND WORKING FAMILIES TO THE TOP
1%.
TRILLIONS HAVE FLOWED TO THE TOP
OF ONE TENTH OF 1%.
ANY OF YOU HEAR AN UPROAR ABOUT
THAT?
WHAT A TERRIBLE THING?
MIDDLE CLASS SHALL SHRINKING,
SAW A DOUBLING, A DOUBLING OF
THE PERCENTAGE OF WEALTH THEY
OWN.
NO ONE TALKED.
THE ESTABLISHED WAS FINE, WALL
STREET WAS HAPPY WITH IT, MEDIA
HAPPEN WITH IT.
I'M TALKING ABOUTNESS LIKE
SAYING EVERY KID IN THE COUNTRY
WHO HAS THE ABILITY SHOULD GET A
TUITION-FREE GOING TO A PUBLIC
COLLEGE OR UNIVERSITY IF THAT'S
THEIR CHOICE.
I'M GOING TO PAY THROUGH THAT
THROUGH A TAX ON WALL STREET
SPECULATION.
WHEN WALL STREET COLLAPSED
BECAUSE OF THEIR GREED, YOU KNOW
WHAT?
YOU BAILED THEM OUT.
NOW I THINK MAYBE IT'S TIME FOR
WALL STREET TO HELP THE MIDDLE
CLASS.
>> WHEN I TALK ABOUT CREATING 13
MILLION JOBS THROUGH A TRILLION
DOLLAR INVESTMENT AND REBUILDING
A CRUMBLING INFRASTRUCTURE AND
ANYONE THINKS IT WAS JUST FLINT,
MICHIGAN WHO WAS IN TROUBLE, YOU
WEEK MISTAKEN.
YOU NAME IT.
I'M GOING TO PAY FOR THAT BY
ENDING LOOPHOLES THAT ALLOWS
PROFITABLE MULTINATIONAL
CORPORATIONS STASHING THEIR
MONEY IN THE CAYMAN ISLANDS AND
IN OTHER TAX HAVENS.
IN SOME CASES NOT PAYING A
NICKEL IN TAXES.
WE'RE GOING TO USE THAT MOVE,
AND BIFF, AND WE'RE GOING TO
TARGETS THOSE INVESTMENTS -- ALL
RIGHT.
SO, TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION,
CLENTE, THE TOP ONE TENTH OF THE
PERCENT OWN -- SO HERE IT IS,
FOLKS, YOU CAN LIKE IT OR NOT.
THIS IS MY VIEW.
WE ARE GOING TO ASK
PROFITABILITY MULTINATIONAL
CORPORATIONS AND THE RICH TO
START PAYING THEIR FAIR SHARE OF
TAXES.
>> TWO THINGS.
FIRST ONE IS, YOU SAID IN IOWA,
I DO NOT REPRESENT THE INTERESTS
OF THE VERY WEALTHY.
IF YOU'RE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES YOU HAVE TO
REPRESENT EVERYBODY, DON'T YOU?
DO YOU BELIEVE THERE'S A RISK OF
SEEMING DIVISIVE IN A STATEMENT
LIKE THAT?
>> DIVISIVE?
>> YOU CAN USE ANY WORD YOU
WANT.
>> WHEN YOU HAVE THE 20
WEALTHIEST PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY OWNING MORE WEALTH THAN
THE BOTTOM 150 MILLION PEOPLE.
WHEN YOU HAVE A HANDFUL OF
BILLIONAIRES SPENDING HUNDREDS
OF MILLIONS TRYING TO BUY
ELECTIONS AND REPRESENT
CANDIDATES AND HAVE CANDIDATES
ELECTED TO REPRESENT THE WEALTHY
AND THE POWERFUL, FRANKLY,
CHRIS, I THINK WE NEED A
MOVEMENT IN THIS COUNTRY, AND NO
INDIVIDUAL CAN DO IT ALONE.
A POLITICAL REVOLUTION WHICH
SAYS TO THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS,
A, YOUR GREED HAS GONE A LONG
WAY TO DESTROY OUR ECONOMY.
AND SECOND OF ALL, YOU CAN'T
HAVE IT ALL.
THIS COUNTRY BELONGS TO ALL OF
US, NOT A HANDFUL.
I WILL TAKE THEM ON.
>> ALL RIGHT.
SO IN TERMS OF WHAT YOU WANT TO
PROVIDE, THEN YOU GET TO THE,
WILL THAT BE ENOUGH?
FOUR FORMER CHAIRS OF THE WHITE
HOUSE COUNCIL OF ECONOMIC
ADVISERS, SAY THERE'S NO
CREDIBILITY ECONOMIC RESEARCH
THAT SUPPORTS THE POSITIVE
IMPACTS YOU'RE TOUTING.
ONE OF THEM GOES SO FAR TO SAY
IT'S LIKE MAGIC FLYING PUPPIES
IS WINNING LOTTO TICKETS TIED TO
THEIR COLLARS.
>> LET ME GUESS.
THOSE WERE ORGANIZED BY THE
CLINTON CAMPAIGN.
A WILD AND CRAZY GUESS.
>> NO, THEY WEREN'T --
>> WELL, TOMORROW WE HAVE WELL
OVER 130 ECONOMISTS AND HEALTH
CARE EXPERTS WHO WILL SAY
EXACTLY THE SAME.
CHRIS, YOU HAVE ENOUGH
EXPERIENCE TO KNOW, YOU CAN GO
TO AN ECONOMIST, ONE WILL SAY
THIS, WE HAVE ECONOMISTS SAY
WHAT THIS COUNTRY NEEDS, ET
CETERA, ET CETERA.
ECONOMISTS HAVE DIFFERENT POINTS
OF VIEW, BUT WE HAVE DOCUMENTED
HOW WE PAY FOR -- LET ME SAY A
WORLD ON HEALTH CARE, BECAUSE
THAT'S WHERE SOME OF THE
CRITICISM COMES FROM.
HERE'S THE STORY, FOLKS.
THE STORY IS, GERMANY, THE
UNITED KINGDOM, FRANCE, SWEDEN,
DECK MARK, HOLLAND, CANADA,
EVERY IMAGINE COUNTRY ON EARTH
GUARANTEES HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE.
GUESS WHAT?
NOT ONLY DO THEY GUARANTEE
HEALTH CARE TO ALL OF THEIR
PEOPLE.
WE, WHO HAVE 29 MILLION
UNEMPLOYED, AND MANY OF YOU
UNDER -- 29 MILLION UNINSURED,
AND MANY OF YOU UNDERINSURED
WITH LARGE COPAYMENTS, MANY OF
YOU AND PRESCRIPTION DRUGS, WE
END UP SPENDING, CHRIS, ALMOST
THREE TIMES MORE THAN THE
BRITISH DO, 50% MORE THAN THE
FRENCH, FAR MORE THAN THE
CANADIANS.
WHEN PEOPLE SAY, WELL, BERNIE WE
CAN'T DO WHAT EVERY OTHER MAJOR
COUNTRY DOES, RUN A
COST-EFFECTIVE HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM THAT GUARANTEES HEALTH
CARE TO ALL PEOPLE, STOP THE
HUGE RIPOFFS THAT COME FROM THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY, SUCH
THAT 1 OUT OF 5 AMERICANS CAN'T
EVEN FILL THEIR PRESCRIPTIONS.
FRANKLY, I DON'T BELIEVE IT.
I DON'T BELIEVE IT.
WE SPEND FAR MORE THAN ANY MAJOR
COUNTRY AND GET MUCH LESS.
WHAT THE REAL ISSUE IS HERE, DO
WE HAVE THE GUTS TO TAKE ON THE
POWER OF THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES?
DO WE HAVE THE GUTS TO TAKE ON
THE PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY WHO
HAS 1300 PAID LOBBYISTS IN
WASHINGTON, D.C.?
AND THESE GUYS SPEND ZILLIONS IN
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS?
I BELIEVE THAT WHEN THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE STAND UP AND THEY SAY,
YOU KNOW WHAT?
HEALTH CARE IS A RIGHT OF ALL
PEOPLE, NOT A PRIVILEGE, YEAH, I
BELIEVE WE CAN DO THAT.
>> ANOTHER QUESTION FOR YOU,
SENATOR.
MEET TRACY JACKSON TO YOUR
RIGHT.
SHE RUNS A NONPROFIT, SAYS SHE
IS VOTING FOR SECRETARY CLINTON,
BUT HAS A QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> HI, SENATOR SANDERS.
I WAS RECENTLY ASKED TO TEACH A
LEADERSHIP COURSE AT MY ALMA
MATER.
IF YOU WERE GOING TO BE A GUEST
SPEAKER IN MY CLASS, WHAT TWO
LEADERSHIP TRUTHS WOULD YOU
SHARE WITH MY UNDERGRADUATE
STUDENTS?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU FOR
WHAT YOU DO.
>> THANK YOU.
>> I BELIEVE THAT YOU CANNOT BE
A GOOD LEADER UNLESS YOU GO INTO
Y
YOUR HEART OF HEARTS AND
PASSIONATELY BELIEVE IN WHAT YOU
WERE LEADING.
I GO AROUND THE COUNTRY AND SEE
KIDS COMING UP, I WOULD LIKE TO
BE A SENATOR, I WOULD LIKE TO BE
A GOVERNOR.
NOT GOOD ENOUGH.
WHY DO YOU WANT TO BE A SENATOR?
WHY DO YOU WANT TO BE A
GOVERNOR?
WHAT IS YOUR PASSION?
WHAT MOTIVATES YOU?
IF YOU DON'T HAVE THAT PASSION,
IF YOU DON'T REALLY BELIEVE IN
SOMETHING, YOU ARE NOT EVER
GOING TO BE A GOOD LEADER.
SO MY AN WOUSWER WOULD BE, WHAT
YOU BELIEVE?
WHAT KIND OF COMMUNITY?
WHAT KIND OF COUNTRY DO YOU WANT
US TO BE?
AND ARE YOU PREPARED TO FIGHT
FOR THAT?
ARE YOU PREPARED TO TAKE ON VERY
POWERFUL SPECIAL INTERESTS?
IN ORDER TO ACHIEVE THE VISION
THAT YOU HAVE?
THAT WOULD BE MY MESSAGE.
THANK YOU.
>>> ALL RIGHT.
LET'S TAKE A SEAT, TAKE A BREAK.
WHEN WE COME BACK, WE'LL HAVE
MORE WITH SENATOR SANDERS AT THE
CNN DEMOCRATIC TOWN HALL.
WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE FROM
COLUMBIA, SOUTH CAROLINA RIGHT
AFTER THIS.
PLEASE, HAVE SOME WATER.
IT'S FREE.
>>> ALL RIGHT.
WE ARE BACK TALKING WITH VERMONT
SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS HERE ON
THE CAMPUS OF THE UNIVERSITY OF
SOUTH CAROLINA SCHOOL OF LAW IN
COLUMBIA.
THE DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY JUST FOUR
DAYS AWAY.
DON'T BE NERVOUS.
I HAVE A QUESTION FOR YOU.
THE CLINTON CAMPAIGN RECENTLY
RELEASED A WEB AD HITTING YOU
FOR WHAT THEY SAY IS BEING A
SINGLE-ISSUE CANDIDATE.
I WANT TO PLAY THE AD.
TAKE A LOOK AND LISTEN.
>> NO BANK IS TOO BIG TO FAIL,
NO EXECUTIVE TOO POWERFUL TO
JAIL.
>> YOU'VE GOT TO BREAK UP THESE
HUGE FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS.
¶
>> ATTACKS ON WALL STREET
SPECULATION.
>> THE DISASTROUS AND ILLEGAL
BEHAVIOR ON WALL STREET.
>> THE WEALTHIEST PEOPLE, THE
TOP 1.5%.
THE CEOs OF WALL STREET
COMPANIES.
>> PRETTY SELF-EXPLANATORY.
WHAT'S YOUR RESPONSE?
ARE YOU TOO SINGLE-ISSUE
FOCUSED?
YOU DIDN'T LIKE IT?
WAS IT A PICTURE THING OR A
MESSAGE --
>> MY HAIR WAS EVEN WORSE.
>> IS THAT WHAT IT WAS?
>> AT LEAST LET ME COMB MY HAIR
THERE OCCASIONALLY.
YOU KNOW, SINGLE ISSUE.
ANYBODY HERE WHO'S GOG TO MY
RALLIES, THEY ARE THE LONGEST,
MOST BORING DISCUSSIONS IN THE
HISTORY OF POLITICS.
I TALK FOR AN HOUR, HOUR AND A
HALF.
OF COURSE I TALK ABOUT WALL
STREET.
I'LL TELL YOU SOMETHING, IF I
MAY, WHY SECRETARY CLINTON IS
NERVOUS.
PEOPLE ARE ASKING, HOW DOES IT
HAPPEN OR WHY DOES HER SUPER-PAC
RECEIVE MILLIONS AND MILLIONS
FROM WALL STREET?
WHAT DOES IT MEANS WHEN YOU GIVE
SPEECHES TO A FINANCIAL
INSTITUTION LIKE GOLDMAN SACHS,
AND A COUPLE HUNDRED THOUSANDS
FOR GIVING THAT SPEECH.
MAYBE THEY'RE NERVOUS ABOUT THE
WALL STREET ISSUE, BUT WHEN I
TALK ABOUT, I TALKED ABOUT A
DISAPPEARING MIDDLE CLASS.
I TALK ABOUT RAISING THE MINIMUM
WAGE.
I TALK ABOUT REBUILDING THE
CRUMBLING INFRASTRUCTURE.
I TALK ABOUT MAKING PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION FREE.
I TALK ABOUT A HEALTH CARE
PROGRAM THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
OUR PEOPLE.
I TALK ABOUT A TAX SYSTEM THAT
IS FAIR AND EQUITABLE.
I TALK ABOUT MAKING CERTAIN THAT
EVERY WOMAN IN THIS COUNTRY HAS
THE RIGHT TO CONTROL HER OWN
BODY.
AND THAT WE FIGHT FOR PAY EQUITY
FOR WOMEN WORKERS.
I TALK ABOUT ENDING A DISASTROUS
TRADE POLICY.
WANT TO TALK ABOUT A DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN SECRETARY AND CLINTON
AND ME?
SHE SUPPORTED NAFTA.
SHE SUPPORTED PERMANENT NORMAL
TRADE RELATIONS WITH CHINA.
I HAVE LED THE OPPOSITION TO
VIRTUALLY ALL OF THESE
DISASTROUS TRADE AGREEMENTS
WHICH HAVE COST US MILLIONS OF
DOLLARS.
WHAT I AM FIGHTING FOR RIGHT NOW
IS A POLITICAL REVOLUTION IN
WHICH GOVERNMENT STARTS WORKING
FOR WORKING PEOPLE AND FOR THE
MIDDLE CLASS, AND THAT A
REVOLUTION, WHICH IS PREPARED TO
TAKE ON THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS
TODAY, WHICH HAS ENORMOUS POWER,
SO THE IDEA THAT I'M JUST
TALKING ABOUT WALL STREET, WALL
STREET IS ENORMOUSLY IMPORTANT,
BY THE WAY, BUT IT'S NOT THE
ONLY ISSUE.
>> TELL PEOPLE WHO THE
REVOLUTION LOOKS LIKE?
THIS IS A BIG PART OF THE
MOTIVATION FOR WHERE YOU THINK
WILL HAVE CHANGE.
>> LAST ELECTION, REPUBLICANS
WANT A LANDSLIDE VICTORY, ALL
OVER THE COUNTRY.
63% OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
DIDN'T VOTE.
80% OF YOUNG PEOPLE DIDN'T VOTE.
REPUBLICANS WILL ALWAYS WIN
ELECTIONS WHEN PEOPLE ARE SO
DISILLUSIONED WITH THE POLITICAL
PROCESS THAT THEY DON'T VOTE,
AND THE VOTER REPRESSION THAT IS
BEING MOUNTED ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY.
HERE IS THE ANSWER MEANS THE
REVITALIZATION OF AMERICAN
DEMOCRAT SICK.
IT MEANS MY VIEW IS WE SHOULD
HAVE ONE OF THE HIGHEST VOTING
TURNOUTS IN THE WORLD, NOT ONE
OF THE LOWEST.
IT MEANS WE MAKE IT EASIER FOR
PEOPLE TO GET INVOLVED IN
POLITICS, NOT HARDER.
THIS IS WHY, CHRIS.
WHEN YOUNG PEOPLE AND WORKING
CLASS PEOPLE AND LOW-INCOME
PEOPLE, PEOPLE ON WHICH DO NOT
PARTICIPATE IN THE POLITICAL
PROCESS.
WHEN THEY GET INVOLVED, WHEN
THEY STAND UP AND SAY, YOU KNOW
WHAT?
I'M A WORKING MOM.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE I HAVE
QUALITY AFFORDABLE CHILD CHAIR,
WE WILL HAVE AFFORD ACQUALITY
CHILD CARE.
WHEN PEOPLE TALK ABOUTED NEED TO
TAKE ON THE FOSSIL FUEL INDUSTRY
TO DEAL WITH THE CLIMATE CHANGE.
I DON'T GO AROUND SAYING VOTE
FOR ME, I'M GOING TO SOLVE YOUR
PROBLEM.
I SAY VOTE FOR ME, TOGETHER WHEN
MILLIONS STAND UP, WE CAN MAKE
REAL CHANGE.
>> SO LET'S HEAR FROM ONE OF THE
VOTE WHO ARE WANTS TO BE PART OF
THE PROCESS.
THOMAS KILPATRICK SAYS HE IS
UNDECIDED.
>> WELCOME TO COLUMBIA.
>> YOU TALKED A LOT ABOUT THE
MILLIONAIRE BILLIONAIRE CLASS.
I'M WONDERING IF YOU COULD NAME
ONE WHO YOU ADMIRE, AND WHY?
>> LOOK, THERE ARE GREAT
BILLIONAIRES.
PEOPLE WHO ARE SERIOUS, I DON'T
GREAT WITH EVERYTHING THAT BILL
GATES HAS DONE, BUT YOU KNOW,
THIS IS A GUY WHO HAS MADE
MASSIVE INVESTMENTS IN EDUCATION
AND HEALTH CARE AROUND THE
WORLD.
HE'S NOT JUST SITTING ON HIS
MONEY.
HE'S TRYING TO MAKE THE WORLD A
BETTER PLACE.
HE'S NOT ALONE.
THERE ARE OTHER PEOPLE.
SO THIS IS NOT SOME KIND OF
PERSONAL VENDETTA AGAINST, YOU
KNOW PEOPLE WHO HAPPEN TO HAVE A
LOT OF MONEY.
ABOUT WHAT ENDS UP HAPPENING IN
THIS COUNTRY, THOMAS IS YOU HAVE
PEOPLE LIKE THE KOCH BROTHERS,
OKAY, SECOND WEALTHIEST FAMILY
IN THIS COUNTRY, THEY AND A FEW
OF THEIR BILLIONAIRE FRIENDS ARE
GOING TO SPEND $900 MILLION ON
THIS CAMPAIGN IN ORDER TO ELECT
CANDIDATES WHO REPRESENT THE
RICH AND POWERFUL.
I THINK THAT STINKS.
I THINK THAT'S UNDERMINES
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY.
I THINK THAT'S WHY WE HAVE TO
OVERTURN THIS DISASTROUS CITIZEN
UNITED SUPREME COURT DECISION.
SO THIS IS NOT PERSONAL.
IT'S NOT PERSONAL.
IT IS SIMPLY SAYING THAT YOU
HAVE A HANDFUL OF PEOPLE WHO
HAVE INCREDIBLE WEALTH AND
INCREDIBLE POWER.
THEY HAVE ECONOMY POWER.
THEY HAVE POLITICAL POWER.
I THINK THAT'S NOT WHAT THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA IS
SUPPOSED TO BE ABOUT.
>>> ANGELA IS AN ATTORNEY WHO
WORKS IN COMMERCIAL REAL ESTATE.
SHE SAYS SHE IS LEANING TOWARD
YOU, SENATOR.
>> KEEP LEANING.
>> WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION?
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I BELIEVE
IT'S FAIR TO SAY THAT YOU'RE A
CAREER POLITICIAN.
YOU'VE BEEN IN GOVERNMENT FOR
OVER 30 YEARS.
CAN YOU UNEQUIVOCALLY ASSURE
YOUR SUPPORTERS THAT WHEN YOU
ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, YOU WILL NOT BE
BEHOLDEN TO ANY PERSONS OR
SPECIAL-INTEREST GROUPS.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR THAT
QUESTION.
LOOK, WHEN WE TALK ABOUT WHY SO
MANY PEOPLE ARE GIVING UP ON THE
POLITICAL PROS, PEOPLE
UNDERSTAND THAT WE HAVE A
POLITICAL SYSTEM, WHICH IS
CORRUPT AND IT'S RIGGED, OKAY?
NOW, I KNOW EVERY POLITICIAN,
DEMOCRAT, REPUBLICAN, WHATEVER,
WHO RECEIVES MILLIONS IN
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS, THEY SAY
OH, THEY CONTRIBUTIONS WILL NOT
IMPACT ME.
THEN THE QUESTION WE ASK IS, WHY
ARE THESE SPECIAL INTERESTS
MAKING THESE CONTRIBUTIONS?
MAKE THEY'RE DUMMIES AND JUST
THROWING THEIR MONEY AROUND?
I DON'T THINK SO.
SO HERE IS WHAT I'M ENORMOUSLY
PROUD OF.
NOT ONLY DO I NOT HAVE A SUPER
PGA PAC, WE DON'T RAISE MONEY
FROM CORPORATE AMERICAN, WALL
STREET OR BILLIONAIRES.
WE HAVE RECEIVED 4 MILLION
INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS FROM
WELL OVER A MILLION PEOPLE.
YOU KNOW THE AVERAGE
CONTRIBUTION?
$27.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SO, ANGELA, I GUESS I AM
INDEBTED TO THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE
CONTRIBUTED $27.
THOSE ARE THE PEOPLE I WILL
STAND FOR AND FIGHT FOR.
>> THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>>> ON YOUR LEFT WE HAVE BARBARA
CUNNINGHAM, A RETIRED PRIVATE
SECTOR HEALTH WORKER.
SHE SAYS SHE IS LEANING TOWARDS
SUPPORTING ON YOU SATURDAY, BUT
SHE HAS A QUESTION.
>> HI ARE SENATOR SANDERS.
I'VE BEEN A LIFELONG DEMOCRAT
AND ALWAYS SUPPORTED THE
CLINTONS, BUT I LOVE WHAT YOU
SAY.
I'VE WAITED FOR MY WHOLE LIFE
FOR A TRULY LIBERAL POLITICIAN
WITH A PLATFORM LIKE YOURS,
INCLUDING AFFORDABLE HEALTH CARE
FOR ALL.
MY CONCERN IS WITH MEDICARE FOR
ALL.
THERE'S HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF
MIDDLE-CLASS JOBS IN THE HEALTH
INSURANCE INDUSTRY ALL ACROSS
THIS COUNTRY THAT COULD BE
ADSERIOUSLY AFFECTED.
DO YOU HAVE A TRANSITION PLAN?
>> WE SURE DO.
>> THAT WOULD KEEP THESE JOBS
FROM BEING PUT IN JEOPARDY IF
YOU CAN IMPLEMENT MEDICARE FOR
ALL?
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
I AM AN ADVOCATE FOR A MEDICARE
FOR ALL PROGRAM, BUT I THINK
WHAT WE NEED IS RATHER THAN
PEOPLE BILLING -- PEOPLE
SPENDING ENORMOUS AMOUNTS OF
TIME DRIVING DOCTORS CRAZY AND
INSURANCE COMPANIES, CAN I
PRESCRIBE THIS DRUG OR NOT?
WE ARE GOING TO NEED WHEN WE
PROVIDE INSURANCE TO 29 MILLION
PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE IT, WHEN
WE DEAL WITH THE PROBLEMS OF
HIGH DEDUCTIBLES AND COPAYMENTS
AND MORE PEOPLE GET THE HEALTH
CARE THEY WANTS AND NEED, WE'LL
HAVE ALL KINDS OF JOBS OPENED IN
HEALTH CARE.
THE FIRST PEOPLE IN LINE SHOULD
BE THOSE PEOPLE CURRENTLY IN THE
PRIVATE HEALTH INSURANCE
INDUSTRY.
OUR GOAL IS TO MAKE SURE THAT
WHEN WE SPEND A DOLLAR, IT'S NOT
ON ADMINISTRATION AND
BUREAUCRACY, BUT ON THE
PROVISION OF HEALTH CARE TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE, AND PEOPLE LIKE
YOU HAVE A WHOLE LOT OF
EXPERIENCE IN THAT AREA, CAN
PLAY A VITAL ROLE IN MAKING US
AND ALLOWING US TO DO THAT.
>> DAVE SPRUNG IS ON YOUR RIGHT.
HE HAS A QUESTION THAT'S HIGHLY
RELATED TO THE DISCUSSION YOU'RE
HAVING RIGHT NOW.
A STUDENT, HE SAYS HE'S
UNDECIDED LEANING A BIT TOWARDS
SECRETARY CLINTON, HAS A
QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, CIGARETTE
SMOKING CONTRIBUTE TO
APPROXIMATELY 480,000 DEATHS
EACH YEAR IN THE UNITED STATES.
I LOST MY FATHER, A LIFETIME
SMOKER TO LUNG CANCER IN 2014.
IF YOU WERE TO BE ELECTED
PRESIDENT, CAN YOU THINK OF ANY
REFORMS PUT IN PLACE?
FOR EXAMPLE, YOU CAN'T CONSIDER
RAISING THE MINIMUM LEGAL
PURCHASES AGE FROM 18 TO 21?
>> I DON'T THAT I WOULD GO IN
THAT DIRECTION.
BY THE WAY, MY DAD SMOKED TWO OR
THREE PACKS A DAY.
I REMEMBER IT LIKE YESTERDAY,
WAKING UP IN THE MORNING AND
COUGHING AND COUGHING.
HE DIED YOUNG, AND CIGARETTES
CERTAINLY CONTRIBUTED TO THAT.
WE HAVE LOST GOD KNOWS HOW MANY
PEOPLE WHO ARE ADDICTED TO
TOBACCO.
WHAT I WOULD DO AND WHAT I THINK
WE'VE GOT TO DO IS TAKE ON --
YOU KNOW, WHEN I TALK ABOUT THE
GREED OF CORPORATE AMERICA, YOU
KNOW, WE TALK ABOUT THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY THAT
MAKES PRESCRIPTION DRUGS
UNAFFORDABLE, MAYBE AT THE TOP
OF THAT LIST ACTUALLY IS THE
TOBACCO INDUSTRY.
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY ARE DOING
RIGHT NOW AROUND THEWORLD?
THEY ARE TRYING TO PEDDLE
CIGARETTES TO KIDS ALL OVER THE
WORLD.
THEY GO INTO COUNTRIES AND THEY
COME UP WITH THESE COLORFUL
PACKAGES, AND HAVE PRETTY GIRLS
LITERALLY GIVING OUT LIKE HEROIN
DEALERS, LITERALLY GIVING OUT
CIGARETTES TO KIDS TO GET THEM
HOOKED ON NICOTINE.
AS INDICATE, THIS PRODUCT IS
KILLING PEOPLE AND COSTING OUR
HEALTH SYSTEM BILLIONS.
I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN.
WE'RE NOT DOING A GOOD ENOUGH
JOB.
WE ARE MAKING SOME PROGRESS.
WE ARE MAKING SOME PROGRESS, BUT
WE COULD DO BETTER.
IF, FOR EXAMPLE YOU ARE A
LOW-INCOME PERSON ADDICTED TO
GRESS AND YOU WANT TO GET OFF,
CAN YOU FIND IN MOST STATES EASY
ACCESS TO THE KINDS OF TREATMENT
THAT YOU NEED TO GET YOU OFF OF
THAT ADDICTION?
THE ANSWER IS NOT REALLY.
ONE OF THE INTERESTING THINGS
THAT ARE HAPPENING, BY THE WAY
IN THIS COUNTRY, YOU KNOW WHO'S
DOING MORE AND MORE?
IT'S THE LOW-INCOME PEOPLE, THE
WORKING-CLASS PEOPLE, PEOPLE WHO
DIDN'T NECESSARILY HAVE AS MUCH
EDUCATION AS OTHERS.
SO I THINK WE HAVE A MAJOR
HEALTH CRISIS WITH REGARD TO
CIGARETTES AND TOBACCO.
WE HAVE TO TAKE ON THE TOBACCO
INDUSTRY AND BE VERY CLEAR, YOU
CANNOT CONTINUE TO CLEAR THE
CHILDREN OF AMERICA.
WE CAN DO THAT IN A NUMBER OF
WAYS.
MAYBE WE RAISE TAXES, MAKE IT
UNAFFORDABLE FOR KIDS TO BUY
THAT PRODUCT, BUT IT'S SOMETHING
I FEEL VERY PASSIONATE ABOUT.
IF I COULD, CHRIS, ONE STORY.
THIS EVEN GETS TO TRADE
AGREEMENTS.
GIVE YOU AN EXAMPLE HOW CRAZY
THESE TRADE AGREEMENTS ARE.
PHILLIP MORRIS, LARGE TOBACCO
COMPANY IN THE WORLD, SUED THE
SMALL LITTLE COUNTRY OF URUGUAY,
AND PHILIP MORRIS SAID YOU ARE
DENYING OR COMPANY FUTURE
PROFITS.
WE WANT THE FREEDOM TO KILL THE
CHILDREN OF URUGUAY AND YOU'RE
TAKING AWAY OUR FREEDOM.
THAT'S HOW CRAZY SOME OF THESE
TRADE AGREEMENTS ARE, BUT THAT'S
A WHOLE OTHER SATIRE, BUT TAKING
ON THE TOBACCO INDUSTRY IS
SOMETHING I WOULD ENJOY DOING
VERY VERY MUCH.
>>> AND ON A FEW PERSONAL
QUESTIONS. AND ON A FEW PERSONA
QUESTIONS.
WE TALKED TO YOU IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
WE TALKED ABOUT RELIGION.
YOU SAID YOUR SPIRITUALITY IS
THAT WE ARE ALL IN THIS
TOGETHER.
EXPLAIN TO PEOPLE WHAT, IN YOUR
HEAD AND IN YOUR HEART,
MOTIVATES THAT TOGETHERNESS?
IS THERE A HIGHER POWER?
IS THERE A HIGHER INTELLIGENCE?
WHAT DO YOU BELIEVE IN?
>> THIS IS WHAT I BELIEVE.
EVERY GREAT RELIGION IN THE
WORLD, CHRISTIANITY, JUDAISM,
ISLAM, BUDDHISM, ESSENTIALLY
COMES DOWN TO DO UNTO OTHERS AS
YOU WOULD LIKE THEM TO DO UNTO
YOU.
AND WHAT I HAVE BELIEVED IN MY
WHOLE LIFE, I BELIEVED IT WHEN I
WAS A 22-YEAR-OLD KID GETTING
ARRESTED IN CHICAGO FIGHTING
SES
SEGREGATION.
I BELIEVED IT MY WHOLE LIFE THAT
WE ARE IN THIS TOGETHER.
NOT WORDS.
THE TRUTH IS AT SOME LEVEL WHEN
YOU HURT, WHEN YOUR CHILDREN
HURT, I HURT.
I HURT.
AND WHEN MY KIDS HURT, YOU HURT.
AND IT'S VERY EASY TO TURN OUR
BACKS ON KIDS WHO ARE HUNGRY OR
VETERANS WHO ARE SLEEPING OUT ON
THE STREET AND WE CAN DEVELOP A
PSYCHE, A PSYCHOLOGY WHICH SAYS
I DON'T HAVE TO WORRY ABOUT
THEM, GOING TO WORRY ABOUT
MYSELF, I NEED TO MAKE ANOTHER
$5 BILLION.
BUT I BELIEVE THAT WHAT HUMAN
NATURE IS ABOUT IS THAT
EVERYBODY IN THIS ROOM IMPACTS
EVERYBODY ELSE IN ALL KINDS OF
WAYS THAT WE CAN'T EVEN
UNDERSTAND.
IT'S BEYOND INTELLECT.
IT'S A SPIRITUAL EMOTIONAL
THING.
SO I BELIEVE THAT WHEN WE DO THE
RIGHT THING, WHEN WE TRY TO
TREAT PEOPLE WITH RESPECT AND
DIGNITY, WHEN WE SAY THAT THAT
CHILD WHO IS HUNGRY IS MY CHILD,
I THINK WE ARE MORE HUMAN WHEN
WE DO THAT THAN WHEN WE SAY THIS
WHOLE WORLD IS ME, I NEED MORE
AND MORE, I DON'T CARE ABOUT
ANYBODY ELSE.
THAT'S MY RELIGION.
I
THAT'S WHAT I BELIEVE IN.
I THINK MOST PEOPLE AROUND THE
WORLD, WHATEVER THEIR RELIGION,
THEIR COLOR, SHARE THAT BELIEF,
THAT WE ARE IN TOGETHER AS HUMAN
BEINGS.
AND IT BECOMES MORE AND MORE
PRACTICAL.
IF WE DESTROY THE PLANET BECAUSE
WE DON'T DEAL WITH CLIMATE
CHANGE, TRUST ME, WE ARE ALL IN
IT TOGETHER.
ALL RIGHT.
SO WE HAVE GOT TO WORK TOGETHER
AND THAT IS -- THAT IS WHO MY
SPIRITUALITY IS ABOUT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SO ON ONE HAND, YOU HAVE THE
NOTION THAT NOTHING WILL LEAVE
YOU AS HUNGRY AS THE APPETITE
FOR MORE.
ON THE OTHER HAND, YOU HAVE
SOMETHING THAT YOU BELIEVE IN SO
DEEPLY THAT YOU WOULD RATHER
LOSE THIS ELECTION THAN WIN AND
HAVE TO COMPROMISE ON THAT
THING.
IS THAT TRUE FOR YOU?
AND IF IT IS, WHAT MATTERS TO
YOU SO MUCH THAT YOU WOULD
RATHER LOSE THAN WIN AND
COMPROMISE?
>> YOU KNOW, THAT'S A FAIR
QUESTION.
WHEN YOU ARE A CANDIDATE FOR
PRESIDENT, IT'S CERTAINLY NOT
JUST ME, IT'S SECRETARY CLINTON,
ANYBODY ELSE, YOU MEET SO MANY
PEOPLE.
MANY, MANY THOUSANDS -- WE'VE
HAD HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE COMING OUT TO OUR
RALLIES.
WONDERFUL PEOPLE.
I MEAN, FROM ALL WALKS OF LIFE.
AND JUST TODAY WE WERE IN
NORFOLK, AND KIDS COME UP TO ME
AND SAY, YOU'VE GIVEN ME HOPE.
AND YOU'VE REKINDLED MY INTEREST
IN DEMOCRACY AND IN POLITICS.
IF I LET THOSE PEOPLE DOWN WHO
HAVE FAITH IN ME, THAT'S A SCARY
THING WHEN SO MANY PEOPLE HAVE
FAITH IN YOU AND BELIEVE YOU CAN
DO SOMETHING.
SO IT SCARES ME VERY MUCH IF I
EVER LET THOSE PEOPLE DOWN, IT
WOULD BE A TERRIBLE, TERRIBLE
THING.
SO I WILL TRY TO CONTINUE TO DO
MY BEST TO RUN A PRINCIPLE
CAMPAIGN FOR STANDING UP FOR THE
PEOPLE WHO TODAY DON'T HAVE A
LOT OF POWER.
AND HOPEFULLY WILL CONTINUE TO
HAVE THE COURAGE TO TAKE ON
THOSE WHO ARE ABUSING THE POWER
THAT THEY HAVE.
>> SENATOR, TAKE 30 SECONDS,
MAKE YOUR CLOSING PITCH TO THE
PEOPLE OF SOUTH CAROLINA.
>> 30 SECONDS?
>> 30 SECONDS.
>> LOOK, I HAVE KNOWN SECRETARY
CLINTON FOR 25 YEARS.
I RESPECT HER AND I LIKE HER.
YOU KNOW, IN THE MIDST OF A
CAMPAIGN, CRAZY THINGS HAPPEN,
BUT THAT'S THE TRUTH.
I LIKE HER AND I RESPECT HER, SO
THIS IS NOT SOME KIND OF
PERSONALITY FIGHT OR STUFF LIKE
THAT.
WE'RE NOT REPUBLICAN, AFTER ALL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT WHAT I DO BELIEVE IS THAT
GIVEN THE CRISES FACING THIS
COUNTRY, YOU KNOW, AND I'VE
TICKED OFF SOME OF THEM, BUT
ESSENTIALLY IT COMES DOWN TO THE
FACT THAT A VERY FEW PEOPLE
CONTROL OUR ECONOMY, CONTROL OUR
POLITICAL SYSTEM.
IT IS TOO LATE, IN MY VIEW, FOR
ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS AND
ESTABLISHMENT ECONOMICS THAT WE
NEED A POLITICAL REVOLUTION WHEN
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE COME
TOGETHER.
AND BASICALLY SAY THAT OUR
GOVERNMENT BELONGS TO ALL OF US
AND IS GOING TO REPRESENT ALL OF
US.
NOT JUST THE FEW ON TOP.
SO WITH THAT, I WOULD VERY MUCH
APPRECIATE THE SUPPORT OF THE
PEOPLE OF SOUTH CAROLINA NEXT
SATURDAY.
THANK YOU, ALL, VERY MUCH.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU
FOR BEING WITH US TONIGHT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT.
STILL TO COME, HILLARY CLINTON
JOINS US.
YOU ARE WATCHING A CNN
DEMOCRATIC TOWN HALL LIVE IN
SOUTH CAROLINA.
REMEMBER, PRIMARY DAY FAST
APPROACHING.
STAY WITH US.
>>> ALL RIGHT.
WE'RE COMING TO YOU TONIGHT FROM
THE SCHOOL OF LAW AT THE
UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH CAROLINA IN
COLUMBIA FOR THE TIME DEMOCRATIC
TOWN HALL BEFORE VOTERS GO TO
THE POLLS THIS WEEKEND.
NOW, YOU'VE ALREADY MET SENATOR
BERNIE SANDERS.
RIGHT NOW, LET US WELCOME FORMER
SECRETARY OF STATE, FORMER U.S.
SENATOR FROM THE STATE OF NEW
YORK, FORMER FIRST LADY, FORMER
2008 PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE,
HILLARY CLINTON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GREAT TO SEE YOU HERE.
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
I'M SORRY IT TOOK ME A SECOND,
THERE WERE A LOT OF TITLES TO
GET THROUGH THERE.
>> I KNOW.
I'M SORRY ABOUT THAT.
>> SO HERE WE ARE.
YOU FOUGHT OFF A LATE SURGE FROM
BERNIE SANDERS IN NEVADA.
YOUR SUPPORTERS SAY THEY'RE
FEELING MOMENTUM.
YOU PICKED UP A BIG ENDORSEMENT.
THERE'S A GENTLEMAN IN THE FRONT
ROW, CONGRESSMAN CLYBURN, WHO
WOUND UP COMING OUT FOR YOU.
WHERE IS YOUR HEAD ON IT?
DO YOU BELIEVE THAT YOU HAVE
TURNED A CORNER.
>> LOOK, I BELIEVE EVERY
ELECTION OR CAUCUS HAS TO BE
TAKEN SERIOUSLY.
YOU HAVE TO WORK HARD FOR EVERY
VOTE.
THAT'S WHAT I'M GOING TO BE
DOING HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA.
I'M TAKING NO VOTE, NO PLACE FOR
GRANTED.
SO THAT'S NOT HOW I THINK ABOUT
IT.
I THINK THAT, YOU KNOW, WE HAVE
HAD THREE CONTESTS, WE HAVE
ABOUT 47 TO GO.
AND I'M GOING TO WORK HARD ON
EACH AND EVERY ONE OF THEM.
>> NOW I NOTICE YOU DID NOT
BRING ME ANY PACKAGE OF PAPER
TONIGHT OF SPEECH TRANSCRIPTS.
EARLIER TONIGHT I ASKED SENATOR
SANDERS WILL YOU GIVE YOUR
TRANSCRIPTS AS SPEECHERS, YOU
SAID WHEN OTHERS GIVE, I'LL
GIVE.
HE SAID HE DOESN'T HAVE THE
SPEECHES.
IF HE CAN FIND THE SPEECHES HE
DID FOR MONEY, HE'LL GLADLY GIVE
THE TRANSCRIPTS UP.
WILL YOU AGREE TO RELEASE THESE
TRAN
TRANSCRIPTS?
THAT HAS BECOME AN ISSUE.
>> IF EVERYBODY DOES IT.
THAT INCLUDES THE REPUBLICANS.
THEY HAVE MADE A LOT OF
SPEECHES.
WHAT IS THIS ABOUT?
THIS IS ABOUT WHETHER I HAVE THE
BEST PLAN TO GO AFTER WALL
STREET, A RECORD THAT ALREADY
DEMONSTRATES MY WILLINGNESS TO
TAKE ON WALL STREET AND
FINANCIAL INTERESTS.
THERE'S NO QUESTION ABOUT THAT.
I DID IT BEFORE THE '08 CRASH.
I'VE DONE IT SINCE IN THIS
CAMPAIGN, I'VE BEEN ABSOLUTELY
CLEAR.
A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE SAID I HAVE
THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE,
EFFECTIVE, COMPREHENSIVE PLAN TO
MAKE SURE WALL STREET NEVER
WRECKS MAIN STREET AGAIN.
I'VE ALSO SAID I WILL USE THE
TOOLS THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA
ACHIEVED IN THE DODD/FRANK
REGULATIONS.
BEST, TIGHTEST REGULATIONS WE'VE
HAD IN A LONG TIME, AND THEY
PROVIDE THE OPPORTUNITY TO BREAK
UP THE BANKS IF THEY POSE
SYSTEMIC RISKS AND I'VE SAID I
WILL DO THAT.
IF THAT BECOMES THE CASE.
>> ALL THE MORE REASON TO MOVE
THIS AS AN ISSUE.
YOU KNOW EVERYBODY IS NOT GOING
TO BRING UP THEIR TRANSCRIPTS.
THERE WILL BE 100 REASONS WHY.
>> WHY IS THERE ONE STANDARD FOR
ME AND NOT FOR EVERYBODY ELSE,
CHRIS?
I MEAN, AT SOME POINT, AT SOL
POINT, YOU KNOW, LOOK, I'M ON
RECORD.
I HAVE A RECORD.
IT CERTAINLY IS FAR DIFFERENT
FROM THE REPUBLICANS BECAUSE
THEY THINK, ACTUALLY, AND HAVE
SAID THAT THE CAUSE OF THE GREAT
RECESSION WAS TOO MUCH
REGULATION ON WALL STREET WHICH
IS AN ABSOLUTE JOKE.
I HAVE BEEN UP FRONT AND STRONG
ON THIS ISSUE FOR A LONG TIME.
AS STRONG, I WOULD ARGUE, AS MY
ESTEEMED OPPONENT.
SO, YOU KNOW WHAT, IF PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO ASK FOR THINGS,
EVERYBODY SHOULD BE ON A LEVEL
PLAYING FIELD AND I'M HAPPY IF
THAT WERE THE CASE.
>> YOU DO UNDERSTAND, THOUGH,
THE TEMPTATION OF THE UNKNOWN?
I DON'T HAVE TO EXPLAIN THIS TO
YOU.
YOU UNDERSTAND THAT WHEN PEOPLE
ASK FOR SOMETHING --
>> WITH ALL DUE RESPECT, THERE
IS NO UNKNOWN.
I AM ON RECORD, I WENT TO WALL
STREET BEFORE THE GREAT
RECESSION.
I CALLED THEM OUT.
I SAID WHAT THEY WERE DOING IN
THE MORTGAGE MARKET WAS GOING TO
CAUSE SERIOUS PROBLEMS.
I CALLED FOR REINING IN CEO PAY,
I CALLED FOR ENDING THE LOOPHOLE
THAT LETS HEDGE FUND MANAGERS
GET A LOWER TAX RATE.
I HAVE BEEN ON RECORD FOR A
REALLY LONG TIME.
I'VE NOW PUT FORTH A PLAN, IT'S
IN PUBLIC ARENA.
I WANT TO PEOPLE TO HOLD ME
ACCOUNTABLE.
THAT'S WHAT I'D DO.
THE OTHER PART OF THIS I FIND
SOMEWHAT CONCERNING, ACTUALLY,
IS THE ARGUMENT SEEMS TO BE THAT
IF YOU EVER TOOK MONEY FROM ANY
BUSINESS, OF ANY KIND, THEN YOU
CAN'T FULFILL YOUR PUBLIC
RESPONSIBILITIES.
WELL, THAT'S JUST NOT THE CASE.
I MEAN, PRESIDENT OBAMA TOOK AN
ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF MONEY, MORE
THAN ANYBODY EVER HAD FROM WALL
STREET IN 2008 WHEN HE WAS
SUCCESSFUL IN HIS ELECTION, AND
THEN HE TURNED AROUND AND PUSHED
THROUGH THE TOUGHEST REGULATIONS
THAT WE'VE SEEN SINCE THE GREAT
DEPRESSION.
SO THE ARGUMENT JUST DOESN'T
HOLD UP, BUT, AGAIN, YOU KNOW,
IF EVERYBODY'S GOING TO DO THE
SAME THING, THEN I'LL BE PART OF
IT.
>> WE WILL CONTINUE TO WAIT,
THEN, AND SEE WHAT HAPPENS ON
THAT ISSUE, BUT THERE ARE OTHERS
THAT MUST BE COVERED, OF COURSE.
PRESIDENT OBAMA JUST RELEASED
HIS PLAN TO CLOSE GUANTANAMO
BAY.
YOU'VE SAID YOU BELIEVE IN THE
PLAN.
ONE PART OF IT, THOUGH, WILL BE
THE TRANSFER OF THE PEOPLE WHO
ARE THERE NOW.
THERE IS A MILITARY HOLDING
FACILITY IN CHARLESTON, SOUTH
CAROLINA, WHICH MAY RECEIVE SOME
OF THE PEOPLE FROM GUANTANAMO.
TELL THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA, I ASKED THE SAME THING
TO SENATOR SANDERS, WHY IS IT
OKAY TO HAVE SOME OF THE WORST
PEOPLE IN THE WORLD IN THEIR
BACKYARD?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, THE
PRESIDENT HASN'T MADE ANY
DECISION ABOUT WHERE THE
TRANSFERS WOULD GO.
AND I THINK WHAT HE WANTS TO,
AND I HOPE HE CAN ACHIEVE THIS,
IS TO WORK WITH THE CONGRESS,
BUT I'VE BEEN ON RECORD IN FAVOR
OF CLOSING GUANTANAMO FOR A LONG
TIME.
SINCE 2008.
WHEN I WAS SECRETARY OF STATE
WORKING CLOSELY WITH THE
PRESIDENT, I HAD A SPECIAL ENVOY
TO FIND PLACES THAT COULD TAKE
BACK SOME OF THE PRISONERS JUST
AS PRESIDENT BUSH HAD DONE
BEFORE PRESIDENT OBAMA.
I BELIEVE THE PRESIDENT IS RIGHT
TO TRY TO CLOSE IT.
I THINK IT IS A CONTINUING
RECRUITMENT ADVERTISEMENT FOR
TERRORISTS.
I KNOW THAT HE WANTS TO WORK
WITH THE CONGRESS AND I HOPE THE
CONGRESS WILL WORK WITH HIM,
CHRIS, BECAUSE THERE IS NO
REASON FOR US TO CONTINUE TO
HAVE GUANTANAMO WHICH IS A VERY
SERIOUS, I GEUESS, SYMBOL, I
WOULD SAY, FOR A LOT OF THE
PEOPLE AROUND THE WORLD WHO
WOULD DO US HARM AND TRY TO
RECRUIT OTHERS TO DO US HARM.
SO WHERE THEY END UP SHOULD BE A
MATTER OF NEGOTIATION.
I KNOW THAT'S WHAT THE PRESIDENT
WANTS TO DO.
I WILL SAY THIS, WE'VE GOT A FEW
PLACES IN THE COUNTRY, NOT HERE,
BUT, YOU KNOW, THE MAXIMUM
SECURITY PLACE THAT I THINK IS
IN COLORADO, THERE'S ONE IN
ILLINOIS, THAT HOLD SOME REALLY
TERRIBLE PEOPLE WHO HAVE
COMMITTED HORRIFIC CRIMES
INCLUDING THE MASTERMIND OF THE
FIRST ATTACK ON THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER IN 1993.
THE PRESIDENT'S TRYING TO FIGURE
OUT WHAT TO DO WITH PEOPLE WHO
ARE TOO DANGEROUS TO BE
RELEASED, WHO HAVE TO BE
MAINTAINED IN A VERY TOUGH
MAXIMUM SECURITY ENVIRONMENT.
AND ALL I CAN HOPE IS THAT THE
CONGRESS WILL WORK WITH HIM.
I REMEMBER BACK IN THE '08
ELECTION, PRESIDENT OBAMA,
SENATOR McCAIN AND I ALL HAD THE
SAME POSITION SO I HOPE SOME OF
THE REPUBLICANS WILL UNDERSTAND
THAT WE'RE IN A FIGHT AGAINST
TERRORISM, WE HAVE TO DEFEAT IT,
WE DON'T NEED TO HAVE GUANTANAMO
HANGING OUT THERE OVER OUR
HEADS.
>> MEMORY IS SHORT FOR
COMPROMISE IN COMEDY THESE DAYS.
COMETY, NOT THE JOKE THAT WE
BEHOLD.
LET'S START WITH FOREIGN POLICY.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET A STUDENT
HERE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH
CAROLINA, RAN FOR STUDENT BODY
PRESIDENT.
HE IS AN INDEPENDENT VOTER, SAYS
HE IS UNDECIDED.
HAS A QUESTION FOR YOU,
SECRETARY.
>> GREAT, GREAT.
>> GOOD EVENING, MRS. CLINTON.
>> GOOD EVENING.
>> FIRST OF ALL, I HOPE YOUR
CAMPAIGN GOES BETTER THAN MINE
DEAD.
>> WELL, DO NOT GIVE UP.
>> OH, NO, MA'AM.
>> KEEP GOING IF IT'S SOMETHING
YOU WANT TO DO, DON'T GET
DETERRED.
>> THANK YOU.
MADAM SECRETARY, YOU ARE FOR A
REGIME CHANGE IN SYRIA.
AS WE LEARNED IN IRAQ, RECENTLY
LIBYA, GETTING RID OF LONGTIME
DICTATORS AND AFFILIATES CAN
LEAD TO PROBLEMS UNFORESEEN.
IF ASSAD WAS TO BE DEPOSED, HOW
WOULD YOU DIRECT THE STATE
DEPARTMENT AND NATIONAL PARTNERS
TO INSTALL WITHIN THAT COUNTRY A
GOVERNMENT CAPABLE OF CONTAINING
AND MITIGATING THE SECTARIAN AND
INSURGENCY VIOLENCE THAT WILL
UNDOUBTEDLY INCREASE THUS
FURTHER DESTABILIZING THE
REGION?
>> THAT'S AN EXCELLENT QUESTION.
LET ME SAY, FIRST OF ALL,
TALKING ABOUT SYRIA AND LIBYA,
IN SYRIA, IT LOOKS LIKE, AND I
HOPE IT'S THE CASE, WE WILL HAVE
A CEASE-FIRE BY THE WEEKEND.
I KNOW THAT SECRETARY KERRY HAS
BEEN WORKING VERY HARD ON THAT
AND I HOPE THAT TAKES HOLD
BECAUSE WE NEED TO TURN THE
ATTENTION OF EVERYONE IN SYRIA
TO DEFEATING THE TERRORISTS AND
WE'VE GOT TO STOP THE ONGOING
BOMBING THAT RUSSIA HAS CARRIED
OUT IN SUPPORT OF THE ASSAD
REGIME AGAINST THE SYRIANS,
THEMSELVES, WHO ARE TRYING TO,
YOU KNOW, WAGE A CIVIL WAR
AGAINST ASSAD.
SO I'M HOPING THAT THAT HAPPENS
BECAUSE WE DO HAVE SOME WORK TO
DO AND I WOULD LIKE IT TO BE
WORK THAT, NUMBER ONE, HAS SAFE
HAVENS FOR PEOPLE IN SYRIA,
NUMBER TWO, BEGINS A POLITICAL
DIALOGUE WHICH WAS YOUR
QUESTION, HOW DO YOU CREATE SOME
KIND OF OUTCOME THAT WILL HAVE A
MORE STABLE FUTURE?
WHO DO YOU GET AT THE TABLE?
I WORKED ON THAT WHEN I WAS
SECRETARY OF STATE.
I KNOW SECRETARY KERRY CONTINUES
THAT WORK.
AND THE RUSSIANS AND THE
IRANIANS ARE THE TWO BIGGEST
SUPPORTERS OF THE ASSAD REGIME.
SO THEY HAVE TO BE PART OF ANY
KIND OF ONGOING POLITICAL
DIPLOMATIC EFFORT.
LIBYA'S A LITTLE DIFFERENT.
YOU KNOW, LIBYA ACTUALLY HELD
ELECTIONS.
THEY ELECTED MODERATES.
THEY HAVE TRIED TO PIECE
TOGETHER A GOVERNMENT AGAINST A
LOT OF REALLY SERIOUS CHALLENGES
INTERNALLY COMING FROM THE
OUTSIDE WITH TERRORIST GROUPS
AND OTHER BAD ACTORS.
THEY'RE WORKING TO TRY TO UNIFY
THE DIFFERENT FACTIONS INSIDE
LIBYA SO THEY CAN TAKE UNITED
ACTION AGAINST THE TERRORISTS
AND TRY TO GET THE EAST AND THE
WEST OF THE COUNTRY WORKING
TOGETHER.
YOU KNOW, THEREY'RE A RICH
COUNTRY.
THEY HAVE OIL.
THEY ARE NOT WITHOUT RESOURCE
BUT THEY'VE GOT TO GET OVER
THEIR INTERNAL DISPUTES AND THE
UNITED STATES, EUROPE, AND
OTHERS ARE HELPING THEM TO TRY
TO DO THAT AND I THINK THEY NEED
TIME AND SUPPORT.
I KNOW THE UNITED STATES HAS
TAKEN ACTIONS AGAINST TERRORISTS
INSIDE LIBYA, PARTICULARLY ISIS
TRAINING CAMPS AND I SUPPORT
THAT BECAUSE I WANT TO GIVE THE
PEOPLE OF LIBYA A CHANCE TO
ACTUALLY FORM A GOVERNMENT AND
REALIZE THE PROMISE OF GETTING
RID OF GADHAFI WHO HAD SO
OPPRESSED THE COUNTRY FOR, YOU
KNOW, MORE THAN 40 YEARS.
HOLLOWED OUT ALL THE
INSTITUTIONS.
THREATENED GENOCIDE AGAINST HIS
OWN PEOPLE WHICH IS ONE OF THE
REASONS WHY THE REST OF THE
WORLD INTERVENED.
AND I'M HOPING THAT WE CAN GIVE
THEM THE TIME AND SPACE TO
ACTUALLY MAKE A DIFFERENCE FOR
THEY'RE COUNTRY IN THE FUTURE.
>> HOW DO YOU EXPLAIN THE TIME
AND SPACE TO PEOPLE?
WHEN YOU LOOK AT -- FOR EXAMPLE,
YOU'RE RIGHT ABOUT ISIS BEING
THERE.
BY MOST ESTIMATES IT'S IN A
NIGHTMARE PHASE.
SEE WHAT HAPPENS WHEN WE GET
INVOLVED, SEE WHAT HAPPENS WHEN
WE TAKE SOMEONE OUT, WE DON'T
KNOW WHAT'S GOING TO REPLACE IT.
DO YOU BELIEVE THERE'S A MISTAKE
INVOLVED IN LIBYA?
>> LET ME MAKE TWO POINTS.
ONE, LET'S REMEMBER WHAT WAS
GOING ON AT THE TIME, THE HEIGHT
OF THE ARAB SPRING.
THE PEOPLE IN LIBYA WERE
EXPRESSING THEMSELVES, WERE
DEMANDING THEIR FREEDOM AND
GADHAFI RESPONDED BRUTALLY AND
SAID THAT HE WOULD JUST HUNT
THEM DOWN LIKE COCKROACHES AND
MADE IT VERY CLEAR HE WOULD USE
HIS MERCENARIES BECAUSE HE
DIDN'T HAVE A STANDING ARMY, HE
HAD A LOT OF HIRED MERCENARIES
FROM AROUND TO DO LITERALLY
THAT.
THE EUROPEANS WHO ARE ACROSS THE
SEA FROM LIBYA, YOU KNOW, CAME
TO US AND SAID, THIS IS ON OUR
DOORSTEP, WE NEED YOUR HELP.
BASICALLY THEY SAID, WE'RE WITH
YOU IN AFGHANISTAN, WE NEED YOU
NOW TO HELP US WITH LIBYA
BECAUSE WE'VE GOT TO PREVENT
THIS TERRIBLE HAPPENING THAT
COULD RESULT FROM GADHAFI.
WE HAD ARABS COME TO US AND SAY
THE SAME THING.
WE FORMED THE FIRST COALITION
BETWEEN NATO AND A ARAB NATIONS.
ARAB NATIONS ACTUALLY RAN A LOT
OF THE AIR CAMPAIGN AND OTHER
SUPPORT SYSTEMS.
SO I THINK YOU HAVE TO LOOK AT
WHAT WAS GOING ON AT THE TIME
AND WHY IT SEEMED, AND I AGREE
WITH THIS, TO MAKE SENSE FOR US
TO BRING OUR SPECIAL ASSETS TO
THE TABLE TO HELP THE PEOPLE OF
LIBYA.
NOW, I GO BACK TO THIS POINT,
THEY HAD AN ELECTION AND IT WAS
A GOOD ELECTION.
IT WAS A FAIR ELECTION.
IT MET INTERNATIONAL STANDARDS.
THAT WAS AN AMAZING
ACCOMPLISHMENT FOR A NATION THAT
HAD BEEN SO DEPRIVED FOR SO
LONG.
YOU KNOW, THE UNITED STATES WAS
IN KOREA AND STILL IS FOR MANY
YEARS.
WE ARE STILL IN GERMANY.
WE ARE STILL IN JAPAN.
WE HAVE A PRESENCE IN A LOT OF
PLACES IN THE WORLD THAT STARTED
OUT AS A RESULT OF CONFLICT.
AND IF YOU THINK ABOUT SOUTH
KOREA, THERE WERE COUPS,
ASSASSINATIONS, A LOT OF
PROBLEMS FOR THE KOREANS TO
BUILD THEIR ECONOMY, CREATE
THEIR DEMOCRACY.
THIS DOESN'T HAPPEN OVERNIGHT.
YES, IT'S BEEN A COUPLE OF
YEARS.
I THINK IT'S WORTH EUROPEAN
SUPPORT, ARAB SUPPORT, AMERICAN
SUPPORT TO TRY TO HELP THE
LIBYAN PEOPLE REALIZE THE DREAM
THEY HAD WHEN THEY WENT AFTER
GADHAFI.
>> A YOUNG LADY STANDING, HAS A
QUESTION FOR YOU.
HER NAME IS KYLA GRAY.
SHE'S A STUDENT AT COLUMBIA
COLLEGE.
SHE'S LEANING IN YOUR FAVORITE
BUT YOU HAVE WORK TO DO WITH
KYLA.
SHE HAS NOT MADE UP HER MIND
COMPLETELY YET.
KYLA, WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION FOR
THE SECRETARY?
>> GOOD EVENING.
RECENTLY I STARTED WEARING MY
HAIR NATURAL --
>> I'M SORRY, STARTED WHAT?
>> RECENTLY I STARTED WEARING MY
HAIR NATURAL AND I'VE NOTICED A
DIFFERENCE IN THE WAY SOME
PEOPLE ADDRESS AND LOOK AT ME.
IN THE WAKE OF THING LIKE
FERGUSON AND BLACK LIVES MATTER
AND THE RECENT BACKLASH AGAINST
BEYONCE FOR HER FORMATION VIDEO.
THERE HAVE BEEN A LOT OF RACIAL
TENSIONS RECENTLY IN OUR NATION.
SO MY QUESTION TO YOU IS WHAT DO
YOU INTEND TO DO TO HELP FIX THE
BROKEN RACIAL RELATIONS IN OUR
NATION?
>> WELL, KYLA, FIRST OF ALL,
THANK YOU FOR BEING SO CANDID
AND BRAVE TO STAND UP AND SAY
THIS ABOUT YOURSELF BECAUSE I
THINK IT REALLY HELPS TO SHINE A
SPOTLIGHT ON WHAT OUR, ONE OF
THE MANY BARRIERS THAT STAND IN
THE WAY OF PEOPLE FEELING LIKE
THEY CAN PURSUE THEIR OWN
DREAMS, BE WHO THEY ARE, THEY
CAN HAVE THE FUTURE THAT THEY
WANT IN OUR COUNTRY, AND I
BELIEVE STRONGLY WE HAVE TO DEAL
WITH SYSTEMIC RACISM AND
SYSTEMIC RACISM IS FOUND IN OUR
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM, IT'S
FOUND IN HOUSING, IN JOB
OPPORTUNITIES, IN EDUCATION.
AND IT'S ALSO CULTURAL.
AND SO THERE ARE BARRIERS THAT
PEOPLE ARE ENCOUNTERING THAT I
THINK WE NEED TO BE HONEST
ABOUT.
YOU KNOW, I JUST CAME FROM
CENTRAL BAPTIST CHURCH WITH
MOTHERS OF THE MOVEMENT.
I THINK THEY MIGHT BE HERE.
AND, YES, THEY ARE.
YOU KNOW, I'D WANT THEM TO STAND
UP, IF YOU DON'T MIND.
I MEAN, THESE ARE THE BRAVEST
WOMEN --
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU KNOW, THESE -- THESE FIVE
WOMEN HAVE LOST CHILDREN TO
POLICE ACTIONS AND TO RANDOM
SENSELESS GUN VIOLENCE.
AND THERE'S NO DOUBT THAT IN
EACH CASE, AS THEY SAID AT THE
CHURCH EARLIER, THERE IS A
RACIAL COMPONENT TO IT.
A YOUNG BLACK TEENAGER, 17 YEARS
OLD, PLAYING THE MUSIC IN HIS
CAR TOO LOUD WITH A BUNCH OF HIS
FRIENDS AND A WHITE GUY COMES UP
AND TELLS THEM TO TURN THE MUSIC
DOWN.
THEY EXCHANGE WORDS.
THE MAN PULLS OUT HIS GUN AND
KILLS HIM.
SO WE HAVE SERIOUS CHALLENGES,
AND I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT FOR
PEOPLE, AND PARTICULARLY FOR
WHITE PEOPLE, TO BE HONEST ABOUT
THOSE AND TO RECOGNIZE THAT OUR
EXPERIENCES MAY NOT EQUIP US TO
UNDERSTAND WHAT A LOT OF OUR
AFRICAN-AMERICAN FELLOW CITIZENS
GO THROUGH EVERY SINGLE DAY.
SO, FOR ME, WHEN I TALK ABOUT
BREAKING DOWN ALL THE BARRIERS
THAT STAND IN THE WAY OF
PEOPLE'S AMBITIONS AND DREAMS,
RACISM ALONG WITH ECONOMIC
ISSUES, EDUCATIONAL ISSUES, AND
ALL THE REST, HAVE TO BE
ADDRESSED.
OTHERWISE, YOU KNOW, WE ARE
NEVER GOING TO BE THE NATION WE
SHOULD BE.
WE'RE NEVER GOING TO OVERCOME
OUR LEGACY.
YOU KNOW, DATING BACK TO
SLAVERY, SEGREGATION, JIM CROW,
IT IS STILL, UNFORTUNATELY,
ALIVE AND WELL AND YOU'VE GOT
PLACES IN THIS STATE WHERE AN
AFRICAN-AMERICAN BABY HAS A
HIGHER RATE OF DYING THAN YOU
HAVE IN A LOT OF OTHER PLACES.
THE INFANT MORTALITY RATE CAN BE
COMPARED TO SOME THIRD WORLD
POOR COUNTRIES.
YOU KNOW, IN THIS STATE, YOUR
GOVERNOR AND LEGISLATURE
WOULDN'T EXTEND MEDICAID AND SO
PEOPLE CAN'T GET THE HEALTH CARE
THAT THEY DESERVE TO HAVE.
SO I THINK THERE ARE A LOT OF
BARRIERS THAT WE HAVE TO BE
HONEST ABOUT, AND I THINK
HONESTY AND WILLINGNESS TO
LISTEN TO EACH OTHER, ACTUALLY
RESPECT EACH OTHER, WOULD GO A
LONG WAY TOWARD US ROLLING UP
OUR SLEEVES AND DEALING WITH A
LOT OF THESE ISSUES AND GIVING
YOU THE FEELING THAT YOU HAVE A
RIGHT TO WEAR YOUR HAIR ANY WAY
YOU WANT TO.
THAT'S YOUR RIGHT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW --
>> YOU LOOK GREAT.
>> AS SOMEBODY WHO HAS HAD A LOT
OF DIFFERENT HAIRSTYLES.
I SAY THAT FROM SOME PERSONAL
EXPERIENCE.
>> I'M JUST HAPPY TO KEEP MY
HAIR.
THAT'S MY WHOLE -- YOU KNOW,
KYLA MENTIONED BEYONCE.
LET'S TALK ABOUT BEYONCE FOR A
SECOND, BECAUSE WHY NOT?
YOU KNOW, SPECIFICALLY, WHAT
HAPPENED AT THE SUPER BOWL
HALFTIME PERFORMANCE.
IT UPSET A LOT OF MEN AND WOMEN
IN THE LAW ENFORCEMENT
COMMUNITY.
THEY FELT THAT THEY WERE
TARGETED.
AND THEY FEEL THAT THIS IS ONE
OF MANY ANTI-POLICE MESSAGES.
AND NOW THERE'S THIS RESULTING
CALL, DON'T BUY HER CDs, DON'T
SUPPORT HER BECAUSE SHE DOES NOT
SUPPORT THE POLICE.
DO YOU UNDERSTAND WHERE THEY'RE
COMING FROM?
DO YOU AGREE?
AND HOW DO YOU SEE IN TERMS OF
RECONCILING THESE POINTS OF
VIEW?
>> YOU KNOW, LOOK, I THINK THERE
ARE AN ENORMOUS NUMBER OF POLICE
OFFICERS IN OUR COUNTRY THAT
PERFORM HONORABLY EVERY SINGLE
DAY.
THEY PUT THEMSELVES IN HARM'S
WAY.
THEY CONNECT WITH THE
COMMUNITIES.
THEY ARE SWORN TO PROTECT.
AND WE SHOULD SHOW THEM ALL THE
RESPECT THAT THEY HAVE EARNED
AND DESERVE.
BUT WE HAVE PROBLEMS IN OUR
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM IN A LOT
OF PLACES THAT WE CAN'T IGNORE.
AND, YOU KNOW, PUT ASIDE ANY
PARTICULAR CELEBRITY OR ANY
PARTICULAR SONG OR PERFORMANCE,
THE FACT IS THAT WE HAVE TOO
MANY INSTANCES HERE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA.
WE HAD WALTER SCOTT, NORTH
CHARLESTON.
THERE WAS A YOUNG WHITE
TEENAGER, IF I BELIEVE RIGHT,
ZACHARY HAMMOND, WHO WAS UNARMED
AND KILLED IN A POLICE ACTION
HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA.
WE HAVE LOST TOO MANY YOUNG
PEOPLE, SO WHAT'S THE ANSWER?
I DON'T THINK THE ANSWER IS FOR
US TO FIND OURSELVES IN OPPOSING
CAMPS WHERE WE'RE JUST GOING TO
BE LOOKING AT EACH OTHER WITH,
YOU KNOW, MISTRUST.
WE HAVE TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE'RE
GOING TO LIFT UP THE GOOD
PRACTICES, REFORM POLICING,
PROVIDE MORE SUPPORT, SO THAT
FORCE IS A LAST RESORT, NOT A
FIRST CHOICE, AND THAT MEANS
HELPING TO TRAIN POLICE SO THAT,
YOU KNOW, WHEN THEY GO OUT ON
THE STREETS, I'M SURE THEY'RE
NERVOUS AND SCARED, TOO, SO HOW
DO WE CREATE A BETTER
UNDERSTANDING ABOUT HOW TO DEAL
WITH DIFFERENT SITUATIONS THAT
DEESCALATE INSTEAD OF ESCALATE?
YOU KNOW, ONE OF THE MOTHERS
HERE, YOU KNOW, LOST HER SON.
SEVERAL POLICE OFFICERS WERE
ASKED TO MOVE HIM OUT OF A
PUBLIC PARK.
THEY SAID, NO, HE HAS A RIGHT TO
BE IN A PUBLIC PARK.
THIS HAPPENED IN MILWAUKEE,
WISCONSIN.
MARIE WRA HAMILTON IS HERE.
HER SON WAS DANTRE.
ONE POLICE OFFICER WHO KNEW
SOMEBODY WHO WAS IN THE
RESTAURANT THAT WANTED HIM MOVED
SHOWED UP AND, YOU KNOW, SO HE
STARTED BEATING THIS YOUNG MAN
WITH A BATON AND WHEN THE YOUNG
MAN, YOU KNOW, TRIED TO PROTECT
HIMSELF AND GRABBED THE BATON,
YOU KNOW, THE OFFICER PULLED OUT
HIS GUN AND SHOT HIM.
NOW, YOU KNOW, NUMEROUS TIMES.
SO WE'VE GOT TO COME TO GRIPS
WITH THE FACT THAT WE'VE GOT TO
DO SOME RETRAINING HERE.
WE'VE GOT TO DO SOME WORK TO
MAKE SURE THAT OUR POLICE ARE
UNDERSTANDING HOW BEST TO DEAL
WITH SITUATIONS WHERE SOMEBODY'S
NOT ARMED, SOMEBODY'S SITTING ON
A PARK BENCH.
AND HE ENDS UP DEAD.
YOU KNOW, SO THERE IS WORK TO BE
DONE, AND I DON'T -- I THINK THE
RIGHT RESPONSE IS, LET'S RESPECT
THE POLICE, LET'S BE SURE THAT
WE HOLD UP THOSE WHO ARE DOING
THE RIGHT THINGS, AND PROTECTING
US AND LET'S TRY TO HELP MORE
POLICE FOLLOW THAT EXAMPLE AND
THEN LET'S HOLD POLICE BEHAVIOR
ACCOUNTABLE SO THAT THERE'S AN
INCENTIVE FOR PEOPLE TO CHANGE
HOW THEY ARE DOING POLICE
PRACTICES.
AND, YOU KNOW, PRESIDENT OBAMA
HAD A POLICING COMMISSION AND,
YOU KNOW, I EMBRACED ALL OF
THEIR RECOMMENDATIONS AND AS
PRESIDENT, YOU KNOW, I WOULD TRY
TO WORK WITH THE POLICE AND WORK
WITH THE COMMUNITY AND WORK WITH
VICTIMS OF VIOLENCE, GETTING
EVERYBODY TOGETHER BECAUSE WHAT
WE WANT TO IS STOP THIS FROM
HAPPENING AGAIN.
WE WANT TO SAVE LIVES.
WE WANT TO PREVENT ANY OTHER
MOTHER FROM GOING THROUGH WHAT
THESE MOTHERS HAVE GONE THROUGH.
THAT WOULD BE MY GOAL AS
PRESIDENT.
>> HAVING ANOTHER FOR YOU.
>> OKAY.
>> SALLY HORN ON THE LEFT, SHE'S
A STUDENT, PART-TIME LAW CLERK.
SAYS SHE'S UNDECIDED.
HAS A QUESTION.
GO AHEAD.
>> HI.
>> WELCOME TO THE PALMETTO
STATE.
>> THANK YOU.
>> I'M FROM ROCKVILLE, SOUTH
CAROLINA AND HAD THE PLEASANT
A
AND DELIGHT OF ATTENDING A
WOMEN'S COLLEGE.
ELABORATE ON HOW ATTENDING A
WOMEN'S COLLEGE PREPARED YOU FOR
THE SPECIFIC CHALLENGE OF
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT ESPECIALLY
WHEN IT'S OFTEN CHALLENGING WHEN
PEOPLE DON'T RECOGNIZE WOMEN'S
ISSUES AS SIGNIFICANT OR WOMEN,
THEMSELVES, AS SIGNIFICANT.
>> WELL, THAT IS A GREAT
QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU.
I HAVE BEEN TO AGNUS SCOTT.
I WENT TO WELLESLEY COLLEGE.
A WOMEN'S COLLEGE.
LOOK, I THINK WHAT I GOT OUT OF
GOING TO A WOMEN'S COLLEGE WAS
THAT WOMEN WERE IN CHARGE OF
EVERYTHING.
YOU KNOW?
THAT'S JUST A FACT.
AND, YOU KNOW, WE RAN THE
STUDENT GOVERNMENT.
WE RAN THE NEWSPAPER.
WE RAN THE YEARBOOK.
WE RAN ALL THE ACTIVITIES.
SO IT WAS A GREAT LEADERSHIP
OPPORTUNITY.
AND, YOU KNOW, I KNOW THAT YOU
CAN FIND THAT IN MANY DIFFERENT
SETTINGS, BUT FOR ME, IT REALLY
HELPED TO GIVE ME THE CONFIDENCE
AND THE UNDERSTANDING OF WHAT
LEADERSHIP MEANT.
IT PUT ME IN SOME CHALLENGING
P
POSITIONS TO ASSOCIATE ISSUES
THAT I LEARNED A LOT FROM.
SO I FEEL VERY GRATEFUL FOR THAT
EXPERIENCE.
AND, YOU KNOW, WHEN I GOT TO THE
UNITED STATES SENATE, I WAS SO
GRATEFUL TO THE WOMEN WHO'D BEEN
THERE BEFORE.
AND WE FORMED A BIPARTISAN GROUP
AND WE USED TO MEET OFF THE
RECORD ON OUR OWN, NO PRESS,
NOTHING EVER REPORTED OUT OF IT,
YOU KNOW, TO TRADE INFORMATION
AND IDEAS ABOUT HOW YOU DID THE
WORK OF BEING A SENATOR.
AND HOW WE COULD SUPPORT EACH
OTHER WHERE APPROPRIATE.
YOU KNOW, FUNNY LITTLE THINGS,
LIKE WHAT DO YOU DO WITH YOUR
HANDBAG?
I MEAN, YOU KNOW, THAT'S AN
ISSUE.
YOU GOT IT FIGURE IT OUT.
SERIOUS THINGS ABOUT HOW WE
COULD SUPPORT EACH OTHER ON
WOMEN'S ISSUES.
HOW WE COULD MAKE SOME OF THE
CONCERNS WE HAD ABOUT CHILDCARE,
ABOUT EQUAL PAY, REAL TO THE
REST OF OUR COLLEAGUES WHO MAY
NOT HAVE THOUGHT ABOUT IT AS
MUCH AS WE HAD.
SO I THINK THERE'S REAL SUPPORT
TO BE FOUND WHEN YOU'RE LUCKY
ENOUGH TO WORK WITH OTHER WOMEN.
AND I WAS CERTAINLY FORTUNATE IN
BOTH THE SENATE AND THE STATE
DEPARTMENT TO HAVE THAT
EXPERIENCE.
AND I GIVE A LOT OF CREDIT TO MY
EDUCATION EQUIPPING ME TO BE
ABLE TO DO THE WORK THAT I'VE
DONE.
>> SECRETARY, HAVE ANOTHER
QUESTION FOR YOU.
JAMIE, SHE'S A LAW STUDENT AT
THE UNIVERSITY OF SOUTH
CAROLINA.
SHE'S LEANING TOWARD SENATOR
SANDERS.
HAS A QUESTION.
>> HI, SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> HI.
>> SO MY MOM SUPPORTS YOU AND
I'VE BEEN LEANING TOWARD BERNIE
FOR SEVERAL REASONS INCLUDING
HE'S NOT CORPORATELY FUNDED.
I FEEL LIKE HE REALLIEY
UNDERSTANDS MY GENERATION'S
PROBLEM WITH STUDENT DEBT AND
HOW MUCH PRESSURE WE'RE UNDER
WITH THAT.
MY QUESTION FOR YOU IS WHAT DO
YOU THINK HAS BEEN CAUSING THIS
COMMON GENERATIONAL GAP THAT I
SEE SO MANY PLACES BETWEEN YOUR
SUPPORTERS AND SENATOR SANDERS'
SUPPORTERS?
>> WELL, I'M NOT SURE, TO BE
HONEST.
I REALLY DON'T KNOW.
I WANT YOU TO KNOW THAT WHETHER
YOU END UP SUPPORTING ME OR NOT,
I WILL SUPPORT YOU.
AND I WILL SUPPORT THE YOUNG
PEOPLE OF THIS COUNTRY BECAUSE
THAT HAS BEEN -- THAT HAS BEEN
MY LIFE'S WORK.
LET ME SAY A WORD ABOUT STUDENT
DEBT BECAUSE I HONESTLY BELIEVE
THAT MY PLAN TO MAKE COLLEGE
AFFORDABLE AND TO HELP YOU PAY
DOWN YOUR STUDENT DEBT IS A VERY
EFFECTIVE WAY OF DOING WHAT I
KNOW MUST BE DONE.
PARTICULARLY WITH STUDENT DEBT,
YOU'RE IN LAW SCHOOL NOW?
>> YES.
>> DID YOU COME OUT OF COLLEGE
WITH DEBT?
>> LUCKILY, I DIDN'T HAVE ANY
DEBT FROM UNDERGRAD, BUT --
>> NOW YOU DO.
>> YES.
>> I BORROWED MONEY WHEN I WAS
IN LAW SCHOOL ALSO.
>> YES.
>> AND I KNOW THAT IS CAN BE A
BURDEN AND SO HERE'S WHAT I WANT
TO DO.
I WANT YOU TO BE ABLE TO
REFINANCE YOUR DEBT AT MUCH
LOWER INTEREST RATES.
IT MAKES NO SENSE AT ALL THAT
YOU'RE PAYING -- DO YOU KNOW
WHAT YOUR INTEREST RATE IS?
>> IT'S BETWEEN 7% AND 9%.
I'M ALREADY $75,000 IN DEBT AND
I'M ONLY HALFWAY THROUGH.
>> YOU KNOW, I WANT EVERYBODY TO
UNDERSTAND THIS, SHE BORROWED
MONEY FOR THE PRINCIPLE AND TO
BE ABLE TO PAY HER FEES TO GO TO
LAW SCHOOL AND I WOULD BET A
GOOD PERCENTAGE OF WHAT YOU NOW
OWE IS BECAUSE OF THE INTEREST.
A 7% TO 9% INTEREST RATE WHEN WE
HAVEN'T HAD INTEREST RATES THAT
HIGH IN YEARS.
IT MAKES ABSOLUTELY NO SENSE.
WE NEED TO REFINANCE IT, WE NEED
TO STRIP AS MUCH OF THE INTEREST
PAYMENTS OUT THAT WE POSSIBLY
CAN.
WE NEED TO GIVE YOU A CHANCE TO
MOVE INTO A CONTINGENCY
REPAYMENT PROGRAM.
THAT'S WHAT I HAD WHEN I WENT TO
LAW SCHOOL.
I PAID BACK MY LOAN AT A
PERCENTAGE OF MY INCOME BECAUSE
I WENT TO WORK FOR THE
CHILDREN'S DEFENSE FUND RIGHT
OUT OF LAW SCHOOL.
AND I DIDN'T MAKE MUCH MONEY AT
ALL.
I CAN'T EVEN REMEMBER.
THINK $14,000 IS WHAT STICKS IN
MY HEAD.
I PAID IT BACK AS A PERCENT OF
MY I CNCOME.
SO I COULD GO TO WORK AND DO THE
WORK I LOVE DOING.
BROUGHT ME TO SOUTH CAROLINA TO
DO A PROJECT TO GET KIDS OUT OF
ADULT JAILS.
I REALLY AM GRATEFUL FOR THAT.
SO I WANT TO MOVE YOU INTO THOSE
PROGRAMS THEN I WANT TO HAVE A
DATE CERTAIN WHEN YOUR DEBT
ENDS.
I DON'T THINK YOU SHOULD BE
PAYING DEBT MORE THAN 20 YEARS
AT ALL AND SHORTER IF WE CAN
FIGURE OUT HOW TO DO IT.
AND I DON'T THINK THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE MAKING
MONEY OFF OF LENDING YOU MONEY
TO GET YOUR EDUCATION.
I THINK WE'VE GOT TO FIX THAT AS
WELL.
AND I'M GOING TO BE INTRODUCING
MORE NATIONAL SERVICE JOBS SO
THAT IF YOU DO NATIONAL SERVICE,
YOU CAN GET BASICALLY YOUR
EDUCATION FREE WHICH I THINK WE
SHOULD DO TO HAVE MORE YOUNG
PEOPLE INVOLVED IN NATIONAL
SERVICE.
AND THEN ON THE AFFORDABILITY
SIDE, I DO DISAGREE WITH SENATOR
SANDERS ABOUT HIS PLAN ABOUT
FREE COLLEGE BECAUSE I WANT TO
HAVE DEBT-FREE TUITION BUT I
DON'T BELIEVE MY FAMILY OR
DONALD TRUMP'S FAMILY OR A LOT
OF OTHER FAMILIES THAT CAN
AFFORD IT SHOULD HAVE THE
ADVANTAGE OF FREE COLLEGE.
I THINK THEY SHOULD BE
CONTRIBUTING ON BEHALF OF THEIR
CHILDREN.
I WANT --
>> SECRETARY --
>> I WANT THIS TO BE A PROGRAM
WHERE WE HAVE AFFORDABILITY AND
I HAVE A PARTICULAR COMMITMENT
TO THE HISTORICALLY BLACK
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
BECAUSE BOTH THE PUBLIC AND THE
PRIVATE HBCUs DO SO MUCH GOOD.
I HOPE YOU'LL GO TO MY WEBSITE,
HILLARYCLINTON.COM AND LOOK AT
WHAT I'M ACTUALLY PROPOSING
BECAUSE I THINK YOU MIGHT FIND
IT INTERESTING THEN GO TALK TO
YOUR MOTHER.
>> ALL RIGHT.
ON YOUR LEFT, WE HAVE THE
REVEREND ROBERT COOPER.
HE'S THE PRESIDING ELDER OF THE
FLORENCE DYLAN DISTRICT FOR THE
AME CHURCH.
>> OKAY.
>> HE'S STILL UNDECIDED AND HAS
A QUESTION FOR YOU.
REVEREND?
>> HI, REVEREND.
>> GOOD EVENING, MADAM
SECRETARY.
I'M REVEREND COOPER.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS THAT MY
CONCERN IS ABOUT THE ILLNESS OF
THE FAMILY, THE DEGENERATION OF
THE VALUE OF THE FAMILY.
WHEN YOU LOOK AT THE STAGE OF
AMERICANS, ALL THE ACTORS,
LITTLE CHILDREN THAT USED TO SIT
AROUND MOM AND DAD TABLE, ALL
THE SHOOTING, THE LOOTING AND
THE KILLING.
THEY ONCE SAT AROUND MOM AND DAD
TABLE.
THAT WAS THE FIRST ACADEMY THEY
EVER ATTENDED.
AND IT POINTS TO THERE IS AN
ILLNESS IN THE FAMILY.
SEEMING THOUGH THE YOUNG PEOPLE
HAVE TO TAKE ALL THE BLAME FOR
IT.
WHEN YOU THINK ABOUT THE
SHOOTING THAT HAPPENED IN
CHARLESTON JUST A FEW MONTHS
AGO, IF THAT YOUNG MAN HAD A
CHANCE TO HAVE BREAKFAST WITH
HIS MOTHER OR A TIGHT-KNIT
FAMILY, SOMEONE WOULD HAVE
DETECTED THAT HE HAD A PROBLEM
AND MIGHT NOT WOULD HAVE
HAPPENED.
IF YOU WERE TO BECOME PRESIDENT,
WHAT WOULD YOU DO TO HELP SOME
WELLNESS COME BACK TO AMERICAN
FAMILIES?
>> YOU KNOW, REVEREND, I THINK
YOUR QUESTION IS AN INCREDIBLY
IMPORTANT ONE BECAUSE STRONG
FAMILIES ARE AT THE CORE OF A
STRONG SOCIETY, A STRONG
AMERICA, AND THE FAMILY IS THE
FIRST INTRODUCTION ANY CHILD HAS
TO HOW TO BEHAVE IN SOCIETY,
WHAT'S EXPECTED, WHAT THE VALUES
SHOULD BE.
SO WE DO HAVE TO DO MORE TO HELP
LIFT UP FAMILIES AND SUPPORT
FAMILIES.
AND A LOT OF FAMILIES ARE UNDER
TREMENDOUS ECONOMIC STRESS RIGHT
NOW.
AND A LOT OF FAMILIES JUST ARE
TRYING TO KEEP BODY AND SOUL
TOGETHER, TRYING TO MAKE ENOUGH
MONEY TO KEEP FOOD ON THE TABLE
AND A ROOF OVER THE HEAD.
AND THE WORKING HOURS THAT ARE
DEMANDED BY SO MANY EMPLOYERS
MAKE IT DIFFICULT FOR A LOT OF
FAMILIES, PARTICULARLY HEADED BY
SINGLE MOTHERS, TO BE ABLE TO
SPEND THE TIME THAT YOU WOULD
WANT AND I WOULD, OF COURSE,
WANT, TO SEE FAMILIES SPEND
TOGETHER.
SO I THINK IT'S BOTH AN ECONOMIC
ISSUE AS WELL AS A SORT OF
PERSONAL ISSUE.
ON THE ECONOMIC FRONT, LET'S
RAISE THAT MINIMUM WAGE.
LET'S GET MORE INCOME INTO THE
POCKETS OF THOSE WOMEN WHO ARE
MINIMUM WAGE WORKERS.
LET'S GET EQUAL PAY SO THAT
PEOPLE WHO ARE WORKING HARD ARE
GIVEN THE DIGNITY, THE RESPECT,
AND THE INCOME THEY DESERVE.
LET'S GET INCOMES RISING AGAIN.
LET'S GET MORE GOOD JOBS FOR
MORE PEOPLE.
SOMETHING THAT WOULD HELP THE
FAMILY FEEL THAT THEY WEREN'T ON
SUCH ROCKY TERRAIN AND NOT SURE
WHERE THE NEXT STEP WOULD BE.
AND ALSO LET'S DO MORE TO HELP
SUPPORT FAMILIES AS THEY RAISE
THEIR CHILDREN.
AND I THINK THIS IS NOT
SOMETHING THAT CAN BE DONE ONLY
BY THE GOVERNMENT.
I WROTE A BOOK CALLED "IT TAKES
A VILLAGE TO RAISE A CHILD."
I BELIEVE THAT.
I THINK FAITH INSTITUTIONS,
COMMUNITY INSTITUTIONS, TRYING
TO GET THE EXTENDED FAMILY TO BE
MORE SUPPORTIVE ARE ALL PART OF
HOW WE HELP FAMILIES DO RIGHT BY
THEIR OWN KIDS.
AND I THINK WE CAN ALSO DO MORE
WITH BETTER EARLY CHILDHOOD
EDUCATION WHEN FAMILIES ARE
LOOKING FOR IT, THEY CAN'T
AFFORD IT.
UNIVERSAL PRE-K PROGRAM SO THAT
MORE KIDS GET OFF TO A GOOD
START IN L SCHOOL.
BUT TIME IS THE MOST PRECIOUS
COMMODITY AND WE NEED TO FIGURE
OUT HOW WE GET MORE INCOME INTO
FAMILIES SO THEY CAN ACTUALLY
HAVE MORE TIME WITH THEIR KIDS.
AND I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN
BECAUSE I BELIEVE IN THIS.
THAT'S HOW I WAS RAISED.
YOU KNOW, MY HUSBAND AND I, YOU
KNOW, CERTAINLY DID EVERYTHING
WE COULD TO MAKE SURE THAT ONE
OR BOTH OF US WAS HOME WITH OUR
DAUGHTER.
THAT WE WERE THERE AT NIGHT TO
HAVE DINNER, TO, YOU KNOW, READ
TO HER BEFORE SHE WENT TO SLEEP.
AND WE BELIEVE IN THAT.
AND WE KNOW IT MAKES A
DIFFERENCE FOR THE CHILDREN.
SO WHAT WE WANT TO IS TO HELP
MORE FAMILIES HAVE THE SUPPORT
THEY NEED WHICH TOO MANY OF THEM
DON'T HAVE RIGHT NOW.
TO BE ABLE TO DO MORE TO GET
THEIR OWN KIDS OFF TO A GOOD
START.
AND I THINK THAT WOULD BE A
GREAT WAY TO HELP FAMILIES AND
TO HELP OUR COUNTRY GET STRONGER
IN THE FUTURE.
>> SECRETARY, SPEAKING OF TIME,
FORTUNATELY WE HAVE MORE TIME
TONIGHT BUT WE DO HAVE TO TAKE A
QUICK BREAK.
>> OKAY.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK.
WHEN WE COME BACK, WE DO HAVE
MORE OF YOUR QUESTIONS FROM
FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE
HILLARY CLINTON AS OUR DEBATE
CONTINUES HERE IN COLUMBIA,
SOUT
>>> ALL RIGHT.
WE ARE BACK HERE AT THE SCHOOL
OF LAW AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
SOUTH CAROLINA.
WE HAVE FORMER SECRETARY OF
STATE HILLARY CLINTON AND I HAVE
A QUESTION FOR YOU AND A LITTLE
BIT OF VIDEO TO WATCH.
>> OKAY.
>> YOU MAY NOT KNOW, BUT THE
LATE-NIGHT COMEDIANS LOVE YOU.
THEY LOVE YOU.
THEY LOVE TO DO THINGS ABOUT
YOU.
STEPHEN COLBERT HAD FUN WITH AN
INTERVIEW YOU HAD RECENTLY WITH
SCOTT PELLEY.
YOU'LL REMEMBER IT.
I WANT TO PLAY YOU A PIECE OF
IT.
>> AND SOMETHING HAS EMERGED,
SOMETHING HAS JUST EMERGED.
JUST LAST NIGHT THAT IS
POTENTIALLY DAMAGING TO HILLARY
CLINTON'S CAMPAIGN, AND IT'S
HILLARY CLINTON.
IT'S TRUE.
WHO HAS BEEN DOGGED BY QUESTIONS
OF TRUSTWORTHINESS.
AND HERE SHE IS YESTERDAY WITH
OUR GOOD FRIEND, SCOTT PELLEY.
>> YOU KNOW, IN 76 JIMMY CARTER
FAMOUSLY SAID, I WILL NOT LIE TO
YOU.
>> I HAVE TO TELL YOU, I HAVE
TRY IN EVERY WAY I KNOW HOW
LITERALLY FROM MY YEARS AS A
YOUNG LAWYER ALL THE WAY THROUGH
MY TIME AS SECRETARY OF STATE TO
LEVEL WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
>> SOME PEOPLE ARE GOING TO CALL
THAT WIGGLE ROOM THAT YOU JUST
GAVE YOURSELF.
>> WELL, NO --
>> ALWAYS TRIED TO.
>> I'VE ALWAYS TRIED TO.
>> JIMMY CARTER SAID I WILL
NEVER LIE TO YOU.
>> YOU'RE ASKING ME TO SAY HAVE
I EVER?
I DON'T BELIEVE I EVER HAVE.
I DON'T BELIEVE I EVER WILL.
I'M GOING TO DO THE BEST I CAN
TO LEVEL WITH THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
>> HOW CAN YOU BE THIS BAD AT
IT?
JUST SAY NO.
YOU'RE RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES.
EVEN -- EVEN RICHARD NIXON KNEW
TO SAY, I AM NOT A CROOK.
HE DIDN'T SAY, IT HAS ALWAYS
BEEN MY INTENTION, AS FAR AS I
BELIEVE, I WILL DO THE BEST I
CAN NOT TO BE A CROOK.
WILL YOU LIE IS THE HOME RUN OF
CAMPAIGN QUESTIONS.
YOU JUST SAY NO AND TOUCH ALL
THE BASES.
>> FUNNY GUY, SERIOUS TOPIC.
IS THAT A QUESTION THAT YOU'D
LIKE ANOTHER SHOT AT ANSWERING?
>> I'LL JUST SAY, NO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU MAKE MR. COLBERT VERY
HAPPY.
>> GOOD, GOOD, I WANT TO MAKE
HIM HAPPY IN.
>> IF YOU DO THAT.
YOU KNOW THE UNIVERSE OF THOUGHT
THIS COMES FROM.
YOU'VE KNOWN IT FOR A LONG TIME.
YOU'VE DEALT WITH IT FOR A LONG
TIME.
MANY OF US HAVE WATCHED IT.
TODAY, A FEDERAL JUDGE, AS YOU
KNOW, ISSUED ON A RULING ON A
MOTION THAT COULD PAVE THE WAY
FOR THE POSSIBILITY THAT YOU
COULD BE SUBPOENAED IN ORDER TO
OBTAIN ANY INFORMATION.
WHATEVER THE DETAILS OF THIS
LATEST CASE, IT'S WHAT THEY CALL
THE DRIP, DRIP, DRIP THEORY OF
THIS.
IT DOESN'T GO AWAY.
WHAT IS YOUR STATEMENT TO
DEMOCRATS WHO ARE AFRAID THAT
THIS RIGHT, WRONG, GOOD, BAD, IT
WILL NOT BELIEVE YOU IN THIS
RACE AND MAY COMPROMISE YOU NOW
AND GOING FORWARD?
>> THAT THERE IS NO BASIS FOR
THAT, CHRIS.
YOU KNOW, LOOK, I'M WELL AWARE
OF THE DRIP, DRIP, DRIP.
I'VE BEEN IN THE PUBLIC ARENA
FOR 25 YEARS AND HAVE BEEN THE
SUBJECT OF A LOT OF ONGOING
ATTACKS AND MISINFORMATION AND
ALL THE REST OF IT.
BUT I CAN ONLY TELL YOU WHAT THE
FACTS ARE, AND, YOU KNOW, THE
FACTS ARE THAT EVERY SINGLE TIME
SOMEBODY HAS HURLED THESE
CHARGES AGAINST ME, WHICH THEY
HAVE DONE, IT'S PROVED TO BE
NOTHING.
AND THIS IS NO DIFFERENT THAN
THAT.
YOU KNOW, AND I TESTIFIED FOR 11
HOURS ON THE BENGHAZI COMMITTEE.
PEOPLE WERE REALLY, OH MY
GOODNESS, OH MY GOODNESS.
I TOLD THE TRUTH.
I TESTIFIED UNDER OATH.
AT THE END, THEY HAD TO SAY,
THERE WAS NOTHING THERE.
HERE I HAVE TURNED OVER 55,000
PAGES OF E-MAILS.
NOBODY IN ANY CABINET POSITION
HAS EVER BEEN AS TRANSPARENT OR
OPEN.
I KNOW THERE ARE, YOU KNOW,
CHALLENGES ABOUT WHAT THE STATE
DEPARTMENT DID OR DIDN'T DO.
THAT WILL ALL BE WORKED OUT.
IT IS JUST NOT SOMETHING THAT,
YOU KNOW, IS GOING TO HAVE ANY
LASTING EFFECT.
AND I AM NOT AT ALL WORRIED
ABOUT IT.
>> SO THEN LET'S GO TO THE
AUD
AUDIENCE.
>> YEAH, LET'S DO IT.
>> MARY McCLELLAND, A RETIRED
HIGH SCHOOL GUIDANCE COUNSELOR.
SHE SAYS SHE IS UNDECIDED.
HAS A QUESTION.
>> GREAT.
GREAT.
>> I'M COMING TO THE RED BECAUSE
I WANT TO BRING THE RED AND BLUE
TOGETHER HERE.
>> THANK YOU.
I AM CURRENTLY RECEIVING SOCIAL
SECURITY BENEFITS, AND THAT'S
AFTER WORKING FOR NEARLY 40
YEARS AS A HIGH SCHOOL GUIDANCE
COUNSELOR.
CURRENTLY, THERE ARE MORE THAN
63 MILLION PEOPLE RECEIVING
SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS.
HARDWORKING PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN
ABLE TO WORK AND SECURE THESE
FUNDS.
MY QUESTION TO YOU, MADAM
SECRETARY, IS THIS.
HOW DO YOU PLAN TO FUND THE
SOCIAL SECURITY TRUST FUND TO
ENABLE US TO HAVE A SOLID AND
SECURE SOCIAL SECURITY SYSTEM
MOVING FORWARD, TO KEEP ME
GIVING MY BENEFITS AND THOSE IN
THE NEXT GENERATION?
THOSE YOUNG PEOPLE WHO ARE
MOVING TOWARD SOCIAL SECURITY
AGE.
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, WE'RE
GOING TO PREVENT THE REPUBLIC
CHANCE FROM PRIVATIZING IT.
THAT HAS TO BE THE HIGHEST
PRIORITY, AND I LISTEN TO THE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES, THE ONES
WHO ARE STILL COMPETING, AND
THEY ALL ARE VERY CRITICAL OF
SOCIAL SECURITY.
I THINK TED CRUZ CALLED IT A
PONZI SCHEME.
THEY'VE ALL SAID THEY SHOULD BE
CHANGING IT DRAMATICALLY.
I'M ABSOLUTELY AGAINST THAT.
I FOUGHT IT WE I WAS A SENATOR.
I WILL NEVER LET THAT HAPPEN AS
PRESIDENT.
WITH RESPECT TO THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TRUST FUND SO WE CAN
EXTEND ITS LIFE AND MAKE SURE IT
IS THERE FOR YOUNGER PEOPLE
COMING UP, WE HAVE TO GO WHERE
THE MONEY IS.
THAT MEANS WE HAVE TO LOOK AT
DIFFERENT WAYS OF TRYING TO GET
MORE MONEY INTO THE TRUST FUND.
RAISING THE CAP ON THE INCOME
THAT IS SUBJECT TO THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TAX IS ONE WAY OF DOING
IT.
ANOTHER WAY OF DOING IT IS
EXPANDING THE SOCIAL SECURITY
TAX TO INVESTMENT INCOME,
SO-CALLED PASSIVE INCOME,
BECAUSE A LOT OF WELL-OFF PEOPLE
DON'T MAKE A LOT OF WHAT WE
WOULD THINK OF AS EARNED INCOME
BUT THEY HAVE A LOT OF INCOME
BECAUSE IT COMES FROM CAPITAL
GAINS AND INVESTMENT AND OTHER
SOURCES.
SO I THINK WE HAVE TO LOOK AT
SOMETHING LIKE EITHER ONE OF
THOSE.
THERE MAY BE SOME OTHER IDEAS,
BUT I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING I
CAN TO EXTEND THE LIFE OF THE
SOCIAL SECURITY TRUST FUND.
AND IT IS ALSO IMPORTANT,
THOUGH, TO LOOK AT PEOPLE WHO
ARE NOT GETTING BY ON WHAT THEY
CURRENTLY HAVE UNDER SOCIAL
SECURITY.
THERE ARE A LOT OF LOW-WAGE
WORKERS WHO DIDN'T MAKE MUCH,
AND IT'S REALLY DIFFICULT FOR
THEM.
THERE ARE A LOT OF WOMEN WHO
WERE NOT IN THE FORMAL
WORKFORCE.
YOU'VE BEEN A PROFESSIONAL,
YOU'VE WORKED FOR ALL THOSE
YEARS BUT A LOT OF WOMEN MAY
HAVE BEEN IN, MAY HAVE BEEN OUT,
MAY HAVE RAISED CHILDRENS MAY
HAVE CARED FOR AN ILL RELATIVE.
THEY DON'T HAVE A LOT OF WHAT
THEY
THEY'VE EARNED IN THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TRUST FUND.
THEN THE OTHER GROUP I'M
CONCERNED ABOUT ARE WIDOWS WHO
LOSE HALF THEIR BENEFIT WHEN
THEIR HUSBAND DIES.
SO I WANT TO PREVENT IT FROM
BEING PRIVATIZED.
I WANT TO EXTEND THE SOCIAL
SECURITY TRUST FUND, AND I WANT
TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE UP THE
BENEFITS FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE
LITERALLY BARELY HANGING ON.
THE THREE GROUPS I MENTIONED ARE
THE ONES I'M LOOKING AT MOST
CL
CLOSELY.
WE'RE GOING TO MAKE SURE WE
EXTEND IT AND IT WILL BE THERE
SO YOUNG PEOPLE HAVE THE SAME
KIND OF GUARANTEE YOU DID AND I
DID WHEN WE STARTED OUT.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> MADAM SECRETARY, YOU HAVE
JOHN ON YOUR RIGHT, THE FOR
INSTANCE
PRINCIPAL OF A CHARTER SCHOOL.
>> HOW ARE YOU?
>> GREAT.
>> WE'RE THE ONLY SCHOOL IN THE
STATE THAT OFFER MORE
INSTRUCTIONAL DAYS THAN REQUIRED
BY LAW.
WE OFFER 230 INSTRUCTIONAL DAYS
VERSUS THE TRADITIONAL 180.
YOU LOOK AT COUNTRIES LIKE INDIA
AND CHINA, THEY OFFER, THEY
REQUIRE THEIR HIGH SCHOOL
STUDENTS TO ATTEND 220 DAYS ON
AVERAGE.
AND THAT'S 40 DAYS MORE THAN OUR
HIGH SCHOOL STUDENTS.
DO YOU THINK THAT PUTS OUR
STUDENTS AT A DISADVANTAGE?
AND IF SO, WOULD YOU WORK WITH
STATES TO HELP MODERNIZE THAT
POLICY?
>> HERE'S WHAT I THINK IT DOES,
AND THANK YOU FOR BEING INVOLVED
IN EDUCATION.
IT'S SO CRITICALLY IMPORTANT.
I THINK WE NEED TO FOCUS ON
DISADVANTAGED KIDS, LOW-INCOME
KIDS, KIDS WITH LEARNING
DIFFICULTIES BECAUSE THEY DO
NEED MORE TIME ON TASK.
OTHERS COULD ALSO BENEFIT FROM
IT, BUT WE UNDERSTAND AND YOU
DO, I'M SURE, FROM THE RESEARCH,
THAT THE MORE TIME THAT KIDS WHO
NEED THAT TIME HAVE, THE MORE
LIKELY THEY WILL MAKE GAINS IN
THEIR LEARNING.
IN FACT, THERE'S A LOT OF
RESEARCH WHICH SHOWS THAT, YOU
KNOW, FOR MOST MIDDLE CLASS OR
WELL-OFF KIDS, THEY GET OUT OF
SCHOOL IN THE SPRING OR EARLY
SUMMER, HAVING GONE TO 180, 185,
WHATEVER THE DAYS ARE IN THEIR
STATE, AND THEN THEY DO THINGS
OVER THE SUMMER THAT KEEP THEM
LEARNING.
WHERE A LOT OF DISADVANTAGED
KIDS GET OUT AND THEY ACTUALLY
LOSE SOME OF THE LEARNING
THEY'VE GAINED DURING THE YEAR.
SO I WANT VERY MUCH TO EXPAND
THE SCHOOL DAY AND THE SCHOOL
YEAR AND PROVIDE MORE STRUCTURE
STARTING WITH KIDS WHO WOULD BE
MOST BENEFITED FROM IT, BUT I AM
IN FAVOR OF STATES LOOKING AT
HOW THEY MIGHT DO THAT FOR EVERY
STUDENT, BUT I'M MOST CONCERNED
ABOUT THE KIDS WHO ARE LEFT OUT
AND LEFT BEHIND AND NEED MORE
TIME ON TASK.
THE RESEARCH ON THIS IS VERY
CLEAR.
IN FACT, YOU KNOW, I HAVE SAID I
WANT TO BE A GOOD PARTNER FOR
EDUCATORS AND TEACHERS, BUT I
WANT TO HELP THEM DO WHAT THEY
KNOW THEY'RE SUPPOSED TO DO.
WE NEED BETTER AND FEWER TESTS.
NOT MORE TESTS.
WE NEED MORE SUPPORT IN THE
CLASSROOM BECAUSE A LOT OF KIDS
COME WITH NEEDS, AND AS THE
REVEREND WAS SAYING, A LOT OF
KIDS WHO HAVE CHALLENGES AT
HOME, YOU KNOW, THE SCHOOL IS
THE ONLY PLACE OTHER THAN THE
FAMILY WHERE THEY MIGHT GET SOME
ADDITIONAL ASSISTANCE.
SO WE NEED TO LOOK AT THIS FROM
A BROADER PERSPECTIVE, AND
YOU'RE RIGHT, MORE DAYS, MORE
HOURS, ACTUALLY DOES PRODUCE
RESULTS PARTICULARLY FOR KIDS
WHO NEED THAT KIND OF STRUCTURE
AND SUPPORT.
>> MADAM SECRETARY, WE HAVE
MARJORIE WENTWORTH ON YOUR LEFT.
SHE IS POET LAUREATE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA.
>> SHE'S THE WHAT?
>> POET LAUREATE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA.
SHE SAYS SHE'S SUPPORTING YOU.
>> THAT MAKES ME VERY HAPPY.
>> I'M NOT GOING TO RECITE A
PROGRAM.
>> I WISH YOU WOULD.
>> THE WORLD WAS ASTONISHED AT
THE GENEROSITY OF THE FORGIVING
STATEMENTS MADE BY FAMILY
MEMBERS WHOSE FAMILY WERE KILLED
IN THE CHARLESTON MASSACRE,
EMANUEL CHURCH.
JUST TWO DAYS AFTER AT THE BOND
HEARING.
AND, YOU KNOW, IT HELPED OUR
CITY HEAL.
YOU WERE THERE.
YOU SAW THAT.
LED TO A NOBEL PEACE PRIZE
NOMINATION WHICH IS
EXTRAORDINARY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND, YES.
AND, YOU KNOW, ONE OF THE THINGS
I WANT TO ASK YOU IS WHY DO YOU
THINK THAT FORGIVENESS IS SO
RARELY AN ACTION THAT WE TAKE,
ESPECIALLY IN TERMS OF VIOLENT
CONFLICT, AND, YOU KNOW, HOW
COULD YOU, AS PRESIDENT, HARNESS
THE POWER OF FORGIVENESS IN
TERMS OF HELPING HEAL ALL THE
DIVISION IN OUR OWN COUNTRY AND
BEYOND?
>> THAT'S A GREAT QUESTION.
YOU KNOW, I COULD NOT BE
STANDING HERE IN I HAD NOT BEEN
FORGIVEN MANY TIMES AND IF I HAD
NOT BEEN ABLE TO FORGIVE MYSELF
THOSE WHO I THOUGHT HAD IN SOME
WAY DISAPPOINTED OR WRONGED ME.
SO I, AS A PERSON OF FAITH,
BELIEVE PROFOUNDLY IN THE POWER
OF FORGIVENESS.
AND WE NEED TO DO MORE TO TRY TO
TAKE
>> AND WE NEED TO DO MORE TO
TAKE THE EXAMPLE.
I WAS VERY FORTUNATE TO SPEND
QUITE A BIT OF TIME WITH NELSON
MANDELA, I KNOW BISHOP TUTU.
IT WAS A LEAP OF FAITH TO BRING
TOGETHER THOSE WHO HAD BEEN O
OPPRESSED, IN A PROCESS THAT
TRULY WAS A NATIONAL EFFORT TO
TRY TO FORGIVE ENOUGH THAT THE
COUNTRY COULD BE HELD TOGETHER,
THAT THE NATION COULD BE BORN,
THAT THE WORK COULD BEGIN AND IT
WAS TO ME A STUNNING EXAMPLE OF
WHAT IS POSSIBLE.
I THINK THERE'S A LOT THAT WE
COULD DO IN THIS COUNTRY IF WE
COULD FIGURE OUT HOW TO HARNESS
THOSE FEELINGS.
AND I SEE SO MUCH ANGER AND FEAR
AND BITTERNESS.
SOME OF IT'S BEING PLAYED OUT IN
OUR POLITICAL SYSTEM RIGHT NOW.
THE KIND OF LANGUAGE THAT'S
BEING USED, VIOLENT IMAGES,
THREATS AGAIN PEOPLE.
IT IS DEEPLY TROUBLING TO ME
BECAUSE WE HAVE TO TRY TO UNITE
OUR COUNTRY, NOT DIVIDE IT IF
WE'RE GOING TO DEAL WITH A LOT
OF THE CHALLENGES THAT WE FACE.
SO I WOULD VERY MUCH CONSIDER IF
THERE WERE A FORMAL WAY AND, IF
NOT, WHAT WE WOULD DO TO TALK
MORE ABOUT FORGIVENESS AND
RECONCILIATION TO TRY TO BEGIN
BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER FROM
DIFFERENT BACKGROUNDS.
OBVIOUS RIFF DIFFERENT RACES,
DIFFERENT ETHNICITIES, EVERY
OTHER OF THE WONDERFUL MOSAIC
THAT MAKES UP OUR COUNTRY SO
PEOPLE COULD BEGIN ONCE AGAIN TO
TRY TO SEE THEM SERVICES IN THE
OTHERS' LIFE.
THE OLD SAYING WALKING IN
SOMEONE ELSE'S SHOES BECAUSE I
THINK THAT'S ESSENTIAL TO SORT
OF NURTURE THE GROUND OUT OF
WHICH FORGIVENESS AND
RECONCILIATION AND UNITY TO
COME.
I THINK IT'S ONE OF OUR BIGGEST
CHALLENGES.
I HOPE WE FIND WAYS TO TRY TO
ADDRESS IT.
I WILL CERTAINLY GIVE IT AS MUCH
THOUGHT AS I CAN AND TRY AS
PRESIDENT TO THINK OF WAYS TO
LEAD THAT.
>> THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HAVE A SEAT PIP HAVE A
QUESTION FOR YOU ON EXACTLY THAT
THEME, I IDEA OF BEING ABLE TO
SEE YOURSELF IN SOMEBODY ELSE
WHO MAY APPEAR AS AN OPPONENT.
YOU SAID RECENTLY WHEN YOU WERE
REMINISCING ABOUT THE
SIGNIFICANCE OF JUSTICE SCALIA,
YOU SAID IT'S SO BEAUTIFUL THAT
NINO SCALIA HAD RUTH BADER
GINSBURG, THAT EITHER THOUGH
THEY WERE IDEOLOGICALLY OR
PHILOSOPHICALLY FROM A LEGAL
PERSPECTIVE DIFFERENT, THEY WERE
STILL VERY CLOSE FRIENDS.
IT MAY ME WONDER WHO DO YOU
CONSIDER, YOUR SCALIA, THIS
PERSON ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THE
AISLE THAT YOU HAVE REAL
DISAGREEMENTS WITH BUT YOU
CONSIDER A FRIEND.
>> YOU KNOW, I THOUGHT A LOT
ABOUT THAT, CHRIS, BECAUSE OF
THE SCALIA EXAMPLE.
I JUST WANT TO MAKE THREE QUICK
POINTS BEFORE I GET TO YOUR
QUESTION.
ONE, SCALIA -- JUSTICE SCALIA
AND JUSTICE GINSBURG ACTUALLY
GOT TO SPEND TIME WITH EACH
OTHER, THEY GOT TO KNOW EACH
OTHER AS PEOPLE.
AND IT WENT JUST A SHOWING UP,
DOING THE WORK AND LEAVING.
WHAT'S HAPPENED IN OUR CONGRESS
AND I'M SURE CONGRESSMAN CLYBURN
CAN REMEMBER THE DAYS WHEN
PEOPLE ACTUALLY GOT TO SPEND
TIME WITH EACH OTHER.
YOU GOT TO KNOW THEIR FAMILIES,
YOU GOT TO KNOW A LITTLE BIT
ABOUT THEM SO THAT THEY WERE NOT
JUST SOME KIND OF POLITICAL
CARICATURE, THEY WERE A REAL
P
PERSON.
I DON'T KNOW HOW WE GET BACK TO
THAT UNDER THE PRECIOUS,
IDEOLOGICALLY, POLITICAL,
PARTISAN PRESSURES WE'RE UNDER.
IT'S A GREAT LOSS FOR OUR
COUNTRY.
WHEN I GOT TO WASHINGTON WHEN MY
HUSBAND BECAME PRESIDENT, I
LOOKED FOR OPPORTUNITIES TO WORK
ACROSS THE AISLE.
YES, WAS IT HARD, THERE WAS A
LOT OF INCOMING BATTLES BACK AND
FORTH -- I WORKED WITH TOM DELAY
ONE OF THE MOST PARTISAN
REPUBLICANS IN THE CONGRESS TO
REFORM THE ADOPTION AND FOSTER
CARE SYSTEM.
WE NEVER BECAME FRIENDS BUT WE
DID SOMETHING GOOD FOR A LOT OF
YOUNG KIDS THAT HAD BETTER LIVES
BECAUSE IT HAVE.
I WORKED WITH LINDSAY GRAHAM TO
GET HEALTH CARE FOR THE NATIONAL
GUARD.
WE TRAVELED TOGETHER.
I TRAVELED WITH JOHN McCAIN WHO
I GREW TO VERY MUCH LIKE AND
RESPECT AND CONSIDER A FRIEND.
THE WOMEN REPUBLICAN SENATORS
ARE PEOPLE, YOU KNOW LIKE SUSAN
COLLINS FROM MAINE THAT I HAVE A
LOT OF REGARD FOR AND HAVE
WORKED WITH AND OTHERS.
IT TOOK TIME, THOUGH, TO GET TO
NE EACH OTHER.
THEY HAD THE SAME FEELING ABOUT
ME.
I CAME INTO THE SENATE, I, YOU
KNOW, WAS A FIRST LADY AND NOW
I'M IN THE SENATE SO I HAD TO
REALLY WORK HARD TO DEVELOP
THOSE RELATIONSHIPS.
THAT'S WHAT I WANT TO DO AS
PRESIDENT BECAUSE RELATIONSHIPS
UNDERLIE EVERYTHING.
IF YOU DON'T HAVE THOSE
RELATIONSHIPS, IT'S REALLY HARD
TO GET THINGS DONE.
IT'S HARD TO GET THEM EVEN WITH
THE RELATIONSHIPS BUT IN THE
ABSENCE, IT'S PRACTICALLY
IMPOSSIBLE.
I WANT TO DO WHAT I CAN TO TRY
TO FIND THAT.
NOW, THERE WILL BE PEOPLE WHO
ARE NOT INTERESTED AT ALL, BUT I
STILL THINK THERE IS A CRITICAL
MASS OF MEMBERS OF CONGRESS WHO
ACTUALLY DO WANT TO GET
SOMETHING DONE AND WHO WOULD BE
INTERESTED IN, YOU KNOW, KIND OF
GETTING TO KNOW ONE ANOTHER,
GETTING TO KNOW ME AS PRESIDENT
IF THEY DON'T KNOW ME BEFORE AS
SENATOR OR SECRETARY OF STATE.
SO PEOPLE LIKE JOHN McCAIN,
SUSAN COLLINS ARE PEOPLE THAT I
FELT, YOU KNOW, I GOT TO KNOW
WELL AND WORKED WELL WITH.
>> SO IT'S MORE OF A GROUP.
YOU DON'T HAVE SOMEONE
SPECIAL --
>> NO, NO.
>> MAYBE TO COME.
>> WELL, I HOPE SO.
I WOULD LOVE THAT TO GET THINGS
DONE, IT WOULD BE GREAT.
>> SO YOU HAVE A BIG DATE COMING
UP HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA.
TAKE 30 SECONDS, PLEASE.
SANDERS HAD THE SAME AMOUNT OF
TIME, AND MAKE A FINAL PITCH TO
THE PEOPLE HERE TONIGHT.
>> FIRST OF ALL, I'M THRILLED TO
BE HERE CAMPAIGNING TOWARD THE
PRIMARY ON SATURDAY.
AS I SAID, THE FIRST TIME I CAME
TO SOUTH CAROLINA WAS AS A YOUNG
LAWYER WITH THE CHILDREN'S
DEFENSE FUND, I'VE BEEN BACK
MANY TIMES SINCE.
I AM GOING TO WORK VERY HARD TO
BREAK DOWN ALL THE BARRIERS THAT
STAND IN THE WAY OF SOUTH
CAROLINIANS AND AMERICANS
ACHIEVING THEIR DREAMS.
THOSE INCLUDE ECONOMIC BARRIERS
WE HAVE WORK TO DO, TO CREATE
JOBS, GET INCOMES RISING AGAIN.
I WANT TO GO AFTER MANUFACTURING
AND INFRASTRUCTURE AND CLEAN
ENERGY AND RAISE THE MINIMUM
WAGE AND GET EQUAL PAY FOR
WOMEN'S WORK AND DEFEND THE --
EXTEND AND FIGURE OUT SOME WAY
WE EXTEND MEDICAID IN STATES
LIKE SOUTH CAROLINA TO TAKE CARE
OF THE PEOPLE WHO DESERVE TO
HAVE HEALTH CARE.
AND, YES, I'M GOING TO WORK ON
EDUCATION.
I WANT TO START WITH EARLY
CHILDHOOD EDUCATION.
WE HAVE WORK TO DO.
BUT MOSTLY I WANT YOU TO KNOW IT
WOULD BE AN INCREDIBLE PRIVILEGE
AND HONOR TO REPRESENT THIS
COUNTRY AT SUCH A CONSEQUENTIAL
TIME.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT WILL FACE
CHALLENGES HERE AT HOME AND
AROUND THE WORLD.
YOU WILL BE VOTING ON SATURDAY
FOR A PRESIDENT AND COMMANDER IN
CHIEF.
I AM WILLING, READY AND I WILL
SERVE YOU WITH THE UTMOST OF MY
ABILITY AND COMMITMENT TO MAKING
THIS COUNTRY ALL IT SHOULD BE
FOR EVERYONE WHO'S IN IT.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THANK YOU
VERY MUCH.
WE THANK ALL OF YOU, WE THANK
THE CANDIDATES.
SPECIAL THANKS TO THE VOTERS FOR
ASKING SUCH GREAT QUESTIONS.
THANKS TO THE VIEWERS AT HOME
AND EVERYBODY HERE IN COLUMBIA
FOR THEIR AMAZING HOSPITALITY.
THURSDAY NIGHT AT 8:30, A CNN
REPUBLICAN DEBATE FROM HOUSTON,
BE SURE TO JOIN US FOR THAT.
TONIGHT IS A HUGE NIGHT IN
POLITICS AND IT'S NOT OVER.
OUR COVERAGE CONTINUES IN
WASHINGTON WITH THE LATEST ON
THE NEVADA CAUCUSES.
ANDERSON COOPER, JAKE TAPPER AND
DANA BASH PICK IT UP AFTER A
QUICK BREAK.
THANKS AGAIN.