[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> I AM READY TO PLAY, AND WIN
FOR YOU.
>> LET'S HAVE THE COURAGE TO
TAKE ON THE BILLIONAIRE.
>> WE MUST BUILD AN AMERICAN
ECONOMY THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
US.
>> I BELIEVE WE SHOULD BREAK UP
THE LAW, HILLARY CLINTON DOES
NOT.
>> SENATOR SANDERS HAS BEEN A
PRETTY RELIABLE VOTE FOR THE GUN
LOBBY.
>> TO SAY THAT I'M KIND OF A
SUPPORTER OF THE NRA IS A
MEAN-SPIRITED, AND INACCURATE
STATEMENT.
>> SENATOR SANDERS VOTED TO GIVE
IMMUNITY TO GUN DEALERS.
SECRETARY CLINTON CHANGES HER
OPINION EVERY YEAR.
>> WE SHOULDN'T BE RIPPING UP
OBAMACARE AND STARTING OVER.
>> NOW SHE'S ATTACKING ME
BECAUSE I SUPPORT UNIVERSAL
HEALTH CARE.
>> I THINK AMERICA IS GREAT.
AND IT'S UP TO US TO MAKE SURE
WE MAKE IT GREATER.
>> I BELIEVE WE'RE GOING TO MAKE
HISTORY ONE MORE TIME.
>> THE DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE'S
DEBATE LIVE FROM THE GILLIARD
CENTER IN CHARLESTON, SOUTH
CAROLINA.
HERE NOW, LESTER HOLT.
>> GOOD EVENING, AND WELCOME TO
THE NBC NEWS YOUTUBE DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATE'S DEBATE.
AFTER ALL THE CAMPAIGNING SOON
AMERICANS WILL HAVE THEIR SAY
WITH THE FIRST VOTES OF THE 2016
CAMPAIGN JUST 15 DAYS AWAY IN
IOWA AND NEW HAMPSHIRE NOT FAR
BEHIND.
TONIGHT WILL BE THE FINAL
OPPORTUNITY TO SEE THESE
CANDIDATES FACE TO FACE BEFORE
THE VOTING BEGINS.
OUR PURPOSE HERE TONIGHT IS TO
HIGHLIGHT AND EXAMINE THE
DIFFERENCES AMONG THE THREE
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES.
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
PLEASE WELCOME, SECRETARY
HILLARY CLINTON, SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS, AND GOVERNOR MARTIN
O'MALLEY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
WELL, WELCOME TO ALL OF YOU.
HOPE YOU'RE EXCITED, WE'RE
EXCITED.
WE TO WANT THANK OUR HOSTS, THE
CONGRESSIONAL BLACK CAUCUS
INSTITUTE.
I'M JOINED BY MY COLLEAGUE
ANDREA MITCHELL TONIGHT.
THE RULES ARE SIMPLE.
60 SECONDS FOR ANSWERS, 30
SECONDS FOR FOLLOW-UPS OR
REBUTTALS.
I KNOW YOU'LL ALL KEEP EXACTLY
TO TIME, SO OUR JOB SHOULD BE
EASY HERE TONIGHT.
WE'LL HAVE QUESTIONS FROM THE
YOUTUBE COMMUNITY THROUGHOUT THE
DEBATE.
THIS IS A CRITICAL POINT IN THE
RACE, YOU'VE BEEN DEFINING YOUR
DIFFERENCES, ESPECIALLY
VIGOROUSLY IN THE LAST WEEK ON
THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL.
WE'RE HERE TO FACILITATE THIS
CONVERSATION ON BEHALF OF THE
VOTERS SO THAT THEY KNOW EXACTLY
WHERE YOU STAND AS YOU FACE OFF
TONIGHT.
LET'S HAVE A GREAT DEBATE.
WE'LL BEGIN WITH 45 SECOND
OPENING STATEMENTS FROM EACH
CANDIDATE, STARTING WITH
SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> WELL GOOD EVENING.
AND I WANT TO THANK THE
CONGRESSIONAL BLACK CAUCUS
INSTITUTE AND THE PEOPLE OF
CHARLESTON FOR HOSTING US HERE
ON THE EVE OF MARTIN LUTHER KING
DAY TOMORROW.
YOU KNOW, I REMEMBER WELL WHEN
MY YOUTH MINISTER TOOK ME TO
HEAR DR. KING.
I WAS A TEENAGER.
AND HIS MORAL CLARITY, THE
MESSAGE THAT HE CONVEYED THAT
EVENING REALLY STAYED WITH ME
AND HELPED TO SET ME ON A PATH
TO SERVICE.
I ALSO REMEMBER THAT HE SPENT
THE LAST DAY OF HIS LIFE IN
MEMPHIS, FIGHTING FOR DIGNITY
AND HIGHER PAY FOR WORKING
PEOPLE.
AND THAT IS OUR FIGHT STILL.
WE HAVE TO GET THE ECONOMY
WORKING AND INCOMES RISING FOR
EVERYONE, INCLUDING THOSE WHO
HAVE BEEN LEFT OUT AND LEFT
BEHIND.
WE HAVE TO KEEP OUR COMMUNITIES
AND OUR COUNTRY SAFE.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO CAN DO
ALL ASPECTS OF THE JOB.
I UNDERSTAND THAT THIS IS THE
HARDEST JOB IN THE WORLD, I'M
PREPARED AND READY TO TAKE IT
ON.
AND I HOPE TO EARN YOUR SUPPORT
TO BE THE NOMINEE OF THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY AND THE NEXT
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS, YOUR OPENING
STATEMENT, SIR.
>> THANK YOU.
AS WE HONOR THE EXTRAORDINARY
LIFE OF DR. MARTIN LUTHER KING
JR., IT'S IMPORTANT THAT WE NOT
ONLY REMEMBER WHAT HE STOOD FOR,
BUT THAT WE PLEDGE TO CONTINUE
HIS VISION TO TRANSFORM OUR
COUNTRY.
AS WE LOOK OUT AT OUR COUNTRY
TODAY, WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
UNDERSTAND IS WE HAVE AN ECONOMY
THAT'S RIGGED.
THAT ORDINARY AMERICANS ARE
WORKING LONGER HOURS FOR LOWER
WAGES.
47 MILLION PEOPLE LIVING IN
POVERTY, AND ALMOST ALL OF THE
NEW INCOME AND WEALTH GOING TO
THE TOP 1%.
AND THEN, MAKE A BAD SITUATION
WORSE WE HAVE A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM WHERE
MILLIONAIRES AND BILLIONAIRES
ARE SPENDING EXTRAORDINARY
AMOUNTS OF MONEY TO BUY
ELECTIONS.
THIS CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION TO NOT ONLY
ELECT THE PRESIDENT, BUT TO
TRANSFORM THIS COUNTRY.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOUR
OPENING STATEMENT, SIR.
>> THANK YOU, MY NAME IS MARTIN
O'MALLEY, I WAS BORN THE YEAR
DR. KING DELIVERED HIS SPEECH.
AND I WANT TO THANK THE PEOPLE
OF SOUTH CAROLINA, NOT ONLY FOR
HOSTING OUR DEBATE HERE TONIGHT,
BUT ALSO FOR WHAT YOU TAUGHT ALL
OF US IN THE AFTERMATH OF THE
TRAGIC SHOOTING AT MOTHER
EMANUEL CHURCH.
YOU TAUGHT US IN FACT IN KEEPING
WITH THE SPEECH THAT LOVE WOULD
HAVE THE FINAL WORD WHEN YOU
TOOK DOWN THE CONFEDERATE FLAG
FROM YOUR STATE HOUSE.
LET GO OF THE PAST AND MOVE
FORWARD.
EIGHT YEARS AGO, YOU BROUGHT
FORWARD A NEW LEADER IN BARACK
OBAMA TO SAVE OUR COUNTRY FROM
THE SECOND GREAT DEPRESSION.
AND THAT'S WHAT HE'S DONE.
OUR COUNTRY'S DOING BETTER,
WE'RE CREATING JOBS AGAIN.
BUT IN ORDER TO MAKE GOOD ON THE
PROMISE OF EQUAL OPPORTUNITY,
AND EQUAL JUSTICE UNDER THE LAW
AND WE HAVE URGENT WORK TO DO
THAT WE'VE HEARD COMING OFF OF
THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
PODIUMS ARE PRETTY LOUD.
WE NEED NEW LEADERSHIP.
WE NEED TO COME TOGETHER AS A
PEOPLE AND BUILD ON THE GOOD
THINGS THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS
DONE.
THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT.
I NEED YOUR HELP.
I ASK FOR YOUR VOTE, AND I LOOK
FORWARD TO MOVING OUR COUNTRY
FORWARD ONCE AGAIN.
THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THE FIRST QUESTION, THE FIRST
QUESTION I'LL BE ADDRESSING TO
ALL OF THE CANDIDATES, PRESIDENT
OBAMA CAME TO OFFICE DETERMINED
TO SWING FOR THE FENCES ON
HEALTH CARE REFORM.
VOTERS WANT TO KNOW HOW YOU
WOULD DEFINE YOUR PRESIDENCY.
HOW WOULD YOU THINK BIG?
SO COMPLETE THIS SENTENCE.
IN MY FIRST 100 DAYS IN OFFICE,
MY TOP THREE PRIORITIES WILL BE,
FILL IN THE BLANK.
SENATOR SANDERS.
>> THAT'S WHAT THE CAMPAIGN IS
ABOUT.
IT IS THINKING BIG.
IT IS UNDERSTANDING THAT IN THE
WEALTHIEST COUNTRY IN THE
HISTORY OF THE WORLD, WE SHOULD
HAVE HEALTH CARE FOR EVERY MAN,
WOMAN, AND CHILD, AS A RIGHT
THAT WE SHOULD RAISE THE MINIMUM
WAGE TO AT LEAST $15 AN HOUR.
THAT WE HAVE GOT TO CREATE
MILLIONS OF DECENT PAYING JOBS
BY REBUILDING OUR CRUMBLING
INFRASTRUCTURE.
SO WHAT MY FIRST DAYS ARE ABOUT
IS BRINGING AMERICA TOGETHER.
TO END THE DECLINE OF THE MIDDLE
CLASS, TO TELL THE WEALTHIEST
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY THAT YES,
THEY ARE GOING TO START PAYING
THEIR FAIR SHARE OF TAXES, AND
THAT WE ARE GOING TO HAVE A
GOVERNMENT THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
US AND NOT JUST BIG CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTORS.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, SAME
QUESTION, MY FIRST 100 DAYS IN
OFFICE, MY THOUGHT FOR THESE
PRIORITIES WOULD BE.
>> I WOULD WORK QUICKLY TO
PRESENT TO THE CONGRESS MY PLANS
FOR CREATING MORE GOOD JOBS AND
MANUFACTURING, INFRASTRUCTURE,
CLEAN AND RENEWABLE ENERGY,
RAISING THE MINIMUM WAGE, AND
GUARANTEEING, FINALLY, EQUAL PAY
FOR WOMEN'S WORK.
I WOULD ALSO --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- I WOULD ALSO BE PRESENTING MY
PLANS TO BUILD ON THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT AND TO IMPROVE IT BY
DECREASING THE OUT OF POCKET
COST BY PUTTING A CAP ON
PRESCRIPTION DRUG COSTS, BY
LOOKING FOR WAYS THAT WE CAN PUT
THE PRESCRIPTION DRUG BUSINESS
AND THE HEALTH INSURANCE COMPANY
BUSINESS ON A MORE STABLE
PLATFORM THAT DOESN'T TAKE TOO
MUCH MONEY OUT OF THE POCKETS OF
HARD-WORKING AMERICANS.
AND THIRD, I WOULD BE WORKING IN
EVERY WAY THAT I KNEW TO BRING
OUR COUNTRY TOGETHER.
WE DO HAVE TOO MUCH DIVISION,
TOO MUCH MEAN-SPIRITEDNESS.
THERE'S A LOT WE HAVE TO DO ON
IMMIGRATION REFORM, ON VOTING
RIGHTS, ON CAMPAIGN FINANCE
REFORM, BUT WE NEED TO DO IT
TOGETHER.
THAT'S HOW WE'LL HAVE THE KIND
OF COUNTRY FOR THE 21st CENTURY
THAT WE KNOW WILL GUARANTEE OUR
CHILDREN AND GRANDCHILDREN THE
KIND OF FUTURE THEY DESERVE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, SAME
QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU.
FIRST OF ALL, I WOULD LAY OUT AN
AGENDA TO MAKE WAGES GO UP AGAIN
FOR ALL AMERICANS, RATHER THAN
DOWN.
EQUAL PAY FOR EQUAL WORK.
MAKING IT EASIER RATHER THAN
HARDER FOR PEOPLE TO JOIN LABOR
UNIONS.
GETTING 11 MILLION OF OUR
NEIGHBORS OUT OF THE UNDERGROUND
SHADOW ECONOMY BY PASSING
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
RAISING THE MINIMUM WAGE TOP $15
AN HOUR, HOWEVER WE CAN,
WHEREVER WE CAN.
SECONDLY, I BELIEVE THE GREATEST
BUSINESS OPPORTUNITY TO COME TO
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA IN
100 YEARS IS CLIMATE CHANGE.
AND I PUT FORWARD A PLAN TO MOVE
US TO A 100% CLEAN ELECTRIC
ENERGY GRID BY 2050 AND CREATE 5
MILLION JOBS ALONG THE WAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU --
>> I'M SORRY, THAT WAS SECOND
LESTER, AND THIRD AND FINALLY,
WE NEED A NEW AGENDA FOR
AMERICAN CITIES.
WE HAVE NOT HAD A NEW AGENDA FOR
AMERICA CITY SINCE JIMMY CARTER.
WE NEED A NEW AGENDA FOR AMERICA
CITIES THAT'LL INVEST IN THE
TALENTS AND SKILLS IN OUR
PEOPLE, INVEST IN
TRANSPORTATION, INFRASTRUCTURE,
AND TRANSIT OPTIONS.
AND MAKE OUR CITIES THE LEADING
EDGE IN THIS MOVE TO A
REDESIGNED, BUILT, CLEAN GREEN
ENERGY FUTURE THAT'LL EMPLOY OUR
PEOPLE.
>> ALL RIGHT GOVERNOR, THANK
YOU.
YOU'VE ALL LAID OUT LARGE
VISIONS AND WE'RE GOING TO COVER
THAT.
LAST COUPLE OF WEEKS OF THIS
CAMPAIGN HAVE FEATURED SOME OF
THE SHARPEST EXCHANGES IN THE
RACE.
LET'S START WITH ONE OF THEM.
THE ISSUE OF GUNS.
SENATOR SANDERS, LAST WEEK
SECRETARY CLINTON CALLED YOU
QUOTE A PRETTY RELIABLE VOTE FOR
THE GUN LOBBY.
RIGHT BEFORE THE DEBATE, YOU
CHANGED YOUR POSITION ON
IMMUNITY FOR LAWSUITS FOR GUN
MANUFACTURERS.
CAN YOU TELL US WHY?
>> WELL, I THINK SECRETARY
CLINTON KNOWS WHAT SHE SAYS IS
DISINGENUOUS.
I HAVE A D-MINUS VOTING RECORD
FROM THE NRA.
YOU WAS IN 1988, THERE WERE
THREE CANDIDATES RUNNING FOR
CONGRESS IN THE STATE OF
VERMONT.
I STOOD UP TO THE GUN LOBBY, AND
CAME OUT AND MAINTAINED THE
POSITION THAT IN THIS COUNTRY,
WE SHOULD NOT BE SELLING
MILITARY-STYLE ASSAULT WEAPONS.
I HAVE SUPPORTED, FROM DAY ONE,
AT INSTANT BACKGROUND CHECK TO
MAKE CERTAIN THAT PEOPLE WHO
SHOULD NOT HAVE GUNS DO NOT HAVE
GUNS.
AND THAT INCLUDES PEOPLE WITH
CRIMINAL BACKGROUNDS, PEOPLE WHO
ARE MENTALLY UNSTABLE.
I SUPPORT WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA
IS DOING IN TERMS OF TRYING TO
CLOSE THE GUN SHOW LOOPHOLES,
AND I THINK IT SHOULD BE A
FEDERAL CRIME IF PEOPLE ACT.
WE HAVE SEEN IN THIS CITY A
HORRENDOUS TRAGEDY OF A CRAZED
PERSON PRAYING WITH PEOPLE AND
COMING OUT AND SHOOTING NINE
PEOPLE.
THIS SHOULD NOT BE A POLITICAL
ISSUE.
WHAT WE SHOULD BE DOING IS
WORKING TOGETHER, AND BY THE
WAY, IF THE SENATOR FROM A RURAL
STATE THAT HAS VIRTUALLY NO GUN
CONTROL, I BELIEVE THAT I AM IN
AN EXCELLENT POSITION TO BRING
PEOPLE TOGETHER --
>> SENATOR, YOU DIDN'T ANSWER
THE QUESTION THAT YOU DID CHANGE
YOUR POSITION ON IMMUNITY FOR
GUN MANUFACTURERS.
CAN YOU ANSWER THE QUESTION AS
TO WHY.
>> WHAT I HAVE SAID IS THAT THE
GUN MANUFACTURERS LIABILITY BILL
HAD SOME GOOD PROVISIONS AMONG
OTHER THINGS, WE PROHIBITED
AMMUNITION THAT WOULD HAVE
KILLED COPS WHO HAD PROTECTION
ON.
WE HAD CHILD SAFETY PROTECTION
ON GUNS IN THAT LEGISLATION, AND
WHAT WE ALSO SAID IS A SMALL,
MOM AND POP GUN SHOP, WHO SELLS
A GUN LEGALLY TO SOMEBODY,
SHOULD NOT BE HELD LIABLE IF
SOMEBODY DOES SOMETHING TERRIBLE
WITH THAT GUN.
I SAID I WOULD RELOOK AT IT THE,
WE ARE GOING TO RELOOK AT IT.
AND I WILL SUPPORT STRONGER
PROVISIONS.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, WOULD YOU
LIKE TO RESPOND TO SENATOR
SANDERS.
>> YES, UM, LOOK, I HAVE MADE IT
CLEAR, BASED ON SENATOR SANDERS
OWN RECORD THAT HE HAS VOTED
WITH THE NRA, WITH THE GUN LOBBY
NUMEROUS TIMES.
VOTED AGAINST THE BRADY BILL
FIVE TIMES.
HE VOTED FOR WHAT WE CALL THE
CHARLESTON LOOPHOLE.
HE VOTED FOR IMMUNITY FROM GUN
MAKERS AND SELLERS, WHICH THE
NRA SAID WAS THE MOST IMPORTANT
PIECE OF GUN LEGISLATION IN 20
YEARS.
HE VOTED TO LET GUNS GO ON TO
AMTRAK, GOES INTO NATIONAL
PARKS, HE VOTED AGAINST DOING
RESEARCH TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE
CAN SAVE LIVES.
LET'S NOT FORGET WHAT THIS IS
ABOUT.
90 PEOPLE A DAY DIE FROM GUN
VIOLENCE IN OUR COUNTRY.
THAT'S 33,000 PEOPLE A YEAR.
ONE OF THE MOST HORRIFIC
EXAMPLES, NOT A BLOCK FROM HERE,
WHERE WE HAD NINE PEOPLE
MURDERED.
NOW, I AM PLEASED TO HEAR THAT
SENATOR SANDERS HAS REVERSED HIS
POSITION ON IMMUNITY, AND I LOOK
FORWARD TO HIM JOINING WITH
THOSE MEMBERS OF CONGRESS WHO
HAVE ALREADY INTRODUCED
LEGISLATION.
THERE IS NO OTHER INDUSTRY IN
AMERICA THAT WAS GIVEN THE TOTAL
PASS THAT THE GUN MAKERS AND
DEALERS WERE, AND THAT NEEDS TO
BE REVERSED.
>> ALL RIGHT.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU SIGNED TOUGH GUN CONTROL
MEASURES AS GOVERNOR OF
MARYLAND, AND THERE ARE A LOT OF
DEMOCRATS IN THE AUDIENCE HERE
IN SOUTH CAROLINA WHO OWN GUNS.
THIS CONVERSATION MIGHT BE
WORRYING MANY OF THEM.
THEY MAY BE HEARING, YOU WANT TO
TAKE MY GUNS.
>> THIS WHAT I WOULD SAY.
I'VE LISTENED TO SECRETARY
CLINTON AND SENATOR SANDERS GO
BACK ON FORTH ON WHICH HAS THE
MOST INCONSISTENT RECORD ON GUN
SAFETY LEGISLATION, AND, AND I
WOULD HAVE TO AGREE WITH BOTH OF
THEM.
THEY'VE BOTH BEEN INCONSISTENT
WHEN IT COMES TO THIS ISSUE.
I'M THE ONE CANDIDATE ON THIS
STAGE THAT ACTUALLY BROUGHT
PEOPLE TOGETHER TO PASS
COMPREHENSIVE GUN SAFETY
LEGISLATION.
THIS IS VERY PERSONAL TO ME
BEING FROM BALTIMORE.
I WILL NEVER FORGET ONE OCCASION
VISITING LITTLE BOY IN JOHN'S
HOPKINS HOSPITAL, BIRTHDAY
HAIRCUT, AGE OF THREE, WHEN DRUG
DEALERS TURN THAT IN A SHOOTING
GALLERY AND BOY'S HEAD WAS
PIERCED WITH A BULLET.
IT DID NOT KILL HIM.
I REMEMBER VISITING HIM AND HIS
MOTHER IN THE HOSPITAL.
AND HIS DIAPERS AND TUBES
RUNNING IN AND OUT OF HIS HEAD.
SAME ANYONE AS MY LITTLE BOY.
AFTER THE SLAUGHTER OF THE KIDS
IN CONNECTICUT, WE BE PASS IN
OUR STATE COMPREHENSIVE GUN
SAFETY LEGISLATION.
IT DID HAVE THE BAN ON COMBAT
ASSAULT WEAPONS, UNIVERSAL
BACKGROUND CHECKS, AND WE DID
NOT INTERRUPT A SINGLE PERSON'S
HUNTING SEASON.
I'VE NEVER MET A SELF-RESPECTING
DEER HUNTER THAT NEEDED AN AR-15
TO DOWN A DEER.
WE'VE DONE THESE THINGS.
>> THANK YOU.
SECRETARY CLINTON, THIS IS A
COMMUNITY THAT HAS SUFFERED A
LOT OF HEART ACHE IN THE LAST
YEAR, OF COURSE AS YOU
MENTIONED, THE CHURCH SHOOTINGS.
WE WON'T FORGET THE VIDEO OF OF
WALTER SCOTT BEING SHOT IN THE
BACK WHILE RUNNING FROM POLICE.
WE UNDERSTAND THAT A JURY WILL
DECIDE WHETHER THAT POLICE
OFFICER WAS JUSTIFIED, BUT IT
PLAYED STRAIGHT TO THE FEARS OF
MANY AFRICAN AMERICAN MEN THAT
THEIR LIVES ARE CHEAP.
IS THAT PERCEPTION OR IN YOUR
VIEW, IS IT REALITY?
>> WELL, SADLY IT'S REALITY.
AND IT HAS BEEN HEART BREAKING
AND INCREDIBLY OUTRAGING TO SEE
THE CONSTANT STORIES OF YOUNG
MEN, LIKE WALTER SCOTT, AS YOU
SAID, WHO HAVE BEEN KILLED BY
POLICE OFFICERS.
THERE NEEDS TO BE A CONCERTED
EFFORT TO ADDRESS THE SYSTEMIC
RACISM IN OUR CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
AND THAT REQUIRES A VERY CLEAR
AGENDA FOR RETRAINING POLICE
OFFICERS, LOOKING AT WAYS TO END
RACIAL PROFILING, FINDING MORE
WAYS TO REALLY BRING THE
DISPARITIES THAT STOCK OUR
COUNTRY INTO HIGH RELIEF.
ONE OUT OF THREE AFRICAN
AMERICAN MEN MAY WELL END UP
GOING TO PRISON.
THAT'S THE STATISTIC.
I WANT PEOPLE HERE TO THINK WHAT
WE WOULD BE DOING IF IT WAS ONE
OUT OF THREE WHITE MEN.
AND VERY OFTEN THE BLACK MEN ARE
ARRESTED, CONVICTED, AND
INCARCERATED FOR OFFENSES THAT
DO NOT LEAD TO THE SAME RESULTS
FOR WHITE MEN.
SO WE HAVE A VERY SERIOUS
PROBLEM THAT WE CAN NO LONGER
IGNORE.
>> AND YOUR TIME IS UP.
SENATOR SANDERS, MY NEXT
QUESTION IS FOR YOU.
>> WHAT THE SECRETARY SAID, WE
HAVE A CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM
WHICH IS BROKEN.
WHO IN AMERICA ARE SATISFIED
THAT WE HAVE MORE PEOPLE IN JAIL
THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY ON EARTH,
INCLUDING CHINA?
DISPROPORTIONALLY AFRICAN
AMERICAN AND LATINO.
WHO IS SATISFIED THAT 51% OF
AFRICAN AMERICAN, YOUNG PEOPLE
ARE EITHER UNEMPLOYED OR
UNDEREMPLOYED.
WHO IS SATISFIED THAT MILLIONS
OF PEOPLE HAVE POLICE RECORDS
FOR POSSESSING MARIJUANA WHEN
THE CEO'S OF WALL STREET
COMPANIES WHO DESTROYED OUR
ECONOMY HAVE NO POLICE RECORD.
>>.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> SENATOR SANDERS --
>> WE NEED TO TAKE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- WE NEED TO TAKE A VERY HARD
LOOK --
>> SENATOR SANDERS --
>> INVESTING IN JOBS AND
INVESTIGATION.
NOT IN JAILS AND INCARCERATION.
>> JUST OVER A WEEK AGO THE
CHAIRMAN OF THE CONGRESSIONAL
BLACK CAUCUS ENDORSED SECRETARY
CLINTON, NOT YOU, HE SAID
CHOOSING HER OVER YOU WAS NOT A
HARD DECISION.
IN FACT OUR POLLING SHOWS SHE'S
BEATING YOU MORE THAN TWO TO ONE
AMONG MINORITY VOTERS.
HOW CAN YOU BE THE NOMINEE IF
YOU DON'T HAVE THE SUPPORT?
>> LET ME TALK ABOUT POLLING.
SECRETARY, SECRETARY CLINTON
WELL KNOWS, WHEN THIS CAMPAIGN
BEGAN, SHE WAS 50 POINTS AHEAD
OF ME.
WE WERE ALL OF 3 PERCENTAGE
POINTS.
GUESS WHAT?
IN IOWA, NEW HAMPSHIRE, THE RACE
IS VERY, VERY CLOSE.
MAYBE WE'RE AHEAD IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
IN TERMS OF POLLING, GUESS WHAT,
WE ARE RUNNING AHEAD OF
SECRETARY CLINTON IN TERMS OF
TAKING ON MY GOOD FRIEND, DONALD
TRUMP.
BEATING HIM BY 19 POINTS IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, 13 POINTS IN THE LAST
NATIONAL POLL THAT I SAW.
TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, WHEN
THE AFRICAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY
BECOMES MY CONGRESSIONAL RECORD
AND WITH OUR GENDER AND WITH OUR
VIEWS ON THE ECONOMY AND
CRIMINAL JUSTICE, JUST ASK THE
GENERAL POPULATION HAS BECOME
MORE SUPPORTIVE, SO WILL THE
AFRICAN AMERICAN COMMUNITY, SO
WILL THE LATINO COMMUNITY, WE
HAVE THE MOMENTUM, WE'RE ON A
PATH TO A VICTORY --
>> GOVERNOR, I'M COMING TO YOU
IN A SECTION.
GOOGLE SEARCHES FOR THE WORDS
BLACK LIVES MATTER SURPASSED
CIVIL RIGHTS MOVEMENT HERE LAST
YEAR.
BLACK LIVES MATTER WAS THE
NUMBER ONE POLITICAL ISSUE.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOU CAMPAIGN
IN YOUR RECORD AS GOVERNOR OF
MARYLAND AND BEFORE THAT, THE
MAYOR OF BALTIMORE LAST YEAR, OF
COURSE BALTIMORE WAS ROCKED BY
VIOLENT UNREST IN THE WAKE OF
THE DEATH OF FREDDIE GRAY.
AND RIGHT FROM THE START OF YOUR
CAMPAIGN, YOU'VE BEEN DOGGED BY
THOSE WHO BLAME YOUR TOUGH-RUN
CRIME, SOB CALLED ZERO-TOLERANCE
POLICIES AS MAYOR FOR
CONTRIBUTING TO THAT UNREST.
WHAT RESPONSIBILITY DO YOU BEAR?
>> YEAH, LET'S TALK ABOUT THIS.
WHEN I RAN FOR MAYOR IN 1999
LESTER, IT WAS NOT BECAUSE THE
CITY WAS DOING WELL.
IT WAS BECAUSE WE WERE BURYING
OVER 300 YOUNG, POOR BLACK MEN
EVERY SINGLE YEAR.
AND THAT'S WHY I RAN.
BECAUSE YES, BLACK LIVES MATTER.
AND WE DID A NUMBER OF THINGS WE
WEREN'T ABLE TO MAKE OUR CITY
IMMUNE FROM SETBACKS SUCH AS
FREDDIE GRAY UNREST AND TRAGIC
DEATH SHOWED.
BUT WE WERE ABLE TO SAVE A LOT
OF LIVES DOING THINGS THAT
ACTUALLY WORK TO IMPROVE POLICE
AND COMMUNITY RELATIONS.
THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS, WE
CREATE A CIVILIAN REVIEW BOARD.
AND MANY OF THESE THINGS ARE IN
THE NEW AGENDA FOR CRIMINAL
JUSTICE REFORM THAT I'VE PUT
FORWARD.
WE CREATED A CIVILIAN REVIEW
BOARD, GAVE THEM THEIR OWN
DETECTIVES, REQUIRED THE
REPORTING OF DISCOURTESY, USE OF
EXCESSIVE FORCE, LETHAL FORCE, I
REPEALED THE POSSESSION OF
MARIJUANA AS A CRIME IN OUR
STATE.
I DROVE OUR INCARCERATE RATE
DOWN TO 20-YEAR LOWS AND DROVE
VIOLENT CRIME DOWN TO 30-YEAR
LOWS AND BECAME THE FIRST
GOVERNOR SOUTH OF THE MAY SON
DIXON LINE TO REPEAL THE DEATH
PENALTY.
I FEEL A RESPONSIBILITY EVERY
DAY TO FIND THINGS THAT WORK.
>> ALL RIGHT --
>> AND DO MORE.
>> LET'S TALK MORE ABOUT
POLICING AND THE CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM.
SENATOR SANDERS, A FEW TIMES
TONIGHT WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM
SOME OF THE MOST PROMINENT
VOICES ON YOUTUBE, STARTING WITH
FRANCESCA RAMSEY WHO TACKLES
RACIAL STEREOTYPES.
>> I BELIEVE THERE'S A HUGE
CONFLICT OF INTEREST WHEN LOCAL
PROSECUTORS INVESTIGATE CASES OF
POLICE VIOLENCE WITHIN THEIR OWN
COMMUNITY.
FOR EXAMPLE, LAST MONTH, THE
OFFICERS INVOLVED IN THE CASE OF
12-YEAR-OLD TAMIR RICE WEREN'T
INDICTED.
HOW WOULD YOUR PRESIDENCY ENSURE
THE INCIDENTS OF POLICE VIOLENCE
ARE INVESTIGATED AND PROSECUTED
FAIRLY?
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> I'M SORRY FOR NOT HEARING ALL
OF THAT QUESTION.
>> WOULD YOU LIKE ME TO READ IT
BACK TO YOU?
>> YEAH.
>> PROSECUTORS, I BELIEVE
THERE'S A HUGE CONFLICT OF
INTEREST WHEN LOCAL PROSECUTORS
INVESTIGATE CASES OF POLICE
VIOLENCE WITHIN THEIR
COMMUNITIES.
MOST RECENTLY, WE SAW THIS WITH
A NON-INDICTMENT OF THE OFFICERS
INVOLVED IN THE CASE OF
12-YEAR-OLD TAMIR RICE.
HOW WOULD YOU PRESIDENCY ENSURE
ZANTS OF POLICE VIOLENCE OR
PROSECUTED FAIRLY?
>> THIS IS A RESPONSIBILITY FOR
THE U.S. JUSTICE DEPARTMENT TO
GET INVOLVED.
WHENEVER ANYBODY IN THIS COUNTRY
IS KILLED WHILE IN POLICE
CUSTODY, THEY SHOULD
AUTOMATICALLY TRIGGER A U.S.
ATTORNEY GENERAL'S
INVESTIGATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SECOND OF ALL, AND I SPEAK AS A
MAYOR WHO WORKED VERY CLOSELY, A
MAJORITY ARE HONEST,
HARD-WORKING PEOPLE TRYING TO DO
A DIFFICULT JOB, BUT LET US BE
CLEAR.
IF A POLICE OFFICER BREAKS THE
LAW, LIKE ANY PUBLIC OFFICIAL,
THAT OFFICER MUST BE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND THIRDLY, WE HAVE GOT TO
DEMILITARIZE OUR POLICE
DEPARTMENTS SO THEY DON'T LOOK
LIKE OCCUPY ARMY.
WE'VE GOT TO MOVE TOWARD
COMMUNITY POLICING, AND
FOURTHLY, WE HAVE GOT TO MAKE
OUR POLICE DEPARTMENTS LOOK LIKE
THE COMMUNITIES THEY SERVE IN
THEIR DIVERSITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THIS
QUESTION IS FOR YOU, TONIGHT
PARTS OF AMERICA ARE ON THE GRIP
OF A DEADLY HEROIN EPIDEMIC,
SPANNING RACE AND CLASS, HITTING
SMALL TOWNS AND CITIES ALIKE.
IT'S BECOME A MAJOR ISSUE IN
THIS RACE.
IN A LOT OF PLACES, WHERE YOU'VE
BEEN CAMPAIGNING, DESPITE AN
ESTIMATED TRILLION DOLLARS
SPENT, MANY SAY THE WAR ON DRUGS
HAS FAILED.
WHAT WOULD YOU DO?
>> WELL, LESTER, YOU'RE RIGHT.
EVERYWHERE I GO TO CAMPAIGN, I'M
MEETING FAMILIES WHO ARE
AFFECTED BY THE DRUG PROBLEM
THAT MOSTLY IS OPIOIDS AND
HEROIN NOW, AND LIVES ARE BEING
LOST AND CHILDREN ARE BEING
ORPHANED.
I'VE MET A LOT OF GRANDPARENTS
THAT ARE TAKING CARE OF
GRANDCHILDREN.
SO I HAVE TRIED TO COME OUT WITH
A COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH THAT
NUMBER ONE, DOES TELL THE STATE
THAT WE WILL WORK WITH YOU FROM
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT PUTTING
MORE MONEY ABOUT A BILLION
DOLLARS A YEAR, TO HELP STATES
HAVE A DIFFERENT APPROACH TO
DEALING WITH THIS EPIDEMIC.
THE POLICING NEEDS TO CHANGE.
POLICE OFFICERS MUST BE EQUIPPED
WITH THE ANECDOTE TO A AARON
OVERDOSE OR AN OPIOID OVERDOSE,
THEY SHOULD BE ABLE TO
ADMINISTRATE IT.
SO SHOULD FIREFIGHTERS AND
OTHER.
WE HAVE TO MOVE AWAY FROM
TREATING THE USE OF DRUGS A AS
CRIME AND INSTEAD, MOVE IT TO
WHERE IT BELONGS, AS A HEALTH
ISSUE.
AND WE NEED TO DIVERT MORE
PEOPLE FROM THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM INTO DRUG COURTS, INTO
TREATMENT, AND RECOVERY.
>> TIME.
>> AND THIS IS THE KIND OF
APPROACH THAT WE SHOULD TAKE IN
DEALING WITH WHAT IS NOW A
GROWING EPIDEMIC.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, WOULD YOU
LIKE TO RESPOND?
>> I AGREE, I AGREE WITH
EVERYTHING THE SECRETARY SAID,
BUT LET ME JUST ADD THIS, THERE
IS A RESPONSIBILITY ON THE PART
OF THE PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY,
AND THE DRUG COMPANIES WHO ARE
PRODUCING ALL OF THESE DRUGS AND
NOT LOOKING AT THE CONSEQUENCE
OF IT.
AND SECOND OF ALL, WHEN WE TALK
ABOUT ADDICTION BEING A DISEASE,
THE SECRETARY IS RIGHT, WHAT
THAT MEANS IS WE NEED A
REVOLUTION IN THIS COUNTRY IN
TERMS OF MENTAL HEALTH
TREATMENT.
PEOPLE SHOULD BE ABLE TO GET THE
TREATMENT THAT THEY NEED, WHEN
THEY NEED IT, NOT TWO MONTHS
FROM NOW, WHICH IS WHY I BELIEVE
IN UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE WITH
MENTAL HEALTH A PART OF THAT.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A
BREAK --
>> JUST TEN SECONDS.
>> AND WHEN WE COME BACK THE
ANGER BREWING IN AMERICA.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO CHARLESTON,
LET'S TURN TO ANOTHER AREA WHERE
THERE'S BEEN FIERCE
DISAGREEMENT, HEALTH CARE.
YOU MENTIONED IT IN YOUR 100-DAY
PRIORITY.
LET'S TURN TO ANDREA MITCHELL
NOW TO LEAD THAT QUESTION.
>> THANK YOU, LESTER.
SECRETARY CLINTON, SENATOR
SANDERS FAVORS WHAT HE CALLS
MEDICARE FOR ALL.
NOW YOU SAID THAT WHAT HE IS
PROPOSING WOULD TEAR UP
OBAMACARE AND REPLACE IT.
SECRETARY CLINTON, IS IT FAIR TO
SAY TO SAY THAT BERNIE SANDERS
WANTS TO KILL OBAMACARE?
>> WELL, ANDREA, I AM COMMITTED
TO UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE.
I HAVE WORKED ON THIS FOR A LONG
TIME, PEOPLE MAY REMEMBER THAT I
TOOK ON THE HEALTH INSURANCE
INDUSTRY BACK IN THE '90s, AND I
DIDN'T QUIT UNTIL WE GOT THE
CHILDREN'S HEALTH INSURANCE AND
ENSURED 8s EIGHT MILLION KIDS.
I CERTAINLY RESPECT SENATOR
SANDERS INTENTION, BUT WHEN
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT HEALTH
CARE, THE DETAILS REALLY MATTER,
AND THEREFORE, WE HAVE BEEN
RAISING QUESTIONS ABOUT THE NINE
BILLS THAT HE INTRODUCED OVER 20
YEARS AS TO HOW THEY WOULD WORK
AND WHAT WOULD BE THE IMPACT ON
PEOPLE'S HEALTH CARE.
HE DIDN'T LIKE THAT, HIS
CAMPAIGN DIDN'T LIKE IT EITHER.
AND TONIGHT, HE'S COME OUT WITH
A NEW HEALTH CARE PLAN, AND
AGAIN, WE NEED TO GET INTO THE
DETAILS, BUT HERE'S WHAT I
BELIEVE, THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY
AND THE UNITED STATES WORKS
SINCE HARRY TRUMAN TO GET THE
AFFORDABLE HEALTH CARE ACT
PASSED.
WE FINALLY HAVE A PATH TO
UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE.
WE HAVE ACCOMPLISHED SO MUCH
ALREADY, I DO NOT TO WANT SEE
THE REPUBLICANS REPEAL IT AND I
DON'T TO WANT SEE US START OVER
AGAIN WITH A CONTENTIOUS DEBATE.
I WANT US TO DEFEND AND BUILD ON
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT AND
IMPROVE IT.
>> OKAY.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> BECAUSE WHAT HER CAMPAIGN WAS
SAYING, BERNIE SANDERS WAS
SAYING, MY ENTIRE LIFE, HE WANTS
TO END MEDICARE AND MEDICAID AND
THE CHILDREN'S HEALTH INSURANCE
PROGRAM.
THAT IS NONSENSE.
WHAT A MEDICARE FOR ALL PROGRAM
DOES IS FINALLY PROVIDE IN THIS
COUNTRY HEALTH CARE FOR EVERY
MAN, WOMAN, AND CHILD, AS A
RIGHT.
NOW, THE TRUTH IS, THAT FRANK
ROOSEVELT, HARRY TRUMAN, DO YOU
KNOW WHAT THEY BELIEVED IN, THEY
BELIEVED THAT HEALTH CARE SHOULD
BE AVAILABLE TO ALL OF OUR
PEOPLE.
I'M ON THE COMMITTEE THAT WROTE
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
I MADE THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT
ALONG WITH JIM CLYBORN A BETTER
PIECE OF LEGISLATION.
I VOTED FOR IT, BUT RIGHT NOW,
WHAT WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH IS THE
FACT THAT 29 MILLION PEOPLE
STILL HAVE NO HEALTH INSURANCE.
WE ARE PAYING THE HIGHEST PRICES
IN THE WORLD FOR PRESCRIPTION
DRUGS.
GETTING RIPPED OFF.
AND HERE'S THE IMPORTANT POINT,
WE ARE SPENDING FAR MORE FOR
PERSON ON HEALTH CARE THAN THE
PEOPLE OF ANY OTHER COUNTRY.
MY PROPOSAL, PROVIDE HEALTH CARE
TO ALL PEOPLE, GET PRIVATE
INSURANCE OUT OF INSURANCE,
LOWER THE COST OF HEALTH CARE
FOR MIDDLE CLASS FAMILIES BY
5,000 BUCKS.
THAT'S THE VISION WE NEED TO
TAKE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> IF I CAN -- YOU KNOW, I HAVE
TO SAY I'M NOT SURE WHETHER
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT THE PLAN YOU
JUST INTRODUCED TONIGHT OR WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT THE PLAN YOU
INTRODUCED NINE TIMES IN THE
CONGRESS, BUT THE FACT IS, WE
HAVE THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
THAT IS ONE OF THE GREATEST
ACCOMPLISHMENTS OF PRESIDENT
OBAMA, OF THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY,
AND OF OUR COUNTRY, AND WE HAVE
ALREADY SEEN 19 MILLION
AMERICANS GET INSURANCE.
WE HAVE SEEN THE END OF
PREEXISTING CONDITIONS KEEPING
PEOPLE FROM GETTING INSURANCE.
WE HAVE SEEN WOMEN NO LONGER
PAYING MORE FOR OUR INSURANCE
THAN MEN.
AND WE HAVE SEEN YOUNG PEOPLE UP
TO THE AGE OF 26 BEING ABLE TO
STAY ON THEIR PARENT'S POLICY,
NOW THERE ARE THINGS WE CAN DO
TO IMPROVE IT, BUT TO TEAR IT UP
AND START OVER AGAIN, PUSHING
OUR COUNTRY BACK INTO THAT KIND
OF A CONTENTIOUS DEBATE, I THINK
IS THE WRONG DIRECTION.
>> IT IS.
>> I HAVE TO TALK ABOUT
SOMETHING THAT'S ACTUALLY
WORKING IN OUR STATE.
>> NO ONE IS TEARING THIS UP.
WE'RE GOING TO GO FORWARD.
BUT WITH THE SECRETARY NEGLECTED
TO MENTION, NOT JUST THE 29
MILLION STILL HAVE NO HEALTH
INSURANCE THAT EVEN MORE ARE
UNDERINSURED WITH HUGE
COPAYMENTS AND DEDUCTIBLES.
TELL ME WHY WE ARE SPENDING OVER
THREE TIMES MORE THAN THE
BRITISH WHO GUARANTEE HEALTH
CARE TO ALL OF THEIR PEOPLE?
50% MORE THAN THE FRENCH.
MORE THAN THE CANADIANS.
THE VISION FROM FDR AND HARRY
TRUMAN WAS HEALTH CARE FOR ALL
PEOPLE AS A RIGHT IN A
COST-EFFECTIVE WAY.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO TEAR UP THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
I HELPED WRITE IT, BUT WE ARE
GOING TO MOVE ON TOP OF THAT TO
A SYSTEM FOR ALL.
>> ANDREA, ANDREA, INSTEAD OF --
ANDREA, I THINK INSTEAD OF
ATTACKING ONE ANOTHER ON HEALTH
CARE.
WE SHOULD BE TALKING ABOUT THE
THINGS THAT ARE ACTUALLY
WORKING.
IN OUR STATE, WE HAVE MOVED TO
AN ALL-PAYER SYSTEM WITH THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, WE NOW HAVE
MOVED ALL OF OUR ACUTE CARE
HOSPITALS THAT DRIVER OF COST AT
THE CENTER, AWAY FROM SERVICE
AND ACTUALLY TO PAY, WE PAY THEM
BASED ON HOW WELL THEY KEEP
PATIENTS OUT OF THE HOSPITAL.
HOW WELL THEY KEEP THEIR
PATIENTS.
THAT'S THE FUTURE.
WE NEED TO BUILD ON THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, DO THE
THINGS THAT WORK, AND REDUCE
COSTS AND INCREASE ACCESS.
>> AND THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT WE
ARE ABLE TO DO BASED ON THE
FOUNDATION OF THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT.
WHAT GOVERNOR O'MALLEY JUST SAID
IS ONE OF THE MODELS THAT WE
WILL BE LOOKING AT TO MAKE SURE
WE DO GET COSTS DOWN.
WE DO LIMIT A LOT OF THE
UNNECESSARY COST THAT WE STILL
HAVE IN THE SYSTEM.
BUT, WITH ALL DO RESPECT, TO
START OVER AGAIN, WITH A WHOLE
NEW DEBATE IS SOMETHING THAT I
THINK WOULD SET US BACK.
THE REPUBLICANS JUST VOTED LAST
WEEK TO REPEAL THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT, AND THANK GOODNESS,
PRESIDENT OBAMA VETOED IT AND
SAVED OBAMACARE FOR THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, LET ME ASK
YOU THIS THOUGH, YOU TALKED
MEDICARE FOR ALL, AND TONIGHT
YOU'VE RELEASED A VERY DETAILED
PLAN JUST --
>> NOT ALL THAT DETAILED.
>> TWO HOURS BEFORE THE DEBATE,
YOU DID.
LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT VERMONT.
YOU TRIED IN THE STATE OF
VERMONT, AND VERMONT WALKED AWAY
FROM THIS KIND OF IDEA OF
MEDICARE FOR ALL SINGLE PAYER
BECAUSE THEY CONCLUDED IT WOULD
REQUIRE MAJOR TAX INCREASES AND
SOME ESTIMATES IT WOULD DOUBLE
THE BUDGET.
>> ANDREA, LET ME JUST SAY THIS,
ASK THE GOVERNOR OF THE STATE OF
VERMONT WHY HE COULD NOT DO IT.
I'M NOT THE GOVERNOR.
I'M THE SENATOR FROM THE STATE
OF VERMONT.
SECOND OF ALL, SECOND OF ALL,
HERE IS WHAT THE REAL POINT IS,
IN TERMS OF ALL OF THE ISSUES
YOU'VE RAISED.
THE GOOD QUESTIONS YOU'VE
RAISED.
WHAT IT ALL COMES DOWN TO, DO
YOU KNOW WHY WE CAN'T DO WHAT
EVERY OTHER MAJOR COUNTRY IS
DOING?
IT'S BECAUSE WE HAVE A CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM THAT IS CORRUPT,
WE HAVE SUPERPACKS, WE HAVE THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY POURING
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
INTO CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS AND
LOBBYING, AND THE PRIVATE
INSURANCE COMPANIES AS WELL.
WHAT IS THIS WILL REALLY ABOUT
NOT THE RATIONAL WAY TO GO
FORWARD, IT'S MEDICARE FOR ALL.
IT IS WHETHER WE HAVE THE GUTS
TO STAND UP THE PRIVATE
INSURANCE COMPANIES AND ALL OF
THEIR MONEY, AND THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY.
THAT'S WHAT THIS DEBATE SHOULD
BE ABOUT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WELL, AS SOMEONE WHO, AS
SOMEONE WHO HAS A LITTLE BIT OF
EXPERIENCE STANDING UP TO THE
HEALTH INSURANCE INDUSTRY, THAT
SPENT, YOU KNOW, MANY, MANY
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS ATTACKING ME
AND PROBABLY WILL SO AGAIN
BECAUSE OF WHAT I BELIEVE WE CAN
DO, BUILDING ON THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT, I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
TO POINT OUT THAT THERE ARE A
LOT OF REASONS WE HAVE THE
HEALTH CARE SYSTEM WE HAVE
TODAY.
I KNOW HOW MUCH MONEY INFLUENCES
THE POLITICAL DECISION-MAKING.
THAT'S WHY I'M FOR HUGE CAMPAIGN
FINANCE REFORM.
HOWEVER, WE STARTED A SYSTEM
THAT HAD PRIVATE HEALTH
INSURANCE.
AND EVEN DURING THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT DEBATE, THERE WAS AN
OPPORTUNITY TO VOTE FOR WHAT WAS
CALLED THE PUBLIC OPTION.
IN OTHER WORDS, PEOPLE COULD
BUY-IN TO MEDICARE, AND WHEN THE
DEMOCRATS WERE IN CHARGE OF THE
CONGRESS, WE COULDN'T GET THE
VOTES FOR THAT.
SO, WHAT I'M SAYING IS REALLY
SIMPLE, THIS HAS BEEN THE FIGHT
OF THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY FOR
DECADES.
WE HAVE THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
LET'S MAKE IT WORK.
LET'S TAKE THE MODELS THAT
STATES ARE DOING.
WE NOW HAVE DRIVEN COSTS DOWN TO
THE LOWEST THEY'VE BEEN IN 50
YEARS.
NOW WE'VE GOT TO GET INDIVIDUAL
COSTS DOWN.
THAT'S WHAT I'M PLANNING TO DO.
>> AND WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A
TURN NOW.
SECRETARY CLINTON, IN HIS FINAL
STATE OF THE UNION ADDRESS,
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID HIS BIGGEST
REGRET WAS HIS INABILITY TO
BRING THE COUNTRY TOGETHER.
IF PRESIDENT OBAMA COULDN'T DO
IT, HOW WILL YOU?
>> GREAT QUESTION.
>> IT'S AN IMPORTANT POINT THE
PRESIDENT MADE IN HIS STATE OF
THE UNION.
AND HERE'S WHAT I WOULD SAY.
LY GO ANYWHERE TO MEET WITH
ANYONE, AT ANY TIME TO FIND
COMMON GROUND.
THAT'S WHAT I DID AS A FIRST
LADY WHEN I WORKED WITH BOTH
DEMOCRATS AND REPUBLICANS TO GET
THE CHILDREN'S HEALTH INSURANCE
PROGRAM.
WHEN I WORKED WITH TOM DELAY,
ONE OF THE MOST PARTISAN OF
REPUBLICANS TO REFORM THE
ADOPTION AND FOSTER CARE SYSTEM.
WHAT I DID, WORKING IN THE
SENATE, WHERE I CROSSED THE
AISLE OFTEN, WORKING EVEN WITH
THE SENATOR FROM SOUTH CAROLINA,
LINDSEY GRAHAM, TO GET TRICARE
FOR NATIONAL GUARDSMEN AND
WOMEN.
AND IT'S WHAT I DID AS SECRETARY
OF STATE.
ON NUMEROUS OCCASIONS, AND MOST
PARTICULARLY, ROUNDING UP
TWO-THIRDS VOTES IN ORDER TO
PASS A TREATY THAT LOWERED THE
NUCLEAR WEAPONS IN BOTH RUSSIA
AND THE UNITED STATES.
SO I KNOW IT'S HARD.
BUT I ALSO KNOW YOU'VE GOT TO
WORK AT IT EVERY SINGLE DAY.
I LOOK OUT HERE, I SEE A LOT OF
MY FRIENDS FROM THE CONGRESS.
AND I KNOW THAT THEY WORK AT IT
EVERY SINGLE DAY.
BECAUSE MAYBE YOU CAN'T ONLY
FIND A LITTLE SLIVER OF COMMON
GROUND TO COOPERATE WITH SOMEONE
FROM THE OTHER PARTY, BUT WHO
KNOWS, IF YOU'RE SUCCESSFUL
THERE, MAYBE YOU CAN BUILD EVEN
MORE.
THAT'S WHAT I WOULD DO.
>> SENATOR SANDERS RESPONSE.
>> A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO WHEN WE
UNDERSTOOD THAT VETERANS WERE
NOT GETTING THE QUALITY CARE
THEY NEEDED IN THE TIMELY
MANNER, I WORKED WITH FOLKS LIKE
JOHN McCAIN AND OTHERS TO PASS
THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE VETERAN'S
HEALTH CARE LEGISLATION IN
MODERN HISTORY.
BUT LET ME REPHRASE YOUR
QUESTION BECAUSE I THINK, IN ALL
DO RESPECT, YOUR EXPRESSION, IN
ALL DO RESPECT, YOU'RE MISSING
THE MAIN POINT.
AND THE MAIN POINT IN THE
CONGRESS IS NOT THE REPUBLICANS
AND DEMOCRATS HATE EACH OTHER.
THAT'S A MYTHOLOGY FROM THE
MEDIA.
THE REAL ISSUE IS THAT CONGRESS
IS OWNED BY BIG MONEY AND
REFUSES TO DO WHAT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WANT THEM TO DO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THE REAL ISSUE IS THAT ON, THE
REAL ISSUE IS THAT IN AREA AFTER
AREA, RAISING THE MINIMUM WAGE
TO 15 BUCKS AN HOUR.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WANT IT.
REBUILDING OUR CRUMBLING
INFRASTRUCTURE, CREATING 13
MILLION JOBS, THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WANT IT THE, PAY EQUITY
FOR WOMEN, THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
WANT IT, DEMANDING THAT THE
WEALTHY START PAYING THEIR FAIR
SHARE OF TAXES, THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WANT IT.
>> THAT'S TIME.
BUT LET ME --
>> THE POINT IS, WE HAVE TO MAKE
CONGRESS RESPOND TO THE NEEDS OF
THE PEOPLE, NOT BIG MONEY.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU CALL
YOURSELF A DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALIST --
>> I DO.
>> AND THROUGHOUT YOUR CAREER IN
POLITICS, YOU'VE BEEN CRITICAL
OF THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY, THERE'S
WASN'T A HELL OF A BIG
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE THE TWO
MAJOR PARTIES --
>> DID I SAY THAT?
>> HOW DID PLAN ON WINNING WITH
LABELING YOURSELF THAT.
>> DEMOCRATIC PARTY NEEDS MAJOR
REFORM.
TO THOSE OF YOU IN SOUTH
CAROLINA, YOU KNOW WHAT, IN
MISSISSIPPI, WE NEED A 50-STATE
STRATEGY SO THAT PEOPLE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA AND MISSISSIPPI CAN GET
THE RESOURCES THAT THEY NEED.
INSTEAD OF BEING DEPENDENT ON
SUPERPACKS, WHAT WE NEED IS TO
BE DEPENDENT ON SMALL,
INDIVIDUAL CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTORS.
WE NEED AN AGENDA THAT SPEAKS TO
THE NEEDS OF WORKING FAMILIES
AND LOW-INCOME PEOPLE.
NOT WEALTHY CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTORS.
>> YEAH, BUT SENATOR, YOU CAN --
>> WE NEED TO EXPAND WHAT THE
INPUT INTO THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
I AM VERY PROUD THAT IN THIS
CAMPAIGN, WE HAVE SEEN AN
ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF EXCITEMENT
FROM YOUNG PEOPLE, FROM WORKING
PEOPLE.
WE HAVE RECEIVED MORE INDIVIDUAL
CONTRIBUTIONS THAN ANY CANDIDATE
IN THE HISTORY OF THIS COUNTRY
UP TO THIS POINT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YEAH, BUT SENATOR YOU NEVER
CAME TO CAMPAIGN FOR VINCENT
WHEN HE WAS RUNNING FOR
GOVERNOR.
IN FACT, NEITHER OF YOU CAME TO
CAMPAIGN FOR HIM WHEN HE WAS
RUNNING FOR GOVERNOR.
WE CAN TALK ALL WE WANT ABOUT
WANTING TO BUILD A STRONGER
DEMOCRATIC PARTY, BUT LESTER,
THE QUESTION YOU ANSWERED, IT'S
NO LAUGHING MATTER.
THE MOST RECURRING QUESTION I
GET WHEN I STAND ON THE CHAIR
ALL ACROSS IOWA AND TALK WITH MY
NEIGHBORS IS, HOW ARE YOU GOING
TO HEAL THE DIVISIONS AND THE
WOUNDS IN OUR COUNTRY?
THIS IS THE BIGGEST CHALLENGE WE
FACE AS A PEOPLE.
ALL MY LIFE, I BROUGHT PEOPLE
TOGETHER OVER DEEP DIVIDES AND
VERY OLD WOUNDS, AND THAT'S WHAT
WE NEED NOW IN A NEW LEADER.
WE CANNOT KEEP TALKING PAST EACH
OTHER DECLARING ALL REPUBLICANS
ARE OUR ENEMIES OR THE WAR IS
ALL ABOUT BEING AGAINST
MILLIONAIRES OR BILLIONAIRES
IT'S ALL AGAINST AMERICAN
MUSLIMS, IT IS FRED LICK DOUGLAS
SAID.
WE ARE ONE, OUR CAUSE IS ONE,
AND WE MUST HELP EACH OTHER.
>> AND THAT IS RIGHT.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, NEXT
QUESTION AFTER YOU --
>> AND I RESPECTFULLY DISAGREE
WITH MY FRIEND OVER HERE.
AND THAT IS, YOU ARE RIGHT.
ALL OF US HAVE DENOUNCED TRUMP
ATTEMPTS TO DIVIDE THIS COUNTRY,
THE ANTI-LATINO RHETORIC, THE
RACIST RHETORIC, BUT WHERE I
DISAGREE WITH YOU, GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY, IS I DO BELIEVE WE
HAVE TO DEAL WITH THE
FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES OF A HANDFUL
OF BILLIONAIRES --
>> I AGREE WITH THAT.
>> WHO CONTROL ECONOMIC AND
POLITICAL LIFE OF THIS COUNTRY.
>> I AGREE.
>> NOTHING REAL WILL GET
HAPPENED.
UNLESS WE HAVE A POLITICAL
REVOLUTION.
WHERE MILLIONS OF PEOPLE FINALLY
STAND UP.
>> AND WE'RE GOING TO GET INTO
THAT COMING UP.
SECRETARY CLINTON, HERE'S A
QUESTION FROM YOUTUBE.
IT'S FROM A YOUNG VIDEO BLOGGER
WHO HAS OVER 5 MILLION
SUBSCRIBERS.
HE HAS A QUESTION ABOUT
IMPORTANCE OF YOUNGER VOTERS.
>> HI, I'M 23 AND MY AUDIENCE IS
AROUND THE SAME AGE.
GETTING MY GENERATION TO VOTE
SHOULD BE A PRIORITY FOR ANY
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.
NOW I KNOW SENATOR SANDERS IS
PRETTY POPULAR AMONG MY PEERS,
BUT WHAT I WANT TO KNOW IS HOW
ARE ALL OF YOU PLANNING ON
ENGAGING US FURTHER IN THIS
ELECTION?
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> WELL, THANKS FOR THE QUESTION
AND CONGRATULATIONS ON FIVE
MILLION VIEWERS ON YOUTUBE.
THAT'S QUITE AN ACCOMPLISHMENT.
LOOK, THIS ELECTION IS MOSTLY
ABOUT THE FUTURE AND THEREFORE
IT IS OF GREATEST URGENCY FOR
YOUNG PEOPLE.
I'VE LAID OUT MY IDEAS ABOUT
WHAT WE CAN DO TO MAKE COLLEGE
AFFORDABLE, HOW WE CAN HELP
PEOPLE PAY OFF THEIR STUDENT
DEBTS AND SAVE THOUSANDS OF
DOLLARS, HOW WE CAN CREATE MORE
GOOD JOBS, BECAUSE A LOT OF THE
YOUNG PEOPLE THAT I TALK WITH
ARE PRETTY DISAPPOINTED ABOUT
THE ECONOMIC PROSPECTS THEY FEEL
THEY'RE FACING.
MAKING COMMUNITY COLLEGE FREE.
MAKING IT POSSIBLE TO ATTEND A
PUBLIC COLLEGE OR UNIVERSITY
WITH DEBT-FREE TUITION.
LOOKING FOR WAYS TO PROTECT OUR
RIGHTS.
ESPECIALLY FROM THE CONCERTED
REPUBLICAN ASSAULT ON VOTING
RIGHTS, ON WOMEN'S RIGHTS, ON
GAY RIGHTS, ON CIVIL RIGHTS, ON
WORKER'S RIGHTS.
AND I KNOW HOW MUCH YOUNG PEOPLE
VALUE THEIR INDEPENDENCE, THEIR
AUTONOMY AND THEIR RIGHTS.
I THINK THIS IS AN ELECTION
WHERE WE HAVE TO PULL YOUNG
PEOPLE, AND OLDER PEOPLE
TOGETHER, TO HAVE A STRATEGY
ABOUT HOW WE'RE GOING TO
ENCOURAGE EVEN MORE AMERICANS TO
VOTE, BECAUSE IT IS ABSOLUTELY
CLEAR TO ME --
>> THAT'S TIME, BUT SECRETARY
CLINTON --
>> TO THE REPUBLICANS WOULD BE
BAD FOR EVERYBODY, ESPECIALLY
YOUNG PEOPLE.
>> QUICK FOLLOW-UP, 30 SECOND
FOLLOW-UP, WHY IS SENATOR
SANDERS BEATING YOU 2-1 AMONG
YOUNGER VOTERS?
>> I HAVE THE GREATEST RESPECT
FOR SENATOR SANDERS AND FOR HIS
SUPPORTERS, AND I'M GOING TO
KEEP WORKING AS HARD AS I CAN TO
REACH AS MANY PEOPLE OF ALL AGES
ABOUT WHAT I WILL DO.
WHAT THE EXPERIENCE AND THE
IDEAS THAT I HAVE THAT I WILL
BRING TO THE WHITE HOUSE, AND I
HOPE TO HAVE THEIR SUPPORT WHEN
I'M THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A BREAK.
BIG BANKS, BIG BUSINESS, AND BIG
DIFFERENCES AMONG THE CANDIDATES
ON THE AMERICAN ECONOMY.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> WELCOME BACK FROM
CHARLESTON, LET'S TURN NOW TO
THE ECONOMY.
SENATOR SANDERS, YOU RELEASED A
TOUGH NEW AD LAST WEEK IN WHICH
WITHOUT MENTIONING SECRETARY
CLINTON BY NAME, YOU TALK ABOUT
TWO DEMOCRATIC VISIONS FOR
REGULATING WALL STREET.
QUOTE, ONE SAYS IT'S OKAY TO
TAKE MILLIONS FROM BIG BANKS AND
TELL THEM WHAT TO DO.
MY PLAN, BREAK UP THE BIG BANKS,
CLOSE THE TAX LOOPHOLES AND MAKE
THEM PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE.
WHAT DO YOU SEE IS THE
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN WHAT YOU
WOULD DO AND WHAT SECRETARY
CLINTON WOULD DO?
>> WELL, THE FIRST DIFFERENCE IS
I DON'T TAKE MONEY FROM BIG
BANKS.
I DON'T GET PERSONAL SPEAKING
FEES FROM GOLDMAN SACHS.
WHAT I WOULD DO --
[ APPLAUSE ]
WHAT I WOULD DO IS UNDERSTAND
THAT WHEN YOU HAVE THREE OUT OF
THE FOUR LARGEST BANKS TODAY,
BIGGER THAN THEY WERE WHEN WE
BAILED THEM OUT BECAUSE THEY
WERE TOO BIG TO FAIL, WHEN YOU
HAVE THE SIX LARGEST FINANCIAL
INSTITUTIONS HAVING ASSETS OF #
0% OF THE -- 60% OF THE GDP OF
AMERICA.
WHICH IS CLEAR WHAT YOU HAVE TO
DO.
BRING BACK THE 21st CENTURY
GLASS EAGLE LEGISLATION AND
BREAK UP THESE HUGE FINANCIAL
INSTITUTIONS.
THEY HAVE TOO MUCH ECONOMIC
POWER AND THEY HAVE TOO MUCH
FINANCIAL POWER OVER OUR ENTIRE
ECONOMY.
IF TEDDY ROOSEVELT WERE ALIVE
TODAY, THE OLD REPUBLICAN TRUST
BUSTER, WHAT HE WOULD SAY IS,
ANESTHESIA GUYS ARE TOO
POWERFUL.
BREAK THEM UP, I BELIEVE THAT'S
WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE TO WANT
SEE.
THAT'S MY VIEW.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, HELP THE
VOTER UNDERSTAND THE DAYLIGHT
BETWEEN THE TWO OF YOU HERE.
>> THERE'S NO DAYLIGHT ON THE
BASIC PREMISE THAT THERE SHOULD
BE NO BANK TOO BIG TO FAIL, AND
NO INDIVIDUAL TOO POWERFUL TO
JAIL.
WE AGREE ON THAT.
BUT WHERE WE DISAGREE IS THE
COMMENTS THAT SENATOR SANDERS
HAS MADE THAT DON'T JUST AFFECT
ME, I CAN TAKE THAT, BUT HE'S
CRITICIZED PRESIDENT OBAMA FOR
TAKING DONATIONS FROM WALL
STREET.
AND PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS LED OUR
COUNTRY OUT OF THE GREAT
RECESSION.
SENATOR SANDERS CALLED HIM WEAK,
DISAPPOINTING, HE IAN IN 2011
PUBLICLY SOUGHT SOMEONE TO RUN
IN A PRIMARY AGAINST PRESIDENT
OBAMA.
NOW, I PERSONALLY BELIEVE THAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S WORK TO PUSH
THROUGH THE DODD FRANK, THE DODD
FRANK BILL AND THEN TO SIGN IT
WAS ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT
REGULATORY SCHEMES WE'VE HAD
SINCE THE 1930s.
SO I'M GOING TO DEFEND DODD
FRANK, AND I'M GOING TO DEFEND
PRESIDENT OBAMA FOR TAKING ON
WALL STREET, TAKING ON THE
FINANCIAL INDUSTRY, AND GETTING
RESULTS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOUR
RESPONSE.
>> LET THE RECORD RIGHT, IN 2006
WHEN I RAN FOR THE SENATE,
SENATOR BARACK OBAMA WAS KIND
ENOUGH TO CAMPAIGN FOR ME.
2008, I DID MY BEST TO SEE THAT
HE WAS ELECTED, AND IN 2012, I
WORKED AS HARD AS I COULD GO SEE
THAT HE WAS REELECTED.
HE AND I ARE FRIENDS, WE'VE
WORKED TOGETHER, WE HAVE
DIFFERENCES OF OPINION.
BUT HERE IS THE ISSUE, SECRETARY
TOUCHED ON IT, CAN YOU REALLY
REFORM WALL STREET?
WHEN THEY ARE SPENDING MILLIONS
AND MILLIONS OF DOLLARS ON
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS.
AND WHEN THEY ARE PROVIDING
SPEAKER FEES TO INDIVIDUALS.
SOP IT'S EASY TO SAY, WELL I'M
GOING TO DO THIS AND DO THAT,
BUT I HAVE DOUBTS WHEN PEOPLE
RECEIVE HUGE AMOUNTS OF MONEY
FROM WALL STREET.
I AM VERY PROUD, I DO NOT HAVE A
SUPERPACK.
I DO NOT WANT WALL STREET'S
MONEY.
I'LL RELY ON THE MIDDLE CLASS
AND WORKING FAMILY --
>> THAT'S TIME.
>> I HAVE A QUESTION FOR YOU --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU KNOW, I THINK SINCE,
SINCE SENATOR STANDERS FOLLOWED
UP ON THIS RESPONSE.
YOUR PROFUSION OF COMMENTS ABOUT
YOUR FEELINGS TOWARDS PRESIDENT
OBAMA ARE A LITTLE STRANGE GIVEN
WHAT YOU SAID ABOUT HIM IN 2011.
BUT LOOK, I HAVE A PLAN THAT
MOST COMMENTATORS HAVE SAID IS
TOUGHER, MORE EFFECTIVE WHEREBY
AND MORE COMPREHENSIVE.
>> THAT'S NOT TRUE.
>> IT BUILDS ON THE DODD
FRANK --
>> YES, IT IS.
>> IT BUILDS ON THE DODD FRANK,
REGULATORY SCHEME, BUT IT GOES
MUCH FURTHER --
>> OH, COME ON.
>> ABUSE BOTH THE GOVERNOR AND
THE SENATOR HAVE FOCUSSED ONLY
ON THE BIG BANKst.
LEHMAN BROTHERS, AIG, THE SHADOW
BANKING SECTOR WERE AS BIG A
PROBLEM OF THE GREAT RECESSION,
I GO AFTER THEM AND I CAN TELL
YOU THAT THE HEDGE FUND
BILLIONAIRES WHO ARE RUNNING ADS
AGAINST ME RIGHT NOW, AND CARL
ROVE WHO STARTED RUNNING AN AD
AGAINST ME RIGHT NOW, FUNDED BY
MONEY FROM THE FINANCIAL
SERVICES SECTOR, SURE THING, I'M
THE ONE THEY DON'T WANT --
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> YEAH, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YEAH, LESTER, WHAT SECRETARY
CLINTON JUST SAID IS ACTUALLY
NOT TRUE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I HAVE PUT FORWARD A PLAN THAT
WOULD ACTUALLY PUT COPS BACK ON
THE BEAT OF WALL STREET.
I HAVE PUT FORWARD A PLAN THAT
WAS HAROLDED AS VERY
COMPREHENSIVE AND REALISTIC.
LOOK, IF A BANK ROBBER ROBS A
BANK AND ALL YOU DO IS SLAP HIM
ON THE WRIST, HE'S GOING TO ROB
AGAIN.
THE SAME THING IS TRUE WITH
PEOPLE IN SUITS.
SECRETARY CLINTON, I HAVE A
TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF RESPECT FOR
YOU, BUT FOR YOU TO SAY THERE'S
NO DAYLIGHT ON THIS BETWEEN THE
THREE OF US IS NOT TRUE.
I SUPPORT REINSTITUTING A MODERN
VERSION OF GLASS STEEL THAT
WOULD INCLUDE GOING AFTER THE
SHADOW BANKS, REQUIRING CAPITAL
REQUIREMENTS THAT WOULD FORCE
THEM TO NO LONGER PUT US ON THE
HOOK FOR THESE SORTS OF THINGS,
AND PRIOR DEBATES I'VE HEARD YOU
EVEN BRING UP, NOW YOU BRING UP
PRESIDENT OBAMA HERE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA IN DEFENSE OF THE FACT
OF YOUR COZY RELATIONSHIP WITH
WALL STREET.
IN AN EARLIER DEBATE, I HEARD
YOU BRING UP EVEN THE 9/11
VICTIMS TO DEFEND IT.
THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS,
SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU DO NOT GO
AS FAR AS RANGING IN WALL STREET
AS I WOULD.
AND THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS,
THE PEOPLE OF AMERICA DESERVE TO
HAVE A PRESIDENT THAT'S ON THEIR
SIDE, PROTECTING THE MAINSTREAM
ECONOMY FROM EXCESSES ON WALL
STREET AND --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, 30 SECOND
RESPONSE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, FIRST OF
ALL, PAUL, BARNEY FRANK, OTHERS
HAVE ALL ENDORSED MY PLAN.
SECONDLY, WE HAVE DODD FRANK.
IT GIVES US THE AUTHORITY
ALREADY TO BREAK UP BIG BANKS
THAT POSE --
>> WE NEVER USED IT.
>> THAT POSE A RISK TO THE
FINANCIAL SECTOR.
I WANT TO GO FURTHER AND ADD TO
THAT, AND YOU KNOW, GOVERNOR,
YOU HAVE RAISED MONEY ON WALL
STREET.
YOU RAISED A LOT OF MONEY ON
WALL STREET WHEN YOU WERE THE
HEAD OF THE DEMOCRATIC
GOVERNOR'S ASSOCIATION --
>> YEAH, BUT I HAVEN'T GOTTEN A
PENNY THIS YEAR, SOMEBODY
PLEASE, GO ON TO
MARTINO'MALLEY.COM, GO ON, SEND
ME YOUR CHECKS.
THEY'RE NOT GIVING ME -- ZERO.
>> YEAH, WELL, THE POINT IS THAT
IF WE'RE GOING TO BE SERIOUS
ABOUT THIS AND NOT JUST TRY TO
SCORE POLITICAL POINTS, WE
SHOULD KNOW WHAT'S IN DODD
FRANK, AND WHAT'S IN DODD FRANK
ALREADY GIVES THE PRESIDENT THE
AUTHORITY TO REGULATORS OR IT
MAKE DECISIONS.
>> LET ME GIVE YOU AN IDEA OF
HOW CORRUPT THIS SYSTEM IS.
GOLDMAN SACHS RECENTLY FINED $5
BILLION.
GOLDMAN SACHS HAS GIVEN THIS
COUNTRY TWO SECRETARIES OF
TREASURY, ONE ON THE
REPUBLICANS, ONE UNDER
DEMOCRATS.
>> SAY IT.
>> THE LEADER OF GOLDMAN SACHS
IS A BILLIONAIRE WHO COMES TO
CONGRESS AND TELLS US WE SHOULD
CUT SOCIAL SECURITY, MEDICARE,
AND MEDICAID.
SECRETARY CLINTON, AND YOU'RE
NOT THE ONLY ONE.
I DON'T MEAN TO JUST POINT THE
FINGER AT YOU, YOU'VE RECEIVED
OVER $600,000 IN SPEAKING FEES
FROM GOLDMAN SACHS IN ONE YEAR.
I FIND IT VERY STRANGE THAT A
MAJOR FINANCIAL INSTITUTION THAT
PAYS $5 BILLION IN FINES FOR
BREAKING THE LAW, NOT ONE OF
THEIR EXECUTIVES IS PROSECUTED,
WHILE KIDS WHO SMOKE MARIJUANA
GET A JAIL TIME.
>> ANDREA.
>> WELL, THE LAST POINT ON THIS
IS, SENATOR SANDERS, YOU'RE THE
ONLY ONE ON THIS STAGE THAT
VOTED TO DEREGULATE THE
FINANCIAL MARKET IN 2000, TO
TAKE THE COPS OFF THE STREET TO
USE GOVERNOR O'MALLEY'S PHRASE,
TO MAKE THE FCC AND THE
COMMODITIES FUTURE'S TRADING
COMMISSION NO LONGER ABLE TO
REGULATE SWAPS AND DERIVATIVES
WHICH WERE ONE OF THE MAIN CAUSE
OF THE COLLAPSE IN '08.
SO THERE'S PLENTY, THERE'S
PLENTY OF PROBLEMS THAT WE ALL
HAVE TO FACE TOGETHER, AND THE
FINAL THING I WOULD SAY.
WE'RE AT LEAST HAVING A VIGOROUS
DEBATE ABOUT REIGNING IN WALL
STREET.
THE REPUBLICANS WANT TO GIVE
THEM MORE POWER AND REPEAL DODD
FRANK.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO STOP.
>> EVERYONE WHO WANTS TO CHECK
MY RECORD -- ANYONE WHO WANTS TO
CHECK MY RECORD AND TAKING ON
WALL STREET AND FIGHTING AGAINST
THE DEREGULATION OF WALL STREET
AND WALL STREET PUT BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS INTO LOBBYING AND
CONTRIBUTION TO TO GET THE
GOVERNMENT OFF THEIR BACKS.
THEY GOT THE GOVERNMENT OFF
THEIR BACKS TURNS OUT THEY WERE
CROOKS AND THEY DESTROYED OUR
ECONOMY.
I THINK IT'S TIME TO PUT THE
GOVERNMENT BACK ON THEIR BACKS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
SENATOR SANDERS, WE'VE TALKED A
LOT ABOUT THINGS YOU WANT TO DO.
YOU WANT FREE EDUCATION FOR
EVERYONE, YOU WANT THE FEDERAL
MINIMUM WAGE RAISED TO $15 AN
HOUR, YOU WANT TO EXPAND SOCIAL
SECURITY BENEFITS, YOU'VE BEEN
SPECIFIC ABOUT WHAT YOU WANT,
LET'S TALK ABOUT HOW TO PAY FOR
ALL OF THIS.
YOU'VE NOW SAID THAT YOU WOULD
RAISE TAXES TODAY, TWO HOURS OR
SO AGO, YOU SAID YOU WOULD RAISE
TAXES TO PAY FOR YOUR HEALTH
CARE PLAN.
YOU HAVEN'T BEEN SPECIFIC ABOUT
HOW TO PAY FOR THE OTHER THINGS.
TELL US TONIGHT.
>> SURE.
YOU'RE RIGHT.
I WANT TO REBUILD OUR CRUMBLING
INFRASTRUCTURE, CREATE 13
MILLION JOBS.
WE DO THAT BY DOING AWAY WITH
THE ABSURD LOOPHOLE THAT NOW
ALLOWS MAJOR PROFITABLE
CORPORATIONS TO FLASH THEIR
MONEY IN THE KAYMAN ISLANDS AND
NOT IN SOME YEARS PAY A NICKEL
IN TAXES.
YES, I DO.
I PLEAD GUILTY.
I WANT EVERY KID IN THIS COUNTRY
WHO HAS THE ABILITY TO BE ABLE
TO GO TO A PUBLIC COLLEGE OR
UNIVERSITY TUITION-FREE, AND BY
THE WAY, I WANT A SUBSTANTIALLY
LOWER STUDENT DEBT INTEREST
RATES IN THIS COUNTRY AS WELL.
HOW DO I PAY FOR IT?
[ APPLAUSE ]
I PAY FOR IT FOR ATTACKS ON WALL
STREET SPECULATION.
THIS COUNTRY AND THE MIDDLE
CLASS BAILED OUT WALL STREET,
NOW IT IS WALL STREET'S TIME TO
HELM THE MIDDLE CLASS.
IN FACT, WE HAVE DOCUMENTED,
UNLIKE SECRETARY CLINTON, I HAVE
DWOMTD KPABTLY HOW I WOULD PAY
FOR OUR AMBITIOUS AGENDA --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, DO YOU
WANT TO RESPOND?
>> WELL, I HAVE ACTUALLY
DOCUMENTED EVERY WAY THAT I'M
GOING TO PAY FOR WHAT I'M DOING.
BECAUSE I THINK THE AMERICAN
PUBLIC DESERVES TO KNOW.
AND YOU CAN GO TO MY WEBSITE AND
ACTUALLY SEE THAT.
BUT THERE ARE SERIOUS QUESTIONS
ABOUT HOW WE'RE GOING TO PAY FOR
WHAT WE WANT TO SEE OUR COUNTRY
DO.
AND I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE,
STANDING HERE TONIGHT WHO HAS
SAID, I WILL NOT RAISE TAXES ON
THE MIDDLE CLASS.
I WANT TO RAISE INCOMES, NOT
TAXES.
AND I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING I
CAN TO MAKE SURE THAT THE
WEALTHY PAY FOR DEBT-FREE
TUITION, FOR CHILD CARE, FOR
PAID FAMILY LEAVE TO HELP US
BRING DOWN STUDENT DEBT, WE'RE
GOING TO REFINANCE THAT STUDENT
DEBT, SAVING KIDS THOUSANDS OF
DOLLARS, YEAH, AND THAT WILL
ALSO COME OUT OF SOME OF THE
POCKETS OF PEOPLE IN THE
FINANCIAL AREA.
BUT I WILL TELL YOU EXACTLY HOW
I PAY FOR EVERYTHING I PROPOSE.
>> HERE IS THE MAJOR POINT --
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT TAXES.
>> YEAH.
>> BECAUSE THE MOST GOOGLE
POLITICAL ISSUE IN THE LAST
MONTH WAS TAXES.
NOW IN YOUR HEALTH CARE PLAN,
THE PLAN YOU RELEASED TONIGHT,
YOU WOULD NOT ONLY RAISE TAXES
ON THE WEALTHY, THE DETAILS
WOULD INDICATE YOU WOULD RAISE
TAKES ON THE MIDDLE CLASS ALSO.
IS THAT CORRECT?
>> WHAT IS CORRECT, AND I'M
DISAPPOINTED THAT SECRETARY
CLINTON'S CAMPAIGN HAS MADE THIS
CRITICISM.
IT'S A REPUBLICAN CRITICISM.
SECRETARY CLINTON DOES KNOW A
LOT ABOUT HEALTH CARE.
AND SHE UNDERSTANDS, I BELIEVE,
THAT A MEDICARE FOR ALL SINGLE
PAYER PROGRAM WOULD
SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER THE COST OF
HEALTH CARE FOR MIDDLE CLASS
FAMILIES SO WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO
ACKNOWLEDGE ABOUT THE SECRETARY
DOES IS WE ARE DOING AWAY WITH
PRIVATE HEALTH INSURANCE
PREMIUMS.
SO INSTEAD OF PAYING $10,000 TO
BLUE CROSS OR BLUE SHIELD, YES,
SOME MIDDLE CLASS FAMILIES WOULD
BE PAYING SLIGHTLY MORE IN
TAXES, BUT THE RESULT WOULD BE
THAT THAT MIDDLE CLASS FAMILY
WOULD BE SAVING SOME $5,000 IN
HEALTH CARE COSTS.
LITTLE BIT MORE IN TAXES, DO
AWAY WITH PRIVATE HEALTH
INSURANCE PREMIUMS, IT'S A GOOD
DEAL.
>> SENATOR, SENATOR, LET ME JUST
FOLLOW OCCUPY ON THAT.
ON MEET THE PRESS, YOU SALD YOU
WOULD ONLY RAISE TAXES ON THE
MIDDLE CLASS TO PAY FOR FAMILY
LEAVE.
AND HAVING SAID THAT, NOW YOU
SAY YOU'RE GOING TO RAISE MIDDLE
CLASS TAXES TO PAY FOR HEALTH
CARE AS WELL.
IS THAT BREAKING YOUR WORD?
>> NO, IT IS NOT BREAKING MY
WORD.
WHEN YOU ARE -- IT'S ONE THING
TO SAY I'M RAISING TAXES, IT'S
ANOTHER THING THAT WE ARE DOING
AWAY WITH PRIVATE HEALTH
INSURANCE PREMIUMS.
IF I SAVE YOU $10,000 IN PRIVATE
HEALTH INSURANCE, AND YOU PAY A
LITTLE BIT MORE IN TAXES IN
TOTAL, THERE ARE HUGE SAVINGS IN
WHAT YOUR FAMILY IS SPENDING.
>> SENATOR, I'M THE ONLY PERSON
ON THIS STAGE THAT'S ACTUALLY
BALANCED A BUDGET EVERY YEAR FOR
15 YEARS.
>> I WAS MAYOR FOR EIGHT YEARS,
I DID THAT FOR EIGHT YEARS AS
WELL.
>> THAT WAS EIGHT YEARS.
I ACTUALLY DID IT DURING A
BUDGET -- DURING A RECESSION.
AND ANDREA, I HAD TO MAKE MORE
CUTS THAN ANY GOVERNOR IN THE
HISTORY OF MARYLAND, WE INVESTED
MORE IN TRANSPORTATION, WE MADE
OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS MORE IN
AMERICA MORE THAN FIVE YEARS IN
A ROW AND FOUR YEARS IN A ROW
WITHOUT A PENNY'S INCREASE TO
COLLEGE TUITION.
THE THINGS WE NEED TO DO IN OUR
COUNTRY, LIKE DEBT-FREE COLLEGE
IN THE NEXT FIVE YEARS.
LIKE MAKING, MAKING NATIONAL
SERVICE A UNIVERSAL OPTION IN
ORDER TO CUT YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT
IN HALF IN FACT NEXT THREE
YEARS, ALL THESE THINGS CAN BE
DONE IF WE ELIMINATE ONE
ENTITLEMENT WE CAN NO LONGER
AFFORD AS A NATION.
AND THAT IS THE SUPERWEALTHY
AMONG US, THOSE MAKING MORE THAN
A MILLION DOLLARS FEEL THEY ARE
ENTITLED TO PAYING A LOWER
MARGINAL TAX RATE, AND IF WE TAX
EARNINGS FROM INVESTMENTS ON
MONEY, NAMELY CAPITAL GAINS AT
THE SAME RATE AS WE TAX SWEAT
AND HARD WORK, WE CAN MAKE THE
INVESTMENTS WE NEED TO MAKE OUR
COUNTRY BETTER.
>> WE HAVE A LOT TO GROUND TO
COVER HERE.
MANY DEMOCRATIC VOTERS ARE
PASSIONATE ABOUT THE NEED TO DO
SOMETHING TO COMBAT THE THREAT
OF CLIMATE CHANGE, INCLUDING THE
TEAM OF SCIENTISTS FROM
YOUTUBE'S MINUTE EARTH CHANNEL.
HERE'S THEIR TAKE.
>> HELLO FROM MINUTE EARTH.
FOSSIL FUELS KEPT OUR CARS
MOVING AND LIGHT BULBS LIT.
WE KNOW THAT BURNING THE FUELS
RELEASES HEAT-TRAPPING GASES
THAT ARE WARMING THE PLANET
CAUSING SEAS TO RISE AND
CONTRIBUTING TO THE DEVASTATING
FLOODING LAST YEAR.
FIGHTING HUMAN CAUSE CLIMATE
CHANGE MEANS GIVING UP THE
ADDICTION TO FOSSIL FUELS AND
TAKING THE BULK ENERGY SUPPLY TO
ALTERNATIVE SOURCES.
SOME COUNTRIES HAVE ACTED TO
MAKE THIS TRANSITION, HERE AT
HOME, WE GET A WHOOPING 82% FROM
COAL, OIL, AND NATURAL GAS.
IN THE U.S., POLITICAL GRIDLOCK,
PRESSURE FROM INDUSTRY LOBBYISTS
AND INSUFFICIENT RND MADE AN
ALREADY TOUGH BATTLE AGAINST
CLIMATE CHANGE EVEN TOUGHER.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, AMERICANS
LOVE THEIR SUVs, WHICH SPIKED IN
SALES LAST YEAR AS GAS PRICES
PLUMMETED.
HOW DO YOU CONVINCE AMERICANS
THAT THE PROBLEM OF CLIMATE
CHANGE IS SO URGENT THAT THEY
NEED TO CHANGE THEIR BEHAVIOR?
>> I THINK WE ALREADY ARE.
YOUNGER GENERATION UNDERSTANDS
IT INSTINCTIVELY.
I WAS HOME IN BURLINGTON,
VERMONT, ON CHRISTMAS EVE, THE
TEMPERATURE WAS 65 DEGREES.
PEOPLE IN VERMONT KNOW WHAT'S
GOING ON.
PEOPLE WHO DID ICE FISHING WHERE
THEIR ICE IS NO LONGER THERE ON
THE LAKE UNDERSTAND WHAT'S GOING
ON.
I'M ON BOTH THE ENVIRONMENTAL
AND THE ENERGY COMMITTEES.
THE DEBATE IS OVER.
CLAIMANT CHANGE IS REAL.
IT IS ALREADY CAUSING MAJOR
PROBLEMS.
AND IF WE DO NOT ACT BOLDLY AND
DECISIVELY, A BAD SITUATION WILL
BECOME WORSE.
IT IS AMAZING TO ME, AND I THINK
WE'LL HAVE AGREEMENT ON THIS UP
HERE, THAT WE HAVE A MAJOR PARTY
CALLED THE REPUBLICAN PARTY THAT
IS SO OWNED BY THE FOSSIL FUEL
INDUSTRY, AND THEIR CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS THAT THEY DON'T
EVEN HAVE THE COURAGE, THE
DECENCY TO LISTEN TO THE
SCIENTISTS.
IT IS BEYOND MY COMPREHENSION
HOW WE CAN ELECT A PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES, SOMEBODY LIKE
TRUMP WHO BELIEVES THAT CLIMATE
CHANGE IS A HOAX, INVENTED BY
THE CHINESE.
[ LAUGHTER ]
BOTTOM LINE IS WE NEED TO BE
BOLD, DECISIVE, CREATE MILLIONS
OF JOBS.
WE MUST FOR THE SAKE OF OUR KIDS
AND GRANDCHILDREN, TRANSFORM OUR
ENERGY SYSTEM AWAY FROM FOSSIL
FUEL TO ENERGY EFFICIENCY.
AND SUSTAINABLE ENERGY, I'VE GOT
THE MOST COMPREHENSIVE
LEGISLATION IN THE SENATE TO DO
THAT.
AND AS PRESIDENT,LY FIGHT TO
MAKE THAT HAPPEN.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, 30
SECONDS.
>> THANK YOU.
LESTER, ON THIS STAGE TONIGHT,
THIS DEMOCRATIC STAGE, WHERE WE
ACTUALLY BELIEVE IN SCIENCE, I
WOULD LIKE TO CHALLENGE, AND
INVITE MY COLLEAGUES HERE ON
THIS STAGE TO JOIN ME IN PUTTING
FORWARD A PLAN TO MOVE US TO A
100% CLEAN, ELECTRIC ENERGY GRID
BY 2050.
IT CAN BE DONE.
WITH SOLAR, WITH WIND, WITH NEW
TECHNOLOGIES, WITH GREEN
BUILDINGS.
THIS CAN HAPPEN, BUT PRESIDENT
OBAMA MADE US MORE ENERGY
INDEPENDENT, BUT IN ALL OF THE
ABOVE STRATEGY DIDN'T LAND US ON
THE MOON, WE NEED AMERICAN
INGENUITY AND WE NEED TO REACH
BY 2050 FOR THE SAKE OF OUR
KIDS.
>> THAT'S TIME.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A BREAK.
WHEN WE RETURN, THE
LATE-BREAKING DEVELOPMENTS
REGARDING IRAN.
THE THREAT OF ISIS NOW MORE REAL
THAN EVER ON U.S. SOIL,
AMERICANS IN FEAR, AND HEARING
FEW GOOD ANSWERS.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> IS ONE OF THE TOP CONCERNS
OF MEMPBS WITH, AND ALSO MORE
LATE-BREAKING NEWS.
>> YEAH, ALL THE NEWS THAT'S
HAPPENED FROM IRAN AND THE
PRESIDENT'S COMMENTS TODAY, AS
WELL AS WHAT THIS MEANS GOING
FORWARD FOR THE WAR ON TERROR.
WHAT DO WE EXPECT FROM IRAN AND
ALSO WHAT'S HAPPENING IN SYRIA?
A LOT OF FOREIGN POLICY COMING
UP.
>> THERE'S A LOT OF DEBATE TO
COME.
WE'LL BE BACK IN CHARLESTON
AFTER THIS.
>> YOU GOT IT.
WELL IT'S THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF
TEST.
THAT'S WHAT'S NEXT.
STAY WITH US, THE DE
>>> CHARLESTON, ANDREA MITCHELL
HAS QUESTIONS NOW FOR THE
CANDIDATES STARTING WITH IRAN.
>> THANK YOU, LESTER.
SENATOR SANDERS, NUCLEAR DEAL IS
NOW ENFORCED IRAN IS GETTING
IT'S BILLIONS OF DOLLARS,
SEVERAL AMERICANS WHO HAVE BEEN
HELD ARE NOW GOING TO BE HEADING
HOME.
THE PRESIDENT SAID TODAY, IT'S A
GOOD DAY.
A GOOD DAY FOR DIPLOMACY, IT'S A
TIME NOW TO RESTORE DIPLOMATIC
RELATIONS SINCE 1979 AND REOPEN
A U.S. EMBASSY IN TEHERAN.
>> I THINK WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO
DO IS MOVE AS AGGRESSIVELY AS WE
CAN TO NORMALIZE RELATIONS WITH
IRAN, UNDERSTANDING, THAT IRAN'S
BEHAVIOR IN SO MANY WAYS IS
SOMETHING THAT WE DISAGREE WITH.
THEIR SUPPORT FOR TERRORISM, THE
ANTI-AMERICAN RHETORIC WE'RE
HEARING FROM SOME OF THEIR
LEADERSHIP IS SOMETHING THAT IS
NOT ACCEPTABLE.
ON THE OTHER HAND, THE FACT THAT
WE'VE MANAGED TO REACH AND
AGREEMENT, SOMETHING THAT I VERY
STRONGLY SUPPORTED THAT PREVENTS
IRAN FROM GETTING A NUCLEAR
WEAPON AND THAT WE DID THAT
WITHOUT GOING TO WAR, AND THAT I
BELIEVE WE'RE SEEING A THOR IN
OUR RELATIONSHIPS WITH IRAN IS A
VERY POSITIVE STEP.
SO IF YOUR QUESTION IS DO I WANT
TO SEE THAT RELATIONSHIP BECOME
MORE POSITIVE IN THE FUTURE?
YES.
COULD I TELL YOU THAT WE SHOULD
OPEN AND EMBASSY IN TEHERAN
TOMORROW, NO, I DON'T THINK WE
SHOULD.
I THINK THE GOAL HAS TO BE, TO
MOVE IN WARM RELATIONS WITH A
VERY POWERFUL AND IMPORTANT
COUNTRY IN THIS WORLD.
>> YOUR RESPONSE, SECRETARY
CLINTON.
>> WELL, I'M VERY PROUD OF THE
IRAN NUCLEAR AGREEMENT.
I WAS VERY PLEASED TO BE PART OF
WHAT THE PRESIDENT PUT INTO
ACTION WHEN HE TOOK OFFICE.
I WAS RESPONSIBLE FOR GETTING
THOSE SANCTIONS IMPOSED, WHICH
PUT THE PRESSURE ON IRAN THAT
BROUGHT THEM TO THE NEGOTIATING
TABLE, WHICH RESULTED IN THIS
AGREEMENT.
AND SO, THEY HAVE BEEN, SO FAR,
FOLLOWING THEIR REQUIREMENTS
UNDER THE AGREEMENT, BUT I THINK
WE STILL HAVE TO CAREFULLY WATCH
THEM.
WE'VE HAD ONE GOOD DAY OVER 36
YEARS, AND I THINK WE NEED MORE
GOOD DAYS BEFORE WE MOVE MORE
RAPIDLY TOWARD ANY KIND OF
NORMALIZATION, AND WE HAVE TO BE
SURE THAT THEY ARE TRULY GOING
TO IMPLEMENT THE AGREEMENT, AND
THEN WE HAVE TO GO AFTER THEM ON
A LOT OF THEIR OTHER BAD
BEHAVIOR IN THE REGION, WHICH IS
CAUSING ENORMOUS PROBLEMS IN
SYRIA, YEMEN, IRAQ, AND
ELSEWHERE.
>> YOU MENTIONED SYRIA, LET ME
ASK YOU ABOUT SYRIA, ALL OF YOU,
LET'S TURN TO SYRIA, THE CIVIL
WAR THAT'S BEEN RAGING THERE.
ARE THERE ANY CIRCUMSTANCES IN
WHICH YOU COULD SEE DEPLOYING
SIGNIFICANT NUMBERS OF GROUND
FORCES IN SYRIA, NOT JUST
SPECIAL OPERATORS, BUT
SIGNIFICANT GROUND FORCES TO
COMBAT ISIS IN A DIRECT COMBAT
ROLE.
LET ME START WITH YOU SECRETARY
CLINTON.
>> ABSOLUTELY NOT.
AFTER I THREE-POINT PLAN THAT
DOES NOT INCLUDE AMERICAN GROUND
FORCES.
IT INCLUDES THE UNITED STATES
LEADING AN AIR COALITION, WHICH
IS WHAT WE ARE DOING, SUPPORTING
FIGHTERS ON THE GROUND, THE
IRAQI ARMY, WHICH IS BEGINNING
TO SHOW MORE ABILITY, THE SUNNI
FIGHTERS THAT WE ARE NOW HELPING
TO RECONSTITUTE AND KURDISH
FIGHTERS ON BOTH SIDES OF THE
BORDER.
I THINK WE ALSO HAVE TO TRY TO
DISRUPT THEIR SUPPLY CHAIN OF
FOREIGN FIGHTERS AND FOREIGN
MONEY, AND WE DO HAVE TO CONTEST
THEM IN ONLINE SPACE.
I'M VERY COMMITTED TO BOTH GOING
AFTER ISIS, BUT ALSO SUPPORTING
WHAT SECRETARY KERRY IS DOING TO
TRY TO MOVE ON A POLITICAL,
DIPLOMATIC COURSE TO TRY TO
BEGIN TO SLOW DOWN AND HOPEFULLY
END THE CARNAGE IN SYRIA, WHICH
IS THE ROOT OF SO MANY OF THE
PROBLEMS THAT WE SEE IN THE
RENAL AND BEYOND.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
GROUND FORCES, YES OR NO?
>> AS EVERYBODY HERE KNOWS, THIS
IS AN INCREDIBLY COMPLICATED AND
DIFFICULT ISSUE.
AND I APPLAUD, I KNOW PRESIDENT
OBAMA'S BEEN GETTING A THE LOVE
CRITICISM ON THIS.
I THINK HE IS DOING THE RIGHT
THING.
WHAT THE NIGHTMARE IS, WHICH
MANY OF MY REPUBLICAN COLLEAGUES
APPEAR TO WANT IS TO NOT HAVE
LEARNED THE LESSON OF IRAQ.
TO GET AMERICAN YOUNG MEN AND
WOMEN INVOLVED IN PERPETUAL
WARFARE IN THE QUAGMIRE OF SYRIA
AND THE MIDDLE EAST WOULD BE AN
UNMITIGATED DISASTER THAT AS
PRESIDENTIALLY DO EVERYTHING IN
MY POWER TO AVOID.
>> ANDREA.
>> WE SHOULD LEARN, WE SHOULD
LEARN FROM KING ABDULLAH OF
JORDAN, ONE OF THE FEW HEROES IN
A VERY UNHEROIC PLACE.
AND WHAT ABDULLAH SAID IS THIS
IS A WAR WITH A SOUL OF ISLAM,
AND THAT MUSLIM TROOPS SHOULD BE
ON THE GROUND WITH OUR SUPPORT
AND THE SUPPORT OF OTHER MAJOR
COUNTRIES.
THAT IS HOW WE DESTROY ISIS, NOT
WITH AMERICAN TROOPS IN
PERPETUAL WARFARE.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> THANK YOU.
ANDREA, GOVERNORS LED USES TO
VICTORY IN TWO WORLD WARS BY
DOING WHAT AMERICA DOES BEST,
AND THAT IS BY JOINING FORCES
WITH OTHERS BY ACTING IN
COALITION.
AND I BELIEVE THAT PRESIDENT
OBAMA IS DOING THE RIGHT THING
IN THIS CASE.
WE NEED TO LEARN THE LESSONS
FROM THE PAST.
WE NEED TO PROVIDE THE SPECIAL,
SPECIAL OPS ADVISORS, WE NEED TO
PROVIDE THE TECHNICAL SUPPORT,
BUT OVER THE LONG-TERM, WE NEED
TO DEVELOP NEW ALLIANCES.
WE NEED A MUCH MORE PROACTIVE
NATIONAL SECURITY STRATEGY THAT
REDUCES THESE THREATS BEFORE
THEY RISE TO A LEVEL WHERE IT
FEELS LIKE WE NEED TO PULL FOR A
DIVISION OF MARINES.
AND I ALSO WANT TO ADD ONE OTHER
THING HERE, I APPRECIATE THE
FACT THAT IN OUR DEBATE, WE
DON'T USE THE TERM YOU HEAR
REPUBLICANS THROWING AROUND
TRYING TO LOOK ALL MACHO SENDING
OTHER KIDS INTO COMBAT, THEY
KEEP USING THE TERM, BOOTS ON
THE GROUND.
A WOMAN IN BURLINGTON, IOWA,
SAID TO ME, WHEN YOU'RE WITH
YOUR COLLEAGUES, DON'T REFER TO
MY SON WHO SERVED TWO TOURS OF
DUTY IN IRAQ AS A PAIR OF BOOTS
ON THE GROUND.
NOW, WE NEED TO BE MINDFUL OF
LEARNING THE LESSONS OF THE
PAST.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> I HAVE A QUESTION FOR SENATOR
SANDERS.
DID THE POLICIES OF THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION IN WHICH
SECRETARY CLINTON OF COURSE WITH
THE PART CREATE A VACUUM IN IRAQ
AND SYRIA THAT HELPS ISIS GROW?
>> NO.
I THINK THE VACUUM WAS CREATED
BY THE DISASTROUS WAR IN IRAQ,
WHICH I VIGOROUSLY OPPOSE, NOT
ONLY AGAINST IT, BUT HELPED LEAD
THE OPPOSITION.
AND WHAT HAPPENED THERE IS YEAH,
IT'S EASE EYEWITNESS TO GET RID
OF A TWO-BIT DICTATOR LIKE SUE
DAM HUSSEIN, BUT THERE WASN'T
THE KIND OF THOUGHT AS TO WHAT
HAPPENS THE DAY AFTER YOU GET
HIM AND WHAT KIND OF POLITICAL
VACUUM OCCURS, AND WHO RISES UP.
GROUPS LIKE ISIS.
SO I THINK THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA
MADE A PROMISE TO THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WHEN HE RAN.
AND HE SAID YOU KNOW WHAT, I'M
GOING TO DO MY BEST TO BRING
AMERICAN TROOPS HOME.
AND I SUPPORTED WHAT HE DID.
OUR JOB IS TO TRAIN AND PROVIDE
MILITARY SUPPORT FOR MUSLIM
COUNTRIES IN THE AREA WHO ARE
PREPARED TO TAKE ON ISIS.
AND ONE POINT I WANT TO MAKE
HERE THAT IS NOT MADE OFTEN, YOU
HAVE INCREDIBLY WEALTHY
COUNTRIES IN THAT REGION,
COUNTRIES LIKE SAUDI ARABIA,
COUNTRIES LIKE QATAR, THE
LARGEST, WEALTHIEST COUNTRY PER
CAPITA IN THE WORLD.
THEY HAVE GOT TO START PUTTING
IN SOME SKIN IN THE GAME, AND
NOT JUST ASK THE UNITED STATES
TO DO IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> I WANT TO TALK TO YOU ABOUT
RED LINES, BECAUSE FORMER
DEFENSE SECRETARY CHUCK HAGEL
SAID IN A RECENT INTERVIEW THAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S DECISION TO
STAND DOWN ON PLANNED MISSILE
STRIKES AGAINST DAMASCUS AFTER
ASSAD HAD USED CHEMICAL WEAPONS
HURT THE PRESIDENT'S
CREDIBILITY.
SHOULD THE PRESIDENT HAVE STUCK
TO HIS RED LINE ONCE HE DREW IT?
>> LOOK, I THINK THAT THE
PRESIDENT'S DECISION TO GO AFTER
THE CHEMICAL WEAPONS ONCE THERE
WAS A POTENTIAL OPPORTUNITY TO
BUILD ON WHEN THE RUSSIANS
OPENED THAT DOOR, RESULTED IN A
VERY POSITIVE OUTCOME.
WE WERE ABLE TO GET THE CHEMICAL
WEAPONS OUT.
I KNOW FROM MY OWN EXPERIENCE AS
SECRETARY OF STATE THAT WE WERE
DEEPLY WORRIED ABOUT ASSAD'S
FORCES USING CHEMICAL WEAPONS
BECAUSE IT WOULD HAVE HAD NOT
ONLY A HORRIFIC AFFECT ON PEOPLE
IN SYRIA, BUT IT COULD VERY WELL
HAVE AFFECTED THE SURROUNDING
STATES, JORDAN, ISRAEL, LEBANON,
TURKEY.
SO GETTING THOSE CHEMICAL
WEAPONS OUT WAS A BIG --
>> BUT SHOULD HE HAVE STUCK TO
HIS LINE?
DID IT HURT U.S. CREDIBILITY?
>> I THINK AS COMMANDER AND
CHIEF, YOU'VE GOT TO CONSTANTLY
BE EVALUATING THE DECISIONS YOU
HAVE TO MAKE.
I KNOW A LITTLE BIT ABOUT THIS,
HAVING SPENT MANY HOURS IN THE
SITUATION ROOM, ADVISING
PRESIDENT OBAMA.
AND I WANT TO JUST ADD TO
SOMETHING THAT SENATOR SANDERS
SAID, THE UNITED STATES HAD A
VERY BIG INTEREST IN TRYING TO
HELP STABILIZE THE REGION.
IF THERE IS ANY BLAME TO BE
SPREAD AROUND, IT STARTS WITH
THE PRIME MINISTER OF IRAQ WHO
SECTARIANIZED HIS MILITARY,
SETTING SHIA AGAINST SUNNI.
IT IS AMPLIFIED BY ASSAD WHO HAS
WAGED ONE OF THE BLOODIEST, MOST
TERRIBLE ATTACKS ON HIS OWN
PEOPLE.
250,000-PLUS DEAD, MILLIONS
FLEEING.
CAUSING THIS VACUUM THAT HAS
BEEN FILLED, UNFORTUNATELY, BY
TERRORIST GROUPS INCLUDING ISIS.
SO I THINK WE ARE IN THE MIDST
OF GREAT TURMOIL IN THIS REGION.
WE HAVE A PROXY CONFLICT GOING
ON BETWEEN SAUDI ARABIA AND
IRAN.
YOU KNOW, ONE OF THE CRITICISMS
I'VE HAD OF SENATOR SANDERS IS
HIS SUGGESTION THAT, YOU KNOW,
IRANIAN TROOPS BE USED TO TRY TO
END THE WAR IN SYRIA --
>> YOUR TIME IS UP.
>> LET ME JUST --
>> WHICH I DON'T THINK WOULD BE
A GOOD IDEA.
>> OVERALL, A LOT OF THE FORCES
AT WORK IN THE REGION ARE ONES
THAT WE CANNOT DIRECTLY
INFLUENCE, BUT WE CAN --
>> YOU'RE OUT OF TIME.
[ OVERLAPPING TALKERS ]
>> I AGREE WITH MOST OF WHAT SHE
SAID.
BUT WHERE I THINK WE HAVE AN
HONEST DISAGREEMENT, IS THAT IN
THE INCREDIBLE QUAGMIRE OF
SYRIA, WHERE IT'S HARD TO KNOW
WHO'S FIGHTING WHO, AND IF YOU
GIVE ARMS TO THIS GUY, IT MAY
END UP IN ISIS'S HAND THE NEXT
DAY.
WE ALL KNOW THE SECRETARY IS
ABSOLUTELY RIGHT, ASSAD IS A
BUTCHER OF HIS OWN PEOPLE, MAN
USING CHEMICAL WEAPONS AGAINST
HIS OWN PEOPLE.
THIS IS BEYOND DISGUSTING.
BUT I THINK IN TERMS OF OUR
PRIORITIES IN THE REGION, OUR
FIRST PRIORITY MUST BE THE
DESTRUCTION OF ISIS.
OUR SECOND PRIORITY MUST BE
GETTING RID OF ASSAD WHO SOME
POLITICAL SETTLEMENT, WORKING
WITH IRAN, WORKING WITH RUSSIA,
BUT THE IMMEDIATE TASK IS TO
BRING ALL INTERESTS TOGETHER WHO
WANT TO DESTROY ISIS, INCLUDING
RUSSIA, INCLUDING IRAN,
INCLUDING OUR MUSLIM ALLIES TO
MAKE THAT THE MAJOR PRIORITY.
>> BUT IN ALL OF THAT SENATOR
AND SECRETARY, I THINK WE'RE
LEAVING OUT SOMETHING VERY
IMPORTANT HERE.
AND THAT IS THAT WE STILL DON'T
HAVE THE HUMAN INTELLIGENCE,
OVERT IN TERMS OF DIPLOMATIC
INTELLIGENCE OR COVERT TO
UNDERSTAND EVEN WHAT THE HECK
HAPPENS AS THE SECONDARY AND
TERTIARY EFFECTS OF SOME OF
THESE THINGS.
WE ARE WALKING THROUGH THE
RENAL, ANDREA, WITHOUT THE HUMAN
INTELLIGENCE THAT WE NEED AND WE
NEED TO MAKE A RENEWED
INVESTMENT AS A COUNTRY IN
BRINGING UP A NEW GENERATION OF
FOREIGN SERVICE OFFICERS, AND
BUSINESS PEOPLE, AND ACTUALLY
UNDERSTANDING AND HAVING
RELATIONSHIPS IN THESE PLACES.
SO WE HAVE A BETTER SENSE OF
WHAT THE HECK HAPPENS AFTER A
DICTATOR TOP MS AND CAN TAKE
ACTION TO PREVENT ANOTHER SAFE
HAVEN AND ANOTHER IT RATION OF
TERROR.
>> YOUR TIME IS US.
LESTER.
>> SENATOR SANDERS MENTIONED
RUSSIA A MOMENT AGO.
SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU FAMOUSLY
HANDED RUSSIA'S FOREIGN MINISTER
A RESET BUTTON IN 2009.
SINCE THEN, RUSSIA AN EXED
CRIMEA, A WAR IN UKRAINE,
PROVIDED WEAPONS THAT DOWNED AN
AIRLINER AND SUPPORTED ASSAD IN
SYRIA.
AS PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU HAND
VLADIMIR PUTIN A RESET BUTTON?
>> IT WOULD DEPEND ON WHAT I GOT
FOR IT.
IT WOULD DEPEND THE FIRST TERM,
WE GOT A NEW START TREATY TO
REDUCE NUCLEAR WEAPONS BETWEEN
THE UNITED STATES AND RUSSIA.
WE GOT PERMISSION TO RESUPPLY
OUR TROOPS IN AFGHANISTAN BY
TRAVELING ACROSS RUSSIA.
WE GOT RUSSIA TO SIGN ON TO OUR
SANCTIONS AGAINST IRAN, AND
OTHER VERY IMPORTANT
COMMITMENTS.
SO LOOK, IN DIPLOMACY, YOU ARE
ALWAYS TRYING TO SEE HOW YOU CAN
FIGURE OUT THE INTEREST OF THE
OTHER TO SEE IF THERE ISN'T SOME
WAY YOU CAN ADVANCE YOUR
SECURITY AND YOUR VALUES.
WHEN PUTIN CAME BACK IN THE FALL
OF 2011, IT WAS VERY CLEAR HE
CAME BACK WITH A MISSION.
AND I BEGAN SPEAKING OUT AS SOON
AS THAT HAPPENED BECAUSE THERE
WERE SOME FRAUDULENT ELECTIONS
HELD, AND RUSSIANS POURED OUT
INTO THE STREETS TO DEMAND THEIR
FREEDOM, AND HE CRACKED DOWN.
AND IN FACT, ACCUSED ME OF
FOEMTING IT.
SO WE NOW KNOW THAT HE HAS A
MIXED RECORD TO SAY THE LEAST,
AND WE HAVE TO FIGURE OUT HOW TO
DEAL WITH HIM.
>> WHAT'S YOUR RELATIONSHIP WITH
HIM?
>> WELL MY RELATIONSHIP WITH
HIM, IT'S -- IT'S, IT'S
INTERESTING.
[ LAUGHTER ]
IT'S ONE I THINK OF RESPECT.
WE'VE HAD SOME VERY TOUGH
DEALINGS WITH ONE ANOTHER.
AND I KNOW THAT HE'S SOMEONE
THAT YOU HAVE TO CONTINUINGLY
STAND UP TO BECAUSE LIKE MANY
BULLIES, HE IS SOMEBODY WHO WILL
TAKE AS MUCH AS HE POSSIBLY CAN
UNLESS YOU DO.
AND WE NEED TO GET THE EUROPEANS
TO BE MORE WILLING TO STAND UP,
I WAS PLEASED THEY PUT SANCTIONS
ON AFTER CRIMEA AND EASTERN
UKRAINE AND THE DOWNING OF THE
AIRLINER, BUT WE GOT TO BE MORE
UNITED IN PREVENTING PUTIN FROM
TAKING A MORE AGGRESSIVE STANCE
IN EUROPE AND THE MIDDLE EAST.
>> WE TO WANT TURN RIGHT NOW TO
THE ISSUE OF BALANCING NATIONAL
SECURITY CONCERNS WITH THE
PRIVACY RIGHTS OF AMERICANS.
THAT BRINGS US TO YOUTUBE AND
THIS QUESTION.
>> HI, I'VE BEEN MAKING YOUTUBE
VIDEO'S ABOUT ELECTRONICS AND
GADGETS FOR THE PAST SEVEN
YEARS.
I THINK AMERICA'S FUTURE SUCCESS
IS TIED TO GETTING ALL KINDS OF
TECH RIGHT.
TECH COMPANIES ARE RESPONSIBLE
FOR THE ENCRYPTION TECHNOLOGY TO
PROTECT PERSONAL DATA, BUT THE
G. WANTS A BACK DOOR INTO THAT
INFORMATION.
SO DO YOU THINK IT'S POSSIBLE TO
FIND COMMON GROUND AND WHERE DO
YOU STAND ON PRIVACY VERSUS
SECURITY.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> THANK YOU.
I BELIEVE WHETHER IT'S A BACK
DOOR OR FRONT DOOR THAT THE
AMERICAN PRINCIPLE OF LAW SHOULD
STILL HOLD THAT OUR FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT SHOULD HAVE TO GET A
WARRANT.
WHETHER THEY WANT TO COME
THROUGH THE BACK DOOR OR YOUR
FRONT DOOR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I ALSO AGREE, LESTER, WITH
BENJAMIN FRANKLIN SAID THAT SAID
NO EL NINO SHOULD GIVE UP
FREEDOMS FOR SECURITY.
WE'RE A COLLABORATIVE PEOPLE.
WE NEED COLLABORATIVE LEADERSHIP
HERE WITH SILICON VALLEY AND
OTHER BRIGHT PEOPLE IN MY OWN
STATE OF MARYLAND AND AROUND NSA
THAT CAN FIGURE THIS OUT, BUT
THERE ARE CERTAIN IMMUTABLE
PRINCIPLES THAT WILL NOT BECOME
ANTIQUE THINGS IN OUR COUNTRY SO
LONG AS WE DEFEND OUR COUNTRY
AND IT'S VALUES AND IT'S
FREEDOMS.
AND ONE OF THOSE THINGS IS OUR
RIGHT TO BE SECURE IN OUR HOMES,
AND OUR RIGHT TO EXPECT THAT OUR
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SHOULD HAVE
TO GET A WARRANT.
I ALSO WANT TO THE SAY THAT
WHILE WE'VE MADE SOME PROGRESS
ON THE PATRIOTIC ACT, I DO
BELIEVE WE NEED AN ADVERSARIAL
COURT SYSTEM THERE, PUBLIC
ADVOCATE, DEVELOP A BODY OF LAW
THAT PROTECTS THE PRIVACY OF
AMERICANS IN THE INFORMATION AND
DIGITAL AGE.
>> THAT'S TIME.
YOU HAVE ALL TALKED ABOUT WHAT
YOU WOULD DO FIGHTING ISIS OVER
THERE, BUT WE'VE BEEN HIT IN
THIS COUNTRY BY HOME GROWN
TERRORISTS, FROM CHATTANOOGA TO
SAN BERNARDINO, THE RECENT
SHOOTING OF A POLICE OFFICER IN
PHILADELPHIA, HOW ARE YOU GOING
TO FIGHT THE LONE WOLVES HERE?
>> YEAH, LESTER, YOU'RE IN AND
YOU'RE OUT.
SENATOR --
>> THAT WAS TO SENATOR SANDERS.
I WASN'T CLEAR, I APOLOGIZE.
>> OKAY.
I JUST WANTED TO ADD IN THE
PREVIOUS QUESTION, I VOTED
AGAINST THE USA PATRIOT ACT FOR
MANY OF THE REASONS THAT
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY MENTIONED.
BUT IT IS NOT ONLY THE
GOVERNMENT THAT WE HAVE TO WORRY
ABOUT, IT IS PROOEFT
CORPORATIONS.
YOU WOULD ALL BE AMAZED OR MAYBE
NOT ABOUT THE AMOUNT OF
INFORMATION, PRIVATE COMPANIES
AND THE GOVERNMENT HAS IN TERMS
OF THE WEBSITES THAT YOU ACCESS,
THE PRODUCTS THAT YOU BUY, WHERE
YOU ARE THIS VERY MOMENT, AND IT
IS VERY CLEAR TO ME THAT PUBLIC
POLICY HAS NOT CAUGHT UP WITH
THE EXPLOSION OF TECHNOLOGY.
SO YES, WE HAVE TO WORK WITH
SILICON VALLEY TO MAKE SURE THAT
WE DO NOT ALLOW ISIS TO
TRANSMIT --
>> BUT IN TERMS OF LONE WOLVES,
THE THREAT --
>> WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO THERE
IS AMONG OTHER THINGS, AS I WAS
JUST SAYING, HAVE SILICON VALLEY
HELP US TO MAKE SURE THAT
INFORMATION TRANSMITTED THROUGH
THE INTERNET AND OTHER WAYS BY
ISIS IS IN FACT DISCOVERED, BUT
I DO BELIEVE WE CAN DO THAT
WITHOUT VIOLATING THE
CONSTITUTIONAL AND PRIVACY
RIGHTS OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
>> WE HAVE TO GO -- WE HAVE TO
GO TO A BREAK, AND WHEN WE COME
BACK, WE'RE GOING TO GET TO SOME
OF THE BURNING QUESTIONS THESE
CANDIDATES WANT TOP TALK ABOUT.
>>> AND WELCOME BACK TO
CHARLESTON AS WE WERE GOING TO A
BREAK, SECRETARY CLINTON, I CUT
YOU OFF.
I'LL GIVE YOU 30 SECONDS TO
RESPOND ON THE ISSUE OF LONE
WOLVES.
>> CAN I GET 30 SECONDS TOO?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> WELL, I WANTED TO SAY, AND
I'LL DO IT QUICKLY, I WAS VERY
PLEASED THAT LEADERS OF
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S ADMINISTRATION
WENT OUT TO SILICON VALLEY LAST
WEEK AND BEGAN EXACTLY THIS
CONVERSATION ABOUT WHAT WE CAN
DO, CONSISTENT WITH PRIVACY AND
SECURITY.
WE NEED BETTER INTELLIGENCE
COOPERATION, WE NEED TO BE SURE
THAT THEY WERE GETTING THE BEST
INTELLIGENCE THAT WE CAN FROM
FRIENDS AND ALLIES AROUND THE
WORLD.
AND THEN, WE'VE GOT TO RECOGNIZE
OUR FIRST LINE OF DEFENSE
AGAINST LONE WOLF ATTACKS A
AMONG MUSLIM AMERICANS.
AND IT IS NOT ONLY SHAMEFUL, IT
IS DANGEROUS FOR THE KINDS OF
COMMENTS YOU'RE HEARING FROM THE
REPUBLICAN SIDE.
WE NEED TO BE REACHING OUT AND
UNIFYING OUR COUNTRY AGAINST
TERRORIST ATTACKS AND LONE
WOLVES, AND WORKING WITH MUSLIM
AMERICANS.
>> ANDREA HAS A FOLLOW-UP.
>> JUST A QUICK FOLLOW-UP --
>> ANDREA, WHEN CAN I GET MY 30
SECONDS?
>> YOU SAID THAT THE LEADERS
FROM THE INTELLIGENCE COMMUNITY
WENT TO SILICON VALLEY, THEY
WERE FLATLY TURNED DOWN.
THEY GOT NOWHERE.
>> THAT IS NOT WHAT I'VE HEARD.
LET ME LEAVE IT AT THAT.
>> I NEED TO TALK ABOUT HOMELAND
SECURITY AND PREPAREDNESS.
EVER SINCE SEPTEMBER 11th, 30
SECONDS, EVER SINCE THE ATTACKS
OF SEPTEMBER 11th, MY COLLEAGUES
DEMOCRATIC AND REPUBLICAN
MAYORS, MADE ME THEIR LEADER ON
HOMELAND SECURITY AND
PREPAREDNESS.
HERE IN THE HOMELAND, UNLIKE
COMBATTING ISIL ABROAD, IT'S
LIKE YOUR BODY'S IMMUNE SYSTEM,
IT'S ABLE TO PROTECT YOUR BODY
AGAINST BAD BUGS, NOTLESSLY
BECAUSE OF NUMBERS, IT'S BETTER
CONNECTED, THE FUSION CENTERS,
THE BIOSURVEILLANCE SYSTEMS,
BETTER PREPARED FIRST
RESPONDERS, BUT THERE'S ANOTHER
FRONT IN THIS BATTLE, AND IT IS
THIS.
THAT'S THE POLITICAL FRONT, AND
IF DONALD TRUMP WANTS TO START A
REGISTRY IN OUR COUNTRY OF
PEOPLE BY BAKED, HE CAN START
WITH ME, AND I WILL SIGN UP AS
ONE WHO IS TOTALLY OPPOSED TO
HIS FASCIST APPEALS THAT WANTS
TO VILIFY AMERICAN MUSLIMS.
THAT CAN DO MORE DAMAGE TO OUR
DEMOCRACY THAN ANYTHING.
>> THAT'S TIME, AND WE DO HAVE O
TO MOVE ON.
SECRETARY CLINTON, THIS IS THE
FIRST TIME --
>> CAN I GATE BRIEF RESPONSE.
>> 30 SECONDS, SENATOR.
>> ONE, AND I AGREE WITH WHAT
THE SECRETARY SAID AND WHAT
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY SAID.
BUT HERE'S AN ISSUE THAT WE ALSO
SHOULD TALK ABOUT.
WE HAVE A $600 BILLION MILITARY
BUDGET.
IT IS A BUDGET LARGER THAN THE
NEXT EIGHT COUNTRIES.
UNFORTUNATELY, MUCH OF THAT
BUDGET CONTINUES TO FIGHT THE
OLD COLD WAR WITH THE SOVIET
UNION.
VERY LITTLE OF THAT BUDGET, LESS
THAN 10% ACTUALLY GOES INTO
FIGHTING ISIS AND INTERNATIONAL
TERRORISM.
WE NEED TO BE THINKING HARD
ABOUT MAKING FUNDAMENTAL CHANGES
IN THE PRIORITIES OF THE DEFENSE
DEPARTMENT.
>> ALL RIGHT. CLINTON.
THIS IS THE FIRST THAT IS OF EL
CLINTON WOULD ADVISE YOU
ECONOMIC
OR A REAL POLICY ROLL?
>> WELL, IT'LL START AT THE
KITCHEN TABLE, WE'LL SEE HOW IT
GOES FROM THERE.
AND I --
[ APPLAUSE ]
I'M GOING HAVE THE VERY BEST
ADVISORS THAT I CAN POSSIBLY
HAVE, AND WHEN IT COMES TO THE
ECONOMY, AND WHAT WAS
ACCOMPLISHED UNDER MY HUSBAND'S
LEADERSHIP AND THE '90s,
ESPECIALLY WHEN IT CAME TO
RAISING INCOMES FOR EVERYBODY,
AND LIFTING MORE PEOPLE OUT OF
POVERTY THAN ANY TIME IN RECENT
HISTORY, YOU BET, I'M GOING TO
ASK FOR HIS IDEAS, I'M GOING ASK
FOR HIS ADVISE AND I'M GOING USE
THEM AS GOODWILL EMISSARY TO GO
AROUND THE COUNTRY TO FIND THE
BEST IDEAS WE'VE GOT.
BECAUSE I DO BELIEVE AS HE SAID,
EVERYTHING THAT'S WRONG WITH
AMERICA HAS BEEN SOLVED
SOMEWHERE IN AMERICA.
WE JUST HAVE TO DO MORE OF IT,
AND WE HAVE TO REACH OUT,
ESPECIALLY INTO POOR
COMMUNITIES, AND COMMUNITIES OF
COLOR TO GIVE MORE PEOPLE THEIR
OWN CHANCE TO GET AHEAD.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, 30 SECOND
RESPONSE, SIR.
>> GREAT IDEAS, GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY, SECRETARY CHRISTIAN
TON, BUT HERE'S THE TRUTH, IF
YOU HAVE AN ADMINISTRATION
STACKED WITH WALL STREET
APPOINTEES, IT AIN'T GOING TO
ACCOMPLISH VERY MUCH.
HERE'S A PROMISE THAT I MAKE,
AND I MENTIONED A MOMENT AGO HOW
CORRUPT THE SYSTEM IS, GOLDMAN
SACHS PAYING A $5 BILLION FINE,
GIVES THIS COUNTRY, IN RECENT
HISTORY, A REPUBLICAN SECRETARY
OF TREASURY, A DEMOCRATIC
SECRETARY OF TREASURY.
HERE'S A PROMISE, IF ELECTED
PRESIDENT, GOLDMAN SACHS IS NOT
GOING TO HAVE, BRING FORTH A
SECRETARY OF TREASURY FOR A
SANDERS ADMINISTRATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, LET ME ASK
YOU A QUESTION, YOU CALLED BILL
CLINTON'S PAST TRANSGRESSIONS,
QUOTE, TOTALLY, TOTALLY, TOTALLY
DISGRACEFUL, AND UNACCEPTABLE.
SENATOR, DO YOU REGRET SAYING
THAT?
>> I WAS ASKED A QUESTION -- YOU
KNOW ONE OF THE THINS, ANDREA,
AND THAT QUESTION, ANNOYS ME.
I CANNOT WALK DOWN THE STREET,
SECRETARY CLINTON KNOWS THAT,
WITHOUT BEING TOLD HOW MUCH I
HAVE TO ATTACK SECRETARY
CLINTON.
TO WANT GET ME ON THE FRONT PAGE
OF THE PAPER, I MAKE A VICIOUS
ATTACK.
I HAVE AVOIDED DOING THAT.
TRYING TO RUN AN ISSUE-ORIENTED
CAMPAIGN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WAS ASKED A QUESTION --
>> YOU DIDN'T HAVE TO ANSWER IT
THAT WAY THOUGH, WHY DID YOU?
>> THEN IF I DON'T, THERE'S
ANOTHER FRONT PAGE.
YES, AND I MEAN THIS SERIOUSLY,
WE'VE BEEN THROUGH THIS.
YES, HIS BEHAVIOR WAS
DEPLORABLE, HAVE A SAID A WORD?
NO, I HAVE NOT.
I'M GOING TO DEBATE SECRETARY
CLINTON, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY ON
THE ISSUES FACING THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE, NOT BILL CLINTON'S
PERSONAL BEHAVIOR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE WILL TAKE A BREAK.
WE WILL CONTINUE FROM CHARLESTON
RIGHT AFTER THIS.
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY.
FINALLY BEFORE WE GO TONIGHT, WE
SAT OUT HERE TO UNDERSTAND
POINTS AND DIFFERENCES BETWEEN
YOU.
WE BELIEVE WE'VE LEARNED A LOT
HERE.
BEFORE WE LEAVE, IS THERE
ANYTHING YOU WANTED TO SAY
TONIGHT THAT YOU HAVEN'T GOTTEN
A CHANCE TO SAY.
AND WE'LL START WITH GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> DIDN'T SEE THAT COMING, DID
YOU.
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO GET 20
MINUTES TO DO IT.
LOOK, I BELIEVE THERE ARE MANY
ISSUES, 60 SECONDS FOR THIS.
>> 60 SECOND.
WE'D APPRECIATE IT.
>> THERE ARE SO MANY ISSUES THAT
WE HAVEN'T BEEN ABLE TO DISCUSS
HERE.
WE HAVE NOT FULLY DISCUSSED
IMMIGRATION REFORM, AND THE
DEPLORABLE NUMBER OF DETENTION
KAMPBS THAT OUR NATION'S NOW
MAINTAINING.
WE HAVEN'T DISCUSSED THE
SHAMEFUL TREATMENT THAT THE
PEOPLE OF PUERTO RICO, OUR
FELLOW AMERICANS WHO ARE BEING
TREATED WITH BY THESE HEDGE
FUNDS THAT ARE WORKING THEM
OVER.
WE HAVEN'T DISCUSSED THE FACT
THAT IN OUR OWN HEMISPHERE, WE
HAVE THE DANGER OF STATE
FAILURES BECAUSE OF DRUG
TRAFFICKERS AND HONDURAS AND
KWAUT MA LA AND EL VALVE DOR, I
GUESS THE BOTTOM LINE IS THIS,
LOOK, WE ARE A GREAT PEOPLE WHEN
WE ACT AT HOME AND ABROAD.
BASED ON THE BELIEFS THAT UNITE
US.
BELIEF IN THE DIGNITY OF EVERY
PERSON, OUR BELIEF IN OUR OWN
COMMON GOOD, THERE IS NO
CHALLENGE THAT IS TOO GREAT FOR
US TO OVERCOME.
PROVIDED WE BRING FORWARD IN
THESE DIVIDED TIMES, NEW
LEADERSHIP THAT CAN HEAL OUR
DIVIDES AT HOME AND BRING OUR
PRINCE.
S ABROAD.
WE'RE ON THE THRESHOLD OF A NEW
ERA OF AMERICAN PROGRESS, AND I
BELIEVE WE HAVE ONLY NEED TO
JOIN FORCES TOGETHER AND CROSS
THAT THRESHOLD INTO A NEW ERA OF
AMERICAN PROSPERITY.
>> AND THAT'S TIME.
>> THANKS A LOT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> LESTER, I SPENT A LOT OF TIME
LAST WEEK BEING OUTRAGED BY
WHAT'S HAPPENING IN FLINT,
MICHIGAN, AND I I THINK EVERY
SINGLE AMERICAN SHOULD BE
OUTRAGED.
WE'VE HAD A CITY IN THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA WHERE THE
POPULATION, WHICH IS POOR IN
MANY WAYS, AND MAJORITY AFRICAN
AMERICAN HAS BEEN DRINKING AND
BATHING IN LEAD-CON TAN NATOED
WATER.
AND THE GOVERNOR OF THAT STATE,
ACTED AS THOUGH HE DIDN'T REALLY
CARE.
HE HAD REQUESTED FOR HELP THAT
HE BASICALLY STONE WALLED.
I'LL TELL YOU WHAT IF THE KIDS
IN A RICH SUBURB OF DETROIT HAD
BEEN DRINKING CONTAMINATED WATER
AND BEING BATHED IN IT, THERE
WOULD HAVE BEEN ACTION.
SO I SENT MY TOP CAMPAIGN AID
DOWN THERE TO TALK TO THE MAYOR
OF FLINT, TO BE SEE WHAT I COULD
DO TO HELP.
AND I ISSUED A STATEMENT ABOUT
WHAT WE NEEDED TO DO, AND THEN I
WENT ON A TV SHOW, AND I SAID IT
WAS OUTRAGEOUS THAT THE GOVERNOR
HADN'T ACTED, I WANT TO BE A
PRESIDENT THAT TAKES CARE OF THE
BIG PROBLEMS AND THE PROBLEMS
THAT ARE AFFECTING THE PEOPLE OF
OUR COUNTRY EVERY DAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON WAS RIGHT,
AND WHAT I DID WAS, WHICH I
THINK IS ALSO RIGHT IS TO
DEMANDED THE RESIGNATION OF THE
GOVERNOR.
A MAN WHO ACTS NOT IRRESPONSIBLY
SHOULD NOT STAY IN POWER.
NOW, WE ARE A GREAT NATION.
AND WE'VE HEARD A LOT OF GREAT
IDEAS HERE TONIGHT.
BUT LET'S BE HONEST AND LET'S BE
TRUTHFUL.
VERY LITTLE IS GOING TO BE DONE
TO TRANSFORM OUR ECONOMY, AND TO
CREATE THE KIND OF MIDDLE CLASS
WE NEED UNLESS WE END A CORRUPT
CAMPAIGN FINANCED SYSTEM, WHICH
IS UNDERMINING AMERICAN
DEMOCRACY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
WE HAVE GOT TO GET RID OF
SUPERPACKS.
CITIZENS UNITED.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO IS
CREATE A POLITICAL REVOLUTION
WHICH REVITALIZES AMERICAN
DEMOCRACY WHICH BRINGS MILLIONS
OF YOUNG PEOPLE AND WORKING
PEOPLE INTO THE POLITICAL
PROCESS.
TO SAY LOUDLY AND CLEARLY, THAT
THE GOVERNMENT OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA BELONGS TO ALL
OF US, AND NOT JUST A HANDFUL OF
WEALTHY CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTORS.
>> ALL RIGHT.
WELL THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND THANKS TO ALL OF YOU FOR
BEING HERE TONIGHT.
SHEDDING LIGHT ON SOME OF THE
DIFFERENCES AS AMERICANS GET
READY TO VOTE.
I WANT TO THANK THE
CONGRESSIONAL BLACK CAUCUS
INSTITUTE AND CERTAINLY MY
FRIEND AND COLLEAGUE ANDREA
MITCHELL.
THIS HAS BEEN GREAT.
IT'S BEEN A GREAT, SPIRITED
CONVERSATION, AND AMERICAN
PEOPLE APPRECIATE IT.
LET ME TURN IT OVER TO MY FRIEND
CHUCK TODD NOW, THANKS.
>> LESTER, THANK YOU.
AND A TERRIFIC JOB, MODERATING
THIS DEBATE TONIGHT.
ANDREA AS WELL.
WHAT A LIVELY, SUBSTANTIVE
DEBATE.
WE THOUGHT THERE WERE GOING TO
BE FIREWORKS, THERE WERE.
YOU HEARD SORT OF THE SHARP,
DISAGREEMENTS WHEN IT COMES TO
GUNS, WHEN IT COMES TO WALL
STREET REFORM.
WHEN IT COMES TO HEALTH CARE.
AND EVEN A FEW THINGS ON FOREIGN
POLICY.
WE'RE GOING TO BREAK ALL OF IT
DOWN HERE IN A FEW MINUTES, BUT
WE'RE GOING TO TRY TO SNEAK IN A
SHORT BREAK.
AND WHEN WE COME BACK, INSTANT
ANALYSIS, WE'LL SEE IF WE CAN
FIND OUT WHAT THE CAMPAIGNS ARE
DOING.
WE'RE LIVE HERE IN THE SPIN ROOM
IN CHA
ONE POINT, DID HE NOT?
WHAT IS HIS RECORD
>> AGAINST THE SANDERS THESIS
BASICALLY.
THAT WHAT WE NEED IS
REVOLUTIONARY CHANGE.
HE'S NOT ABOUT REVOLUTIONARY
CHANGE.
HE'S ABOUT EVOLUTIONARY CHANGE.
INCREMENTAL CHANGE.
>> SOMETIMES PEOPLE WRAPPING
THEMSELVES IN THE FLAG.
HILLARY CLINTON WAS WRAPPING
HERSELF IN PRESIDENT OBAMA
TONIGHT.
WE WERE LOOKING AT THERE IS
INSTANCE AFTER INSTANCE, I PLAN
ON BUILDING UPON PRESIDENT
OBAMA, DODD FRANK, HEALTH CARE,
AND IT WAS CLEARLY DESIGNED TO
SAY, BERNIE SANDERS, HE'S NOT
WRAPPING HIMSELF IN OBAMA.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
AND THERE'S SUCH A HISTORICAL
RESONANCE HERE OF COURSE BECAUSE
EIGHT YEARS AGO, THE SOUTH
CAROLINA PRIMARY BETWEEN OBAMA
AND CLINTON, PERHAPS THE
NASTIEST OF ALL, AND THE
BITTERNESS WAS WHEN THEY CLASHED
AT THAT POINT IS IN STARK
CONTRAST TO SAY THE LEAST WITH
THE WAY SHE EMBRACED OBAMA AS A
PERSON, AS A LEADER, EMBRACED
ALL OF HIS POLICIES, THAT WE
CAN'T DO WHAT BENGHAZI WANTS TO
DO ON -- BERNIE SANDERS WANTS TO
DO ON HEALTH CARE.
I HAVE A FEELING THIS IS THE
BEGINNING OF A LIVELY FINAL 15
DAYS.
WE WILL HAVE CONTINUING LIVE
ANALYSIS OF TONIGHT'S DEBATE ON
MSNBC.COM.
AND IF YOU MISSED PART OF THIS
DEBATE, YOU CAN SEE IT BEGIN
STARTING RIGHT NOW ON MSNBC.
FOR NOW, I'M CHUCK TODD IN
CHARLESTON, SOUTH CAROLINA.
FROM ALL OF WITH US, WE SAY GOOD
NIGHT.