Captioning sponsored by
NEWSHOUR PRODUCTIONS, LLC
>> THANK YOU, NEW HAMPSHIRE.
>> THANK YOU, IOWA.
>> IT LOOKS LIKE WE ARE IN A
VIRTUAL TIE.
(CHEERS AND APPLAUSE)
>> THERE IS SO MUCH AT STAKE IN
THIS ELECTION.
>> WE WILL NEED TO COME TOGETHER
AND UNITE THIS PARTY.
>> BERNIE SANDERS AND I SHARE A
LOT OF THE SAME GOALS, BUT THERE
ARE DIFFERENCES.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON DOES
REPRESENT THE ESTABLISHMENT.
>> I AM NOT GOING TO MAKE
PROMISES I CAN'T KEEP.
>> WHAT HAPPENED HERE IS NEW
HAMPSHIRE, THAT IS WHAT WILL
HAPPEN ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY.
(CHEERS AND APPLAUSE)
>> WE'RE GOING TO FIGHT FOR
EVERY VOTE IN EVERY STATE.
>> ARE YOU GUYS READY FOR A
RADICAL IDEA?
>> YOU'VE GOT TO BE READY ON DAY
ONE.
>> THIS IS THE PBS NEWSHOUR
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE IN PARTNERSHIP
WITH FACEBOOK.
NOW LIVE FROM MILWAUKEE, GWEN
IFILL AND JUDY WOODRUFF.
(APPLAUSE)
>> THANK YOU.
>> Woodruff: GOOD EVENING, WE'RE
HAPPY TO WELCOME YOU TO
MILWAUKEE FOR THIS DEMOCRATIC
DEBATE.
WE'RE ESPECIALLY PLEASED TO
THANK OUR PARTNERS AT FACEBOOK,
WHO HAVE HELPED US ESTABLISH A
VIBRANT CONVERSATION AMONG
UNDECIDED VOTERS.
TONIGHT YOU'LL HEAR SOME OF
THEIR QUESTIONS FOR THE
CANDIDATES.
AND YOU CAN FOLLOW ALONG AT HOME
ON THE PBS NEWSHOUR PAGE ON
FACEBOOK.
WE ALSO WANT TO THANK OUR HOSTS,
THE UNIVERSITY OF WISCONSIN,
MILWAUKEE, ON WHOSE CAMPUS WE
MEET, HERE IN THE BEAUTIFUL
HELEN BADER CONCERT HALL.
>> Ifill: WE WANT TO EXTEND OUR
WARM THANKS TO MILWAUKEE PUBLIC
RADIO AND MILWAUKEE PUBLIC
TELEVISION, AS WELL AS ALL OF
OUR FRIENDS AT THE PBS MEMBER
STATIONS ACROSS THE COUNTRY
TUNING IN TONIGHT.
THIS IS THE SIXTH TIME THE
DEMOCRATS HAVE MET FACE TO FACE.
EACH TIME WE LEARN MORE ABOUT
THEM AND THE PRESIDENTS THEY SAY
THEY WANT TO BE.
YOU KNOW YOU'RE WATCHING--
WHETHER YOU'RE A DEMOCRAT, A
REPUBLICAN, OR NEITHER-- BECAUSE
YOU BELIEVE THE OUTCOME OF THE
ELECTION IS IMPORTANT TO YOU.
WE BELIEVE THAT TOO.
WITH THAT, LET'S WELCOME THE
CANDIDATES TO THE STAGE, SENATOR
BERNIE SANDERS OF VERMONT.
WELCOME SENATOR, GREAT TO SEE
YOU!
>> Woodruff: AND FORMER
SECRETARY OF STATE HILLARY
CLINTON.
(APPLAUSE)
>> THANK
>> Woodruff: A WORD ABOUT
FORMAT.
THERE WILL BE TWO SHORT BREAKS,
AND THE RULES ARE SIMPLE: 90
SECONDS TO ANSWER, AND 30
SECONDS FOR THE OTHER CANDIDATE
TO RESPOND.
>> Ifill: WITH IOWA AND NEW
HAMPSHIRE BEHIND US, WE ARE NOW
BROADENING THE CONVERSATION, TO
AMERICA'S HEARTLAND AND BEYOND,
INCLUDING HERE IN WISCONSIN.
NOW, LET'S TURN TO THE
CANDIDATES FOR THEIR OPENING
STATEMENTS.
THE ORDER WAS DETERMINED BY A
COIN TOSS.
SENATOR SANDERS, YOU GO FIRST.
>> GWEN AND JUDY, THANK YOU VERY
MUCH FOR HOSTING THIS EVENT AND
PBS, THANK YOU.
NINE MONTHS AGO OUR CAMPAIGN
BEGAN.
AND WHEN IT BEGAN, WE HAD NO
POLITICAL ORGANIZATION, NO MONEY
AND NOT MUCH NAME RECOGNITION
OUTSIDE OF THE STATE OF VERMONT.
A LOT HAS HAPPENED IN NINE
MONTHS.
AND WHAT HAS HAPPENED IS, I
THINK, THE AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE
RESPONDED TO A SERIES OF BASIC
TRUTHS.
AND THAT IS THAT WE HAVE TODAY A
CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM WHICH IS
CORRUPT, WHICH IS UNDERMINING
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY, WHICH ALLOWS
WALL STREET AND BILLIONAIRES TO
POUR HUGE SUMS OF MONEY INTO THE
POLITICAL PROCESS TO ELECT THE
CANDIDATES OF THEIR CHOICE.
AND ALIGNED WITH THE CORRUPT
CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM IS A
RIGGED ECONOMY.
AND THAT'S AN ECONOMY WHERE
ORDINARY AMERICANS ARE WORKING
LONGER HOURS FOR LOWER WAGES,
THEY ARE WORRIED TO DEATH ABOUT
THE FUTURE OF THEIR KIDS, AND
YET THEY ARE SEEING ALMOST ALL
NEW INCOME AND ALL NEW WEALTH
GOING TO THE TOP 1 PERCENT.
AND THAT IN ADDITION TO THAT,
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE LOOKING
AROUND AND THEY SEE A BROKEN
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
THEY SEE MORE PEOPLE IN JAIL IN
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY ON EARTH,
2.2 MILLION.
WE'RE SPENDING $80 BILLION A
YEAR LOCKING UP FELLOW
AMERICANS.
THEY SEE KIDS GETTING ARRESTED
FOR MARIJUANA, GETTING IN
PRISON, GETTING A CRIMINAL
RECORD, WHILE THEY SEE
EXECUTIVES ON WALL STREET WHO
PAY BILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN
SETTLEMENTS AND GET NO
PROSECUTION AT ALL.
NO CRIMINAL RECORDS FOR THEM.
I THINK WHAT OUR CAMPAIGN IS
INDICATING IS THAT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE ARE TIRED OF
ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS, TIRED OF
ESTABLISHMENT ECONOMICS.
THEY WANT A POLITICAL REVOLUTION
IN WHICH MILLIONS OF AMERICANS
STAND UP, COME TOGETHER, NOT LET
THE TRUMPS OF THE WORLD DIVIDE
US AND SAY, YOU KNOW WHAT, IN
THIS GREAT COUNTRY, WE NEED A
GOVERNMENT THAT REPRESENTS ALL
OF US, NOT JUST A HANDFUL OF
WEALTHY CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTORS.
THANK YOU.
>> Moderator: THANK YOU,
SENATOR SANDERS.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: THANK YOU,
SENATOR SANDERS.
SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT TO
KNOCK DOWN ALL THE BARRIERS THAT
ARE HOLDING AMERICANS BACK, AND
TO REBUILD THE LADDERS OF
OPPORTUNITY THAT WILL GIVE EVERY
AMERICAN A CHANCE TO ADVANCE,
ESPECIALLY THOSE WHO HAVE BEEN
LEFT OUT AND LEFT BEHIND.
I KNOW A LOT OF AMERICANS ARE
ANGRY ABOUT THE ECONOMY.
AND FOR GOOD CAUSE.
AMERICANS HAVEN'T HAD A RAISE IN
15 YEARS.
THERE AREN'T ENOUGH GOOD PAYING
JOBS, ESPECIALLY FOR YOUNG
PEOPLE.
AND YES, THE ECONOMY IS RIGGED
IN FAVOR OF THOSE AT THE TOP.
WE BOTH AGREE THAT WE HAVE TO
GET UNACCOUNTABLE MONEY OUT OF
OUR POLITICAL SYSTEM AND THAT WE
HAVE TO DO MUCH MORE TO ENSURE
THAT WALL STREET NEVER WRECKS
MAIN STREET AGAIN.
BUT I WANT TO GO FURTHER.
I WANT TO TACKLE THOSE BARRIERS
THAT STAND IN THE WAY OF TOO
MANY AMERICANS RIGHT NOW.
AFRICAN-AMERICANS WHO FACE
DISCRIMINATION IN THE JOB
MARKET, EDUCATION, HOUSING AND
THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
HARDWORKING IMMIGRANT FAMILIES
LIVING IN FEAR, WHO SHOULD BE
BROUGHT OUT OF THE SHADOWS SO
THEY AND THEIR CHILDREN CAN HAVE
A BETTER FUTURE.
GUARANTEEING THAT WOMENS' WORK
FINALLY GETS THE PAY, THE EQUAL
PAY THAT WE DESERVE.
I THINK AMERICA CAN ONLY LIVE UP
TO ITS POTENTIAL WHEN WE MAKE
SURE THAT EVERY AMERICAN HAS A
CHANCE TO LIVE UP TO HIS OR HER
POTENTIAL.
THAT WILL BE MY MISSION AS
PRESIDENT.
AND I THINK TOGETHER WE WILL
MAKE PROGRESS.
>> Moderator: THANK YOU BOTH.
(APPLAUSE)
THANK YOU BOTH.
AND WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK AFTER A
SHORT BREAK TO BEGIN QUESTIONS.
>> THE PBS NEWSHOUR DEMOCRATIC
DEBATE IN PARTNERSHIP WITH
FACEBOOK CONTINUES.
LIVE FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF
WISCONSIN IN MILWAUKEE, ONCE
AGAIN GWEN IFILL AND JUDY
WOODRUFF.
>> Moderator: AND WELCOME BACK
TO THIS PBS NEWSHOUR DEBATE,
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE HERE IN
MILWAUKEE.
LET'S GET RIGHT TO THE
QUESTIONS.
SENATOR SANDERS TO YOU FIRST.
COMING OFF THE RESULTS IN IOWA
AND NEW HAMPSHIRE, THERE ARE
MANY VOTERS WHO ARE TAKING A
CLOSER LOOK AT YOU AND YOUR
IDEAS.
AND THEY'RE ASKING, HOW BIG A
ROLE DO YOU FORE SEE FOR THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
IT'S ALREADY SPENDING 21% OF THE
ENTIRE U.S. ECONOMY.
HOW MUCH LARGER WOULD GOVERNMENT
BE IN THE LIVES OF AMERICANS
UNDER A SANDERS PRESIDENCY?
>> WELL, TO PUT THAT INTO
CONTEXT, JUDY, I THINK WE HAVE
TO UNDERSTAND THAT IN THE LAST
30 YEARS IN THIS COUNTRY, THERE
HAS BEEN A MASSIVE TRANSFER OF
WEALTH GOING FROM THE HANDS OF
WORKING FAMILIES INTO THE TOP
1/10 OF 1 PERCENT WHOSE
PERCENTAGE OF WEALTH HAS
DOUBLED.
IN OTHER WORDS, THE VERY RICH
ARE GETTING RICHER.
ALMOST EVERYBODY ELSE IS GETTING
POORER.
WHAT I BELIEVE IS THE UNITED
STATES, IN FACT, SHOULD JOIN THE
REST OF THE INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD
AND GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE.
OUR MEDICARE FOR
ALL SINGLE
PAYOR PROPOSAL WILL SAVE THE
AVERAGE MIDDLE CLASS FAMILY
$5,000 A YEAR.
I DO BELIEVE THAT IN THE YEAR
2016 WE HAVE TO LOOK IN TERMS OF
PUBLIC EDUCATION.
AND COLLEGES AS PART OF PUBLIC
EDUCATION MAKING PUBLIC COLLEGES
AND UNIVERSITIES TUITION-FREE.
I BELIEVE THAT WHEN REAL
UNEMPLOYMENT IS CLOSE TO 10% AND
WHEN OUR INFRASTRUCTURE, OUR
ROADS, OUR BRIDGES, OUR WATER
SYSTEMS, FLINT, MICHIGAN, COMES
TO MIND, OUR WASTE WATER PLANT,
OUR RAIL, OUR AIRPORTS IN MANY
PLACES ARE DISINTEGRATING.
WE CAN CREATE 13 MILLION JOBS BY
REBUILDING OUR INFRASTRUCTURE AT
A COST OF A TRILLION DOLLARS.
>> Moderator: BUT MY QUESTION
IS HOW BIG WOULD GOVERNMENT BE.
WOULD THERE BE ANY LIMIT ON THE
SIZE AND ROLE OF GOVERNMENT?
>> OF COURSE THERE WILL BE A
LIMIT.
BUT WHEN TODAY YOU HAVE MASSIVE
LEVELS OF INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY, WHEN THE MIDDLE
CLASS IS DISAPPEARING, YOU HAVE
THE HIGHEST RATE OF CHILDHOOD
POVERTY OF ALMOST ANY MAJOR
COUNTRY ON EARTH, YES, IN MY
VIEW, THE GOVERNMENT OF A
DEMOCRATIC SOCIETY HAS A MORAL
RESPONSIBILITY TO PLAY A VITAL
ROLE IN MAKING SURE THAT ALL OF
OUR PEOPLE HAVE A DECENT
STANDARD OF LIVING.
>> JUDY, I THINK THAT THE BEST
ANALYSIS THAT I HAVE SEEN BASED
ON SENATOR SANDERS PLAN IS THAT
IT WOULD PROBABLY INCREASE THE
SIZE OF THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
BY ABOUT 40%.
BUT WHAT IS MOST CONCERNING TO
ME IS THAT IN LOOKING AT THE
PLANS, LET'S TAKE HEALTH CARE,
FOR EXAMPLE.
LAST WEEK IN A CNN TOWNHALL THE
SENATOR TOLD A QUESTIONER THAT
THE-- THE QUESTIONER WOULD SPEND
ABOUT $500 IN TAXES TO GET ABOUT
$5,000 IN HEALTH CARE.
EVERY PROGRESSIVE ECONOMIST WHO
HAS ANALYZED THAT SAYS THAT THE
NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP.
AND THAT IS A PROMISE THAT
CANNOT BE KEPT.
AND IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT NOW
THAT WE ARE GETTING INTO THE
REST OF THE COUNTRY, THAT BOTH
OF US ARE HELD TO ACCOUNT.
FOR EXPLAINING WHAT WE ARE
PROPOSING.
BECAUSE ESPECIALLY WITH HEALTH
CARE, THIS IS NOT ABOUT MATH.
THIS IS ABOUT PEOPLE'S LIVES.
AND WE SHOULD LEVEL WITH THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE ABOUT WHAT WE
CAN DO TO MAKE SURE THEY GET
QUALITY, AFFORDABLE HEALTH CARE.
>> LET US LEVEL WITH THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
SECRETARY CLINTON HAS BEEN GOING
AROUND THE COUNTRY SAYING BERNIE
SANDERS WANTS TO DISMANTLE THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
PEOPLE ARE GOING TO LOSE THEIR
MEDICAID, THEY'RE GOING TO LOSE
THEIR PROGRAM.
I HAVE FOUGHT MY ENTIRE LIFE TO
MAKE SURE THAT HEALTH CARE IS A
RIGHT FOR ALL PEOPLE.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO DISMANTLE
ANYTHING.
BUT HERE IS THE TRUTH.
29 MILLION PEOPLE HAVE NO HEALTH
INSURANCE TODAY IN AMERICA.
WE PAY BY FAR THE HIGHEST PRICES
IN THE WORLD FOR PRESCRIPTION
DRUGS.
ONE OUT OF FIVE AMERICANS CAN'T
EVEN AFFORD THE PRESCRIPTIONS
THE DOCTORS ARE WRITING.
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE HAVE HIGH
DEDUCTIBLES AND COPAYMENTS.
WHAT I SAID, AND LET ME REPEAT
IT I DON'T KNOW WHAT ECONOMISTS
SECRETARY CLINTON IS TALKING TO.
BUT WHAT I HAVE SAID, AND LET ME
REPEAT IT, THAT YES, THE MIDDLE,
THE FAMILY RIGHT IN THE MIDDLE
OF THE ECONOMY WOULD PAY $500
MORE IN TAXES AND GET A
REDUCTION IN THEIR HEALTH-CARE
COSTS OF $5,000.
IN MY VIEW, HEALTH CARE IS A
RIGHT OF ALL PEOPLE, NOT A
PRIVILEGE.
AND I WILL FIGHT FOR THAT.
PLAWS PLAWS.
>> WELL, I CAN ONLY SAY THAT WE
BOTH SHARE THE GOAL OF UNIVERSAL
HEALTH-CARE COVERAGE.
YOU KNOW BEFORE IT WAS CALLED
OBAMACARE, IT WAS CALLED
HILLARYCARE AND I TOOK ON THE
DRUG COMPANIES AND I TOOK ON THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES TO TRY TO
GET US UNIVERSAL HEALTH-CARE
COVERAGE.
(APPLAUSE)
AND WHY I AM A STAWNCH SUPPORTER
OF PRESIDENT OBAMA'S PRINCIPLE
ACCOMPLISHMENT-- PRINCIPAL
ACCOMPLISHMENT, NAMELY THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, IS BECAUSE
I KNOW HOW HARD IT WAS TO GET
THAT DONE.
WE ARE AT 90% COVERAGE.
WE HAVE TO GET THE REMAINING
TEN.
I'VE SET FORTH VERY SPECIFIC
PLANS ABOUT HOW TO GET COSTS
DOWN, ESPECIALLY PRESCRIPTION
DRUG COSTS.
AND IT IS DIFFICULT TO IN ANYWAY
ARGUE WITH THE GOAL THAT WE BOTH
SHARE.
BUT I THINK THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
DESERVE TO KNOW SPECIFICALLY HOW
THIS WOULD WORK.
IF IT'S MEDICARE FOR ALL, THEN
YOU NO LONGER HAVE THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT BECAUSE THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, AS YOU KNOW
VERY WELL, IS BASED ON THE
INSURANCE SYSTEM, BASED ON
EXCHANGES, BASED ON A SUBSIDY
SYSTEM.
THE CHILDREN'S HEALTH INSURANCE
PROGRAM WHICH I HELPED TO CREATE
WHICH COVERS 8 MILLION KIDS IS
ALSO A DIFFERENT KIND OF
PROGRAM.
SO IF YOU ARE HAVING MEDICARE
FOR ALL, SINGLE PAYOR, YOU NEED
TO LEVEL WITH PEOPLE ABOUT WHAT
THEY WILL HAVE AT THE END OF THE
PROCESS YOU ARE PROPOSING.
AND BASED ON EVERY ANALYSIS THAT
I CAN FIND BY PEOPLE WHO ARE SIM
PATHETIC TO THE GOAL, THE
NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP.
AND MANY PEOPLE WILL ACTUALLY BE
WORSE OFF THAN THEY ARE RIGHT
NOW.
>> Moderator: FINAL THOUGHT,
SENATOR.
>> THAT IS ABSOLUTELY
INACCURATE.
LOOK, HERE IS THE REALITY,
FOLKS.
THERE IS ONE MAJOR COUNTRY ON
EARTH THAT DOES NOT GUARANTEE
HEALTH CARE TO ALL PEOPLE.
THERE IS ONE MAJOR COUNTRY, THE
UNITED STATES, WHICH ENDS UP
SPENDING ALMOST THREE TIMES PER
CAPITA WHAT THEY DO IN THE U.K.
GUARANTEEING HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE, 50% MORE THAN THEY DO IN
FRANCE, GUARANTEEING HEALTH CARE
TO ALL PEOPLE, FAR MORE THAN OUR
CANADIAN NEIGHBORS WHO GUARANTEE
HEALTH CARE TO ALL PEOPLE.
PLEASE DO NOT TELL ME THAT IN
THIS COUNTRY, IF AND HERE'S THE
IF, WE HAVE THE COURAGE TO TAKE
ON THE DRUG COMPANIES, AND HAVE
THE COURAGE TO TAKE ON THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES, AND THE
MEDICAL EQUIPMENT SUPPLIERS, IF
WE DO THAT, YES, WE CAN
GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE IN A MUCH MORE
COST-EFFECTIVE WAY.
>> WELL, LET ME JUST SAY, ONCE
AGAIN--
(APPLAUSE)
>> THAT HAVING BEEN IN THE
TRENCHES FIGHTING FOR THIS, I
BELIEVE STRONGLY WE HAVE TO
GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE.
I BELIEVE WE ARE ON THE PATH TO
DOING THAT.
THE LAST THING WE NEED IS TO
THROW OUR COUNTRY INTO A
CONTENTIOUS DEBATE ABOUT HEALTH
CARE AGAIN.
AND WE ARE NOT ENGLAND.
WE ARE NOT FRANCE.
WE INHERITED A SYSTEM THAT WAS
SET UP DURING WORLD WAR II, 170
MILLION AMERICANS GET HEALTH
INSURANCE RIGHT NOW THROUGH
THEIR EMPLOYERS.
SO WHAT WE HAVE TRIED TO DO AND
WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA SUCCEEDED
IN DOING WAS TO BUILD ON THE
HEALTH-CARE SYSTEM WE HAVE, GET
US TO 90% COVERAGE.
WE HAVE TO GET THE OTHER 10% OF
THE WAY TO A HUNDRED.
I FAR PREFER THAT AND THE
CHANCES WE HAVE TO BE SUCCESSFUL
THERE THAN TRYING TO START ALL
OVER AGAIN, GRIDLOCKING OUR
SYSTEM AND TRYING TO GET FROM
ZERO TO 100 PERCENT.
>> Moderator: I WOULD LIKE TO
MOVE ALONG.
I WOULD LIKE TO MOVE ALONG.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SECRETARY
CLINTON, YOU ALSO HAVE PROPOSED
FAIRLY EXPANSIVE IDEAS ABOUT
GOVERNMENT.
YOU MAY REMEMBER THIS PLEDGE
FROM A STATE OF THE UNION
ADDRESS IN WHICH I BELIEVE YOU
WERE PRESENT, IN WHICH THESE
WORDS WERE SAID.
THE ERA OF BIG GOVERNMENT IS
OVER.
YOU MAY REMEMBER THAT.
WHEN ASKED YOUR FEELINGS ABOUT
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT THIS WEEK
61% OF NEW HAMPSHIRE DEMOCRATS
TOLD EXIT POLLERS THAT THEY ARE
ANGRY OR AT LEAST DISSATISFIED.
GIFN WHAT YOU AND SENATOR
SANDERS ARE PROPOSING, IN
EXPANDING GOVERNMENT IN ALMOST
EVERY AREA OF OUR LIVES, IS IT
FAIR FOR AMERICANS WHO FEAR
GOVERNMENT TO FEAR YOU?
>> NO.
BUT IT IS, ABSOLUTELY FAIR AND
NECESSARY FOR AMERICANS TO VET
BOTH OF OUR PROPOSALS.
TO ASK THE REALLY HARD QUESTIONS
ABOUT WHAT IS IT WE THINK WE CAN
ACCOMPLISH, WHY DO WE BELIEVE
THAT, AND WHAT WOULD BE THE
RESULTS FOR THE AVERAGE AMERICAN
FAMILY.
IN MY CASE, WHETHER IT'S HEALTH
CARE OR GETTING US TO DEBT-FREE
TUITION, OR MOVING US TOWARD
PAID FAMILY LEAVE, I HAVE BEEN
VERY SPECIFIC ABOUT WHERE I
WOULD RAISE THE MONEY, HOW MUCH
IT WOULD COST, AND HOW I WOULD
MOVE THIS AGENDA FORWARD.
I HAVE TRIED TO BE AS SPECIFIC
TO ANSWER QUESTIONS SO THAT MY
PROPOSALS CAN BE VETTED.
BECAUSE I FEEL LIKE WE HAVE TO
LEVEL WITH PEOPLE FOR THE VERY
REASON, GWEN, THAT YOU ARE
MENTIONING.
THERE IS A GREAT DEAL OF
SKEPTICISM ABOUT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT.
I AM A AWARE OF THAT.
IT COMES FROM THE RIGHT, FROM
THE LEFT, FROM PEOPLE ON ALL
SIDES OF THE POLITICAL SPECTRUM.
SO WE HAVE A SPECIAL OBLIGATION
TO MAKE CLEAR WHAT WE STAND FOR,
WHICH IS WHY I THINK WE SHOULD
NOT MAKE PROMISES WE CAN'T KEEP.
BECAUSE THAT WILL FURTHER, I
THINK, ALIENATE AMERICANS FROM
UNDERSTANDING AND BELIEVING WE
CAN TOGETHER MAKE SOME REAL
CHANGES IN PEOPLE'S LIVES.
>> Moderator: BUT I VNLT HEARD
EITHER OF YOU PUT A PRICE TAG
ON.
>> I WILL PUT A PRICE TAG.
MY PRICE TAG IS ABOUT $100
BILLION A YEAR.
AND AGAIN, PAID FOR.
AND WHAT I HAVE SAID IS I WILL
NOT THROW US FURTHER INTO DEBT.
I BELIEVE I CAN GET THE MONEY
THAT I NEED BY TAXING THE
WEALTHY, BY CLOSING LOOPHOLES,
THINGS THAT WE ARE WAY OVERDUE
FOR DOING.
AND I THINK ONCE I'M IN THE
WHITE HOUSE WE WILL HAVE ENOUGH
POLITICAL CAPITAL TO BE ABLE TO
DO THAT.
BUT I'M CONSCIENCE OF THE FACT
THAT WE HAVE TO ALSO BE VERY
CLEAR, ESPECIALLY WITH YOUNG
PEOPLE, ABOUT WHAT KIND OF
GOVERNMENT IS GOING TO DO WHAT
FOR THEM AND WHAT IT WILL COST.
>> Moderator: SENATOR?
>> WELL, SECRETARY CLINTON,
YOU'RE NOT IN THE WHITE HOUSE
YET.
AND LET US BE CLEAR THAT EVERY
PROPOSAL THAT I HAVE INTRODUCED
HAS BEEN PAID FOR.
FOR EXAMPLE, ALL RIGHT, WHO IN
AMERICA DENIES THAT WE HAVE AN
INFRASTRUCTURE THAT IS
CRUMBLING.
ROADS, BRIDGES, WATER SYSTEMS,
WASTE WATER PLANTS WHO DENIES
THAT?
WHO DENIES THAT REAL
UNEMPLOYMENT TODAY, INCLUDING
THOSE THAT HAVE GIVEN UP LOOKING
FOR WORK AND WORKING WART TIME
IS CLOSE TO SO% WHO DENIES THAT
AFRICAN-AMERICAN YOUTH
UNEMPLOYMENT IS OVER 50%.
WE NEED TO CREATE JOBS.
SO YES, I WILL DO AWAY WITH THE
OUTRAGE US LOOPHOLES THAT ALLOW
PROFITABLE MULTINATIONAL
CORPORATIONS TO STASH BILLIONS
OF DOLLARS IN THE CAYMAN ISLANDS
AND BERMUDA AND IN A GIVEN YEAR
PAY ZER ZERO, ZERO IN FEDERAL
INCOME TAXES.
YEAH, I WILL DO AWAY WITH THAT,
WE WILL USE THOSE PROCEEDS, A
HUNDRED BILLION A YEAR TO
REINVEST IN OUR INFRASTRUCTURE.
I BELIEVE THAT AS A RESULT OF
THE ILLEGAL BEHAVIOR ON WALL
STREET, THAT THEY ARE A WALL
STREET THAT DROVE THIS COUNTRY
INTO THE WORST ECONOMIC DOWNTURN
SINCE THE GREAT
RECESSION-- GREAT DEPRESSION.
YEAH, I DO BELIEVE THAT NOW
AFTER THE AMERICAN PEOPLE BAILED
WALL STREET OUT, YES, THEY
SHOULD PAY A WALL STREET
SPECULATION TAX SO THAT WE CAN
MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES TUITION-FREE.
WE BAILED THEM OUT.
NOW IT IS THEIR TIME TO HELP THE
MIDDLE CLASS.
(APPLAUSE)
>> YOU KNOW, I THINK AGAIN, BOTH
OF US SHARE THE GOAL OF TRYING
TO MAKE COLLEGE AFFORDABLE FOR
ALL YOUNG AMERICANS.
AND I HAVE SET FORTH A COMPACT
THAT WOULD DO JUST THAT FOR
DEBT-FREE TUITION.
WE DIFFER, HOWEVER, ON A COUPLE
OF KEY POINTS.
ONE OF THEM BEING THAT IF YOU
DON'T HAVE SOME AGREEMENT WITHIN
THE SYSTEM FROM STATES AND FROM
FAMILIES AND FROM STUDENTS, IT'S
HARD TO GET TO WHERE WE NEED TO
GO.
AND SENATOR SANDERS PLAN REALLY
RESTS ON MAKING SURE THAT
GOVERNORS LIKE SCOTT WALKER
CONTRIBUTE $23 BILLION ON THE
FIRST DAY TO MAKE COLLEGE FREE.
I AM A LITTLE SCEPTICAL ABOUT
YOUR GOVERNOR ACTUALLY CARING
ENOUGH ABOUT HIGHER EDUCATION TO
MAKE ANY KIND OF COMMITMENT LIKE
THAT.
>> Moderator: NEXT.
WE'RE GOING TO.
>> A BRIEF RESPONSE.
>> Moderator: VERY BRIEF,
THANK YOU.
>> HERE IS WHERE WE ARE WITH
PUBLIC EDUCATION.
A HUNDRED, 150 YEARS AGO
INCREDIBLY BRAVE AMERICANS SAID
YOU KNOW WHAT, WORKING CLASS
KIDS, LOW INCOME KIDS SHOULD
KNOT HAVE TO WORK IN FACTORIES
OR ON THE FARMS.
LIKE RICH KIDS THEY DESERVE TO
GET A FREE EDUCATION.
AND THAT FREE EDUCATION OF
EXTRAORDINARY ACCOMPLISHMENT WAS
F FIRST GRADE TO 12th GRADE.
THE WORLD HAS CHANGED.
THIS IS 2016.
IN MANY WAYS, A COLLEGE DEGREE
TODAY IS EQUIVALENT TO WHAT A
HIGH SCHOOL DEGREE WAS 50, 60
YEARS AGO.
SO YEAH, I DO BELIEVE THAT WHEN
WE TALK ABOUT PUBLIC EDUCATION
IN AMERICA, TODAY IN A RAPIDLY
CHANGING WORLD, WE SHOULD HAVE
FREE TUITION AT PUBLIC COLLEGES
AND UNIVERSITIES.
THAT SHOULD BE A RIGHT OF ALL
AMERICANS REGARDLESS OF THE
INCOME OF THEIR FAMILIES.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SECRETARY
CLINTON, YOUR CAMPAIGN, YOU AND
YOUR CAMPAIGN HAVE MADE A CLEAR
APPEAL TO WOMEN VOTERS.
YOU HAVE TALKED REPEATEDLY ABOUT
THE FACT, YOU KNOW OF IF ELECTED
THE FIRST WOMAN PRESIDENT.
BUT IN NEW HAMPSHIRE 55% OF THE
WOMEN VOTERS SUPPORTED AND VOTED
FOR SENATOR SANDERS.
WHAT ARE WOMEN MISSING ABOUT
YOU?
>> WELL, FIRST JUDY, I HAVE
SPENT MY ENTIRE ADULT LIFE
WORKING TOWARD MAKING SURE THAT
WOMEN ARE EMPOWERED TO MAKE
THEIR OWN CHOICES, EVEN IF THAT
CHOICE IS NOT TO VOTE FOR ME.
I BELIEVE THAT IT'S MOST
IMPORTANT THAT WE UNLEASH THE
FULL POTENTIAL OF WOMEN AND
GIRLS IN OUR SOCIETY.
AND I FEEL VERY STRONGLY THAT I
HAVE AN AGENDA.
I HAVE A RECORD THAT REALLY DOES
RESPOND TO A LOT OF THE SPECIFIC
NEEDS THAT THE WOMEN IN OUR
COUNTRY FACE.
SO I'M GOING TO KEEP MAKING THAT
CASE.
I'M GOING TO KEEP MAKING SURE
THAT EVERYTHING I'VE DONE,
EVERYTHING THAT I STAND FOR IS
GOING TO BE WELL-KNOWN.
BUT I HAVE NO ARGUMENT WITH ANY
ONE MAKING UP HER MIND ABOUT WHO
TO SUPPORT.
I JUST HOPE THAT BY THE END OF
THIS CAMPAIGN THERE WILL BE A
LOT MORE SUPPORTING ME.
THAT'S WHAT I AM WORKING TOWARD.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: AS YOU KNOW JUST
QUICKLY, AS YOU KNOW, YOUR
STRONG SUPPORTER FORM SECRETARY
OF STATE MAD-LINE ALLBRIGHT SAID
THE OTHER DAY THAT THERE IS A
SPECIAL PLACE IN HELL FOR WOMEN
WITHOUT DON'T SUPPORT OTHER
WOMEN.
DO YOU AGREE WITH WHAT SHE SAID.
>> WELL, LOOK, I THINK THAT SHE
HAS BEEN SAYING THAT FOR AS LONG
AS I HAVE KNOWN HER WHICH IS
ABOUT 25 YEARS.
BUT IT DOESN'T CHANGE MY VIEW
THAT WE NEED TO EMPOWER
EVERYONE, WOMEN AND MEN TO MAKE
THE BEST DECISION IN THEIR MINDS
THAT THEY CAN MAKE.
THAT IS WHAT I HAVE ALWAYS STOOD
FOR.
AND WHEN IT COMES TO THE ISSUES
THAT ARE REALLY ON THE FRONT
LINES AS TO WHETHER WE'RE GOING
TO HAVE EQUAL PAY, PAID FAMILY
LEAVE, SOME OPPORTUNITY FOR, YOU
KNOW, WOMEN TO GO AS FAR AS
THEIR HARD WORK AND TALENT TAKE
THEM, I THINK THAT WE STILL HAVE
SOME BARRIERS TO KNOCK DOWN.
WHICH IS WHY IT IS AT THE CORE
OF MY CAMPAIGN.
I WOULD NOTE JUST FOR AN
HISTORIC ASIDE, SOMEBODY TOLD ME
EARLIER TODAY WE'VE HAD LIKE 200
PRESIDENTIAL PRIMARY DEBATES.
AND THIS IS THE FIRST TIME THERE
HAVE BEEN A MAJORITY OF WOMEN ON
THE STAGE.
SO YOU KNOW, WE'LL TAKE OUR
PROGRESS WHEREVER WE CAN FIND
IT.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SENATOR SANDERS,
YOU'RE IN THE MINORITY BUT WE
STILL WANT TO HEAR FROM YOU.
(LAUGHTER)
>> LOOK, WE ARE FIGHTING FOR
EVERY VOTE THAT WE CAN GET FROM
WOMEN, FROM MEN, STRAIGHT, GAY,
AFRICAN-AMERICANS, LATINOS,
ASIAN AMERICANS.
WE ARE TRYING TO BRING AMERICA
TOGETHER AROUND AN AGENDA THAT
WORKS FOR WORKING FAMILIES AND
THE MIDDLE CLASS.
I'M VERY PROUD IF MY MEMORY IS
NOT CORRECT, I THINK I AM, THAT
I HAVE A LIFETIME, I'VE BEEN IN
CONGRESS A FEW YEARS.
A LIFETIME 100% PROCHOICE VOTING
RECORD.
I AM VERY PROUD THAT OVER THE
YEARS WE HAVE HAD THE SUPPORT IN
MY STATE OF VERMONT FROM VERY
SIGNIFICANT MAJORITIES OF WOMEN.
I'M VERY PROUD THAT I SUPPORT
LEGISLATION THAT IS CURRENTLY IN
THE CONGRESS, SUPPORT OF ALMOST
ALL PROGRESSIVE DEMOCRATS IN THE
HOUSE AND SENATE WHICH SAYS WE
WILL END THE ABSURDITY OF WOMEN
TODAY MAKING 79 CENTS ON THE
DLOFER COMPARED TO MEN AND WE
WILL JOIN THE REST OF THE
OVER-- THE INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD
IN SAYING THAT PAID FAMILY AND
MEDICAL LEAVE SHOULD BE A RIGHT
OF ALL WORKING FAMILIES.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SENATOR, DO YOU
WORRY AT ALL THAT YOU WILL BE
THE INSTRUMENT OF THAT WARTING
HISTORY AS SENATOR CLINTON KEEPS
CLAIMING, THAT SHE MIGHT BE THE
FIRST WOMAN PRESIDENT?
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, I THINK FROM
AN HISTORICAL POINT OF VIEW
SOMEBODY WITH MY BACKGROUND,
SOMEBODY WITH MY VIEWS, SOMEBODY
WHO HAS SPENT HIS ENTIRE LIFE
TAKING ON THE BIG MONEY
INTERESTS, I THINK A SANDERS
VICTORY WOULD BE OF SOME
HISTORICAL ACCOMPLISHMENT AS
WELL.
(APPLAUSE)
>> YOU KNOW, I HAVE SAID MANY
TIMES, YOU KNOW, I'M NOT ASKING
PEOPLE TO SUPPORT ME BECAUSE I'M
A WOMAN.
I'M ASKING PEOPLE TO SUPPORT ME
BECAUSE I THINK I'M THE MOST
QUALIFIED, EXPERIENCED AND READY
PERSON TO BE THE PRESIDENT AND
THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
AND I APPRECIATE GREATLY SENATOR
SANDERS VOTING RECORD.
AND I WAS VERY PROUD TO GET THE
ENDORSEMENT OF THE PLANNED
PARENTHOOD ACTION FUND BECAUSE I
HAVE BEEN A LEADER ON THESE
ISSUES.
I HAVE GONE TIME AND TIME AGAIN
TO TAKE ON THE VESTED INTERESTS
WHO WOULD KEEP WOMENS' HEALTH
CARE DECISIONS THE PROVINCE OF
THE GOVERNMENT INSTEAD OF WOMEN
OURSELVES.
I'M VERY PROUD THAT NARAL
ENDORSED ME BECAUSE WHEN IT
COMES TO IT WE NEED A LEADER ON
WOMEN'S ISSUES.
SOMEBODY WHO YES VOTES RIGHT BUT
MUCH MORE THAN THAT, LEADS THE
EFFORTS TO PROTECT THE
HARD-FOUGHT GAINS THAT WOMEN
HAVE MADE, THAT MAKE NO MISTAKE
ABOUT IT, ARE UNDER TREMENDOUS
ATTACK.
NOT JUST BY THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES BUT BY A
WHOLE NATIONAL EFFORT TO TRY TO
SETBACK WOMEN'S RIGHTS.
SO I'M ASKING WOMEN, I'M ASKING
MEN, TO SUPPORT ME BECAUSE I'M
READY TO GO INTO THE WHITE HOUSE
ON JANUARY 20th, 2017 AND
GET TO WORK ON BOTH DOMESTIC AND
FOREIGN POLICY CHALLENGES.
>> Moderator: LAST COMMENT.
>> LET ME CONCUR WITH THE
SECRETARY, NO QUESTION WOMEN'S
RIGHTS ARE UNDER FIERCE ATTACK
ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY.
AND I WILL TELL YOU SOMETHING
THAT REALLY GALLS ME.
I WILL NOT SHOCK ANYBODY TO
SUGGEST THAT IN POLITICS THERE
IS OCCASIONALLY A LITTLE BIT OF
HYPOCRISY.
JUST A LITTLE BIT.
ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY WE HAVE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES FOR
PRESIDENT SAYING WE HATE THE
GOVERNMENT.
GOVERNMENT IS THE ENEMY.
WE'RE GOING TO CUT SOCIAL
SECURITY TO HELP YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO CUT MEDICARE AND
MEDICAID, FEDERAL AID TO
EDUCATION TO HELP YOU, BECAUSE
THE GOVERNMENT IS SO TERRIBLE.
BUT BY THE WAY, WHEN IT COMES TO
A WOMAN HAVING TO MAKE A VERY
PERSONAL CHOICE, AH, IN THAT
CASE, MY REPUBLICAN COLLEAGUES
LOVE THE GOVERNMENT AND WANT THE
GOVERNMENT TO MAKE THAT CLOIS
FOR EVERY WOMAN IN AMERICA.
IF THAT'S NOT HYPOCRISY, I DON'T
KNOW WHAT HYPOCRISY IS.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: THANK YOU BOTH.
WE TURN NOW TO THE FIRST OF
SEVERAL QUESTIONS FROM OUR
PARTNERS AT FACEBOOK.
THEY WERE SELECTED FROM A
CURATED GROUP OF PEOPLE.
WE'VE BEEN FOLLOWING OF
UNDECIDED VOTERS.
THE FIRST COMES FROM CLAUDIA, A
54 YEAR OLD WOMAN WHO WORKS AS A
PROGRAM MANAGER AT A PUBLIC
AFFAIRS CABLE NETWORK IN
MADISON, WISCONSIN.
AND SHE WRITES WISCONSIN IS
NUMBER ONE IN AFRICAN-AMERICAN
MALE INCARCERATION.
ACCORDING TO THE UNIVERSITY OF
WISCONSIN STUDY.
THEY FOUND THAT WISCONSIN'S
INCARCERATION RATE FOR BLACK MEN
WHICH IS AT 13% WAS NEARLY
DOUBLE THE COUNTRY'S RATE.
WHAT CAN WE DO ACROSS THE NATION
TO ADDRESS THIS.
SENATOR SANDERS.
>> THIS IS ONE OF THE GREAT
TRAGEDIES IN OUR COUNTRY TODAY.
AND WE CAN NO LONGER CONTINUE TO
SWEEP IT UNDER THE RUG.
IT HAS TO BE DEALT WITH.
TODAY A MALE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
BABY BORN TODAY STANDS A ONE IN
FOUR CHANCE OF ENDING UP IN
JAIL.
THAT IS BEYOND UNSPEAKABLE.
SO WHAT WE HAVE TO DO IS THE
RADICAL REFORM OF A BROKEN
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
(APPLAUSE)
WHAT WE HAVE TO DO IS END
OVERPOLICING IN AFRICAN-AMERICAN
NEIGHBORHOODS.
THE REALITY IS THAT BOTH
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITIES AND
THE WHITE COMMUNITY DO MARIJUANA
AT ABOUT EQUAL RATES.
THE REALITY IS FOUR TIMES AS
MANY BLACKS GET ARRESTED FOR
MARIJUANA.
TRUTH IS THAT FAR MORE BLACKS
GET STOPPED FOR TRAFFIC
VIOLATIONS.
THE TRUTH IS THAT SENTENCING FOR
BLACKS IS HIGHER THAN FOR
WHITES.
WE NEED FUNDAMENTAL POLICE
REFORM, CLEARLY, CLEARLY, WHEN
WE TALK ABOUT A CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
I WOULD HOPE THAT WE COULD ALL
AGREE THAT WE ARE SICK AND TIRED
OF SEEING VIDEOS ON TELEVISION
OF UNARMED PEOPLE OFTEN
AFRICAN-AMERICANS SHOT BY POLICE
OFFICERS.
WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO IS MAKE
IT CLEAR THAT ANY POLICE OFFICER
WHO BREAKS THE LAW WILL, IN
FACT, BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE.
(APPLAUSE)
>> YOU KNOW, I COMPLETELY AGREE
WITH SENATOR SANDERS.
THE FIRST SPEECH I GAVE IN THIS
CAMPAIGN BACK IN APRIL WAS ABOUT
CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORM AND
ENDING THE ERA OF MASS
INCARCERATION.
THE STATISTICS FROM WISCONSIN
ARE PARTICULARLY TROUBLING.
BECAUSE IT IS THE HIGHEST RATE
OF INCARCERATION FOR
AFRICAN-AMERICANS IN OUR NATION,
TWICE THE NATIONAL AVERAGE.
AND WE KNOW OF THE TRAGIC,
TERRIBLE EVENT THAT LEAD TO THE
DEATH OF DANTRE HAMILTON RIGHT
HERE IN MILWAUKEE.
A YOUNG MAN UNARMED, WHO SHOULD
STILL BE WITH US.
HIS FAMILY CERTAINLY BELIEVES
THAT.
AND SO DO I.
SO WE HAVE WORK TO DO.
THERE HAVE BEEN SOME GOOD
RECOMMENDATIONS ABOUT WHAT NEEDS
TO HAPPEN.
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S POLICING
COMMISSION CAME OUT WITH SOME.
I HAVE FULLY ENDORSED THOSE.
BUT WE HAVE TO RESTORE POLICING
THAT WILL ACTUALLY PROTECT THE
COMMUNITIES THAT POLICE OFFICERS
ARE SWORN TO PROTECT.
AND THEN WE HAVE TO GO AFTER
SENTENCING AND THAT'S ONE OF THE
PROBLEMS HERE IN WISCONSIN
BECAUSE SO MUCH OF WHAT HAPPENS
IN THE CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM
DOESN'T HAPPEN AT THE FEDERAL
LEVEL, IT HAPPENS AT THE STATE
AND LOCAL LEVEL.
BUT I WOULD ALSO ADD THIS.
THERE ARE OTHER RACIAL DISCEP
SEES, REALLY SYSTEMIC RACISM IN
THIS STATE AND IN OTHERS IN
EDUCATION, IN EMPLOYMENT, IN THE
KINDS OF FACTORS THAT TOO OFTEN
LEAD FROM A POSITION WHERE YOUNG
PEOPLE PARTICULARLY YOUNG MEN
ARE PUSHED OUT OF SCHOOL EARLY,
ARE DENIED EMPLOYMENT
OPPORTUNITIES.
SO WHEN WE TALK ABOUT CRIMINAL
JUSTICE REFORM AND ENDING THE
ERA OF MASS INCARCERATION.
WE ALSO HAVE TO TALK ABOUT JOBS,
EDUCATION, HOUSING AND OTHER
WAYS OF HELPING COMMUNITIES DO
BETTER.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SENATOR.
>> NOTHING, NOTHING THAT
SECRETARY CLINTON SAID DO I
DISAGREE WITH.
THIS MANDATORY SENTENCING, VERY
BAD IDEA.
TAKES AWAY DISCRETION FROM
JUDGES.
WE HAVE GOT TO DEMILL TARRIZE
LOCAL POLICE DEPARTMENTS SO THEY
DO NOT LOOK LIKE OCCUPYING
ARMIES.
(APPLAUSE)
WE HAVE GOT TO MAKE SURE THAT
LOCAL POLICE DEPARTMENTS LOOK
LIKE THE COMMUNITIES THEY SERVE
IN THEIR DIVERSITY.
(APPLAUSE)
AND WHERE WE ARE FAILING
ABYSMALLY IS IN THE VERY HIGH
RATE OF RECIDIVISM THAT WE SEE.
PEOPLE ARE BEING RELEASED FROM
JAIL WITHOUT THE EDUCATION,
WITHOUT THE JOB TRAINING,
WITHOUT THE RESOURCES THEY NEED
TO GET THEIR LIVES TOGETHER.
AND THEN THEY END UP, WE'RE
SHOCKED THAT THEY END UP BACK IN
JAIL AGAIN.
SO WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO.
BUT HERE IS THE PLEDGE THAT I
HAVE MADE THROUGHOUT THIS
CAMPAIGN.
AND IT'S REALLY NOT A VERY
RADICAL PLEDGE.
WHEN WE HAVE MORE PEOPLE IN
JAIL, DISPROPORTIONATELY
AFRICAN-AMERICAN AND LATINO,
THAN CHINA DOES, A COMMUNIST
AUTHOR TAIRIAN SOCIETY FOUR
TIMES OUR SIZE, HERE IS MY
PROMISE.
AT THE END OF MY FIRST TERM AS
PRESIDENT, WE WILL NOT HAVE MORE
PEOPLE IN JAIL THAN ANY OTHER
COUNTRY.
WE WILL INVEST IN EDUCATION AND
JOBS FOR OUR KIDS, NOT
INCARCERATION AND MORE JAILS.
>> Moderator: SECRETARY
CLINTON, I WAS TALKING RECENTLY
WITH A 23 YEAR OLD BLACK WOMAN
WHO VOTED FOR PRESIDENT OBAMA
BECAUSE SHE SAID THEY THOUGHT
RELATIONS BETWEEN THE RACES
WOULD GET BETTER UNDER HIS
LEADERSHIP.
AND HIS EXAMPLE.
HARDLY ANYONE BELIEVES THAT THEY
HAVE.
WHY DO YOU THINK RACE RELATIONS
WOULD BE BETTER UNDER A CLINTON
PRESIDENCY?
WHAT WOULD YOU DO THAT THE
NATION'S FIRST AFRICAN-AMERICAN
PRESIDENT HAS NOT BEEN ABLE TO?
>> WELL, I'M JUST NOT SURE I
AGREE COMPLETELY WITH THAT
ASSESSMENT.
I THINK UNDER PRESIDENT OBAMA WE
HAVE SEEN A LOT OF ADVANCES.
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT HAS
HELPED MORE AFRICAN-AMERICANS
THAN ANY OTHER GROUP TO GET
INSURANCE, TO BE TAKEN CARE OF.
BUT WE ALSO KNOW A LOT MORE THAN
WE DID.
WE HAVE A LOT MORE SOCIAL MEDIA.
WE HAVE EVERYBODY WITH A CELL
PHONE.
SO WE ARE SEEING THE DARK SIDE
OF THE REMAINING SYSTEMIC RACISM
THAT WE HAVE TO ROOT OUT IN OUR
SOCIETY.
I THINK PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS SET
A GREAT EXAMPLE.
I THINK HE HAS ADDRESSED A LOT
OF THESE ISSUES THAT HAVE BEEN
QUITE DIFFICULT.
BUT HE HAS GONE FORWARD.
NOW WHAT WE HAVE TO DO IS TO
BUILD ON AN HONEST CONVERSATION
ABOUT WHERE WE GO NEXT.
WE NOW HAVE MUCH MORE
INFORMATION ABOUT WHAT MUST BE
DONE TO FIX OUR CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
WE NOW HAVE SOME GOOD MODELS
ABOUT HOW BETTER TO PROVIDE
EMPLOYMENT, HOUSING AND
EDUCATION.
SO I THINK WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA
DID WAS TO EXEMPT FIE THE
IMPORTANCE OF THIS ISSUE AS OUR
FIRST AFRICAN-AMERICAN PRESIDENT
AND TO ADDRESS IT, BOTH FROM THE
PRESIDENT'S OFFICE AND THROUGH
HIS ADVO CASS-- ADVOCACY SUCH AS
WORKING WITH YOUNG MEN AND
MRS. OBAMA'S WORK WITH YOUNG
WOMEN.
BUT WE CAN'T REST.
WE HAVE WORK TO DO.
AND WE NOW KNOW A LOT MORE THAN
WE EVER DID BEFORE.
SO IT'S GOING TO BE MY
RESPONSIBILITY TO MAKE SURE WE
MOVE FORWARD TO SOLVE THESE
PROBLEMS THAT ARE NOW OUT IN THE
OPEN.
NOBODY CAN DENY THEM.
TO USE THE JUSTICE DEPARTMENT AS
WE JUST SAW WHERE THEY HAVE SAID
THEY'RE GOING TO SUE FERGUSON,
THAT ENTERED INTO A CONSENT
AGREEMENT AND THEN TRIED TO BACK
OUT.
SO WE'RE GOING TO ENFORCE THE
LAW.
WE'RE GOING TO CHANGE POLICING
PRACTICES, WE'RE GOING TO CHANGE
INCARCERATION PRACTICES BUT
WE'RE ALSO GOING TO EMPHASIZE
EDUCATION, JOBS AND HOUSING.
>> Moderator: SENATOR SANDERS.
>> WELL, I THINK JUDY WHAT HAS
TO BE APPRECIATED IS THAT AS A
RESULT OF THE DISASTROUS AND
ILLEGAL BEHAVIOR ON WALL STREET,
MILLIONS OF LIVES WERE HURT.
PEOPLE LOST THEIR JOBS, THEIR
HOMES, THEIR LIFESAVINGS.
TURNS OUT THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
AND THE LATINO COMMUNITY WERE
HIT ESPECIALLY HARD.
AS I UNDERSTAND IT THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY LOST
HALF OF THEIR WEALTH AS A RESULT
OF THE WALL STREET COLLAPSE.
SO WHEN YOU HAVE CHILDHOOD
AFRICAN-AMERICAN POVERTY RATES
OF 35%, WHEN YOU HAVE YOUTH
UNEMPLOYMENT AT 51%, WHEN YOU
HAVE UNBELIEVABLE RATES OF
INCARCERATION WHICH, BY THE WAY,
LEAVES THE CHILDREN BACK HOME
WITHOUT A DAD OR EVEN A MOTHER,
CLEARLY WE ARE LOOKING AT
INSTITUTIONAL RACISM.
WE ARE LOOKING AT AN ECONOMY IN
WHICH THE RICH GET RICHER AND
THE POOR GET POORER AND SADLY IN
AMERICA TODAY, IN OUR ECONOMY, A
WHOLE LOT OF THOSE POOR PEOPLE
ARE AFRICAN-AMERICAN.
>> Moderator: SO RACE RELATION
WAS BE BETTER UNDER A SANDERS
PRESIDENCY THAN THEY'VE BEEN?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
BECAUSE WHAT WE WILL DO IS SAY
INSTEAD OF GIVING TAX BREAKS TO
BILLIONAIRES, WE ARE GOING TO
CREATE MILLIONS OF JOBS FOR LOW
INCOME KIDS SO THEY'RE NOT
HANGING OUT ON STREET CORNERS.
WE'RE GOING TO MAKE SURE THAT
THOSE KIDS STAY IN SCHOOL OR ARE
ABLE TO GET A COLLEGE EDUCATION.
AND I THINK WHEN YOU GIVE
LOW-INCOME KIDS,
AFRICAN-AMERICAN, WHITE, LATINO
KIDS THE OPPORTUNITIES TO GET
THEIR LIVES TOGETHER, THEY ARE
NOT GOING TO END UP IN JAIL.
THEY'RE GOING TO END UP IN THE
PRODUCTIVE ECONOMY WHICH IS
WHERE WE WANT THEM.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: LET ME TURN THIS
ON ITS HEAD.
BECAUSE WHEN WE TALK ABOUT RACE
IN THIS COUNTRY, WE ALWAYS TALK
ABOUT AFRICAN-AMERICANS, PEOPLE
OF COLOR.
I WANT TO TALK ABOUT WHITE
PEOPLE, OKAY.
>> WHITE PEOPLE.
>> Moderator: I KNOW.
MANY PEOPLE WILL BE SURPRISED TO
FIND OUT THAT WE ARE SITTING IN
ONE OF THE MOST RACIALLY
POLARIZED METROPOLITAN AREAS IN
THE COUNTRY.
BY THE MIDDLE OF THIS CENTURY
THE NATION IS GOING TO BE
MAJORITY NONWHITE.
OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS ARE ALREADY
THERE.
IF WORKING CLASS WHITE AMERICANS
ARE ABOUT TO BE OUTNUMBERED, ARE
ALREADY UNDER EMPLOYED IN MANY
CASES AND ONE STUDY FOUND THEY
ARE DYING SOONER, DON'T THEY
HAVE A REASON TO BE RESENTFUL,
SENATOR, SECRETARY CLINTON?
>> LOOK, I'M DEEPLY CONCERNED
ABOUT WHAT IS HAPPENING IN EVERY
COMMUNITY IN AMERICA.
AND THAT INCLUDES WHITE
COMMUNITIES WHERE WE ARE SEEING
AN INCREASE IN ALCOHOLISM,
ADDICTION, EARLIER DEATHS,
PEOPLE WITH A HIGH SCHOOL
EDUCATION OR LESS ARE NOT EVEN
LIVING AS LONG AS THEIR PARENTS
LIVED.
THIS IS A REMARKABLE AND
HORRIFYING FACT.
AND THAT'S WHY I HAVE COME
FORWARD WITH, FOR EXAMPLE, A
PLAN TO REVITALIZE COAL COUNTRY.
THE COAL FIELD COMMUNITIES THAT
HAVE BNG SO HARD HIT BY THE
CHANGING ECONOMY, BY THE
REDUCTION IN THE USE OF COAL.
YOU KNOW COAL MINE ERRS AND
THEIR FAMILIES WHO HELP TURN ON
THE LIGHTS AND POWER OUR
FACTORIES FOR GENERATIONS ARE
NOW WONDERING, HAS OUR COUNTRY
FORGOT ENUS?
DO PEOPLE NOT CARE ABOUT ALL OF
OUR SACRIFICE.
AND I'M GOING TO DO EVERYTHING I
CAN TO ADDRESS DISTRESSED
COMMUNITIES.
WHETHER THEY ARE COMMUNITIES OF
COLOR, WHETHER THEY ARE WHITE
COMMUNITIES, WHETHER THEY ARE IN
ANY PART OF OUR COUNTRY.
I PARTICULARLY APPRECIATE THE
PROPOSAL THAT CONGRESSMAN JIM
CLYBURN HAS, THE 10, 20, 30
PROPOSAL TO TRY TO SPEND MORE
FEDERAL DOLLARS IN COMMUNITIES
WITH PERSISTENT GENERATIONAL
POVERTY.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT, IF YOU LOOK
AT THE NUMBERS, THERE ARE
ACTUALLY AS MANY IF NOT MORE
WHITE COMMUNITIES THAT ARE TRULY
BEING LEFT BEHIND AND LEFT OUT.
SO YES, I DO THINK IF WOULD BE A
TERRIBLE OVERSIGHT NOT TO FRIDAY
TO ADDRESS THE-- TO TRY TO
ADDRESS THE VERY REAL PROBLEMS
THAT WHITE AMERICANS,
PARTICULARLY THOSE WITHOUT A LOT
OF EDUCATION WHOSE JOBS HAVE NO
LONGER PROVIDED THEM OR EVEN NO
LONGER PRESENT IN THEIR
COMMUNITIES.
BECAUSE WE HAVE TO FOCUS WHERE
THE REAL HURT IS.
AND THAT'S WHY AS PRESIDENT, I
WILL LOOK AT COMMUNITIES THAT
NEED SPECIAL HELP AND TRY TO
DELIVER THAT.
PLAWS PLAWSES.
>> Moderator: SENATOR, I WANT
YOU TO RESPOND TO THAT BUT I
ALSO WANT YOU TO-- AM I WRONG.
IS IT EVEN RIGHT TO BE
DESCRIBING THIS AS A MATTER OF
RACE?
>> YEAH, YOU CAN.
BECAUSE AFRICAN-AMERICANS AND
LATINOS NOT ONLY FACE THE
GENERAL ECONOMIC CRISES OF LOW
WAGES AND HIGH UNEMPLOYMENT AND
POOR EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES,
BUT THEY FACE OTHER PROBLEMS AS
WELL.
SO YES, WE CAN TALK ABOUT IT AS
A RACIAL ISSUE.
BUT IT IS A GENERAL ECONOMIC
ISSUE.
AND HERE'S WHAT THE ECONOMIC
ISSUE IS.
THE WAGES THAT HIGH SCHOOL
GRADUATES RECEIVED TODAY ARE
SIGNIFICANTLY LESS WHETHER YOU
ARE WHITE OR BLACK THEN THEY
USED TO BE.
WHY IS THAT?
BECAUSE OF THE SERIES OF
DISASTROUS TRADE POLICIES WHICH
HAVE ALLOWED CORPORATE AMERICA
THROUGH NAFTA AND PERMANENT
NORMAL TRADE RELATIONS WITH
CHINA, SECRETARY CLINTON AND I
DISAGREE ON THOSE ISSUES.
BUT PLIE IDEA IS THAT THOSE
TRADE ISSUES HAVE FLAIBLED
CORPORATE AMERICA TO SHUT DOWN
IN THIS COUNTRY, SO MILLIONS OF
PEOPLE OUT ON THE STREET.
NO NO ONE THINKS WORKING IN THE
FACTORY IS THE GREATEST JOB IN
THE WORLD.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT, YOU CAN MAKE
A MIDDLE CLASS WAGE, YOU HAVE
DECENT HEALTH CARE, DECENT
BENEFITS.
YOU ONCE HAD A PENGS.
THOSE JOBS IN MANY CASES ARE NOW
GONE.
THEY'RE OFF TO CHINA.
NOW YOU ARE A WORKER, WHITE
WORKER, BLACK WORKER, WHO HAD A
DECENT JOB, THAT MANUFACTURING
JOB IS GONE.
WHAT ARE YOU DOING NOW, WORKING
IN MCDONALD'S.
THAT IS WHY THERE IS MASSIVE
DESPAIR ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY.
PEOPLE HAVE WORKED THEIR ENTIRE
LIVES.
THEY'RE MAKING A HALF, TWO
THIRDS WHAT THEY USED TO MAKE.
THEIR KIDS ARE HAVING A HARD
TIME FINDK ANY WORK AT ALL.
AND THAT'S WHY THIS STUDY WHICH
SHOWS THAT IF YOU CAN BELIEVE IT
TODAY FOR WHITE, WORKING CLASS
PEOPLE BETWEEN 45 AND 54, LIFE
EXPECTANCY IS ACTUALLY GOING
DOWN.
SUICIDE, ALCOHOLISM, DRUGS
THAT'S WHY WE NEED TO START
PAYING ATTENTION TO THE NEEDS OF
WORKING FAMILIES IN THIS COUNTRY
AND NOT JUST A HANDFUL OF
BILLIONAIRES WHO HAVE ENORMOUS
ECONOMIC AND POLITICAL POWER.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS, ONE OF THE
CAUSES OF ANXIETY FOR WORKING
CLASS AMERICANS IS CONNECTED TO
IMMIGRANTS.
PRESIDENT OBAMA AS YOU KNOW HAS
ISSUED EXECUTIVE ACTIONS TO
PERMIT SOME FIVE MILLION
UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS WHO ARE
LIVING NOW IN THE UNITED STATES
TO COME OUT OF THE SHADOWS
WITHOUT FEAR OF DEPORTATION TO
GET WORK PERMITS.
WOULD YOU GO FURTHER THAN THAT?
AND IF SO, HOW SPECIFICALLY
WOULD YOU DO IT?
SHOULD ANGRY UNDOCUMENTED FAMILY
WATCHING THIS DEBATE TONIGHT SAY
IN NEVADA REST EASY NOT FEAR OF
FURTHER DEPORTATIONS UNDER A
SANDERS PRESIDENCY?
>> THE ANSWER IS YES.
WE'VE GOT 11 MILLION
UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY.
I HAVE TALKED TO SOME OF THE
YOUNG KIDS WITH TEARS ROLLING
DOWN THEIR CHEEKS, ARE SCARED
TODAY THAT TODAY THEY MAY OR
THEIR PARENTS MAY BE DEPORTED.
I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE GOT TO
PASS COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM, SOMETHING THAT I
STRONGLY SUPPORTED.
I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE GOT TO
MOVE TOWARD A PATH TOWARD
CITIZENSHIP.
I AGREE WITH PRESIDENT OBAMA WHO
USED EXECUTIVE ORDERS TO PROTECT
FAMILIES.
BECAUSE THE CONGRESS, THE HOUSE
WAS UNABLE OR REFUSED TO ACT.
AND IN FACT I WOULD GO FURTHER.
WHAT WOULD MOTIVATE ME AND WHAT
WOULD BE THE "GUIDING LIGHT" FOR
ME IN TERMS OF IMMIGRATION
REFORM, JUDY, IS TO BRING
FAMILIES TOGETHER, NOT DIVIDE
THEM UP.
AND LET ME SAY THIS ALSO.
SOMEBODY WHO IS VERY FOND OF THE
PRESIDENT, AGREES WITH HIM MOST
OF THE TIME, I DISAGREE WITH HIS
RECENT DEPORTATION POLICIES.
AND I WOULD NOT SUPPORT THOSE.
BOTTOMLINE IS A PATH TOWARDS
CITIZENSHIP FOR 11 MILLION
UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE, IF CONGRESS
DOESN'T DO THE RIGHT THING, WE
USE THE EXECUTIVE ORDERS OF THE
PRESIDENT.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator:.
>> I STRONGLY SUPPORT THE
PRESIDENT'S EXECUTIVE ACTION.
I HOPE THE SUPREME COURT UPHOLDS
THEM.
I THINK THERE IS CONSTITUTIONAL
AND LEGAL AUTHORITY FOR THE
PRESIDENT TO HAVE DONE WHAT HE
DID.
I AM AGAINST THE RAIDS.
I'M AGAINST THE KIND OF INHUMANE
TREATMENT THAT IS NOW BEING
VISITED UPON FAMILIES, WAKING
THEM UP IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
NIGHT, ROUNDING THEM UP.
WE SHOULD BE DEPORTING
CRIMINALS, NOT HARDWORKING
IMMIGRANT FAMILIES WHO DO THE
VERY BEST THEY CAN AND OFTEN ARE
KEEPING ECONOMIES GOING IN MANY
PLACES IN OUR COUNTRY.
I'M A STRONG SUPPORTER OF
COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
HAVE BEEN EVER SINCE I WAS IN
THE SENATE.
I WAS ONE OF THE ORIGINAL
SPONSORS OF THE DREAM ACT.
I VOTED FOR COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM IN 2007.
SENATOR SANDERS VOTED AGAINST IT
AT THAT TIME.
BECAUSE I THINK WE HAVE TO GET
THE COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM WITH A PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP.
AND AS PRESIDENT I WOULD EXPAND
ENORMOUS ENERGY.
LITERALLY CALL EVERY MEMBER OF
CONGRESS THAT I THOUGHT I COULD
PERSUADE, HOPEFULLY AFTER THE
2016 ELECTION, SOME.
REPUBLICANS WILL COME TO THEIR
SENSES AND REALIZE WE ARE NOT
GOING TO DEPORT 11 OR 12 MILLION
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY.
AND THEY WILL WORK WITH ME TO
GET COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
(APPLAUSE)
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I DO HAVE
A DISAGREEMENT HERE.
IF MY MEMORY IS CORRECT, I THINK
WHEN WE SAW CHILDREN COMING FROM
THESE HORRENDOUS, HORRENDOUSLY
VIOLENT AREAS OF HONDURAS AND
NEIGHBORING COUNTRIES, PEOPLE
WHO ARE FLEEING DRUG VIOLENCE
AND CAR TELL VIOLENCE-- KARTDEL
VIOLENCE, I THOUGHT IT WAS A
GOOD IDEA TO ALLOW THOSE CLIRN
TO STAY IN THIS COUNTRY.
THAT WAS NOT AS I UNDERSTAND IT
THE SECRETARY'S POSITION.
IN TERMS OF 2007 IMMIGRATION
REFORM, YEAH, I DID VOTE AGAINST
IT.
I VOTED AGAINST IT BECAUSE THE
SOUTHERN POVERTY LAW CENTER
AMONG OTHER GROUPS SAID THAT THE
GUEST WORKER PROGRAMS THAT WERE
EMBEDDED IN THIS AGREEMENT WERE
AKIN TO SLAVERY.
WHERE PEOPLE CAME INTO THIS
COUNTRY TO DO GUEST WORK, WERE
ABUSED, WERE EXPLOITED.
AND IF THEY STOOD UP FOR THEIR
RIGHTS THEY WOULD BE THROWN OUT
OF THIS COUNTRY.
SO IT WASN'T JUST ME WHO OPPOSED
IT.
IT WAS LU LAC, ONE OF THE LARGE
LATINO ORGANIZATIONS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
IT WAS THE A.F.L./C.I.O. IT WAS
SOME OF THE MOST PROGRESSIVE
MEMBERS OF THE UNITIED STATES
CONGRESS WHO OPPOSED IT FOR THAT
REASON.
BUT WE ALL WHERE WE ARE RIGHT
NOW.
AND WHERE WE ARE RIGHT NOW IS WE
HAVE GOT TO STAND UP TO THE
TRUMPS OF THE WORLD WHO ARE
TRYING TO DIVIDE US UP.
WHAT WE HAVE TO DO RIGHT NOW IS
BRING OUR PEOPLE TOGETHER AND
UNDERSTAND THAT WE MUST PROVIDE
A PATH TOWARDS CITIZENSHIP FOR
11 MILLION UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE.
>> TWO QUICK RESPONSES.
ONE, WITH RESPECT TO THE CENTRAL
AMERICAN CHILDREN.
I MADE IT VERY CLEAR THAT THOSE
CHILDREN NEEDED TO BE PROCESSED
APPROPRIATELY.
BUT WE ALSO HAD TO SEND A
MESSAGE TO FAMILIES AND
COMMUNITIES IN CENTRAL AMERICA
NOT TO SEND THEIR CHILDREN ON
THIS DANGEROUS JOURNEY IN THE
HANDS OF SMUGGLERS.
I'VE ALSO CALLED FOR THE ENDS OF
FAMILY DETENTION, FOR THE ENDS
OF PRIVATELY RUN DETENTION
CENTERS ALONG WITH PRIVATE
PRISONS WHICH I THINK ARE REALLY
AGAINST THE COMMON GOOD AND THE
RULE OF LAW.
AND WITH RESPECT TO THE 2007
BILL, THIS WAS TED KENNEDY'S
BILL.
AND I THINK TED KENNEDY HAD A
VERY CLEAR IDEA ABOUT WHAT
NEEDED TO BE DONE.
AND I WAS PROUD TO STAND WITH
HIM AND SUPPORT IT.
(APPLAUSE)
>> LET ME JUST RESPOND.
I WORKED WITH TED KENNEDY.
HE WAS THE CHAIRMAN OF MY
COMMITTEE AND I LOVED TED
KENNEDY.
BUT ON THIS ISSUE, WHEN YOU HAVE
ONE OF THE LARGE LATINO
ORGANIZATIONS IN AMERICA SAYING
VOTE NO, THE AFL-CIO SAYING VOTE
NO, YOU HAVE LEADING PROGRESSIVE
DEMOCRATS, IN FACT, VOTING NO, I
DON'T APOLOGIZE FOR THAT VOTE.
BUT IN TERMS OF THE CHILDREN, I
DON'T KNOW TO WHOM YOU ARE
SENDING A MESSAGE.
WHO ARE YOU SENDING A MESSAGE
TOO?
THESE ARE CHILDREN WHO ARE
LEAVING COUNTRIES AND
NEIGHBORHOODS WHERE THEIR LIVES
ARE AT STEAK.
THAT WAS THE FACT.
I DON'T THINK WE USE THEM TO
SEND A MESSAGE.
I THINK WE WELCOME THEM INTO
THIS COUNTRY AND DO THE BEST WE
CAN TO HELP THEM GET THEIR LIVES
TOBLGHT.
>> WELL, THAT JUST WASN'T-- THAT
JUST WASN'T THE FACT, SENATOR.
THE FACT IS THAT THERE WAS A
GREAT EFFORT MADE BY THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION AND OTHERS TO
REALLY SEND A CLEAR MESSAGE
BECAUSE WE KNEW THAT SO MANY OF
THESE CHILDREN WERE BEING
ABUSED, BEING TREATED TERRIBLY
WHILE THEY TRIED TO GET TO OUR
BORDER.
SO WE HAVE A DISAGREEMENT ON
THIS.
I THINK NOW WHAT I HAVE CALLED
FOR IS COUNCIL FOR EVERY CHILD
SO THAT NO CHILD HAS TO FACE ANY
KIND OF PROCESS WITHOUT SOME ONE
WHO SPEAKS AND ADVOCATES FOR
THAT CHILD.
SO THAT THE RIGHT DECISION
HOPEFULLY CAN BE MADE.
>> IF YOU WOULD ALLOW ME NOW TO
MOVE ON.
WE'VE BEEN TALKING ABOUT
CHILDREN.
I WANT TO TALK ABOUT SENIORS.
THAT TAKES US TO OUR SECOND
FACEBOOK QUESTION, WHO WRITES MY
FATHER, SHE IS A 140 YEAR OLD
WOMAN WHO WORKS FOR A NONPROFIT
HERE IN MILWAUKEE.
SHE WRITES MY FATHER GETS JUST
$16 IN FOOD ASSISTANCE FOR MONTH
AS PART OF MEDICAID'S FAMILY
COMMUNITY PROGRAM IN MILWAUKEE
COUNTY FOR LOW INCOME SENIORS.
HOW WILL YOU AS PRESIDENT WORK
TO INSURE LOW INCOME SENIORS
GETS THEIR BASIC NEEDS MET.
START WITH YOU, SENATOR SANDERS.
>> OKAY.
YOU KNOW, YOU JUDGE A NATION NOT
BY THE NUMBER OF MILLIONARES AND
BILLIONAIRES IT HAS.
BUT BY HOW YOU TREAT, WE TREAT
THE MOST VULNERABLE AND FRAGILE
PEOPLE IN OUR NATION.
AND BY THOSE STANDARDS, WE'RE
NOT DOING PARTICULARLY WELL.
WE HAVE THE HIGHEST RATE OF
CHILDHOOD POVERTY AMONG ALMOST
ANY MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH.
AND IN TERMS OF SENIORS, THERE
ARE MILLIONS OF SENIORS, AND
I'VE TALKED TO THEM IN MY STATE
OF VERMONT AND ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY, WHO ARE TRYING TO GET
BY ON 11, 12, 13,000 A YEAR
SOCIAL SECURITY.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT, YOU DO THE
ARITHMETIC.
YOU CAN'T GET BY ON 11, 12, 13
THEU A YEAR.
AND HERE'S AN AREA WHERE
SECRETARY CLINTON AND I BELIEVE
WE HAVE A DIFFERENCE.
I HAVE LONG SUPPORTED THE
PROPOSITION THAT WE SHOULD LIFT
THE CAP ON TAXABLE INCOME COMING
INTO THE SOCIAL SECURITY TRUST
FUND, STARTING AT $250,000.
AND WHEN WE DO THAT, WE DON'T DO
WHAT THE REPUBLICANS WANT WHICH
IS TO CUT SOCIAL SECURITY, WE DO
WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WANT,
TO EXPAND SOCIAL SECURITY BY
1300 A YEAR FOR PEOPLE UNDER
16,000.
AND WE EXTEND THE LIFE OF SOCIAL
SECURITY FOR 58 YEARS.
YES, THE WEALTHIEST PEOPLE, THE
TOP ONE AND A HALF PERCENT WILL
PAY MORE IN TAXES.
BUT A GREAT NATION LIKE OURS
SHOULD NOT BE IN A POSITION
WHERE ELDERLY PEOPLE ARE CUTTING
THEIR PILLS IN HALF, WHERE THEY
DON'T HAVE DESENT NUTRITION,
WHERE THEY CAN'T HEAT THEIR
HOMES IN THE WINTERTIME.
THAT IS NOT WHAT AMERICA SHOULD
BE ABOUT.
IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, I WILL DO
EVERYTHING I CAN TO EXPAND
SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS, NOT
JUST FOR SENIORS BUT FOR
DISABILITY-- DISABLED VETERANS
AS WELL.
>> I THINK IT'S FAIR TO SAY WE
DON'T HAVE A DISAGREEMENT.
WE BOTH BELIEVE THERE HAS TO BE
MORE MONEY GOING INTO THE SOCIAL
SECURITY SYSTEM.
I SAID I'M LOOKING AT A COUPLE
OF DIFFERENT WAYS.
ONE WHICH YOU MENTIONED,
SENATOR.
BUT ALSO TRYING TO EXPAND THE
EXISTING TAX TO PASSIVE INCOME
THAT WEALTHY PEOPLE HAVE.
SO THAT WE DO GET MORE REVENUE
INTO THE SOCIAL SECURITY TRUST
FUND.
I HAVE A SLIGHTLY DIFFERENT
APPROACH, THOUGH, ABOUT WHAT WE
SHOULD DO WITH THAT INITIALLY.
FIRST RATHER THAN EXPAND
BENEFITS FOR EVERYONE, I DO WANT
TO TAKE CARE OF LOW INCOME
SENIORS WHO WORKED AT LOW-WAGE
JOBS.
I WANT TO TAKE CARE OF WOMEN
WHEN THE SOCIAL SECURITY PROGRAM
WAS STARTED IN THE 1930s, NOT
VERY MANY WOMEN WORKED.
AND WOMEN HAVE BEEN
DISADVANTAGED EVER SINCE.
THEY DO NOT GET ANY CREDIT FOR
THEIR CARE-TAKING
RESPONSIBILITIES.
AND THE PEOPLE WHO ARE OFTEN THE
MOST HARD-HIT IS WIDOWS BECAUSE
WHEN THEIR SPOUSE DIES, THEY CAN
LOSE UP TO ONE HALF OF THEIR
SOCIAL SECURITY MONTHLY PAYMENT.
SO WE HAVE NO DISAGREEMENT ABOUT
THE NEED TO BUTT RES SOCIAL
SECURITY, GET MORE REVENUE INTO
THE PROGRAM.
BUT I WANT TO START BY HELPING
THOSE PEOPLE WHO ARE MOST AT
RISK, THE ONES WHO YES, ARE
CUTTING THEIR PILLS IN HALF, WHO
DON'T BELIEVE THEY CAN MAKE THE
RENT, WHO ARE WORRIED ABOUT WHAT
COMES NEXT FOR THEM.
>> IN ALL DUE RESPECT--
(APPLAUSE)
>> IN ALL DUE RESPECT SECRETARY
CLINTON A LOT OF THE PROGRESSIVE
GROUPS, THE ONLINE GROUPS HAVE
REALLY ASKED YOU A SIMPLE
QUESTION.
ARE YOU COMING ON BOARD A
PROPOSAL, AND WHAT IS THAT
PROPOSAL.
NOW THE PROPOSAL THAT I HAVE
OUTLINED, YOU KNOW, SHOULD BE
FAMILIAR TO YOU BECAUSE IT IS
WHAT ESSENTIAL ESPECIALLY BARACK
OBAMA EXAINED PAY-- CAMPAIGNED
ON IN 2008.
YOU OPPOSED HIM THEN.
I WOULD HOPE THAT YOU WOULD COME
ON BOARD AND SAY THIS IS THE
SIMPLE AND STRAIGHT FORWARD
THING TO DO WE'RE ASKING THE TOP
ONE AND A HALF PERCENT INCLUDING
PASSIVE INCOME TO START PAYING A
LITTLE BIT MORE SO THAT THE
ELDERLY AND DISABLED VETS IN
THIS COUNTRY CAN LIVE WITH
SECURITY AND DIGNITY.
I HOPE YOU WILL MAKE A DECISION
SOON ON THIS.
>> SENATOR, LOOK, I THINK WE ARE
IN VIGOROUS AGREEMENT HERE.
WE BOTH WANT TO GET MORE REVENUE
IN.
I HAVE YET TO SEE A PROPOSAL
THAT YOU ARE DESCRIBING THAT THE
RACING THE CAP WOULD APPLY TO
PASSIVE INCOME.
THAT IS NOT BEEN.
>> THAT IS MY BILL.
>> THAT HAS NOT BEEN A PART OF
MOST OF THE PROPOSITIONALS THAT
I HAVE SEEN.
I'M INTERESTED IN MAKING SURE
THAT WE GET THE MAXIMUM AMOUNT
OF REVENUE FROM THOSE WHO CAN
WELL AFFORD TO PROVIDE IT.
SO I'M GOING TO COME UP WITH THE
BEST WAY FORWARD.
WE'RE GOING TO END UP IN THE
SAME PLACE.
WE'RE GOING TO GET MORE REVENUE.
I'M GOING TO PRIORITIZE THOSE
RECIPIENTS WHO NEED THE MOST
HELP FIRST.
>> WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON.
SECRETARY CLINTON YOUR CAMPAIGN
HAS RECENTLY RAMPED UP CRITICISM
OF SENATOR SANDERS FOR ATTENDING
DEMOCRATIC PARTY FUNDRAISERS
FROM WHICH YOU SAY EBEN FITTED.
BUT NEARLY HALF OF YOUR
FINANCIAL SECTOR DONATIONS
APPEAR TO COME FROM JUST TWO
WEALTHY FINANCE YEARS, GEORGE
SORROUS AND DONE ALT SUSMAN FOR
A TOTAL OF ABOUT $10 MILLION.
YOU HAVE SAID THAT THERE IS NO
QUID PRO QUO INVOLVED.
BUT IS THAT ALSO TRUE OF THE
DONATIONS THAT WEALTHY
REPUBLICANS GIVE TO REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES, CONTRIBUTORS
INCLUDING THE KOCH BROTHERS.
>> I CAN'T SPEAK FOR THE KOCH
BROTHERS.
ARE YOU REFERRING TO A SUPERPAC
THAT WE DON'T COORDINATE WITH,
THAT WAS SET UP TO SUPPORT
PRESIDENT OBAMA THAT HAS NOW
DECIDED THEY WANT TO SUPPORT ME.
THEY ARE THE ONES WHO SHOULD
RESPOND TO ANY QUESTIONS.
LET'S TALK ABOUT OUR CAMPAIGNS.
I'M VERY PROUD OF THE FACT THAT
WE HAVE MORE THAN 750,000
DONORS.
AND THE VAST MAJORITY OF THEM
ARE GIVING SMALL CONTRIBUTIONS.
SO I AM PROUD OF SENATOR
SANDERS, AND HIS SUPPORTERS.
I THINK IT'S GREAT THAT, YOU
KNOW, SENATOR SANDERS, PRESIDENT
OBAMA AND I, HAVE MORE DONORS
THAN ANY THREE PEOPLE WHO HAVE
EVER RUN AND CERTAINLY ON THE
DEMOCRATIC SIDE.
THAT'S THE WAY IT SHOULD BE.
AND I AM GOING TO CONTINUE TO
REACH OUT, TO THANK ALL MY
ONLINE CONTRIBUTORS FOR
EVERYTHING THEY ARE DOING FOR
ME.
TO ENCOURAGE THEM TO HELP ME AND
DO MORE.
JUST AS SENATOR SANDERS IS.
AND I THINK THAT IS THE REAL KEY
HERE.
WE BOTH HAVE A LOT OF SMALL
DONORS.
I THINK THAT SETS US APART FROM
A LOT OF WHAT IS HAPPENING ON
THE REPUBLICAN SIDE.
THE KOCH BROTHERS HAVE A VERY
CLEAR POLITICAL AGENDA.
IT IS AN AGENDA IN MY VIEW THAT
WOULD DO GREAT HARM TO OUR
COUNTRY.
WE'RE GOING TO FIGHT IT AS HARD
AS WE CAN.
AND WE'RE GOING TO FIGHT WHOEVER
THE REPUBLICANS NOMINATE WHO
WILL BE VERY DEPEND ENT UPON THE
KOCH BROTHERS AND OTHERS.
(APPLAUSE)
>> I'M ASKING IF DEMOCRATIC
DONORS ARE DIFFERENT FROM
REPUBLICAN DONORS.
>> WHAT WE ARE TALKING ABOUT IN
REALITY IS A CORRUPT CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM.
THAT IS WHAT WE ARE TALKING
ABOUT.
WE HAVE TO BE HONEST ABOUT IT.
AND IT IS UNDERMINING AMERICAN
DEMOCRACY.
WHEN EXTRAORDINARILY WEALTHY
PEOPLE MAKE VERY LARGE
CONTRIBUTIONS TO SUPERPACS AND
IN MANY CASES IN THIS CAMPAIGN,
SUPERPACS HAVE MORE MONEY, HAVE
RAISED MORE MONEY THAN
INDIVIDUAL CANDIDATES HAVE.
OKAY.
WE HAD A DECISION TO MAKE EARLY
ON.
DO WE DO A SUPERPAC.
AND SEA WE SAID NO.
WE DON'T REPRESENT WALL STREET.
WE DON'T REPRESENT THE
BILLIONAIRE CLASS SO TENDS UP
I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE UP HERE
OF THE MANY CANDIDATES, WHO HAS
NO SUPERPAC.
BUT WHAT WE DID IS WE SAID TO
THE WORKING FAMILIES OF THIS
COUNTRY LOOK, WE KNOW THINGS ARE
TOUGH.
BUT IF YOU WANT TO HELP US, GO
BEYOND ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS
AND ESTABLISHMENT ECONOMICS.
SEND US SOMETHING.
AND IT TURNS OUT THAT-- AND THIS
HAS BLOWN ME AWAY, NEVER IN A
MILLIONARES WOULD I HAVE
BELIEVED THAT I WOULD BE
STANDING HERE TONIGHT TELLING
YOU THAT WE HAVE RECEIVED
$APPROXIMATE MILLION MILLION-- 3
MILLION INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS
FROM WELL OVER A MILLION PEOPLE.
SECRETARY CLINTON'S SUPERPAC AS
I UNDERSTAND IT RECEIVED $25
MILLION LAST REPORTING PERIOD,
15 MILLION DOLLARS FROM WALL
STREET.
OUR AVERAGE CONTRIBUTION IS $27,
I'M VERY PROUD OF THAT.
>> Moderator: SENATOR,
SENATOR.
>> LET ME JUST RESPOND.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SENATOR SANDERS,
ARE YOU SAYING.
>> WE ARE MIXING APPLES AND
ORANGES.
MY 750,000 DONORS HAVE
CONTRIBUTED MORE THAN A MILLION
AND A HALF DONATIONS.
I'M VERY PROUD.
THAT I THINK BETWEEN THE TWO OF
US DEMG CRATE-- DEMONSTRATES THE
STRENGTH OF THE SUPPORT WE HAVE
AMONG PEOPLE WHO WANT TO SEE
CHANGE IN OUR COUNTRY.
BUT THE REAL ISSUE THAT I THINK
THE SENATOR IS INJECTING INTO
THIS IS THAT IF YOU HAD A
SUPERPACK LIKE PRESIDENT OBAMA
HAD WHICH NOW SAYS IT WANTS TO
SUPPORT ME, IT'S NOT MY PAC.
IF YOU TAKE DONATIONS FROM WALL
STREET, YOU CAN'T BE
INDEPENDENT.
I WOULD JUST SAY, I DEBATED THEN
SENATOR OBAMA NUMEROUS TIME ON
STAGES LIKE THIS.
AND HE WAS THE RECIPIENT OF THE
LARGEST NUMBER OF WALL STREET
DONATIONS OF ANYBODY RUNNING ON
THE DEMOCRATIC SIDE EVER.
NOW WHEN IT MATTERED, HE STOOD
UP AND TOOK ON WALL STREET.
HE PUSHED THROUGH AND HE PASSED
THE DODD-FRANK REGULATION, THE
TOUGHEST REGULATION SINCE THE
1930s.
SO LET'S NOT IN ANYWAY IMPLY
HERE THAT EITHER PRESIDENT OBAMA
OR MYSELF WOULD IN ANYWAY NOT
TAKE ON ANY VESTED INTEREST,
WHETHER IT'S WALL STREET OR DRUG
COMPANIES OR INSURANCE COMPANIES
OR FRANKLY, THE GUN LOBBY, TO
STAND UP TO WHAT TO DO WHAT IS
BEST FOR THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
(APPLAUSE)
>> BUT LET'S NOT-- LET'S NOT
INSULT-- LET'S NOT INSULT THE
INTELLIGENCE OF THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
PEOPLE AREN'T DUMB.
WHY "IN GOD'S NAME" DOES WALL
STREET MAKE HUGE CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS?
I GUESS JUST FOR THE FUN OF IT.
THEY WANT TO THROW MONEY AROUND.
WHY DOES THE SPHARK FARK
INDUSTRY MAKE-- PHARMACEUTICAL
MAKE-- PHARMACEUTICAL-- INDUSTRY
MAKE HUGE CAMPAIGN
DISTRIBUTIONS, ANY CONNECTION
MAYBE THAT OUR PEOPLE PAY THE
HIGHEST PRICES IN THE WORLD FOR
PRESCRIPTION DRUGS?  WHY DOES
THE FOSSIL FUEL INDUSTRY PAY
HUGE AMOUNTS OF MONEY ON
CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS.
ANY CONNECTION TO THE FACT THAT
NOT ONE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATE FOR
PRESIDENT THINKS AND AGREES WITH
THE SCIENTIFIC COMMUNITY THAT
CLIMATE CHANGE IS REAL?
AND THAT WE HAVE GOT TO
TRANSFORM OUR ENERGY SYSTEM?
AND WHEN WE TALK ABOUT WALL
STREET, LET'S TALK ABOUT WALL
STREET.
I VOTED FOR DO-- DODD-FRANK, IT
HAS AN IMPORTANT AMENDMENT IN
IT.
IN MY VIEW IT DOESN'T GO NEAR
FAR ENOUGH.
BUT WHEN WE TALK ABOUT WALL
STREET, YOU HAVE WALL STREET AND
MAJOR BANKS HAVE PAID $200
BILLION IN FINES SINCE THE GREAT
CRASH.
NO WALL STREET EXECUTIVE HAS
BEEN PROSECUTED.
>> LET'S JUST FOLLOW UP ON THIS.
BECAUSE YOU KNOW, I'VE MADE IT
VERY CLEAR THAT NO BANK IS TOO
BIG TO FAIL.
NO EXECUTIVE TOO POWERFUL TO
JAIL, AND BECAUSE OF DODD-FRANK,
WE NOW HAVE IN LAW A PROCESS
THAT THE PRESIDENT, THE FEDERAL
RESERVE AND OTHERS CAN USE IF
ANY BANK POSES A SYSTEMIC RISK.
I THINK THAT'S A MAJOR
ACCOMPLISHMENT.
I AGREE, HOWEVER T DOESN'T GO
FAR ENOUGH.
BECAUSE WHAT IT FOCUSES ON ARE
THE BIG BANKS WHICH SENATOR
SANDERS HAS TALKED ABOUT A LOT
FOR GOOD REASON.
I GO FURTHER IN THE PLAN THAT I
HAVE PROPOSED WHICH HAS BEEN
CALLED THE TOUGHEST, MOST
EFFECTIVE COMPREHENSIVE PLAN FOR
REIGNING IN THE OTHER RISKS THAT
THE FINANCIAL SYSTEM COULD FACE.
IT WAS AN INVESTMENT BANK LEEMAN
BROTHERS-- LEHMAN BROTHERS THAT
CONTRIBUTED TO OUR COLLAPSE.
IT WAS A BIG INSURANCE COMPANY,
AIG, IT WAS COUNTRYWIDE
MORTGAGE.
MY PLAN WOULD SWEEP ALL OF THEM
INTO A REGULATORY FRAMEWORK SO
WE CAN TRY TO GET AHEAD OF WHAT
THE NEXT PROBLEMS MIGHT BE.
AND I BELIEVE THAT NOT ONLY
BARNEY FRANK, PULL KRU GMAN AND
OTHERS HAVE SAID THAT WHAT I
PROPOSED IS THE MOST EFFECTIVE,
IT GOES IN THE RIGHT DIRECTION.
WE HAVE DODD-FRANK.
WE CAN USE IT TO BREAK UP THE
BANKS IF THAT'S APPROPRIATE.
BUT LET'S NOT KID OURSELVES.
AS WE SPEAK, THERE ARE NEW
PROBLEMS ON THE HORIZON.
I WANT TO GET AHEAD OF THOSE AND
THAT'S WHY I HAVE PROPOSED A
MUCH MORE COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH
TO DEAL WITH THIS.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: WE HAVE TO GO TO
A BREAK.
>> LET ME, RESPECTFULLY DISAGREE
WITH SECRETARY CLINTON HERE.
WHEN YOU HAVE THREE OUT OF THE
FOUR LARGEST FINANCIAL
INSTITUTIONS IN THIS COUNTRY
BIGGER TODAY THAN THEY WERE WHEN
WE BAILED THEM OUT BECAUSE THEY
WERE TOO BIG TO FAIL, WHEN YOU
HAVE SIX FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS
HAVING ASSETS EQUIVALENT TO 68%
OF THE GDP OF AMERICA, BY
ISSUING TWO THIRDS OF THE CREDIT
CARDS AND A THIRD OF THE
MORTGAGES, LOOK, I THINK IT
TEDDY ROOSEVELT WERE ALIVE TODAY
THAT GREAT TRUST BUSTER WOULD
HAVE SAID BREAK THEM UP.
I THINK HE WOULD HAVE BEEN
RIGHT.
I THINK HE WOULD HAVE SAID BRING
BACK A 21s CENTURY GLASS
STEAGALL LEGISLATION, I THINK
THAT WOULD HAVE BEEN RIGHT AS
WELL.
THAT'S MY VIEW.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: THANK YOU BOTH
STVMENT IS TIME FOR A BREAK.
AND WHEN WE COME BACK WE'RE
GOING TO TURN TO SOME NEW TOPICS
INCLUDING HOW THESE CANDIDATES
WILL KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
>> Moderator: THERE'S A LOT
MORE TO COME IN JUST A FEW
MINUTES.
STAY WITH US FOR MORE OF THE PBS
NEWSHOUR DEMOCRATIC
HAS SOME WORK TO DO.
>> Sreenivasan: WE'RE HEADED
BACK TO THE DEBATE, THANK YOU.
(APPLAUSE)
>> Ifill: WELCOME BACK TO THE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
BEFORE WE RETURN TO OUR
QUESTIONS, WE HAVE A FOLLOW UP
QUESTION FROM OUR FACEBOOK
GROUP.
AND IT IS TO SENATOR SANDERS.
SENATOR, IT COMES FROM BILL
CORFIELD, A 55 YEAR OLD MUSICIAN
FROM TROY, OHIO.
HE ASKS ARE THERE ANY AREAS OF
GOVERNMENT YOU WOULD LIKE TO
REDUCE?
>> I'M IN THE UNITED STATES
SENATE AND ANYONE WHO DOESN'T
THINK THAT THERE IS AN ENORMOUS
AMOUNT OF WASTE AND INEFFICIENCY
AND BUREAUCRACY THROUGHOUT
GOVERNMENT WOULD BE VERY, VERY
MISTAKEN.
I BELIEVE IN GOVERNMENT BUT I
BELIEVE IN EFFICIENT GOVERNMENT,
NOT WASTEFUL GOVERNMENT.
>> Moderator: HOW ABOUT YOU
SECRETARY CLINTON?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
AND YOU KNOW THERE ARE A NUMBER
OF PROGRAMS THAT I THINK ARE
DUPLICATIVE, REDUNDANT AND NOT
PRODUCING THE RESULTS PEOPLE
DESERVE.
THERE ARE A LOT OF TRAINING
PROGRAMS AND EDUCATION PROGRAMS
THAT I THINK CAN BE STREAM LINED
AND PUT INTO A MUCH BELTER FORE
MAT SO THAT IF WE DO CONTINUE
THEM THEY CAN BE MORE USEFUL IN
PUBLIC SCHOOLS, COMMUNITY
COLLEGES AND COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES.
I WOULD LIKE TO TAKE A HARD LOOK
AT EVERY PART OF THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT AND REALLY DO THE
KIND OF ANALYSIS A THAT WOULD
REBUILD SOME CONFIDENCE IN
PEOPLE.
THAT WERE TAKING A HARD LOOK
ABOUT WHAT WE HAVE.
YOU KNOW, AND WHAT WE DON'T NEED
ANY MORE.
AND THAT'S WHAT I INTEND TO DO.
>> IF YOU COULD JUST ANSWER THAT
WE HAVE ALSO GOT TO TAKE A LOOK
AT THE WASTE AND INEFFICIENCIES
IN THE DEPARTMENT OF DEFENSE
WHICH IS THE ONE MAJOR AGENCY OF
GOVERNMENT THAT HAS NOT BEEN
ABLE TO BE AUDITED.
AND I HAVE THE FEELING YOU ARE
GOING TO FIND A LOT OF COST
OVERRETURN THERE, AND A LOT OF
WASTE AND DUPLICATIVE
ACTIVITIES.
>> YOU SAID THE FIRST PART OF
THIS DEBATE TALKING ABOUT
DOMESTIC INSECURITY, THE SECOND
PART WE WANT TO TALK ABOUT ARE
FOREIGN POLICY INSECURITIES.
WE WANT TO START WITH A QUESTION
TO YOU SECRETARY CLINTON ABOUT
AMERICA'S ROLE IN THE WORLD.
AMERICANS ARE BECOMING
INCREASINGLY WORRIED THAT
ATTACKS ABROAD ARE COMING HOME.
THAT THEY ARE ALREADY IN FACT
HERE.
ACCORDING TO EXIT POLLS FROM
LAST WEEK, FROM EARLIER THIS
WEEK, MORE THAN TWO THIRDS OF
DEMOCRATS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE ARE
CONCERNED ABOUT SENDING THEIR
CHILDREN TO FIGHT IN WARS THEY
CAN'T WIN.
THEY FRET THAT THE NEXT ATTACK
IS JUST AROUND THE CORNER AND WE
ARE NOT READY.
ARE WE?
>> LOOK, I THINK WE ARE READIER
THAN WE USED TO BE.
BUT IT'S A CONSTANT EFFORT THAT
HAS TO BE UNDERTAKEN TO MAKE
SURE WE ARE AS READY AS WE NEED
TO BE.
WE HAVE MADE A LOT OF
IMPROVEMENTS IN OUR DOMESTIC
SECURITY SINCE 9/11.
AND WE HAVE BEEN ABLE TO FOIL
AND PREVENT ATTACKS YET WE SEE
THE TERRIBLE ATTACK IN SAN
BERNARDINO AND KNOW THAT WE
HAVEN'T DONE ENOUGH.
SO WE HAVE TO GO AFTER THIS BOTH
ABROAD AND AT HOME.
WE HAVE TO GO AFTER TERRORIST
NETWORKS PREDOMINANTLY ISIS,
THAT'S NOT THE ONLY ONE BUT
LET'S FOCUS ON THAT FOR A
MINUTE.
WE HAVE TO LEAD A COALITION THAT
WILL TAKE BACK TERRITORY FROM
ISIS, THAT IS PRINCIPLEFULLY AN
AMERICAN LEAD AIR CAMPAIGN THAT
WE ARE NOW ENGAGED IN.
WE HAVE TO SUPPORT THE FIGHTERS
ON THE GROUND, PRINCIPALLY THE
ARABS AND KURDS WHO ARE WILLING
TO STAND UP AND TAKE TERRITORY
BACK FROM RAQQA TO RAMADI.
WE HAVE TO CONTINUE TO WORK WITH
THE IRAQI ARMY SO THAT THEY ARE
BETTER PREPARED TO ADVANCE ON
SOME OF THE OTHER STRONGHOLDS
INSIDE IRAQ LIKE MOSU L WHEN
THEY ARE ABLE TO DO SO.
AND WE HAVE TO CUT OFF THE FLOW
OF FOREIGN FUNDING AND FOREIGN
FIGHTERS.
AND WE HAVE TO TAKE ON ISIS
ONLINE.
THEY ARE A SOPHISTICATED
PURVEYOR OF PROPAGANDA.
A CELEBRATOR OF VIOLENCE.
AN INSTIGATOR OF ATTACKS USING
THEIR ONLINE PRESENCE.
HERE AT HOME WE'VE GOT TO DO A
BETTER JOB COORDINATING BETWEEN
FEDERAL, STATE AND LOCAL LAW
ENFORCE.
WE NEED THE BEST POSSIBLE
INTELLIGENCE NOT ONLY FROM OUR
OWN SOURCES BUT FROM SOWRSZS
OVERSEAS THAT CAN BE A REALTIME
FUTION EFFORT TO GET INFORMATION
WHERE IT'S NEEDED.
THE FINAL THING I WANT TO SAY
ABOUT THERE IS THE FOLLOWING.
YOU KNOW, AFTER 9/11 ONE OF THE
EFFORTS THAT WE DID IN NEW YORK
WAS IF YOU SEE SOMETHING OR HEAR
SOMETHING SUSPICIOUS, REPORT IT.
AND WE NEED TO DO THAT
THROUGHOUT THE COUNTRY.
BUT WE NEED TO UNDERSTAND THAT
AMERICAN MUSLIMS ARE ON THE
FRONT LINE OF OUR DEFENSE.
THEY ARE MORE LIKELY TO KNOW
WHAT'S HAPPENING IN THEIR
FAMILIES AND THEIR COMMUNITIES.
AND THEY NEED TO FEEL NOT JUST
INVITED BUT WELCOMED WITHIN THE
AMERICAN SOCIETY.
SO WHEN SOMEBODY LIKE DONALD
TRUMP AND OTHERS--
(APPLAUSE)
STIRS UP THE DEM GOINGRY AGAINST
AMERICAN-- DERKSZ EMOGOGERY
AGAINST MUSLIMS THAT HURTS US AT
HOME IT IS NOT ONLY OFFENSIVE
BUT DANGEROUS.
AND THE SAME OVERSEAS WORK VE TO
PUT TOGETHER A COALITION OF
MUSLIM NATIONS.
I KNOW HOW TO DO THAT I PUT
TOGETHER THE-- THAT GOT US TO
THE NEGOTIATING TABLE TO PUT A
LID ON IRAN NEW CLEAR WEAPONS
PROGRAM.
AND YOU DON'T GO TELL MUSLIM
NATIONS YOU WANT THEM TO BE PART
OF A COALITION WHEN YOU HAVE A
LEADING CANDIDATE FOR PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES WHO INSULTS
THEIR RELIGION.
SO THIS HAS TO BE LOOKED AT
OVERALL AND WE HAVE TO GO AT IT
FROM EVERY POSSIBLE ANGLE.
>> Moderator: SENATOR
SANDERS,--
(APPLAUSE)
>> LET ME JUST SAY THIS.
WHAT A PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES HAS GOT TO DO, AND WHAT
IS HIS OR HER MAJOR, I THINK
RESPONSIBILITY, IS TO A, MAKE
CERTAIN THAT WE KEEP OUR PEOPLE
SAFE.
THAT WE WORK WITH ALLIES AROUND
THE WORLD TO PROTECT DEMOCRATIC
VALUES.
THAT WE DO ALL THAT WE CAN TO
CREATE A WORLD OF PEACE AND
PROSPERITY.
I VOTED AGAINST THE WAR IN IRAQ
BECAUSE I LISTENED VERY
CAREFULLY TO WHAT PRESIDENT BUSH
AND VICE PRESIDENT CHAINY HAD TO
SAY-- CHENEY HAD TO SAY AND I
DIDN'T BELIEVE THEM.
AND IF YOU GO TO MY WEBSITE
BERNIE SANDERS.COM, WHAT YOU
FIND IS NOT ONLY GOING TO HELP
LEAD THE OPPOSITION TO THAT WAR,
BUT MUCH OF WHAT I FEARED WOULD
HAPPEN, WHEN I SPOKE ON THE
FLOOR OF THE HOUSE, IN FACT, DID
HAPPEN IN TERMS OF THE
INSTABILITY THAT OCCURRED.  NOW
I THINK IN KIND OF A VAGUE WAY
OR NOT SO VAGUE WHERE SECRETARY
CLINTON AND I DISAGREE IS THE
AREA OF REGIME CHANGE.
THE TRUTH IS THAT A POWERFUL
NATION LIKE THE UNITED STATES
CERTAINLY WORKING WITH OUR
ALLIES, WE CAN OVERTHROW DIK
TAILTERS ALL OVER-- DICTATORS
ALL OVER THE WORLD.
AND GOD ONLY KNOWS SADDAM
HUSSEIN WAS A BRUTAL DICTATOR.
WE COULD THROW A SADZ TOMORROW
IF WE WANTED TO.
WE GOT RID OF QADDAFI.
BUT THE POINT ABOUT FOREIGN
POLICY IS NOT JUST TO KNOW THAT
YOU CAN OVERTHROW A TERRIBLE
DICTATOR, IT DID TO UNDERSTAND
WHAT HAPPENS THE DAY AFTER.
AND IN LIBYA, FOR EXAMPLE, THE
UNITED STATES, SECRETARY
CLINTON, AS SECRETARY OF STATE
WORKING WITH SOME OTHER
COUNTRIES DID GET RID OF A
TERRIBLE DICTATOR NAMED QADDAFI.
BUT WHAT HAPPENED IS THE
POLITICAL VACUUM DEVELOPED.
ISIS CAME IN, AND NOW OCCUPIES
SIGNIFICANT TERRITORY IN LIBYA.
AND IS NOW PREPARED UNLESS WE
STOP THEM, TO HAVE A TERRORIST
FOOTHOLD.
BUT THIS IS NOTHING NEW.
THIS HAS GONE ON 50 OR 6 O-- 60
YEARS WITH THE UNITED STATES HAS
BEEN INVOLVED IN OVERTHROWING
GOVERNMENTS.
BACK IN 19534.
NOBODY KNOWS WHO MOSADEQ WAS,
DEMOCRATICALLY ELECTED PRIME
MINISTER OF IRAN.
HE WAS OVERTHROWN BY BRITISH AND
AMERICAN INTERESTS BECAUSE HE
THREATENED OIL INTERESTS OF THE
BRITISH.
AND AS A RESULT OF THAT, THE
SHAH OF IRAN CAME IN, TERRIBLE
DICTATOR-- DICTATOR.
AS A RESULT OF THAT, YOU HAVE
THE IRANIAN REVOLUTION COMING
IN, AND THAT IS WHERE WE ARE
TODAY.
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES.
SO I BELIEVE AS PRESIDENT I WILL
LOOK VERY CAREFULLY ABOUT
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES.
I WILL DO EVERYTHING I CAN TO
MAKE CERTAIN THAT THE UNITED
STATES AND OUR BRAVE MEN AND
WOMEN IN THE MILITARY DO NOT GET
BOGGED DOWN IN WARFARE IN THE
MIDDLE EAST.
>> IF I COULD JUST RESPOND.
TWO POINTS.
ONE, SENATOR SANDERS VOTED IN
1998 ON WHAT I THINK IS FAIR TO
CALL A REGIME CHANGE RESOLUTION
WITH RESPECT TO IRAQ.
CALLING FOR THE END OF SADDAM
HUSSEIN'S REGIME.
HE VOTED IN FAVOR OF REGIME
CHANGE WITH LIBYA, VOTED IN FAIR
OF-- FAVOR OF THE SECURITY
COUNCIL, BEING AN ACTIVE
PARTICIPATE IN SETTING THE
PARAMETERS FOR WHAT WE WOULD DO.
WHICH OF COURSE WE FOLLOWED
THROUGH ON.
I DO NOT BELIEVE A VOTE IN 2002
IS A PLAN TO DEFEAT ISIS IN
2016.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT WE FOCUS ON
THE THREATS WE FACE TODAY.
AND THAT WE UNDERSTAND THE
COMPLICATED AND DANGEROUS WORLD
WE ARE IN.
WOULD PEOPLE GO TO VOTE IN
PRIMARIES OR CAUCUSES, THEY ARE
VOTING NOT ONLY FOR THE
PRESIDENT, THEY ARE VOTING FOR
THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
AND IT'S IMPORTANT THAT PEOPLE
REALLY LOOK HARD AT WHAT THE
THREATS AND DANGERS WE FACE ARE.
AND WHO IS BEST PREPARED FOR
DEALING WITH THEM.
AS WE ALL REMEMBER, SENATOR
OBAMA WHEN HE RAN AGAINST ME WAS
AGAINST THE WAR IN IRAQ.
AND YET WHEN HE WON, HE TURNED
TO ME TRUSTING MY JUDGEMENT, MY
EXPERIENCE, TO BECOME SECRETARY
OF STATE.
I WAS VERY HONORED TO BE ASKED
TO DO THAT AND VERY HONORED TO
SERVE WITH HIM THOSE FIRST FOUR
YEARS.
>> JUDY, IF I CAN, THERE IS NO
QUESTION SECRETARY CLINTON AND I
ARE FRIENDS.
AND I HAVE A LOT OF RESPECT FOR
HER.
THAT SHE HAS ENORMOUS EXPERIENCE
IN FOREIGN AFFAIRS.
SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOUR
YEARS.
YOU HAVE A BIT OF EXPERIENCE, I
WOULD IMAGINE.
BUT JUDGEMENT MATTERS AS WELL.
JUDGEMENT MATTERS AS WELL.
AND SHE AND I LOOKED AT THE SAME
EVIDENCE COMING FROM THE BUSH
ADMINISTRATION REGARDING IRAQ.
I LEAD THE OPPOSITION AGAINST
IT.
SHE VOTED FOR IT.
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY, IN TERMS
OF THE LIBYA RESOLUTION THAT YOU
HAVE NOTED BEFORE, THIS WAS A
VIRTUALLY UNANIMOUS CONSENT.
EVERYBODY VOTED FOR IT, WANTING
TO SEE LIBYA MOVE TOWARD
DEMOCRACY.
OF COURSE WE ALL WANTED TO DO
THAT.
THAT IS VERY DIFFERENT THAN
TALKING ABOUT SPECIFIC ACTION
FOR REGIME CHANGE WHICH I DID
NOT SUPPORT.
>> YOU DID SUPPORT A UVMENTD IN
SECURITY COUNCIL APPROACH WHICH
WE DID FOLLOW UP ON.
AND LOOK, I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
TO LOOK AT WHAT THE MOST PORNLT
COUNTERTERRORISM-- THE MOST
IMPORTANT COUNTERTERRORISM
JUDGEMENT OF THE FIRST FOUR
YEARS OF THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION WAS.
AND THAT WAS THE VERY DIFFICULT
DECISION AS TO WHETHER OR NOT TO
ADVISE THE PRESIDENT TO GO AFTER
BIN LADEN.
I LOOKED AT THE EVIDENCE.
I LOOKED AT THE INTELLIGENCE.
I GOT THE BRIEFINGS.
I RECOMMENDED THAT THE PRESIDENT
GO FORWARD.
IT WAS A HARD CHOICE.
NOT ALL OF HIS TOP NATIONAL
SECURITY ADVISORS AGREED WITH
THAT.
AND AT THE END OF THE DAY, IT
WAS THE PRESIDENT'S DECISION.
SO HE HAD TO LEAVE THE SITUATION
ROOM AFTER HEARING FROM THE
SMALL GROUP ADVISING HIM AND HE
HAD TO MAKE THAT DECISION.
I'M PROUD THAT HE GAVE HIM THAT
ADVICE.
AND I'M VERY GRATEFUL TO THE
BRAVE NAVY SEALS THAT CARRIED
OUT THAT MISSION.
>> JUDY, ONE VERY BRIEFLY.
>> Moderator: JUST A FINAL
WORD.
>> WHERE THE SECRETARY AND I
HAVE A VERY PROFOUND DIFFERENCE,
IN THE LAST DEBATE AND I BELIEVE
IN HER BOOK, VERY GOOD BOOK, BY
THE WAY, IN HER BOOK AND IN THIS
LAST DEBATE, SHE TALKED ABOUT
GEGHT THE APPROVAL OR THE
SUPPORT OR THE MENTORING OF
HENRY KISSING CERTIFICATE.
NOW-- KISSINGER.
AND YOU FIND IT REMEMBER A
MACING.
BECAUSE I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE THAT
HENRY KISSINGER WAS ONE OF THE
MOST DESTRUCTIVE SECRETARIES OF
STATE IN THE MODERN HISTORY OF
THIS COUNTRY.
(APPLAUSE)
>> I'M PROUD TO SAY THAT HENRY
KISSINGER IS NOT MY FRIEND.
I WILL NOT TAKE ADVICE FROM
HENRY KISSINGER.
AND IN FACT, KISSINGER'S ACTIONS
IN CAM BOD YA WHEN THE UNITED
STATES BOMBED THAT COUNTRY,
OVERTHROUGH THE PRINCE, CREATED
THE INSTABILITY FOR POL POT AND
THE CAM IRROUGE TO COME IN WHO
BUMPED SOME 3 MILLION NNTD
PEOPLE ONE OF THE WORST AGAIN O
SIGHS IN THE HISTORY OF THE
WORLD.
SO COUNT ME IN AS SOMEBODY WHO
WILL NOT BE LISTENING TO HENRY
KITIONER.
(APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: SECRETARY
CLINTON.
>> WELL, I KNOW JOURNALISTS HAVE
ASKED WHO YOU DO LISTEN TO ON
FOREIGN POLICY AND WE HAVE YET
TO KNOW WHO THAT IS.
>> WELL, IT AIN'T HENRY
KISSINGER, THAT'S FOR SURE.
>> THAT'S FINE.
I LISTEN TO A WIDE VARIETY OF
VOICES.
THAT HAVE EXPERTESE IN VARIOUS
AREAS.
I THINK IT IS FAIR TO SAY
WHATEVER THE COMPLAINTS THAT YOU
WANT TO MAKE ABOUT HIM ARE, THAT
WITH RESPECT TO CHINA, ONE OF
THE MOST CHALLENGING
RELATIONSHIPS WE HAVE, HIS
OPENING UP CHINA AND HIS ONGOING
RELATIONSHIP WITH THE LEADERS OF
CHINA IS AN INCREDIBLY USEFUL
RELATIONSHIP FOR THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
SO IF WE WANT TO PICK AND
CHOOSE, AND I CERTAINLY DO,
PEOPLE I LISTEN TO, PEOPLE I
DON'T LISTEN TO, PEOPLE I LISTEN
TO FOR CERTAIN AREAS, THEN I
THINK WE HAVE TO BE FAIR AND
LOOK AT THE ENTIRE WORLD BECAUSE
IT IS A BIG, COMPLICATED WORLD
OUT THERE.
>> IT IS.
>> YES, PEOPLE WE MAY DISAGREE
WITH ON A NUMBER OF THINGS, MAY
HAVE SOME INSIGHT, MAY HAVE SOME
RELATIONSHIP THAT ARE IMPORTANT
FORP THE PRESIDENT TO UNDERSTAND
IN ORDER TO BEST PROTECT THE
UNITED STATES.
(APPLAUSE)
>> I FIND A VERY DIFFERENT
HISTORICAL PERSPECTIVE HERE.
KISSINGER WAS ONE OF THOSE
PEOPLE DURING THE VIETNAM ERA
WHO TALKED ABOUT THE DOMINO
THEORY, NOT EVERYBODY REMEMBERS
THAT.
YOU DO, I DO.
THE DOMINO THEORY.
YOU KNOW, AS VIETNAM GOES,
CHINA, DA, DA, DA.
THAT IS WHAT HE TALKED ABOUT.
THE GREAT THREAT OF CHINA.
AND THEN AFTER THE WAR, THIS IS
THE GUY WHO, IN FACT, YES, YOU
ARE RIGHT, HE OPENED UP
RELATIONS WITH CHINA.
AND NOW PUSHED VARIOUS TYPE OF
TRADE AGREEMENTS RESULTING IN
AMERICAN WORKERS LOSING THEIR
JOBS AS CORPORATIONS MOVED TO
CHINA, THE TERRIBLE
AUTHORITARIAN DICTATORSHIP HE
WARNED US ABOUT, NOW HE IS
URGING COMPANIES TO SHUT DOWN
AND MOVE TO CHINA.
NOT MY KIND OF GUY.
>> Moderator: SENATOR, LET ME
MOVE ON TO ANOTHER COUNTRY WITH
WHICH THE U.S. HAS A COMPLICATED
RELATIONSHIP, SENATOR SANDERS,
AND THAT IS RUSSIA.
ON THE ONE HAND, WE ARE AWARE
THAT RUSSIA IS A COUNTRY THAT
THE UNITED STATES SNIEDS TO
COOPERATE WITH, JUST TONIGHT
SECRETARY OF STATE JOHN KERRY
HAS ANNOUNCED WHAT APPEARS TO BE
AN AGREEMENT WITH THE RUSSIANS
TO LEAD-- THAT COULD LEAD TOWARD
A CEASEFIRE IN SYRIA, WOULD BE
THE FIRST SESATION OF CONFLICT
IN THAT COUNTRY IN THAT CIVIL
WAR IN FIVE YEARS BUT IT COMES
AT A VERY HIGH PRICE.
BECAUSE NOT ONLY HAVE WE SEEN
THE DEATHS, THE REMOVAL OF SO
MANY PEOPLE, MILLIONS OF PEOPLE,
WE NOW SEE THE RUSSIANS IN THE
LAST FEW WEEKS HAVE BOMBED IN A
WAY THAT BENEFITS PRESIDENT
ASSAD, HAS NOT GONE AFTER ISIS.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS WHEN IT
COMES TO DEALING WITH RUSSIA,
HOW HARD ARE YOU PREPARED TO BE?
ARE YOU PREPARED TO INSTITUTE
FURTHER ECONOMIC SANCTIONS?
WOULD YOU BE PREPARED TO MOVE
MILITARILY IF RUSSIA MOVES ON
EASTERN EUROPE?
IT SEEMS TO ME THAT RUSSIA
RECENTLY HAS GOTTEN THE BETTER
OF THE UNITED STATES.
>> THIS IS WHAT I WOULD SAY.
IT IS A COMPLICATED
RELATIONSHIP.
I CONGRATULATE SECRETARY OF
STATE JOHN KERRY AND THE
PRESIDENT FOR WORKING ON THIS
AGREEMENT AS YOU'VE INDICATED.
WHAT IS HAPPENING IN SYRIA, THE
NUMBER OF PEOPLE, THE HUNDREDS
OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE
BEEN KILLED, MEN, WOMEN, 20,000
CHILDREN, THE PEOPLE WHO ARE
FORCED TO FLEE THEIR OWN
COUNTRY, IT IS UNSPEAKABLE.
IT IS A REAL HORROR.
NOW WHAT I THINK IS THAT RIGHT
NOW, WE HAVE GOT TO DO OUR BEST
IN TO DEVELOPING POSITIVE
RELATIONS WITH RUSSIA.
BUT LET'S BE CLEAR.
RUSSIA'S AGGRESSIVE ACTIONS IN
THE CRIMEA AND IN UKRAINE HAVE
BROUGHT ABOUT A SITUATION WHERE
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND NATO
CORRECTLY, I BELIEVE, ARE SAYING
YOU KNOW WHAT, WE WILL HAVE TO
BEEF UP OUR TROOP LEVEL, IN THAT
PART OF THE WORLD, TO TELL PUTIN
THAT HIS AGGRESSIVENESS IS NOT
GOING TO GO UNMATCHED.
THAT HE IS NOT GOING TO GET AWAY
WITH AGGRESSIVE ACTION.
I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE THAT PUTIN
IS DOING WHAT HE IS DOING
BECAUSE HIS ECONOMY IS
INCREASINGLY IN SHAMABLES AND
HE'S TRYING TO RALLY HIS PEOPLE
IN SUPPORT OF HIM.
BUT BOTTOMLINE IS THE PRESIDENT
IS RIGHT.
WE HAVE TO PUT MORE MONEY.
WE HAVE TO WORK WITH
NATIONALA-- NATO TO PROTECT
EASTERN EUROPE AGAINST ANY KIND
OF RUSSIAN AGGRESSION.
>> WITH RESPECT TO SYRIA, I
REALLY DO APPRECIATE THE EFFORTS
THAT SECRETARY KERRY HAS MADE.
THE AGREEMENT ON HUMANITARIAN
RELIEF NOW NEEDS TO BE
IMPLEMENTED BECAUSE THERE ARE
ENCLAVES THAT ARE LITERALLY
FILLED WITH STARVING PEOPLE
THROUGHOUT SYRIA.
THE AGREEMENT ON A CEASEFIRE
THOUGH IS SOMETHING THAT HAS TO
BE IMPLEMENTED MORE QUICKLY THAN
THE SCHEDULE THAT THE RUSSIANS
AGREED TO.
THE RUSSIANS WANTED TO BUY TIME.
ARE THEY BUYING TIME TO CONTINUE
THEIR BOMBARDMENT ON BEHALF OF
THE ASSAD REGIME TO FURTHER
DECIMATE WHAT IS LEFT OF THE
OPPOSITION, WHICH WOULD BE A
GRAVE DISSERVICE TO ANY KIND OF
EVENTUAL CEASEFIRE.
SO I KNOW SECRETARY KERRY IS
WORKING EXTREMELY HARD TO TRY TO
MOVE THAT CEASEFIRE UP AS
QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE.
BUT I WOULD ADD THIS, YOU KNOW,
THE SECURITY COUNCIL FINALLY GOT
AROUND TO ADOPTING A RESOLUTION.
AT THE CORE OF THAT RESOLUTION
IS AN AGREEMENT I NEGOTIATED IN
JUNE OF 2012 IN GENEVA WHICH
SETS FORTH A CEASEFIRE AND
MOVING TOWARD A POLITICAL
RESOLUTION.
TRYING TO BRING THE PARTIES AT
STAKE IN SYRIA TOGETHER.
THIS IS INCREDIBLY COMPLICATED
BECAUSE WE'VE GOT IRAN AS A BIG
PLAYER, IN ADDITION TO RUSSIA.
WE HAVE SAUDI ARABIA, TURKEY AND
OTHERS WHO HAVE VERY IMPORTANT
ISSUES IN THEIR VIEW.
THIS IS ONE OF THE AREAS I HAVE
DISAGREED WITH SENATOR SANDERS
ON WHO HAS CALLED FOR IRANIAN
TROOPS TRYING TO END THE CIVIL
WAR IN SYRIA WHICH I THINK WOULD
BE A GRAVE MISTAKE, PUTTING
IRANIAN TROOPS RIGHT ON THE
BORDER OF THE GOLAN RIGHT NEXT
TO ISRAEL WOULD BE A NONSTARTER
FOR ME.
TRYING TO GET IRAN AND SAUDI
ARABIA TO WORK TOGETHER AS HE
HAS SUGGESTED IN THE PAST IS
EQUALLY A NONSTARTER.
SO LET'S' SUPPORT WHAT SECRETARY
KERRY AND THE PRESIDENT ARE
DOING BUT LET'S HOPE THAT WE CAN
ACCELERATE THE CEASEFIRE BECAUSE
I FEAR THAT THE RUSSIANS WILL
CONTINUE THEIR BOMBS.
TRY TO DO EVERYTHING THEY CAN TO
DESTROY WHAT'S LEFT OF THE
OPPOSITION AND REMEMBER THE
RUSSIANS HAVE NOT GONE AFTER
ISIS OR ANY OF THE OTHER
TERRORIST GROUPS.
SO AS WE GET A CEASEFIRE AND
MAYBE SOME HUMANITARIAN
CORRIDORS, THAT STILL LEAVES THE
TERRORIST GROUPS ON THE DOOR
STEP OF OTHERS IN SYRIA, TURKEY,
LEBANON, JORDAN AND THE LIKE.
SO WE'VE GOT SOME REAL WORK TO
DO AND LET'S TRY TO MAKE SURE WE
ACTUALLY IMPLEMENT WHAT HAS BEEN
AGREED TO WITH THE RUSSIANS.
(APPLAUSE)
>> LET ME JUST SAY THIS.
FOR A START THE SECRETARY AND I
DISAGREE AND I THINK THE
PRESIDENT DOES NOT AGREE WITH
HER.
IN TERMS OF THE CONCEPT OF A
NO-FLY ZONE IN SYRIA.
I THINK YOU DO HAVE A
HUMANITARIAN TRAGEDY THERE AS I
MENTIONED A MOMENT AGO.
I APPLAUD SECRETARY KERRY AND
THE PRESIDENT FOR TRYING TO PUT
TOGETHER THIS AGREEMENT.
LET'S HOPE THAT IT HOLDS.
BUT FURTHER MORE WHAT WE HAVE
GOT TO DO I'M SORRY, YEAH, I DO
BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO
EVERYTHING THAT WE CAN AND IT
WILL NOT HAPPEN TOMORROW.
BUT I DO HOPE THAT IN YEARS TO
COME, JUST AS THE KURD
WITH-- JUST AS OCCURRED WITH
CUBA, 10, 20 YEARS AGO, PEOPLE
SAID REACH NORMALIZED RELATIONS
WITH CUBA.
AND BY THE WAY I HOPE WE CAN END
THE TRADE EMBARGO WITH CUBA AS
WELL.
BUT THE IDEA THAT WE SOME DAY
MAYBE HAVE DECENT RELATIONS WITH
IRAN, MAYBE PUT PRESSURE ON THEM
SO THEY END THEIR SUPPORT FOR
TERRORISM AROUND THE WORLD,
YEAH, THAT IS SOMETHING I WANT
TO ACHIEVE.
AND I BELIEVE THAT THE BEST WAY
TO DO THAT IS TO BE AGGRESSIVE,
TO BE PRINCIPALLED BUT TO HAVE
THE GOAL OF TRYING TO IMPROVE
RELATIONS.
THAT'S HOW YOU MAKE PEACE IN THE
WORLD.
YOU SIT DOWN AND YOU WORK WITH
PEOPLE, YOU MAKE DEMANDS OF
PEOPLE, IN THIS CASE DEMANDING
IRAN STOP THE SUPPORT OF
INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM.
>> WELL, I RESPECTFULLY
DISAGREE.
I THINK WE HAVE ACHIEVED A GREAT
DEAL WITH THE IRANIAN NEW CLEAR
AGREEMENT TO PUT A LID ON THE
IRANIAN NEW CLEAR WEAPONS
PROGRAM.
THAT HAS TO BE ENFORCED.
ABSOLUTELY WITH CONSEQUENCES FOR
IRAN AT THE SLIGHTEST DEVIATION
FROM THEIR REQUIREMENTS UNDER
THE AGREEMENT.
I DO NOT THINK WE SHOULD PROMISE
OR EVEN LOOK TOWARD NORMALIZING
RELATIONS BECAUSE WE HAVE A LOT
OF OTHER BUSINESS TO GET DONE
WITH IRAN.
YES, THEY HAVE TO STOP BEING THE
MAIN STATE SPONSOR OF TERRORISM.
YES, THEY HAVE TO STOP TRYING TO
DESTABILIZE THE MIDDLE EAST
CAUSING EVEN MORE CHAOS.
YES, THEY'VE GOT TO GET OUT OF
SYRIA.
THEY'VE GOT TO QUIT SPONSORING
HEZBOLLAH AND HAMAS.
THEY HAVE TO QUIT TRYING TO SHIP
ROCKETS INTO GAZA THAT CAN BE
USED AGAINST ISRAEL.
WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO WITH
IRAN BEFORE WE EVER SAY THAT
THEY COULD MOVE TOWARD
NORMALIZED RELATIONS WITH US.
(APPLAUSE)
>> WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO.
WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO.
BUT I RECALL WHEN SECRETARY
CLINTON RAN AGAINST STHEN
SENATOR OBAMA, SHE WAS CRITICAL
OF HIM FOR SUGGESTING THAT MAYBE
YOU WANT TO TALK TO IRAN, THAT
YOU WANT TO TALK TO OUR ENEMIES.
I HAVE NO ILLUSION.
OF COURSE YOU ARE RIGHT.
I RAN IS SPONSORING TERRORISM IN
MANY PARTS OF THE WORLD,
DESTABILIZING AREAS.
EVERYBODY KNOWS THAT.
BUT OUR GOAL IS, IN FACT, TO TRY
OVER A PERIOD OF TIME TO, IN
FACT, DEAL WITH OUR ENEMIES, NOT
JUST IGNORE THAT.
>> Moderator: FINAL COMMENT.
>> QUOTE-- THE QUESTION WAS
WOULD YOU MEET WITH AN ADVERSARY
WITHOUT CONDITIONS.
I SAID NO.
AND IN FACT IN OT BAMA
ADMINISTRATION, WE DID NOT MEET
WITH ANYBODY WITHOUT CONDITIONS.
THAT IS THE APPROPRIATE APPROACH
IN ORDER TO GET THE RESULTS THAT
YOU ARE SEEKING.
(APPLAUSE)
>> I THINK THE IDEA WAS THAT
PRESIDENT-- THEN SENATOR OBAMA
WAS WRONG FOR SUGGESTING THAT IT
IS A GOOD IDEA TO TALK TO YOUR
OPPONENTS.
IT IS EASY TO TALK TO YOUR
FRIENDS.
IT'S HARDER TO TALK TO YOUR
ENEMIES.
I THINK WE SHOULD DO BOTH.
>> Moderator: LET ME MOVE ON.
YOU BOTH MENTIONED THE
HUMANITARIAN TRAGEDIES WHICH
HAVE BEEN AN YOUTH GROWTH IN
PART OF WHAT HAS HAPPENED IN SIR
WHY AND LIBYA.
MORE THAN A MILLION REFUGEES
ENTERED EUROPE IN 2015.
ANOTHER 76,000 JUST LAST MONTH,
THAT IS ABOUT 2,000 ARRIVALS
EVERY DAY.
NEARLY 400 PEOPLE HAVE BEEN LOST
AT SEA SO FAR THIS YEAR,
CROSSING THE MEDITERRANEAN.
AND THERE ARE REPORTS THAT TEN
THOUSAND CHILDREN ARE MISSING.
IF WE ARE LEADERS IN THIS WORLD,
WHERE SHOULD THE U.S. BE ON
THIS?
WHAT SHOULD THE UNITED STATES BE
DOING SECRETARY CLINTON?
>> WELL, I WAS PLEASED THAT NATO
ANNOUNCED YUS THIS WEEK THAT
THEY'RE GOING TO START DOING
PATROLS IN THE MEDITERRANEAN IN
THE AEGAN TO TRY TO INTERDICT
THE SMUGGLERS, TO TRY TO
PREVENTD THE KIND OF TRAGEDIES
THAT WE HAVE SEEN ALL TOO OFTEN.
ALSO TO TRY TO PREVENT MORE
REFUGEES FROM COMING TO THE
EUROPEAN UNION.
AND IT'S ESPECIALLY SIGNIFICANT
THAT THEY ARE WORKING WITH BOTH
TURKEY AND GREECE IN ORDER TO DO
THIS.
WITH RESPECT TO THE UNITED
STATES, I THINK OUR ROLE IN
NATO, OUR SUPPORT FOR THE EU AS
WELL AS OUR WILLINGNESS TO TAKE
REFUGEES SO LONG AS THEY ARE
THOROUGHLY VETTED AND THAT WE
HAVE CONFIDENCE FROM
INTELLIGENCE AND OTHER SOURCES
THAT THEY CAN COME TO OUR
COUNTRY, WE SHOULD BE DOING OUR
PART.
AND WE SHOULD BACK UNDER THE
RECENT DOARNS CONFERENCE TO MAKE
SURE WE HAVE MADE OUR
CONTRIBUTION TO TRY TO DEAL WITH
THE ENORMOUS COST THAT THESE
REFUGEES ARE POSING TO TURKEY
AND TO MEMBERS OF THE EU IN
PARTICULAR.
THIS IS A HUMANITARIAN
CATASTROPHE.
THERE IS NO OTHER KRIPTION OF
IT.
SO WE DO AT THE UNITED STATES
HAVE TO SUPPORT OUR FRIENDS, OUR
ALLIES IF EUROPE.
WE HAVE TO STAND WITH THEM.
WE HAVE TO PROVIDE FINANCIAL
SUPPORT TO THEM.
WE HAVE TO PROVIDE THE NATO
SUPPORT TO BACK UP THE MISSION
THAT IS GOING ON.
AND WE HAVE TO TAKE PROPERLY
VETTED REFUGEES OURSELVE.
>> A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO I HAD
THE OPPORTUNITY TO GO ON A
CONGRESSIONAL DELEGATION.
AND I WENT TO ONE OF THESE
TURKISH REFUGEE CAMPS RIGHT ON
THE BOORDER-- BORPDER OF SYRIA.
AND WHAT A SAD SIGHT THAT WAS.
MEN, WOMEN, CHILDREN, FORCED OUT
OF THEIR HOMES.
AND TURKEY BY THE WAY DID A VERY
DECENT THING PROVIDING WHAT WAS
REASONABLE HOUSING AND
CONDITIONS FOR THOSE PEOPLE.
IT SEEMS TO ME THAT GIVEN OUR
HISTORY, AS A NATION THAT HAS
BEEN A BEACON OF HOPE FOR THE
OPPRESSED, FOR THE DOWN TRODEN,
THAT I VERY STRONGLY DISAGREE
WITH THOSE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES
WHO SAY YOU KNOW WHAT, WE'VE GOT
TO TURN OUR BACKS ON WOMEN AND
CHILDREN WHO LEFT THEIR HOME
WITH NOTHING, NOTHING AT ALL.
THAT IS NOT WHAT AMERICA IS
SUPPOSED TO BE ABOUT.
SO I BELIEVE THAT WORKING WITH
EUROPE AND BY THE WAY, YOU KNOW,
WE'VE GOT SOME VERY WEALTHY
COUNTRY THERE IN THAT PART OF
THE WORLD.
YOU HAVE YOU CAN WAIT AND QATAR
AND YOU'VE GOT SAUDI ARABIA.
THEY HAVE A RESPONSIBILITY AS
WELL.
BUT I THINK THIS IS A WORLD
WIDE, THAT THE ENTIRE WORLD
NEEDS TO COME TOGETHER TO DEAL
WITH THIS HORRIFIC REFUGEE
CRISIS WE'RE SEEING FROM SYRIA
AND AFGHANISTAN AS WELL.
>> Moderator: AND WE HAVE A
FINAL QUESTION FROM OUR FACEBOOK
FAMILY.
AND IT GOES TO SENATOR SANDERS.
IT COMES IN ROBERT AN GREECE
SHALL-- ANDREAS 40EU YEAR OLD
STAY AT HOME DAD IN COVER,
MASS-- DOVER, MASSACHUSETTS.
HE SAYS THE WORLD HAS SEEN MANY
GREAT LEADERS IN THE WORLD OF
HISTORY, CAN YOU NAME TWO
LEADERS ONE AMERICAN AND ONE
FOREIGN WHO WOULD INFLUENCE YR
FOREIGN POLICY DECISIONS AND WHY
DO YOU SEEP THEM-- WHY ARE THEY
INFLUENTIAL?
>> YOU KNOW FRANKLIN ROOSEVELT
TOOK THE OATH OF OFFICE IN 1933
AT A TIME WHEN 25% OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE WERE UNEMPLOYED,
COUNTRY WAS IN INCREDIBLE
DESPAIR.
HE STOOD BEFORE THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE AND HE SAID THE ONLY
THING WE HAVE TO FEAR IS FEAR
ITSELF.
A PROFOUND STATEMENT THAT GAVE
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE THE COURAGE
TO BELIEVE THAT YES, WE COULD
GET OUT OF THAT TERRIBLE
DEPRESSION.
AND THEN WHAT HE DID IS REDEFINE
THE ROLE OF GOVERNMENT.
YOU HAD HERBERT HOOVER BEFORE
THAT SAYING NO, YOU HAVE TO ONLY
WORRY ABOUT THE DEFICIT.
SO WHAT IF MASS UNEMPLOYMENT
EXISTS, SO WHAT IF CHILDREN ARE
GOING HUNGRY.
THAT IS NOT THE ROLE OF THE
GOVERNMENT.
AND WHEN FDR SAID YEAH T IS,
THAT WE ARE GOING TO USE ALL OF
THE RESOURCES THAT WE HAVE TO
CREATE JOBS, TO BUILD HOMES, TO
FEED PEOPLE, TO PROTECT THE
FARMERS, WE ARE A NATION WHICH
IF WE COME TOGHTD-- TOGETHER
THERE IS NOTHING THAT WE COULD
NOT ACCOMPLISH.
AND KIND OF THAT IS WHAT I SEE
OUR CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT RIGHT NOW.
IN THIS PARTICULAR MOMENT OF
SERIOUS CRISES, SAYING TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE DON'T GIVE UP ON
THE POLITICAL PROCESSMENT DON'T
LISTEN TO THE TRUMPS OF THE
WORLD AND ALLOWING THEM TO
DIVIDE US.
IF WE REENGAGE AND GET INVOLVED,
YEAH, WE CAN HAVE HEALTH CARE
FOR ALL PEOPLE.
WE CAN MAKE PUBLIC COLLEGES AND
UNIVERSITIES TUITION FREE.
WE DO NOT HAVE TO HAVE MASSIVE
LEVELS OF INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY, IN THE SAME LIGHT AS
THE FOREIGN LEADER.
WINSTON CHURCH ILL'S POLITICS
WERE NOT MY POLL TIKS.
HE WAS KIND OF A CONSERVATIVE
GUY IN MANY RESPECTS.
BUT NOBODY CAN DENY THAT AS A
BAR TIME LEADER, HE RALLIED THE
BRITISH PEOPLE WHEN THEY STOOD
VIRTUALLY ALONE AGAINST THE NAZI
JUGGER NAUGHT AND RALLIED THEM
AND EVENTUALLY WON AN
EXTRAORDINARY VICTORY.
THOSE ARE TWO LEADERS THAT I
ADMIRE VERY MUCH.
(APPLAUSE)
>> I CERTAINLY AGREE WZ FDR FOR
ALL THE REASONS SENATOR SANDERS
SAID.
AND I AGREE ABOUT THE ROAM THAT
HE PLAYED BOTH IN WAR AND IN
PEACE ON THE ECONOMY AND IN
DEFEATING FASHISM AROUND THE
WORLD.
I WOULD CHOOSE NELSON MANDELA
FOR HIS GENEROSITY OF HEART, HIS
UNDERSTANDING OF THE NEED FOR
RECONCILIATION.
BUT I WANT TO FOLLOWUP ON
SOMETHING HAVING TO DO WITH
LEADERSHIP.
BECAUSE YOU KNOW, TODAY SENATOR
SANDERS SAID THAT PRESIDENT
OBAMA FAILED THE PRESIDENTIAL
LEADERSHIP TEST.
AND THIS IS NOT THE FIRST TIME
THAT HE HAS CRITICIZED PRESIDENT
OBAMA IN THE PAST HE'S CALLED
HIM WEEK.
HE HAS CALLED HIM A
DISAPPOINTMENT.
HE WROTE A FORWARD FOR A BOOK
THAT BASICALLY ARGUED VOTERS
SHOULD HAVE BUYERS REMORSE WHEN
IT COMES TO PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
LEADERSHIP AND LEGACY.
AND I JUST COULDN'T AGREE,
DISAGREE MORE WITH THOSE KINDS
OF COMMENTS.
YOU KNOW, FROM MY PERSPECTIVE
MAYBE BECAUSE I UNDERSTAND WHAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA INHERITED, NOT
ONLY THE WORST FINANCIAL CRISIS
BUT THE ANTIPATHY OF THE
REPUBLICANS IN CONGRESS, I DON'T
THINK HE GETS THE CREDIT HE
DESERVES FOR BEING A PRESIDENT.
AND SEND US INTO THE FUTURE.
AND IT IS A, THE KIND OF
CRITICISM THAT WE'VE HEARD FROM
SENATOR SANDERS ABOUT OUR
PRESIDENT I EXPECT FROM
REPUBLICANS.
I DO NOT EXPECT FROM SOMEONE
RUNNING FOR THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINATION TO SUCCEED PRESIDENT
O BAMA.
>> MAD AM SECRETARY, THAT IS A
LOW BLOW.
I HAVE WORKED WITH PRESIDENT
OBAMA FOR THE LAST SEVEN YEARS.
WHEN PRESIDENT OBAMA CAME INTO
OFFICE WE WERE LOSING 800,000
JOBS A MONTH.
800,000 JOBS A MONTH.
WE ARE 1.4 TRILLION DOLLAR
DEFICIT AND THE WORLD'S
FINANCIAL SYSTEM IS ON THE VERGE
OF COLLAPSE.
AS A RESULT OF HIS EFFORTS AND
THE EFFORTS OF JOE BIDEN AGAINST
UNPRECEDENTED, I WAS THERE,
UNPRESS DENLTED REPUBLICAN
OBSTRUCTIONISM, WE HAVE MADE
ENORMOUS PROGRESS.
(APPLAUSE)
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT?
LAST I HEARD WE LIVED IN A
DEMOCRATIC SOCIETY.
LAST I HEARD, A UNITED STATES
SENATOR HAD THE RIGHT TO
DISAGREE WITH THE PRESIDENT
INCLUDING A PRESIDENT WHO HAS
DONE SUCH AN EXTRAORDINARY JOB.
SO I HAVE VOICED CRITICISM.
MAYBE YOU HAVEN'T.
I HAVE.
BUT I THINK TO SUGGEST THAT I
HAVE VOICED CRITICISM, THIS
BLUSH THAT YOU TALK ABOUT, YOU
KNOW WHAT THE BLU RB SAID T SAID
THAT THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES HAS GOT TO BE
AGGRESSIVE IN BRINGING PEOPLE
INTO THE POLITICAL PROCESS.
THAT'S WHAT I SAID.
THAT IS WHAT I BELIEVE.
PRESIDENT OBAMA AND I ARE
FRIENDS.
AS YOU KNOW, HE CAME TO VERMONT
TO CAMPAIGN FOR ME WHEN HE WAS A
SENATOR.
I HAVE WORKED FOR HIS
RE-ELECTION.
HIS FIRST ELECTION AND HIS
BUT I THINK IT IS REALLY UNFAIR
TO SUGGEST THAT I HAVE NOT BEEN
SUPPORTIVE OF THE PRESIDENT.
I HAVE BEEN A STRONG ALLY WITH
HIM ON VIRTUALLY EVERY ISSUE.
DO SENATORS HAVE THE RIGHT TO
DISAGREE WITH THE PRESIDENT.
HAVE YOU EVER DISAGREED WITH A
PRESIDENT.
I RESPECT YOU-- SUSPECT YOU
HAVE.
>> SENATOR, WHAT I AM CONCERNED
ABOUT, IS NOT DISAGREEMENT ON
ISSUES SAYING THAT THIS IS WHAT
I WOULD RATHER DO, I DON'T AGREE
WITH THE PRESIDENT ON THAT
CALLING THE PRESIDENT WEAK,
CALLING HIM A DISAPPOINTMENT,
CALLING SEVERAL TIMES THAT HE
SHOULD HAVE A PRIME AERO UPON
ENT WHEN HE RAN FOR RE-ELECTION
IN 2012, YOU KNOW, I THINK THAT
GOES FURTHER THAN SAYING WE HAVE
OUR DISAGREEMENTS.
AS A SENATOR, YES, I WAS A
SENATOR.
I UNDERSTAND WE CAN DISAGREE ON
THE PATH FORWARD.
BUT THOSE KINDS OF PERSONAL
A-- ASSESSMENTS AND CHARGES ARE
ONES THAT I FIND-- TROUBLING.
>> YOU MAY RESPOND TO THAT BUT
IT IS TIME FOR CLOSING
STATEMENTS AND YOU CAN USE YOUR
TIME FOR CLOSING STATEMENTS TO
DO THAT.
>> ONE OF US RAN AGAINST BARACK
OBAMA.
I WAS NOT THAT CANDIDATE.
(APPLAUSE)
ALL RIGHT, LOOK, THIS HAS BEEN A
GREAT DEBATE.
A LOT OF INTERESTING ISSUES HAVE
COME TOGETHER.
LET ME CONCLUDE BY JUST SAYING
THIS.
THERE IS NO PRESIDENT IN MY
VIEW, NOT HILLARY CLINTON, NOT
BERNIE SANDERS, WHO HAS THE
CAPABILITY OR THE POWER TO TAKE
ON WALL STREET, LARGE CAMPAIGN
DONORS, THE CORPORATE MEDIA, THE
BIG MONEY INTERESTS IN THIS
COUNTRY ALONE.
THIS CAMPAIGN IS NOT JUST ABOUT
ELECTING A PRESIDENT.
WHAT THIS CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT IS
CREATING A PROCESS FOR A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION IN WHICH
MILLIONS OF AMERICANS, WORKING
PEOPLE WHO HAVE GIVEN UP ON THE
POLITICAL PROCESS, THEY DON'T
THINK ANYBODY HEARS THEIR PAINS
OR THEIR CONCERNS.
YOUNG PEOPLE FOR WHOM GETTING
INVOLVED IN POLITICS IS AS, YOU
KNOW, IT'S LIKE GOING TO THE
MOON.
IT AIN'T GOING TO HAPPEN.
LOW INCOME PEOPLE WHO ARE NOT AS
INVOLVED IN THE POLITICAL
PROCESS.
WHAT THIS CAMPAIGN IS NOT ONLY
ABOUT ELECTING SOMEONE WHO HAS
THE MOST PROGRESSIVE A-- AGENDA
IT IS ABOUT BRINGING TENS OF
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE TOGETHER TO
DEMAND THAT WE HAVE A GOVERNMENT
THAT REPRESENTS ALL OF US AND
NOT JUST THE ONE PERCENT WHO
TODAY HAVE SO MUCH ECONOMIC AND
POLITICAL POWER.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
(APPLAUSE)
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> WE AGREE THAT EF WITH A GOT
TO GET UNACCOUNTABLE MONEY OUT
OF POLITICS.
WE AGREE THAT WALL STREET SHOULD
NEVER BE ALLOWED TO WRECK MAIN
STREET AGAIN.
BUT HERE'S THE POINT I WANT TO
MAKE TOBT.
I AM NOT A SINGLE ISSUE
CANDIDATE AND I DO NOT BELIEVE
WE LIVE IN A SINGLE ISSUE
COUNTRY.
I THINK THAT A LOT OF WHAT WE
HAVE TO OVERCOME TO BREAK DOWN
THE BARRIERS THAT ARE HOLDING
PEOPLE BACK, WHETHER IT'S POISON
IN THE WATER OF THE CHILDREN OF
FLINT, OR WHETHER IT'S THE POOR
MINE ERRS WHO ARE BEING LEFT OUT
AND LEFT BEHIND IN COAL COUNTRY
OR WHETHER IT IS ANY OTHER
AMERICAN TODAY WHO FEELS SHOW
PUT DOWN AND OPPRESSED BY
RACISM, BY SEXISM, BY
DISCRIMINATION AGAINST THE LGBT
COMMUNITY, AGAINST THE KIND OF
EFFORTS THAT NEED TO BE MADE TO
ROOT OUT ALL OF THESE BARRIERS,
THAT IS WHAT I WANT TO TAKE ON.
AND HERE IN WISCONSIN I WANT TO
REITERATE, WE'VE GOT TO STAND UP
FOR UNIONS AND WORKING PEOPLE
WHO HAVE-- , THE AMERICAN MIDDLE
CLASS AND WHO ARE BEING ATTACKED
BY IDEA DDZ LOGS, BY DEMAGOGUES,
DOES WALL STREETK BIG FINANCIAL
INTERESTS, OIL COMPANIES,
INSURANCE COMPANIES, BIG OILK
ALL OF IT HAVE TOO MUCH
INFLUENCE, YOU'RE RIGHT.
BUT IF WE WERE TO STOP THAT
TOMORROW, WE WOULD STILL HAVE
THE INDIFFERENCE, THE NEDGES
THAT WE SAW IN FLINT.
WE WOULD STILL HAVE RACISM
HOLDING PEOPLE BACK.
WE WOULD STILL HAVE SEXISM
PREVENTING WOMEN FROM GETTING
EQUAL PAY.
WE WOULD STILL HAVE LGBT PEOPLE
WITHOUT GET MARRIED ON SATURDAY
AND GET FIRED ON MONDAY, AND WE
WOULD STILL HAVE GOVERNORS LIKE
SCOTT WALKER AND OTHERS TRYING
TO RIP OUT THE HEART OF THE
MIDDLE CLASS BY MAKING IT
IMPOSSIBLE TO ORGANIZE AND STAND
UP FOR BETTER WAGES AND WORKING
CONDITIONS.
SO I'M GOING TO KEEP TALKING
ABOUT TEARING DOWN ALL THE
BARRIERS THAT STAND IN THE WAY
OF AMERICANS FULFILLING THEIR
POTENTIAL BECAUSE I DON'T THINK
OUR COUNTRY CAN LIVE UP TO ITS
POTENTIAL UNLESS WE GIVE A
CHANCE TOAF REE SINGLE AMERICAN
TO LIVE UP TO THEIRS.
(CHEERS AND APPLAUSE).
>> Moderator: THANK YOU
SENATOR CLINTON, SHAW SENATOR
SANDER.
WE ALSO WANT TO THANK OUR
PARTNERS AT FACEBOOK AND OUR
PARTNERS AT FACEBOOK, AND OUR
HOSTS HERE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
WISCONSIN MILWAUKEE.
>> Woodruff: WE ALSO WANT TO
THANK OUR AUDIENCE IN THE HELEN
BADER CONCERT HALL AND OUR
AUDIENCE WATCHING AND LISTENING.
THANK YOU ALL.
STAY TUNED FOR ANALYSIS OF THE
DEBATE AND THE OVERALL RACE FOR
THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINATION COMING
UP NEXT HERE ON PBS STATIONS AND
ONLINE AT pbs.org/newshour.
>> Ifill: I WILL REMAIN HERE IN
MILWAUKEE TOMORROW EVENING FOR A
SPECIAL EDITION OF WASHINGTON
WEEK ON PBS.
>> Woodruff: AND I'M GOING TO BE
RETURNING TO WASHINGTON.
I HOPE YOU WILL JOIN US FOR THE
PBS NEWSHOUR TOMORROW AND EVERY
NIGHT.
THAT'S IT FROM ALL OF US HERE IN
MILWAUKEE, THANK YOU.