THE FIELD OF CANDIDATES IS
GETTING SMALLER.
AND WITH EVERY DAY THE END OF
THE ROAD GETS CLOSER.
TONIGHT THE ROAD LEADS TO
SOUTH CAROLINA, HOME OF THE
FIRST IN THE SOUTH REPUBLICAN
PRIMARY.
WHERE HISTORY HAS PROVEN THE
EVENTUAL NOMINEE NEEDS A STRONG
FINISH.
AMERICAN INDUSTRY IS THRIVING,
UNEMPLOYMENT IS ON THE DECLINE,
AND PEOPLE ARE MOVING HERE IN
RECORD NUMBERS.
CHARLESTON HAS ALSO SUFFERED
UNIMAGINABLE TRAGEDY.
IT HAS LIVED THE NIGHTMARE THAT
HAS HAUNTED TOO MANY AMERICAN
COMMUNITIES.
BUT ITS CITIZENS HAVE COME
TOGETHER AND THEY LOOK TOWARD A
BRIGHTER FUTURE.
THERE ARE JUST 18 DAYS UNTIL THE
IOWA CAUCUSES.
37 DAYS UNTIL THE SOUTH CAROLINA
PRIMARY.
TONIGHT THE ELECTION YEAR
OFFICIALLY KICKS OFF.
WITH THE VERY FIRST DEBATE OF
2016.
¶¶
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: IT IS 9:00 P.M. HERE
AT THE NORTH CHALLENGES TON
COLISEUM AND PERFORMING ARTS
CENTER IN CHARLESTON,
SOUTH CAROLINA.
WELCOME TO THE SIXTH REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE OF 2016
CAMPAIGN.
HERE ON THE FOX BUSINESS
NETWORK.
I'M NEIL CAVUTO ALONGSIDE MY
FRIEND AND COMODERATOR MARIA
BARTIROMO.
MODERATOR: TONIGHT WE'RE WORKING
WITH FACEBOOK TO ASK THE
CANDIDATES THE QUESTIONS VOTERS
WANT ANSWERED.
AND ACCORDING TO FACEBOOK THE
U.S. ELECTION HAS DOMINATED THE
GLOBAL CONVERSATION WITH
131 MILLION PEOPLE TALKING ABOUT
THE 2016 RACE.
THAT MAKES IT THE NUMBER ONE
ISSUE TALKED ABOUT FACEBOOK LAST
YEAR WORLDWIDE.
MODERATOR: NOW THE SEVEN
CANDIDATES ON THE STAGE TONIGHT
WERE SELECTED BASED ON THEIR
STANDING IN SIX NATIONAL POLLS
AS WELL AS POLLS IN THE EARLY
VOTING STATES OF IOWA AND NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
THOSE STANDINGS DETERMINING THE
POSITION ON THE STAGE OF THE
CANDIDATES TONIGHT.
AND HERE THEY ARE.
BUSINESSMAN, DONALD TRUMP.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
TEXAS SENATOR TED CRUZ.
FLORIDA SENATOR MARCO RUBIO.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
SURGEON BEN CARSON.
NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR
CHRIS CHRISTIE.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
FORMER FLORIDA GOVERNOR
JEB BUSH.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
AND OHIO GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH.
MODERATOR: TONIGHT'S RULES ARE
SIMPLE.
UP TO 90 SECONDS FOR EACH
ANSWER, ONE MINUTE FOR EACH
FOLLOW-UP RESPONSE.
IF A CANDIDATE GOES OVER THE
ALLOTTED TIME YOU WILL HEAR
THIS.
[BELL RINGING]
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
CANDIDATES, JOBS AND GROWTH, TWO
OF THE BIGGEST ISSUES FACING THE
COUNTRY RIGHT NOW.
IN HIS STATE OF THE UNION
ADDRESS EARLIER THIS WEEK THE
PRESIDENT SAID, QUOTE, WE HAVE
THE STRONGEST, MOST DURABLE QUON
ECONOMY IN THE WORLD.
ACCORDING TO OUR FACEBOOK
RESEARCH JOBS IS ONE OF THE
BIGGEST ISSUES RESONATING ACROSS
THE COUNTRY, INCLUDING HERE IN
SOUTH CAROLINA.
THE PRESIDENT IS TOUTING
14 MILLION NEW JOBS AND
UNEMPLOYMENT RATE CUT IN HALF.
THE PRESIDENT SAID THAT ANYONE
WHO CLAIMS AMERICA'S ECONOMY IS
IN DECLINE IS PEDALING --
PEDDLING FICTION.
SENATOR CRUZ, WHAT DO YOU SEE
THAT HE DOESN'T?
>> WELL, MARIA, THANK YOU FOR
THAT QUESTION AND LET ME SAY
THANK YOU TO THE STATE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA FOR WELCOMING US.
LET ME START, I WANT TO GET TO
THE SUBSTANCE OF THE QUESTION ON
JOBS BUT I WANT TO START WITH
SOMETHING, TODAY MANY OF US
PICKED UP OUR NEWSPAPERS AND WE
WERE WHO ARE FRIED TO SEE THE
SIGHT OF 10 AMERICAN SAILORS ON
THEIR KNEES WITH THEIR HANDS ON
THEIR HEAD.
IN THAT STATE OF THE UNION
PRESIDENT OBAMA DIDN'T SO MUCH
AS MENTION THE 10 SAILORS THAT
HAD BEEN CAPTURED BY IRAN.
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S PREPARING TO
SEND $100 BILLION OR MORE TO THE
AYATOLLAH KHOMENI.
I WILL TELL YOU, IT WAS
HEART-BREAKING, BUT THE GOOD
NEWS IS THE NEXT
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF IS STANDING
ON THIS STAGE.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
AND I GIVE YOU MY WORD IF I AM
ELECTED PRESIDENT NO SERVICEMAN
OR SERVICEWOMAN WILL BE FORCED
TO BE ON THEIR KNEES IN ANY
NATION THAT CAPTURES OUR
FIGHTING MEN AND WOMEN WILL FEEL
THE FULL FORCE AND FURY OF THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
NOW ON TO YOUR SUBSTANTIVE
QUESTION, THE PRESIDENT TRIED TO
PAINT A ROSY PICTURE OF JOBS.
YOU KNOW HE'S RIGHT.
IF YOU'RE A WASHINGTON LOBBIEST,
IF YOU MAKE YOUR MONEY IN AND
AROUND WASHINGTON THINKS ARE
DOING GREAT.
THE MILLIONAIRES AND
BILLIONAIRES ARE DOING GREAT
UNDER OBAMA BUT WE HAVE THE
LOWEST PERCENTAGE OF AMERICANS
WORKING TODAY OF ANY YEAR SINCE
1977.
MEDIAN WAGES HAVE STAGNATED AND
THE OBAMA-CLINTON ECONOMY HAS
LEFT BEHIND THE WORKING MEN AND
WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY.
THE REASON ALL OF US ARE HERE WE
BELIEVE WE SHOULD BE FIGHTING
FOR WORKING MEN AND WOMEN OF
THIS COUNTRY, AND NOT
WASHINGTON, D.C.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SIR.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR KASICH, WE
ARE NOT EVEN TWO WEEKS INTO THIS
STOCK TRADING YEAR.
THINK ABOUT IT INVESTORS HAVE
ALREADY LOST $1.6 TRILLION IN
MARKET VALUE.
THAT MAKES IT THE WORST START TO
A NEW YEAR EVER.
MANY WORRY THINGS WILL GET EVEN
WORSE, BANKS AND FINANCIAL
STOCKS ARE PARTICULARLY
VULNERABLE.
IF THIS ESCALATES LIKE IT DID
BACK WHEN BARACK OBAMA FIRST
ASSUMED THE PRESIDENCY, WHAT
ACTIONS WOULD YOU TAKE, IF THE
SAME THING HAPPENS ALL OVER
AGAIN JUST AS IN THIS EXAMPLE
YOU ARE TAKING OVER THE
PRESIDENCY?
>> IT TAKES THREE THINGS TO
BASICALLY GROW JOBS.
I HAVE DONE IT WHEN I WAS IN
WASHINGTON WHEN WE HAD A
BALANCED BUDGET.
HAD FOUR YEARS OF BALANCED
BUDGETS.
PAID DOWN HALF A TRILLION IN
DEBT AND OUR ECONOMY WAS GROWING
LIKE CRAZY.
IT IS SAME THING LIKE I DID IN
OHIO.
IT IS A SIMPLE FORMULA.
COMMON SENSE REGULATIONS.
WHY I THINK WE SHOULD FREEZE ALL
FEDERAL REGULATIONS FOR ONE
YEAR, EXCEPT FOR HEALTH AND
SAFETY.
IT REQUIRES TAX CUTS BECAUSE
THAT SENDS A MESSAGE TO THE JOB
CREATORS THAT THINGS ARE HEADED
RIGHT WAY.
IF YOU TAX CUTS -- CUT TAXES FOR
CORPORATIONS AND CUT TAXES FOR
INDIVIDUALS YOU'RE GOING TO MAKE
THINGS MOVE, PARTICULARLY THE
CORPORATE TAX WHICH IS THE
HIGHEST OF COURSE IN THE WORLD.
BUT IN ADDITION TO THAT WE HAVE
TO HAVE FISCAL DISCIPLINE.
WE HAVE TO SHOW WE CAN MARCH TO
A BALANCED BUDGET.
WHEN YOU DO THAT, WHEN YOU'RE IN
POSITION OF MANAGING
REGULATIONS, WHEN YOU REDUCE
TAXES AND WHEN YOU HAVE FISCAL
DISCIPLINE, YOU SEE THE JOB
CREATORS BEGIN TO GET VERY
COMFORTABLE WITH THE FACT THAT
THEY CAN INVEST.
RIGHT NOW YOU DON'T HAVE, YOU
HAVE TAXES THAT ARE TOO HIGH.GHU
HAVE TAXES THAT ARE TOO HIGH.
YOU HAVE REGULATION, I MEAN COME
ON, THEY'RE AFFECTING EVERYBODY
HERE PARTICULARLY OUR SMALL
BUSINESSES.
THEY'RE IN THE POSITION WHERE
THEY'RE SMOTHERING PEOPLE.
I MEAN ARE YOU KIDDING ME?
WE'RE NOWHERE CLOSE TO BALANCED
BUDGET OR FISCAL DISCIPLINE OF
THE THOSE THREE THINGS PUT
TOGETHER WILL GIVE CONFIDENCE TO
JOB CREATORS AND YOU WILL BEGIN
TO SEE WAGES RISE.
YOU WILL BEGIN TO SEE JOBS
CREATED IN A ROBUST ECONOMY.
AND HOW DO I KNOW IT?
BECAUSE I'VE DONE IT.
I DID IT AS CHAIRMAN OF THE
BUDGET COMMITTEE WORKING WITH
SENATOR DOMENICI AND I'VE DONE
IT IN THE STATE OF OHIO AS THE
CHIEF EXECUTIVE.
OUR WAGES ARE GROWING FASTER
THAN NATIONAL AVERAGE.
WE'RE RUNNING SURPLUSES AND WE
CAN TAKE THAT MESSAGE AND THAT
FORMULA TO WASHINGTON TO LIFT
EVERY SINGLE AMERICAN TO A
BETTER LIFE.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: WE KNOW THAT RECENT
GLOBAL EVENTS HAVE MANY PEOPLE
WORRIED.
IRAN DETAINING AMERICAN SAILORS,
FORCING THEM TO APOLOGIZE.
NORTH KOREA AND ITS NUCLEAR
AMBITIONS, AGGRESSIVE CHINA AND
MIDDLE EAST THAT CONTINUES TO
DETERIORATE.
NOT TO MENTION ISIS IS GETTING
STRONGER.
ABOVEGOVERNOR CHRISTIE, SOMETIMT
SEEMS THE WORLD IS ON FIRE.
WHERE AND WHEN SHOULD A
PRESIDENT USE MILITARY ACTION TO
RESTORE ORDER?
>> WELL, MARIA I'M GLAD TO HAVE
HEARD FROM YOU IN THE SUMMARY OF
THAT QUESTION ABOUT WHAT IS
GOING ON IN THE WORLD BECAUSE
TUESDAY NIGHT I WATCHED STORY
TIME WITH BARACK OBAMA.
I GOT TO TELL YOU, IT SOUNDED
LIKE EVERYTHING IN THE WORLD WAS
GOING AMAZING, YOU KNOW?
[APPLAUSE]
THE FACT IS A NUMBER OF THINGS
THE NEXT PRESIDENT WILL HAVE TO
DO TO CLEAN UP THIS MESS.
FIRST THING WE HAVE TO
STRENGTHEN OUR ALLIANCES AROUND
THE WORLD.
AND THE BEST WAY TO DO THAT IS
START TALKING TO OUR ALLIES
AGAIN AND HAVE THEM BE ABLE TO
COUNT ON OUR WORD.
LOTS OF PEOPLE SAY LOTS OF
DIFFERENT THINGS ABOUT ME IN
THIS CAMPAIGN AND OTHERS BUT THE
ONE THING THEY HAVE NEVER SAID
ABOUT ME I'M MISUNDERSTOOD.
AND SO WHEN WE TALK TO OUR
ALLIES AND WE GIVE THEM OUR WORD
IN CHRISTIE ADMINISTRATION WE'RE
GOING TO KEEP IT.
NEXT WE HAVE TO TALK TO OUR
ADVERSARIES.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE THEY
UNDERSTAND THE LIMITS OF OUR
PATIENCE.
AND THIS PRESIDENT GIVEN WHAT
TED SAID RIGHT AT BEGINNING HE
IS ABSOLUTELY RIGHT, IT IS
ABSOLUTELY DISGRACEFUL THAT
SECRETARY KERRY AND OTHERS SAID,
IN THEIR RESPONSE TO WHAT'S
GOING ON, IN IRAN, THAT THIS WAS
GOOD THING.
IT SHOWED HOW RELATIONSHIP WAS
GETTING BETTER.
THE PRESIDENT DOESN'T UNDERSTAND
AND BY THE WAY NEITHER DOES
SECRETARY CLINTON.
HERE IS MY WARNING TO EVERYBODY
OUT IN THE AUDIENCE TONIGHT.
IF YOU'RE WORRIED ABOUT WORLD
BEING ON FIRE, WORRIED HOW WE
WILL USE OUR MILITARY, WORRIED
ABOUT STRENGTHENING OUR MILITARY
AND YOU'RE WORRIED MOST OF ALL
KEEPING YOUR HOMES AND FAMILIES
SAFE AND SECURE, YOU CAN NOT
GIVE HILLARY CLINTON A THIRD
TERM OF BARACK OBAMA'S
LEADERSHIP.
I WILL NOT DO THAT IF I'M NOT
NOMINEE.
SHE WON'T GET WITHIN 10 MILES OF
THE WHITE HOUSE.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: JUST TO BE CLEAR,
GOVERNOR, WHERE AND WHEN WOULD
YOU USE MILITARY ACTION?
>> MILITARY ACTION, MARIA WOULD
BE USED WHEN IT WAS ABSOLUTELY
NECESSARY TO PROTECT AMERICAN
LIVES AND PROTECT AMERICAN
INTERESTS AROUND THE WORLD.
WE ARE NOT THE WORLD'S POLICEMAN
BUT WE NEED TO STAND UP AN BE
READY, THE PROBLEM, MARIA THE
MILITARY IS NOT READY EITHER.
WE NEEDREBUILD THE MILITARY.
THIS PRESIDENT LET IT DIMINISH
TO POINT LIKE TIN POT DICTATORS
LIKE MULLAHS IN IRAN TAKING OUR
NAVY SHIPS.
IT IS DISGRACEFUL N A CHRISTIE
ADMINISTRATION THEY WOULD KNOW
MUCH, MUCH BETTER THAN TO DO
THAT.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR BUSH, THE
PRESIDENT TOLD THE NATION TWO
NIGHTS AGO THAT THE OUR ENEMIES
ARE GETTING STRONG OTHER THIS
COUNTRY IS GETTING WEAKER IT IS
RHETORIC AND HOT AIR.
NOW THE DEMOCRATS GO EVEN
FURTHER, SIR, SAYING REPUBLICANS
EVEN SUGGESTING SUCH COMMENTS
ACTUALLY EMBOLDEN OUR ENEMIES.
I GUESS THEY WOULD INCLUDE YOU.
WHAT DO YOU THINK?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL THE IDEA
THAT SOMEHOW WE'RE BETTER OFF
TODAY THAN THE DAY THAT PUPIL
OBAMA WAS INAUGURATED PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES IS TOTALLY
ALTERNATIVE UNIVERSE.
THE SIMPLE FACT IS THE WORLD HAS
BEEN TORN ASUNDER.
THINK ABOUT IT WITH GRANDIOSE
LANGUAGE THE PRESIDENT TALKS
ABOUT RED LINES, WITH NOTHING TO
FOLLOW IT UP.
PRESIDENT TALKS ABOUT BEING A JV
TEAM.
THEY FORM A CALIPHATE THE SIZE
OF INDIANA WITH 35 OR 40,000
BATTLE-TESTED TERRORISTS.
HE IS MISSING THE POINT.
AMERICA'S LEADERSHIP IN THE
WORLD IS REQUIRED FOR PEACE AND
STABILITY.
IN THE CROWD TODAY IS MAJOR
GENERAL JAMES LIVINGSTON, WHO IS
CO-CHAIR OF MY CAMPAIGN HERE IN
SOUTH CAROLINA, A MEDAL OF HONOR
RECIPIENT.
I LEARNED FROM HIM IS PEACE
THROUGH STRENGTH.
IN THIS ADMINISTRATION EVERY
WEAPONS SYSTEM HAS BEEN GUTTED.
WE CAN'T EVEN GO DOWN TO LEVEL
WHERE WE CAN'T PROJECT FORCE.
OUR FRIEND NO LONGER THINK WE
HAVE THEIR BACK AND OUR ENEMIES
NO LONGER FEAR US.
WE'RE IN MUCH DIFFERENT POSITION
THAN WE SHOULD BE.
FOR THE LIFE OF ME I HAVE NO
UNDERSTANDING WHY THE PRESIDENT
THINKS THAT EVERYTHING IS GOING
WELL.
TERRORISM IS ON THE RUN.
CHINA, RUSSIA IS ADVANCING THEIR
AGENDA AT WARP SPEED.
AND WE PULL BACK.
AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES I WILL BE A
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF THAT HAVE THE
BACK OF THE MILITARY.
WE WILL REBUILD THE MILITARY TO
MAKE SURE IT IS A SOLID FORCE.
NOT TO BE THE WORLD'S POLICEMAN
TO MAKE SURE IN PEACEFUL WORLD
PEOPLE KNOW THAT THE UNITED
STATES IS THERE TO TAKE CARE OF
OUR OWN NATIONAL INTERESTS AND
TAKE CARE OF OUR ALLIES.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: TAKE IT FROM THAT YOU
DO NOT AGREE WITH THE PRESIDENT?
>> NO.
WORST YET, TO BE HONEST WITH YOU
HILLARY CLINTON WOULD BE
NATIONAL SECURITY DISASTER.
THINK ABOUT IT SHE WANTS TO
CONTINUE DOWN THE PATH OF IRAN,
BENGHAZI, RUSSIAN RESET,
DODD-FRANK, ALL THE THINGS THAT
HAVE GONE WRONG IN THIS COUNTRY.
SHE WOULD BE A NATIONAL SECURITY
MESS.
AND THAT IS WRONG.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
HERE'S THE PROBLEM.
IF SHE GETS ELECTED SHE SUNDAY
INVESTIGATION WITH THE FBI RIGHT
NOW.
IF SHE GETS ELECTED HER FIRST
100 DAYS INSTEAD OF SETTING
AGENDA SHE MIGHT BE GOING BACK
AND FORTH BETWEEN THE
WHITE HOUSE AN COURTHOUSE.
WE NEED TO STOP THAT.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: SENATOR RUBIO, THE
PRESIDENT SAYS THAT ISIS DOESN'T
THREATEN OUR NATIONAL EXISTENCE
LIKE A GERMANY OR JAPAN DID BACK
IN WORLD WAR II.
THAT THE TERROR GRIPE IS NOTHING
MORE THAN TWISTED SOULS PLOTTING
ATTACKS IN THEIR GARAGES.
BUT, HOUSE HOMELAND SECURITY
COMMITTEE RECENTLY SAID OVER
1000 ONGOING INVESTIGATIONS OF
HOMEGROWN EXTREMISM IN 50
STATES.
SO HOW DO YOU DEFINE THE THREAT?
GERMANY THEN OR DANGEROUS
NUTCASES NOW?
>> I WOULD GO FIRST OF ALL ONE
STEP FURTHER IN THIS DESCRIPTION
OF HILLARY CLINTON.
SHE WOULDN'T JUST BE A DISASTER.
HILLARY CLINTON IS DISQUALIFIED
FROM BEING COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF OF
THE UNITED STATES.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
SOMEONE, SOMEONE WHO CAN NOT
HANDLE INTELLIGENCE INFORMATION
APPROPRIATELY, CAN NOT BE
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF AND SOMEONE
WHO LIES TO THE FAMILIES OF
THOSE FOUR VICTIMS IN BENGHAZI
CAN NEVER BE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
ON THE ISSUE OF BARACK OBAMA,
BARACK OBAMA DOES NOT BELIEVE
THAT AMERICA IS A GREAT GLOBAL
POWER.
BARACK OBAMA BELIEVES AMERICA IS
A ARROGANT GLOBAL POWER THAT
NEEDS TO BE CUT DOWN TO SIZE.
THAT IS HOW YOU GET A FOREIGN
POLICY WHERE WE CUT DEALS WITH
OUR ENEMIES LIKE IRAN AND WE
BETRAY OUR ALLIES LIKE ISRAEL
AND WE GUT OUR MILITARY AND WE
GO AROUND THE WORLD LIKE HE HAS
DONE ON 10 SEPARATE OCCASIONS
AND APOLOGIZED FOR AMERICA.
HE DOESN'T UNDERSTAND THE THREAT
IN ISIS.
HE CONSISTENTLY UNDERESTIMATES
IT BUT I DO NOT.
THERE IS A WAR AGAINST ISIS, NOT
JUST AGAINST ISIS BUT AGAINST
RADICAL JIHADISTS TERRORISTS.
THAT IS WAR THEY WIN OR WE WIN.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES WE WILL WIN THE WAR
BEGINS ISIS.
MOST POWERFUL INTELLIGENCE
AGENCY WILL TELL US WHERE WE
ARE, THE MOST POWERFUL MILITARY
IN THE WORLD WILL DESTROY THEM.
IF WE CAPTURE THEM ALIVE, THEY
ARE GETTING ONE-WAY TICKET TO
GUANTANAMO, CUBA, AND WE'LL FIND
OUT EVERYTHING THEY KNOW.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR.
MODERATOR: DR. CARSON THE
PRESIDENT SAYS HE DOES NOT WANT
TO TREAT ISIS AS FOREIGN ARMY
BUT ISIS NEITHER A COUNTRY NOR A
GOVERNMENT.
HOW DO YOU ATTACK A NETWORK THAT
DOES NOT RESPECT NATIONAL
BORDERS?
>> WELL, I AM VERY HAPPY TO BET
A QUESTION THIS EARLY ON.
I WAS GOING TO ASK YOU TO WAKE
ME UP WHEN THE TIME CAME.
[LAUGHTER]
YOU KNOW, I FIND IT REALLY QUITE
FASCINATING SOME OF THE
PRESIDENT'S PROCLAMATIONS.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, HE
DOESN'T REALIZE THAT WE NOW LIVE
IN THE 21st CENTURY, AND
THAT WAR IS VERY DIFFERENT THAN
IT USED TO BE BEFORE.
NOT ARMIES, MASSIVELY MARCHING
ON EACH OTHER AND AIR FORCES BUT
NOW WE HAVE DIRTY BOMBS AND WE
HAVE CYBER ATTACKS AND WE HAVE
PEOPLE WHO WILL BE ATTACKING OUR
ELECTRICAL GRID.
AND YOU KNOW, WE HAVE A WHOLE
VARIETY OF THINGS THAT THEY CAN
DO AND THEY CAN DO THESE THINGS
SIMULTANEOUSLY.
AND WE HAVE ENEMIES WHO ARE
OBTAINING NUCLEAR WEAPONS THAT
THEY CAN EXPLODE IN OUR XO
ATMOSPHERE AND DESTROY OUR
ELECTRIC GRID.
SYMPATHY ABOUT A SCENARIO LIKE
THAT.
THEY, THEY EXPLODE THE BOMB, WE
HAVE ELECTROMAGNETIC PULSE.
THEY HIT US WITH A CYBERATTACK
SIMULTANEOUSLY AND DIRTY BOMBS.
CAN YOU IMAGINE THE CHAOS THAT
WOULD ENSUE AT THAT POINT?
HE NEEDS TO RECOGNIZE THAT THOSE
KINDS OF THINGS ARE IN FACT AN
EXISTENTIAL THREAT TO US, BUT,
HERE'S THE REAL KEY.
WE HAVE THE WORLD'S BEST
MILITARY, EVEN THOUGH HE HAS
DONE EVERYTHING HE CAN TO
DIMINISH IT.
AND THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS,
IF WE GIVE THEM A MISSION AND WE
DON'T TIE THEIR HANDS BEHIND
THEIR BACK THEY CAN GET IT
ACCOMPLISHED.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: MR. TRUMP, AT THE
STATE OF THE UNION THE PRESIDENT
POINTED TO A GUEST WHO WAS
SYRIAN REFUGEE YOU MIGHT RECALL
WHOSE WIFE AND DAUGHTER AND
OTHER FAMILY MEMBERS WERE KILLED
IN AN AIR ATTACK.
NOW HE FLED THAT COUNTRY SEEKING
ASYLUM HERE.
ULTIMATELY ENDED UP IN DETROIT
WHERE HE IS NOW TRYING TO START
A NEW LIFE.
THE PRESIDENT SAYS THAT THAT
DOCTOR IS THE REAL FACE OF THESE
REFUGEES AND NOT THE ONE THAT
YOU AND SOME OF YOUR COLLEAGUES
ON THIS STAGE ARE PAINTING.
THAT YOU PREFER THE FACE OF FEAR
AND TERROR.
AND THAT YOU WOULD REFUSE TO LET
IN ANYONE INTO THIS COUNTRY
SEEKING LEGITIMATE ASYLUM.
HOW DO YOU ANSWER THAT?
>> IT'S NOT FEAR AND TERROR.
IT'S REALITY.
YOU JUST HAVE TO LOOK TODAY AT
INDONESIA, BOMBINGS ALL OVER.
YOU LOOK AT CALIFORNIA.
YOU LOOK FRANKLY AT PARIS WHERE
THERE'S A STRICTEST NO-GUN
POLICY OF ANY CITY ANYWHERE IN
THE WORLD AND YOU SEE WHAT
HAPPENS.
130 PEOPLE DEAD WITH MANY TO
FOLLOW.
THEY'RE VERY, VERY BADLY
WOUNDED.
SOME WILL FOLLOW.
AND YOU LOOK AROUND, AND YOU SEE
WHAT'S HAPPENING AND THIS IS NOT
THE CASE WHEN HE INTRODUCED THE
DOCTOR, VERY NICE, EVERYTHING
PERFECT BUT THAT IS NOT
REPRESENTATIVE OF WHAT YOU HAVE
IN THAT LINE OF MIGRATION.
THAT COULD BE THE GREAT TROJAN
HORSE.
IT COULD BE PEOPLE THAT ARE
GOING TO DO GREAT, GREAT
DESTRUCTION.
WHEN I LOOK AT THE MIGRATION, I
LOOK AT THE LINE, I SAID
ACTUALLY ON YOUR SHOW RECENTLY,
WHERE ARE THE WOMEN?
IT LOOKED LIKE VERY FEW WOMEN.
VERY FEW CHILDREN.
STRONG, POWERFUL MEN, YOUNG AND
PEOPLE ARE LOOKING AT THAT AND
THEY'RE SAYING WHAT'S GOING ON?
YOU LOOK AT THE KIND OF DAMAGE
THAT TWO PEOPLE THAT GOT
MARRIED, THEY WERE RADICALIZED,
THEY GOT MARRIED, THEY KILLED 15
PEOPLE, 14, GOING TO BE PROBABLY
16, YOU LOOK AT THAT, AND YOU
TAKE A LOOK, GOOD STRONG LOOK,
AND THAT'S WHAT WE HAVE.
WE OWE $19 TRILLION, OUR
COUNTRY'S A MESS AND WE CAN'T
LET ALL THESE PEOPLE COME INTO
OUR COUNTRIES AND BREAK OUR
BORDERS.
WE CAN'T DO IT.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: SENATOR CRUZ,
"THE NEW YORK TIMES" IS
REPORTING THAT YOU FAILED TO
PROPERLY DISCLOSE A MILLION
DOLLARS IN LOANS FROM
GOLDMAN SACHS AND CITIBANK
DURING YOUR SENATE RACE.
YOUR CAMPAIGN SAYS IT WAS
INADVERTENT.
A MILLION DOLLARS IS
INADVERTENT?
>> WELL, MARIA, THANK YOU FOR
PASSING ON THAT HIT PIECE ON THE
FRONT PAGE OF "THE NEW YORK
TIMES."
[LAUGHTER].
YOU KNOW THE NICE THING ABOUT
THE MAINSTREAM MEDIA, THEY DON'T
HIDE THEIR VIEWS.
"THE NEW YORK TIMES" A FEW WEEKS
BACK HAD A COLUMNIST WHO WROTE A
COLUMN SAYING ANYBODY BUT CRUZ.
HAD THAT SAME COLUMNIST WROTE A
COLUMN COMPARING ME TO AN EVIL,
DEMONIC SPIRIT FROM THE MOVIE,
"IT FOLLOWS," THAT JUMPS
APPARENTLY FROM BODY TO BODY
POSSESSING PEOPLE.
SO, YOU KNOW
"THE NEW YORK TIMES" AND I DON'T
EXACTLY HAVE THE WARMEST OF
RELATIONSHIPS.
NOW, IN TERMS OF THEIR REALLY
STUNNING HIT PIECE, WHAT THEY
MENTIONED IS WHEN I WAS RUNNING
FOR SENATE, UNLIKE HILLARY
CLINTON, I DON'T HAVE MASSES OF
MONEY IN THE BANK, HUNDREDS OF
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS.
WHEN I WAS RUNNING FOR SENATE
JUST ABOUT EVERY LOBBIEST, JUST
ABOUT ALL THE ESTABLISHMENT
OPPOSED ME IN THE SENATE RACE IN
TEXAS.
AND MY OPPONENT IN THAT RACE WAS
WORTH OVER $200 MILLION.
HE PUT A $25 MILLION CHECK UP
FROM HIS OWN POCKET TO FUND THAT
CAMPAIGN.
AND MY WIFE HEIDI AND I, WE
ENDED UP INVESTING EVERYTHING WE
OWNED.
WE TOOK A LOAN AGAINST OUR
ASSETS TO INVEST IT IN THAT
CAMPAIGN TO DEFEND OURSELVES
AGAINST THOSE ATTACKS AND ENTIRE
"NEW YORK TIMES" ATTACK IS THAT
I DISCLOSED THAT LOAN ON ONE
FILING WITH THE UNITED STATES
SENATE, THAT WAS A PUBLIC FILING
BUT IT WAS NOT ON A SECOND
FILING WITH THE FEC.
BOTH OF THOSE FILINGS WERE
PUBLIC.
AND YES, I MADE A PAPERWORK
ERROR DISCLOSING IT ON ONE PIECE
OF PAPER INSTEAD OF THE OTHER.
BUT IF THAT IS THE BEST HIT
"NEW YORK TIMES" HAS GOT, THEY
BETTER GO BACK TO THE WELL.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR.
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT, WE'RE JUST
GETTING STARTED HERE IN
SOUTH CAROLINA.
THERE IS A A LOT TO GET TO, THIS
LIKE GUN RIGHTS AND NATIONAL
DEBT AND SOMETIMES NASTY WAR OF
WORDS BETWEEN A COUPLE OF THESE
FELLOWS UP HERE.
MORE AFTER THIS.
[APPLAUSE]
¶¶
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT.
WELCOME BACK TO THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE RIGHT HERE
IN NORTH
CHARLESTON, SOUTH CAROLINA.
LET'S GET RIGHT BACK TO THE
QUESTIONS.
I WILL START WITH YOU, SENATOR
CRUZ.
NOW YOU ARE OF COURSE A STRICT
CONSTITUTIONALIST, NO ONE WOULD
DOUBT THAT.
AND AS YOU KNOW THE U.S.
CONSTITUTION SAYS ONLY NATURAL
BORN CITIZENS ARE ELGIBLE FOR
THE OFFICE OF PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
STOP ME IF YOU HEARD THIS
BEFORE.
NOW YOU WERE BORN, YOU WERE BORN
IN CANADA TO AN AMERICAN MOTHER.
SO YOU WERE AND ARE CONSIDERED
AN AMERICAN CITIZEN.
BUT THAT FELLOW NEXT TO YOU,
DONALD TRUMP AND OTHERS, HAVE
SAID BEING BORN IN CANADA MEANS
YOU ARE NOT NATURAL BORN AND
THAT HAS RAISED QUESTIONS ABOUT
YOUR ELIGIBILITY.
DO YOU WANT TO TRY TO CLOSE THIS
TOPIC ONCE AND FOR ALL TONIGHT?
>> WELL, NEIL, I'M GLAD WE'RE
FOCUSING ON THE IMPORTANT TOPICS
OF THE EVENING.
[LAUGHTER]
[CHEERING]
[APPLAUSE]
BACK IN SEPTEMBER, MY FRIEND
DONALD SAID HE HAD HIS LAWYERS
LOOK AT THIS FROM EVERY WHICH
WAY AND THERE WAS NO ISSUE
THERE.
THERE WAS NOTHING TO THIS
BIRTHER ISSUE.
NOW SINCE SEPTEMBER, THE
CONSTITUTION HASN'T CHANGED.
[LAUGHTER]
BUT THE POLL NUMBERS HAVE.
[CHEERING]
AND I RECOGNIZE, I RECOGNIZE
THAT DONALD IS DISMAYED THAT HIS
POLL NUMBERS ARE FALLING IN
IOWA.
BUT THE FACTS AND LAW HERE ARE
REALLY QUITE CLEAR.
UNDER LONGSTANDING U.S. LAW, THE
CHILD OF A U.S. CITIZEN BORN
ABROAD IS A NATURAL BORN
CITIZEN.
IF A SOLDIER HAS A CHILD ABROAD,
THAT CHILD IS A NATURAL BORN
CITIZEN.
THAT IS WHY JOHN McCAIN, EVEN
THOUGH HE WAS BORN IN PANAMA WAS
ELIGIBLE TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT.
IF AN AMERICAN MISSIONARY HAS A
CHILD ABROAD, THAT CHILD IS A
NATURAL BORN CITIZEN.
THAT IS WHY GEORGE ROMNEY,
M.I.T.'S DAD WAS ELIGIBLE TO RUN
FOR PRESIDENT, EVEN THOUGH HE
WAS BORN IN MEXICO.
AT END OF THE DAY THE LEGAL
ISSUE IS QUITE STRAIGHTFORWARD
BUT I WOULD NOTE THAT THE BIRTH
THEY ARE THEORIES THAT RELYING
ON, ONE OF THE MORE EXTREMES ONE
YOU MUST NOT ONLY BE BORN ON
U.S. SOIL BUT HAVE TWO PARENTS
BORN ON U.S. SOIL UNDER THAT
THEORY, NOT ONLY WOULD I BE
DISQUALIFIED, MARCO RUBIO WOULD
BE DISQUALIFIED, BOBBY JINDAL
WOULD BE DISQUALIFIED AND
INTERESTINGLY ENOUGH,
DONALD J. TRUMP WOULD BE
DISQUALIFIED.
[CHEERING]
BECAUSE, BECAUSE, DONALD'S
MOTHER WAS BORN IN SCOTLAND.
SHE WAS NATURALIZED.
NOW DONALD --
>> BUT I WAS BORN HERE.
>> ON THE ISSUE OF CITIZENSHIP
DONALD --
>> BIG DIFFERENCE.
>> ON ISSUE OF CITIZENSHIP I'M
NOT GOING TO USE YOUR MOTHER'S
BIRTH AGAINST YOU.
>> BECAUSE IT WOULDN'T WORK.
>> YOU'RE AN AMERICAN.
AS IS EVERYBODY ELSE ON THIS
STAGE AND I WOULD SUGGEST WE
FOCUS ON WHO'S BEST PREPARED TO
BE COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF BECAUSE
THAT'S THE MOST IMPORTANT
QUESTION FACING THE COUNTRY.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: MR. TRUMP, YOU RAISED
IT, BECAUSE OF HIS RISING POLL
NUMBERS.
>> YOU SAW THE NUMBERS YOURSELF,
NBC "WALL STREET JOURNAL" CAME
OUT WITH A POLL HEADLINE, TRUMP
WAY UP, CRUZ GOING DOWN.
I MEAN SO DON'T -- SEE YOU
CAN'T, YOU CAN'T, THEY DON'T
LIKE "THE WALL STREET JOURNAL."
THEY DON'T LIKE NBC BUT I LIKE
THE POLL.
AND FRANKLY IT JUST CAME OUT
AND, IN IOWA NOW, AS YOU KNOW,
TED, IN THE LAST THREE POLLS I'M
BEATING YOU.
SO YOU SHOULDN'T MISREPRESENT
HOW WELL YOU'RE DOING WITH THE
POLLS.
[APPLAUSE]
YOU DON'T HAVE TO SAY THAT.
IN FACT I WAS ALL FOR YOU
BECAUSE YOU STARTED DOING THAT.
THAT IS MISREPRESENTATION.
NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO.
THIS ISN'T ME SAYING IT.
I DON'T CARE.
I THINK I WILL WIN FAIR AND
SQUARE.
I DON'T HAVE TO WIN THIS WAY.
THANK YOU.
LAURENCE TRIBE AND NUMEROUS FROM
HARVARD, OF HARVARD SAID THERE
IS A SERIOUS QUESTION TO WHETHER
OR NOT TED CAN DO THIS, OKAY?
THERE ARE OTHER ATTORNEYS THAT
FEEL, AND VERY, VERY FINE
CONSTITUTIONAL ATTORNEYS, THAT
FEEL THAT BECAUSE HE WAS NOT
BORN ON THE LAND, HE CAN NOT RUN
FOR OFFICE.
HERE'S THE PROBLEM.
WE'RE RUNNING, WE'RE RUNNING.
HE DOES GREAT.
I WIN.
I CHOOSE HIM AS MY
VICE-PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE AND
THE DEMOCRATS SUE, BECAUSE WE
CAN'T TAKE HIM ALONG FOR THE
RIDE.
I DON'T LIKE THAT.
OKAY?
THE FACT IS, AND IF, FOR SOME
REASON HE BEATS THE REST OF THE
FIELD, HE BEATS THE REST OF THE
FIELD WHO IS -- SEE THEY DON'T
LIKE THAT.
THEY DON'T LIKE THAT.
[.
[BOOING]
THEY DON'T LIKE HE BEATS REST OF
THE FIELD BECAUSE THEY WANT ME.
IF FOR SOME REASON, NEIL HE
BEATS REST OF THE FIELD I
ALREADY KNOW THE DEMOCRATS ARE
GOING TO BE BRINGING A SUIT.
YOU HAVE A BIG LAWSUIT OVER YOUR
HEAD WHILE YOU'RE RUNNING AND IF
YOU BECOME THE NOMINEE, WHO THE
HELL KNOWS IF YOU CAN EVEN SERVE
IN OFFICE.
SO YOU SHOULD GO OUT AND GET A
DECLARATORY JUDGMENT.
LET THE COURTS DECIDE AND --
MODERATOR: WHY ARE YOU SAYING
THIS NOW?
WHY ARE YOU RAISING THIS ISSUE
NOW?
>> BECAUSE NOW HE IS DOING A
LITTLE BIT BETTER.
NO, I DIDN'T CARE IF HE, NO, IT
IS TRUE.
HE NEVER HAD A CHANCE.
NOW HE IS DOING BETTER.
HE GOT PROBABLY 4 OR 5% CHANCE.
[BOOING]
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, MR. TRUMP.
>> NEIL --
>> THE FACT HIS, THERE IS BIG
OVERHANG.
THERE IS A BIG QUESTION MARK ON
YOUR HEAD.
AND YOU CAN'T DO THAT TO THE
PARTY.
YOU REALLY CAN'T.
YOU CAN'T DO THAT TO THE PARTY.
YOU HAVE TO HAVE CERTAINTY.
EVEN IF IT WAS 1% CHANCE AND FAR
GREATER THAN 1% BECAUSE WASN'T
BORN -- YOU HAVE GREAT
CONSTITUTIONAL LAWYERS SAY YOU
CAN'T RUN.
YOU KNOW, I'M NOT BRINGING A
SUIT, I PROMISE BUT THE
DEMOCRATS ARE GOING TO BRING A
LAWSUIT.
AND YOU HAVE TO HAVE CERTAINTY.
YOU CAN'T HAVE A QUESTION.
I CAN AGREE WITH YOU OR NOT.
BUT YOU CAN'T HAVE A QUESTION
OVER YOUR HEAD.
[SHOUTING]
MODERATOR: SENATOR, WANT TO
RESPOND?
>> LISTEN, I SPENT MY ENTIRE
LIFE DEFENDING THE CONSTITUTION
BEFORE THE U.S. SUPREME COURT
AND I'LL TELL YOU I'M NOT GOING
TO BE TAKING LEGAL ADVICE FROM
DONALD TRUMP.
>> YOU DON'T HAVE TO.
TAKE IT FROM LAURENCE TRIBE.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
TAKE IT FROM YOUR PROFESSOR.
TAKE IT FROM YOUR OWN PROFESSOR.
>> CHANCES OF ANY LITIGATION
PROCEEDING AND SUCCEEDING ON
THIS, ARE ZERO.
NOW MR. TRUMP --
>> THAT'S WRONG.
>> HE IS VERY FOCUSED ON LARRY
TRIBE.
LET ME TELL YOU WHO LARRY TRIBE
IS.
LEFT-WING JUDICIAL ACTIVIST
HARVARD LAW PROFESSOR, AL GORE'S
LAWYER IN BUSH VERSUS GORE.
HE IS MAJOR HILLARY CLINTON
SUPPORTER.
THERE IS REASON WHY HILLARY
SUPPORTERS ARE ECHOING DONALD'S
ATTACKS ON ME.
BECAUSE --
>> HE IS NOT ONLY ONE.
NOT ONLY ONE.
THERE ARE MANY LAWYERS.
>> AND I'LL TELL YOU WHAT,
DONALD, YOU VERY KINDLY JUST A
MOMENT AGO OFFERED ME VP SLOT.
I'LL TELL YOU WHAT.
IF THIS ALL WORKS OUT I'M HAPPY
TO CONSIDER NAMING YOU AS VP AND
SO IF YOU HAPPEN TO BE RIGHT,
YOU COULD GET THE TOP JOB AT END
OF THE DAY.
>> NO.
I THINK --
[APPLAUSE]
I LIKE IT, I WOULD CONSIDER IT
BUT I THINK I WILL GO BACK TO
BUILDING BUILDINGS IF IT DOESN'T
WORK OUT.
>> ACTUALLY I I LOVE YOU TO BUID
A WALL.
>> I HAVE A FEELING IT WILL WORK
OUT ACTUALLY.
>> NEIL, I COULD TELL YOU THIS,
I WAS INVOKED IN THAT QUESTION.
IN THAT ANSWER.
LET ME, THE REAL QUESTION, HERE
I HATE TO INTERRUPT THIS EPISODE
OF "COURT TV" BUT THE REAL --
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
BUT, I THINK WE HAVE TO GET TO
WHAT THIS ELECTION HAS TO BE
ABOUT.
THIS IS THE GREATEST COUNTRY IN
THE HISTORY OF MANKIND BUT IN
2008 WE ELECTED A PRESIDENT THAT
DIDN'T WANT TO FIX AMERICA.
HE WANTS TO CHANGE AMERICA.
WE ELECTED A PRESIDENT THAT
DOESN'T BELIEVE IN THE
CONSTITUTION.
HE UNDERMINES IT.
WE ELECTED A PRESIDENT THAT IS
WEAKENING AMERICA ON THE GLOBAL
STAGE.
WE ELECTED A PRESIDENT THAT
DOESN'T BELIEVE IN THE FREE
ENTERPRISE SYSTEM.
THIS ELECTION HAS TO BE ABOUT
REVERSING ALL OF THAT DAMAGE.
THAT IS WHY I'M RUNNING FOR
OFFICE.
BECAUSE WHEN I BECOME PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, ON MY
FIRST DAY IN OFFICE, WE ARE
GOING TO REPEAL EVERY SINGLE ONE
OF HIS UNCONSTITUTIONAL
EXECUTIVE ORDERS.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES --
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
-- WE ARE GETTING RID OF
OBAMACARE AND WE'RE REBUILDING
OUR MILITARY.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT WE WILL NOT
JUST HAVE A PRESIDENT THAT GIVES
STATE OF THE UNION THAT SAYS
AMERICA IS GREATEST COUNTRY OF
THE WORLD.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE WILL HAVE
A PRESIDENT THAT ACTS LIKE IT.
[BELL RINGING]
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SENATOR.
MR. TRUMP, SOUTH CAROLINA
GOVERNOR NIKKI HALEY IN THE
RESPONSE TO THE STATE OF THE
UNION ADDRESS --
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
APPEARED TO CHOOSE SIDES WITHIN
THE PARTY SAYING REPUBLICANS
SHOULD RESIST, QUOTE, THE SIREN
CALL OF THE ANGRIEST VOICES.
SHE CONFIRMED, SHE WAS REFERRING
TO YOU AMONG OTHERS.
WAS SHE OUT OF LINE?
, AND HOW WOULD A PRESIDENT
TRUMP UNITE THE PARTY?
>> OKAY.
FIRST OF ALL NICKY, THIS
AFTERNOON SAID I'M A FRIEND OF
HERS.
ACTUALLY A CLOSE FRIEND.
WHEREVER YOU ARE SITTING NICKY,
I'M A FRIEND.
WE'RE FRIEND.
THAT'S GOOD.
[LAUGHTER]
SHE DID SAY THERE WAS ANGER.
I'M VERY ANGRY BECAUSE OUR
COUNTRY IS BEING RUN HORRIBLY
AND I WILL GLADLY ACCEPT THE
MANTLE OF ANGER.
OUR MILITARY IS A DISASTER.
[APPLAUSE]
OUR HEALTH CARE IS HORROR SHOW.
OBAMACARE, WE'RE GOING TO REPEAL
IT AND REPLACE IT.
WE HAVE NO BORDERS.
OUR VETS ARE BEING TREATED
HORRIBLY.
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION IS BEYOND
BELIEF.
OUR COUNTRY IS BEING RUN BY
INCOMPETENT PEOPLE.
AND YES, I AM ANGRY.
AND I WON'T BE ANGRY WHEN WE FIX
IT BUT UNTIL WE FIX IT, I'M
VERY, VERY ANGRY.
I SAY THAT TO NICKY.
SO WHEN NICKY SAID THAT, I
WASN'T OFFENDED.
SHE SAID THE TRUTH.
ONE OF YOUR COLLEAGUES
INTERVIEWED ME.
AND SAID, WELL, SHE SAID YOU
WERE ANGRY.
I SAID TO MYSELF, HUH, SHE'S
RIGHT.
I'M NOT FIGHTING THAT.
I DIDN'T FIND IT OFFENSIVE AT
ALL.
I'M ANGRY BECAUSE OUR COUNTRY IS
A MESS.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: BUT WHAT ARE YOU
GOING TO DO ABOUT IT?
>> TIME CONSTRAINT.
YOU AND GOVERNOR CHRISTIE HAVE
BEEN EXCHANGING FAIRLY NASTY
WORDS OF LATE, I WILL ALLOW THE
GOVERNOR TO RESPOND AS WELL.
THE GOVERNOR WENT SO FAR TO SAY
YOU WON'T BE ABLE TO SLIME YOUR
WAY TO THE WHITE HOUSE.
REFERRING TO A SERIES OF ADS
DONE BY A PAC SPEAKING ON YOUR
BEHALF SAY QUOTE, ONE HIGH TAX
COMMON CORE LIBERAL
ENERGY-LOVING OBAMACARE MEDICAID
EXPANDING PRESIDENT IS ENOUGH.
YOU THINK YOU WENT TOO FAR ON
THAT AND DO YOU WANT TO
APOLOGIZE TO THE GOVERNOR?
>> YOU KNOW, AS I SAID ALREADY
TWICE IN THIS DEBATE WE HAVE
VERY SERIOUS PROBLEM IN THIS
COUNTRY.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES THAT IS
UNDERMINING THIS COUNTRY'S
SECURITY AND EXPANDING THE ROLE
OF --
MODERATOR: THAT IS NOT MY
QUESTION.
>> I WILL ANSWER YOUR QUESTION,
NEIL.
THIS PRESIDENT IS UNDERMINING
THE CONSTITUTIONAL BASIS OF THIS
GOVERNMENT.
THIS PRESIDENT IS UNDERMINING
OUR MILITARY.
HE IS UNDERMINING OUR STANDING
IN THE WORLD.
I LIKE CHRIS CHRISTIE BUT WE CAN
NOT AFFORD TO HAVE A PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES THAT
SUPPORTS COMMON CORE.
WE CAN NOT AFFORD TO HAVE A
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
THAT SUPPORTS GUN CONTROL.
THIS PRESIDENT, THIS PRESIDENT
IS MORE INTERESTED IN FUNDING,
LESS INTERESTED IN FUNDING
MILITARY THAN HE IS IN -- MORE
INTERESTED IN FUNDING PLANNED
PARENTHOOD THAN HE IS IN FUNDING
THE MILITARY.
CHRIS CHRISTIE WROTE A CHECK TO
PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
ALL I'M SAYING OUR NEXT
PRESIDENT IS SOMEONE THAT UNDOES
THE DAMAGE BARACK OBAMA HAS DONE
TO THIS COUNTRY.
IT CAN NOT BE SOMEONE THAT
AGREES WITH HIS AGENDA.
THE DAMAGE HE HAS DONE TO
AMERICA IS EXTRAORDINARY.
IF WE DON'T GET THIS ELECTION
RIGHT THERE MAY BE NO TURNING
BACK ON AMERICA.
WE'RE ON VERN OF FIRST
GENERATION OF AMERICANS THAT
LEAVE OUR CHILDREN WORSE OFF
TRAN OURSELVES.
I TRULY WITH ALL MY HEART
BELIEF, I LIKE EVERYBODY ON THE
STAGE.
NO ONE IS SOCIAL IT.
NO ONE HERE IS UNDER FBI
INVESTIGATION.
WE HAVE GOOD GROUP OF PEOPLE.
MODERATOR: IS HE A LIBERAL?
>> UNFORTUNATELY GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE HAS ENDORSED MANY OF
THE IDEAS THAT BARACK OBAMA
SUPPORTS WHETHER IT IS COMMON
CORE OR GUN CONTROL OR POINTMENT
OF SONIA SOTOMAYOR OR DONATION
HE MADE TO PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
OUR NEXT PRESIDENT, REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE CAN NOT BE SOMEONE WHO
SUPPORTS THOSE POSITIONS.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR?
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> I STOOD ON STAGE AND WATCHED
MARCO IN RATHER INDIGNANTLY LOOK
AT GOVERNOR BUSH AND SAY,
SOMEONE TOLD YOU THAT BECAUSE
WE'RE RUNNING FOR THE SAME
OFFICE THAT CRITICIZING ME WILL
GET YOU TO THAT OFFICE.
IT APPEARS THE SAME SOMEONE HAS
BEEN WHISPERING IN OLD MARCO'S
EAR TOO.
SO THE INDIGNATION THAT YOU
CARRY ON, SOME OF THE STUFF YOU
HAVE TO ALSO OWN THEN.
SO LET'S SET THE FACTS STRAIGHT.
FIRST OF AIL I DIDN'T SUPPORT
SONIA SOTOMAYOR.
SECONDLY I NEVER WROTE A CHECK
TO PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
THIRD, IF YOU LOOK AT MY RECORD
AS GOVERNOR OF NEW JERSEY, I
HAVE VETOED 50-CALIBER RIFLE
BAN.
I VETOED REDUCTION THIS CLIP
SIZE.
I VETOED STATEWIDE I.D. SYSTEM
FOR GUN OWNERS AND I PARDON, SIX
OUT-OF-STATE FOLKS WHO CAME
THROUGH OUR STATE ARRESTED FOR
OWNING A GUN LEGALLY IN ANOTHER
STATE SO THEY DIDN'T HAVE TO
FACE CHARGES.
COMMON CORE HAS BEEN ELIMINATED
IN NEW JERSEY.
THIS IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
GOVERNOR AND A SENATOR.
SEE WHEN YOU'RE SENATOR, WHAT
YOU GET TO DO IS TALK AND TALK
AND TALK YOU TALK SO MUCH THAT
NOBODY CAN EVER KEEP UP WITH
WHAT YOU'RE SAYING IS ACCURATE
OR NOT.
WHEN YOU'RE A GOVERNOR, YOU'RE
HELD ACCOUNTABLE FOR EVERYTHING
YOU DO.
AND THE PEOPLE OF NEW JERSEY
HAVE SEEN IT.
[APPLAUSE]
AND LAST PIECE IS THIS.
I LIKE MARCO TOO.
AND, TWO YEARS AGO HE CALLED ME
A CONSERVATIVE REFORMER THAT
NEW JERSEY NEEDED.
THAT WAS BEFORE HE WAS RUNNING
AGAINST ME.
NOW THAT HE IS HE CHANGED HIS
TUNE.
I'M NEVER GOING TO CHANGE MY
I LIKE MARCO RUBIO.
HE IS A GOOD GUY, A SMART GUY
AND HE WOULD BE A HECK OF A LOT
BETTER PRESIDENT THAN HILLARY
RODHAM CLINTON WOULD EVER BE.
>> NEIL MY NAME WAS MENTIONED
HERE.
NEIL MY NAME WAS MENTIONED AS
WILL.
[APPLAUSE]
HERE'S THE DEAL, CHRIS IS
TOTALLY RIGHT.
HE HAS BEEN A GOOD GOVERNOR.
AND HE IS A HECK OF A LOT BETTER
THAN HIS PREDECESSOR THAT WOULD
HAVE BANKRUPTED NEW JERSEY.
EVERYBODY ON THIS STAGE IS
BETTER THAN HILLARY CLINTON.
AND I THINK THE FOCUS OUGHT TO
BE ON MAKING SURE THAT WE LEAVE
THIS NOMINATION PROCESS AS WILD
AND WOOLY AS IT IS GOING TO BE,
THIS IS NOT BEING BAD, THESE
ATTACK ADS ARE PART OF LIFE.
EVERYBODY NEEDS TO GET USED TO
IT.
EVERYBODY'S RECORD WILL BE
SCRUTINIZED.
AT END OF THE DAY WE NEED TO
UNITE BEHIND THE WINNER SO WE
CAN DEFEAT HILLARY CLINTON
BECAUSE SHE IS A DISASTER.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
OUR COUNTRY RISE UP AGAIN BUT WE
NEED A COMPELLING CONSERVATIVE
AGENDA WE PRESENT TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE IN A WAY THAT
DOESN'T DISPARAGE PEOPLE, THAT
UNITES US AROUND OUR COMMON
PURPOSE.
EVERYBODY NEEDS TO DISCOUNT SOME
OF THE THINGS YOU HEAR IN THE
ADS AND DISCOUNT THE BACK AND
FORTH BECAUSE EVERY PERSON HERE
IS BETTER THAN HILLARY CLINTON.
>> NEIL, I WAS MENTIONED TO.
MODERATOR: YOU WERE?
>> YAY, THEY SAID EVERYBODY.
[LAUGHTER]
AND I WANT TO TAKE THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO SAY, IN THE 2012
ELECTION, YOU KNOW WE, AND WHEN
I SAY WE, REPUBLICANS TORE
THEMSELVES APART.
YOU KNOW, WE HAVE TO STOP THIS
BECAUSE, YOU KNOW, IF WE MANAGE
TO DAMAGE OURSELVES, AND WE LOSE
THE NEXT ELECTION, AND
PROGRESSIVE GETS IN THERE AND
THEY GET TWO OR THREE SUPREME
COURT PICKS, THIS NATION IS OVER
AS WE KNOW IT.
WE HAVE TO LOOK AT THE BIG
PICTURE HERE.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR KASICH --
[APPLAUSE]
GOVERNOR KASICH, HILLARY CLINTON
IS GETTING SERIOUS COMPETITION
FROM SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
HE IS NOW AT 41% IN THE LATEST
"CBS/NEW YORK TIMES POLL."
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN SANG HIS
PRAISES SAYING BERNIE IS
SPEAKING TO A YEARNING THAT IS
DEEP AND REAL.
HE HAS CREDIBILITY ON IT.
SO WHAT DOES IT SAY ABOUT OUR
COUNTRY THAT A CANDIDATE WHO IS
THE SELF-AVOWED SOCIAL IT, AND
WHO DOESN'T THINK A 90% TAX RATE
IS TOO HIGH, COULD BE THE
DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE?
>> WELL, IF THAT IS THE CASE,
WE'RE GOING TO WIN EVERY STATE
IF BERNIE SANDERS IS THE
NOMINEE.
THAT IS NOT EVEN AN ISSUE.
BUT LOOK --
[APPLAUSE]
AND I KNOW BERNIE AND I CAN
PROMISE YOU HE WILL NOT BE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
HERE IS THE SITUATION, I THINK,
MARIA.
THIS IS -- I HAVE TO TELL YOU
WHEN WAGES DON'T RISE, AND THEY
HAVEN'T FOR A LOT OF FAMILIES
FOR A NUMBER OF YEARS IT IS
VERY, VERY DIFFICULT FOR THEM.
PART OF THE REASON WHY IT HASN'T
RISEN BECAUSE SOMETIMES WE'RE
NOT GIVING PEOPLE THE SKILLS
THEY NEED.
SOMETIMES IT'S BECAUSE THE
FEDERAL RESERVE KEPT INTEREST
RATES SO LOW THAT THE WEALTHY
WERE ABLE TO INVEST IN STRONG
ASSETS LIKE THE STOCK MARKET
WHEN EVERYBODY ELSE WAS LEFT
BEHIND.
PEOPLE ARE UPSET ABOUT IT.
TELL YOU WHAT UPSET THEY'RE
UPSET B YOU'RE 50, 51 YEARS OLD
AND SOME KID WALKS IN TELLS
YOU'RE OUT OF WORK AND YOU DON'T
KNOW WHERE TO GO OR WHERE TO
TURN.
DO WE HAVE ANSWER TO THAT?
WE DO.
THERE ARE WAYS TO TRAIN 50 AND
51-YEAR-OLDS BECAUSE THEY HAVE
GREAT VALUE.
TELL YOU WHAT ELSE PEOPLE ARE
CONCERNED ABOUT.
THE KIDS COME OUT OF COLLEGE,
THEY HAVE HIGH DEBT AND CAN'T
GET A GOOD JOB.
WE HAVE TO DO A LOT ABOUT HIGH
COST OF EDUCATION BUT WE HAVE TO
MAKE SURE WE'RE TRAINING PEOPLE
FOR JOBS THAT EXIST ARE GOOD
JOBS THAT CAN PAY.
LET ME TELL YOU THAT IN THIS
COUNTRY, IN THIS COUNTRY, PEOPLE
ARE CONCERNED ABOUT THEIR
ECONOMIC FUTURE.
THEY'RE VERY CONCERNED ABOUT IT.
AND THEY WONDER WHETHER SOMEBODY
IS GETTING SOMETHING TO KEEPING
THEM FROM GETTING IT.
THAT IS NOT THE AMERICA THAT I
EVER KNOW.
MY FATHER USED TO SAY, JOHNNY,
WE DON'T HATE THE RICH.
WE JUST WANT TO BE THE RICH.
WE GOT TO MAKE SURE THAT EVERY
AMERICAN HAS THE TOOLS.
IN K THROUGH 12 AND VOCATIONAL
EDUCATION AND HIGHER EDUCATION.
WE GOT TO FIGHT LIKE CRAZY SO
PEOPLE CAN THINK THE AMERICAN
DREAM STILL EXISTS BECAUSE IT
DOES, WITH RISING WAGES, WITH
FULL EMPLOYMENT, AND WITH
EVERYBODY IN AMERICA.
I MEAN EVERYBODY IN AMERICA.
HAVING AN OPPORTUNITY TO REALIZE
THE AMERICAN DREAM OF HAVING A
BETTER LIFE THAN THEIR MOTHER
AND THEIR FATHER.
I'M PRESIDENT.
LOOK, I'VE DONE IT ONCE.
I'VE DONE IT ONCE IN WASHINGTON
WITH GREAT JOBS AND LOWER TAXES.
THE ECONOMY WAS REALLY BOOMING.
AND NOW IN OHIO, WITH THE SAME
FORMULA, WAGES HIGHER THAN THE
NATIONAL AVERAGE.
A GROWTH OF 385,000 JOBS.
IT IS NOT THAT HARD.
JUST KNOW WHERE YOU WANT TO GO,
STICK TO YOUR GUTS.
GET IT DONE BECAUSE OUR CHILDREN
AND GRANDCHILDREN ARE COUNTING
ON US TO GET IT DONE.
AND FOLKS WE WILL.
YOU COUNT ON IT.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: DR. CARSON, ONE OF
THE OTHER CANDIDATES ON THIS
STAGE HAS BROUGHT UP BILL
CLINTON'S PAST INDISCRETIONS.
IS THAT A LEGITIMATE TOPIC IN
THIS ELECTION?
AND WHAT DO YOU THINK OF THE
NOTION THAT:IS AN ENABLER OF
SEXUAL MISCONDUCT?
>> WELL THERE IS NO QUESTION
THAT WE SHOULD BE ABLE TO LOOK
AT ANY PAST PRESIDENT, WHETHER
THEY'RE MARRIED TO SOMEBODY WHO
IS RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT OR NOT
IN TERMS OF THEIR PAST BEHAVIOR
AND WHAT IT MEANS.
BUT YOU KNOW, HERE'S THE REAL
ISSUE.
IS THIS AMERICA ANYMORE?
DO WE STILL HAVE STANDARDS?
DO WE STILL HAVE VALUES AND
PRINCIPLES?
YOU LOOK AT WHAT IS GOING ON.
YOU SEE ALL THE DIVISIVENESS AND
HATRED THAT GOES ON IN OUR
SOCIETY.
WE HAVE A WAR ON VIRTUALLY.
>>.
RACE CARS, GENDER WARS, INCOME
WARS, RELIGIOUS WARS, AGE WARS.
EVERY WAR YOU CAN IMAGINE WE
HAVE PEOPLE AT EACH OTHER'S
THROATS.
AND OUR STRENGTH IS ACTUALLY IN
OUR UNITY.
YOU KNOW, YOU GO TO THE
INTERNET, START READING ARTICLE,
GO THROUGH THE COMMENT SECTION,
YOU CAN NOT GO FIVE COMMENTS
DOWN BEFORE PEOPLE ARE CALLING
EACH OTHER ALL MANNER OF NAMES.
WHERE DID THAT SPIRIT COME FROM
IN AMERICA?
IT DID NOT COME FROM OUR
JUDEO-CHRISTIAN ROOTS, I CAN
TELL YOU THAT AND WHEREVER IT
CAME FROM --
[APPLAUSE]
WE NEED TO START ONCE AGAIN
RECOGNIZING THAT THERE IS SUCH A
THING AS RIGHT AND WRONG.
AND LET'S NOT LET THE SECULAR
PROGRESSIVES DRIVE THAT OUT OF
US.
THE MAJORITY OF PEOPLE IN
AMERICA ACTUALLY HAVE VALUES AND
PRINCIPLES AND BELIEVE IN VERY
THINGS THAT MADE AMERICA GREAT.
THEY HAVE BEEN BEATEN INTO
SUBMISSION.
TIME FOR US TO STAND UP FOR WHAT
WE BELIEVE IN.
[APPLAUSE]
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT, WE ARE NOT
DONE.
COMING UP, ONE OF TOP ISSUES
PEOPLE ARE TALKING ABOUT ON
FACEBOOK, GUNS.
AND YOU CAN JOIN US LIVE ON THIS
STAGE IN THE CONVERSATION.
DURING THIS COMMERCIAL BREAK
RIGHT FROM HOME.
YOU CAN GO TO FACEBOOK.COM/FOX
BUSINESS.
WE WILL BE STREAMING LIVE AND
TALKING ABOUT HOW WE THINK THE
DEBATE IS GOING SO FAR.
WE'RE BACK IN A MOMENT FROM
CHARLESTON, SOUTH CAROLINA.
[APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
RIGHT HERE IN NORTH CHARLESTON.
RIGHT BACK TO THE QUESTIONS.
GOVERNOR BUSH, GUN RIGHTS, ONE
OF THE TOP ISSUES SEEN ON
FACEBOOK.
WITH CLOSE TO 3 MILLION PEOPLE
TALKING ABOUT IT IN THE PAST
MONTH.
RIGHT HERE IN CHARLESTON,
DYLANN ROOF ACCUSED OF KILLING
NINE PEOPLE IN A NEARBY CHURCH
REPORTEDLY HAD NOT PASSED HIS
BACKGROUND CHECK WHEN HE GOT
HIS GUN.
WHAT IS THE HARM IN TIGHTENING
STANDARDS FOR NOT ONLY WHO BUYS
GUNS, BUT THOSE WHO SELL THEM?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I'D LIKE TO
RECOGNIZE GOVERNOR HALEY FOR
HER INCREDIBLE LEADERSHIP IN
THE AFTERMATH OF THE --
[APPLAUSE]
>> THE EMANUEL AME CHURCH
KILLINGS, AND WANT TO RECOGNIZE
THE PEOPLE IN THAT CHURCH THAT
SHOWED THE GRACE OF GOD AND THE
GRACE OF FORGIVENESS AND THE
MERCY THAT THEY SHOWED.
[APPLAUSE]
>> I DON'T KNOW IF ANY OF US
COULD HAVE DONE WHAT THEY DID
WITHIN 48 HOURS AFTER THAT
TRAGEDY TAKING PLACE.
HERE'S THE DEAL, IN THIS
PARTICULAR CASE, THE FBI MADE A
MISTAKE.
THE LAW ITSELF REQUIRES A
BACKGROUND CHECK, BUT THEY
DIDN'T FULFILL THEIR PART OF
THE BARGAIN WITHIN THE TIME
THAT THEY WERE SUPPOSED TO DO.
WE DON'T NEED TO ADD NEW RULES,
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THE FBI
DOES ITS JOB.
THAT PERSON SHOULD NOT HAVE
GOTTEN A GUN, WOULD NOT HAVE
PASSED A BACKGROUND CHECK.
THE FIRST IMPULSE OF BARACK
OBAMA AND HILLARY CLINTON IS TO
TAKE RIGHTS AWAY FROM
LAW-ABIDING CITIZENS, THAT'S
WHAT THEY DO, WHETHER IT'S THE
SAN BERNARDINO ATTACK OR THE
TERRORIST TRAGEDIES THAT TAKE
PLACE, WE NEED TO FOCUS ON WHAT
THE BIGGER ISSUE IS.
IT ISN'T LAW-ABIDING GUN
OWNERS.
I HAVE A+ RATING IN THE NRA, IN
FLORIDA IF YOU COMMIT A CRIME
WITH A GUN, YOU'RE GOING AWAY,
GOING AWAY FOR A LONG, LONG
WHILE.
WE SHOULD FOCUS ON THE VIOLENCE
IN OUR COMMUNITIES, TARGET THE
EFFORTS FOR PEOPLE COMMITTING
CRIMES WITH GUNS, IF YOU DO
THAT AND GET IT RIGHT, YOU'RE
MUCH BETTER OFF THAN CREATING A
POLITICAL ARGUMENT WHERE
THERE'S A BIG DIVIDE.
THE OTHER ISSUE IS MENTAL
HEALTH.
THAT'S A SERIOUS ISSUE THAT WE
COULD WORK ON.
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS ALIKE
BELIEVE THIS.
[APPLAUSE]
>> THE PRESIDENT'S FIRST
IMPULSE IS DO IT BY EXECUTIVE
ORDER, POWER HE DOESN'T HAVE.
BEGIN THE PROCESS OF MENTAL
HEALTH ISSUES SO THAT PEOPLE
THAT ARE SPIRALING OUT OF
CONTROL BECAUSE OF MENTAL
HEALTH CHALLENGES DON'T HAVE
ACCESS TO GUNS.
[APPLAUSE]
>> THANK YOU, SIR, MR. TRUMP,
ARE THERE ANY CIRCUMSTANCES
THAT YOU THINK WE SHOULD BE
LIMITING GUN SALES OF ANY KIND
IN AMERICA?
>> NO.
I AM A 2nd AMENDMENT PERSON.
IF WE HAD GUNS IN CALIFORNIA ON
THE OTHER SIDE WHERE THE
BULLETS WENT IN THE DIFFERENT
DIRECTION, YOU WOULDN'T HAVE 14
OR 15 PEOPLE DEAD RIGHT NOW.
IF EVEN IN PARIS IF THEY HAD
GUNS GOING IN THE OPPOSITE
DRECK, YOU WOULDN'T HAVE 130
PEOPLE PLUS DEAD.
THE ANSWER IS NO.
WHAT JEB SAID IS ABSOLUTELY
CORRECT.
WE HAVE A HUGE MENTAL HEALTH
PROBLEM IN THIS COUNTRY.
WE'RE CLOSING HOSPITALS, WE'RE
CLOSING WARDS, WE'RE CLOSING SO
MANY BECAUSE THE STATES WANT TO
SAVE MONEY.
WE HAVE TO GET BACK INTO
LOOKING AT WHAT'S CAUSING IT.
THE GUNS DON'T PULL THE
TRIGGER.
IT'S THE PEOPLE THAT PULL THE
TRIGGER, AND WE HAVE TO FIND
OUT WHAT IS GOING ON.
[APPLAUSE]
>> WE HAVE TO PROTECT OUR 2nd
AMENDMENT AND YOU CANNOT DO
THIS AND CERTAINLY WHAT BARACK
OBAMA WAS DOING WITH THE
EXECUTIVE ORDER.
HE DOESN'T WANT TO GET PEOPLE
TOGETHER, THE OLD-FASHIONED
WAY, WHERE YOU GET CONGRESS,
THE CONGRESS, YOU GET THE
SENATE, YOU GET TOGETHER, YOU
DO LEGISLATION.
HE JUST WRITES OUT EXECUTIVE
ORDER.
NOT SUPPOSED TO HAPPEN THAT
WAY.
[APPLAUSE]
>> THANK YOU, SIR.
SENATOR RUBIO YOU SAID
PRESIDENT OBAMA WANTS TO TAKE
PEOPLE'S GUNS AWAY, UNDER HIS
PRESIDENCY GUN SALES HAVE MORE
THAN DOUBLE.
THAT DOESN'T SOUND LIKE A WHITE
HOUSE UNFRIENDLY TO GUN OWNERS.
>> SOUNDS LIKE PEOPLE -- THE
PRESIDENT IS GOING TO TAKE GUN
AWAY.
[APPLAUSE]
>> LOOK, THE 2nd AMENDMENT IS
NOT AN OPTION, NOT A
SUGGESTION, IT IS A
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT OF EVERY
AMERICAN TO BE ABLE TO PROTECT
THEMSELVES AND THEIR FAMILIES.
I AM CONVINCED IF THIS
PRESIDENT COULD CONFISCATE
EVERY GUN, HE WOULD.
I AM CONVINCED IF HE COULD GET
RID OF THE 2nd AMENDMENT HE
WOULD.
I SEE HOW HE WORKS WITH THE
ATTORNEY GENERAL, NOT TO DEFEND
THE 2nd AMENDMENT BUT FIGURE
OUT WAYS TO UNDERMINE IT.
I HAVE SEEN HIM APPOINT PEOPLE
TO OUR COURTS NOT TO DEFEAT THE
2nd AMENDMENT BUT FIGURE OUT
WAYS TO UNDERMINE IT.
HERE'S MY SECOND PROBLEM.
NONE OF THE INSTANCES AS THE
REASON WHY HE'S DOING THESE
THINGS WOULD HAVE BEEN
PREVENTED.
YOU KNOW WHY?
CRIMINALS DON'T BUY GUNS FROM A
GUN SHOW OR COLLECTOR, AND
DON'T BUY GUNS FROM A GUN
STORE.
THEY STEAL THEM, GET THEM ON
THE BLACK MARKET.
AND LET ME TELL YOU, ISIS AND
TERRORISTS DO NOT GET GUNS FROM
A GUN SHOW.
[APPLAUSE]
>> HIS ANSWER, YOU NAME IT, IF
THERE IS AN ACT OF VIOLENCE IN
AMERICA, HIS IMMEDIATE ANSWER
BEFORE HE KNOWS THE FACTS IS
GUN CONTROL.
HERE'S A FACT, WE ARE IN A WAR
AGAINST ISIS.
THEY ARE TRYING TO ATTACKIS IN
AMERICA, ATTACKED US IN
PHILADELPHIA LAST WEEK,
ATTACKED US IN SAN BERNARDINO
TWO WEEKS AGO, AND THE LAST
LINE STANDING BETWEEN US AND
OUR FAMILIES MIGHT BE A GUN, WE
ARE DEFENDING THE 2nd
AMENDMENT, NOT UNDERMINING IT
THE WAY BARACK OBAMA DOES.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: WHAT CAN YOU POINT
TO, SENATOR.
>> WHAT FACT?
MODERATOR: WHAT FACT THAT THE
PRESIDENT WOULD TAKE AWAY
EVERYONE'S GUNS, YOU DON'T
THINK THAT'S EXTREME?
>> EVERY TWO WEEKS HE HOLDS A
PRESS CONFERENCE ABOUT HOW HE
CAN'T WAIT TO RESTRICT PEOPLE'S
ACCESS TO GUNS.
LET ME TELL YOU THIS, DO YOU
REMEMBER WHEN HE RAN FOR
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
AND HE WAS A CANDIDATE AND HE
WENT AND SAID THESE AMERICANS
ARE TRADITIONAL VALUES, THEY
ARE BITTER PEOPLE, AND THEY
CLING TO THEIR GUNS AND TO
THEIR RELIGION.
THAT TELLS YOU RIGHT AWAY WHERE
HE WAS HEADED IN ALL OF THIS.
THIS PRESIDENT EVER CHANCE HE
HAS EVER GOTTEN TRIED TO
UNDERMINE THE 2nd AMENDMENT.
HE DOESN'T MEET --
[APPLAUSE]
>> HERE'S THE DIFFERENCE, WHEN
HE MEETS WITH THE ATTORNEY
GENERAL IN THE WHITE HOUSE,
IT'S NOT HOW CAN WE PROTECT THE
2nd AMENDMENT RIGHTS OF
AMERICANS, GIVE ME OPTIONS HOW
IT WILL MAKE IT HARDER FOR
PEOPLE TO BUY GUNS.
THAT WILL NEVER HAPPEN WHEN I
AM PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
[APPLAUSE]
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, YOU
CRITICIZED THE PRESIDENT'S
VALUES ON GUN CONTROL, HASN'T
YOUR OWN POSITION ON GUNS
EVOLVED A NEW JERSEY LETTER
SAID YOU SIGNED SEVERAL LAWS TO
REGULATE THE POSSESSION OF
FIREARMS AND ARGUED BACK IN
AUGUST OF 2013, AND I QUOTE,
THE COMMONSENSE MEASURES WILL
STRENGTHEN NEW JERSEY'S TOUGH
GUN LAWS.
ISN'T THAT KIND OF WHAT THE
PRESIDENT WANTS TO DO NOW?
>> NO, ABSOLUTELY NOT.
THE PRESIDENT WANTS TO DO
THINGS WITHOUT WORKING WITH HIS
CONGRESS, WITHOUT WORKING WITH
THE LEGISLATURE, WITHOUT
GETTING THE CONSENT OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
AND THE FACT IS THAT'S NOT A
DEMOCRACY, THAT'S A
DICTATORSHIP.
AND WE NEED TO BE VERY, VERY
CONCERNED ABOUT THAT.
SEE HERE'S THE THING.
I DON'T THINK THE FOUNDERS PUT
THE 2nd AMENDMENT AS NUMBER 2
BY ACCIDENT.
I DON'T THINK THEY DROPPED ALL
THE AMENDMENTS INTO A HAT AND
PICKED THEM OUT OF A HAT.
THEY MADE THE 2nd AMENDMENT THE
2nd AMENDMENT BECAUSE IT IS
THAT IMPORTANT.
IN FACT IN NEW JERSEY, WE MADE
IT EASIER TO GET A CONCEAL AND
CARRY PERMIT.
WE MADE IT EASIER, NOT HARDER.
AND THE WAY WE'VE DONE IT IS
PROPERLY THROUGH REGULATORY
ACTION, NOT SIGNING
UNCONSTITUTIONAL EXECUTIVE
ORDERS, THIS GUY IS A PETULANT
CHILD.
THAT'S WHAT HE IS.
[APPLAUSE]
>> THE FACT IS, NEIL, LET'S
THINK ABOUT, I HOPE THE
PRESIDENT IS WATCHING TONIGHT
BECAUSE HERE'S WHAT I'D LIKE TO
TELL HIM.
MR. PRESIDENT, WE'RE NOT
AGAINST YOU, WE'RE AGAINST YOUR
POLICIES.
WHEN YOU BECAME PRESIDENT, YOU
HAD A DEMOCRATIC CONGRESS AND A
FILIBUSTER-PROOF DEMOCRATIC
SENATE.
YOU HAD ONLY 21 REPUBLICAN
GOVERNORS IN THIS COUNTRY, AND
NOW AFTER SEVEN YEARS OF YOUR
POLICIES, WE HAVE THE BIGGEST
MAJORITY SINCE THE 1920s IN THE
HOUSE, A REPUBLICAN MAJORITY IN
THE SENATE, AND 31 OUT OF 50
REPUBLICAN GOVERNORS.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE
REJECTED YOUR AGENDA AND NOW
YOU'RE TRYING TO GO AROUND IT.
THAT'S NOT RIGHT.
IT'S NOT CONSTITUTIONAL, AND WE
ARE GOING TO KICK YOUR REAR END
OUT OF THE WHITE HOUSE COME
THIS FALL.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: SO WHAT IS THE
ANSWER, SENATOR CRUZ, TO STOP
MASS SHOOTINGS AND VIOLENCE
CRIME UP IN 30 CITIES ACROSS
THE COUNTRY?
>> THE ANSWER IS SIMPLE, YOU
PROSECUTE CRIMINALS.
YOU TARGET THE BAD GUYS.
A MINUTE AGO NEIL ASKED WHAT
HAS PRESIDENT OBAMA DONE TO
ILLUSTRATE HE WANTS TO GO AFTER
GUNS?
WELL, HE APPOINTED ERIC HOLDER
AS ATTORNEY GENERAL, HE VIEWED
HIS MISSION AS BRAINWASHING THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE AGAINST GUNS.
HE APPOINTED SONIA SOTOMAYOR IN
THE SUPREME COURT, HE LAUNCHED
FAST AND FURIOUS, ILLEGALLY
SELLING GUNS TO MEXICAN DRUG
LORDS THAT WERE USED TO SHOOT
LAW ENFORCEMENT OFFICIAL.
AND I'LL TELL YOU WHAT HILLARY
CLINTON SAID, HILLARY CLINTON
SAID SHE AGREES WITH THE
DISSENTERS, THE SUPREME COURT
DISSENTERS IN THE HELLER CASE.
THERE WERE FOUR DISSENTERS AND
THEY SAID THEY BELIEVE THE 2nd
AMENDMENT PROTECTS NO
INDIVIDUAL RIGHT TO PROTECT AND
BEAR ARMS WHATSOEVER.
WHICH MEANS IF THEIR VIEW
PREVAILED AND THE NEXT
PRESIDENT GETS ONE, TWO, THREE,
MAYBE FOUR SUPREME COURT
JUSTICES, THE COURT WILL RULE
THAT NOT A SINGLE PERSON IN THE
ROOM HAS ANY RIGHT UNDER THE
2nd AMENDMENT AND THE
GOVERNMENT CAN CONFISCATE YOUR
GUNS.
AND I'LL NOTE THAT CALIFORNIA
DEMOCRATIC SENATOR DIANNE
FEINSTEIN SAID IF SHE COULD SAY
TO MR. AMERICA AND MRS. AMERICA
GIVE ME YOUR GUNS, I'M ROUNDING
THEM UP, SHE WOULD.
AND LET ME MAKE A FINAL POINT
ON THIS.
IN ANY REPUBLICAN PRIMARY,
EVERYONE IS GOING TO SAY THEY
SUPPORT THE 2nd AMENDMENT.
UNLESS YOU ARE CLINICALLY
INSANE --
[LAUGHTER]
>> THAT'S WHAT YOU SAY IN A
PRIMARY.
BUT THE VOTERS ARE SAFFIER THAN
THAT, THEY RECOGNIZE THAT
PEOPLE'S ACTIONS DON'T ALWAYS
MATCH THEIR WORDS.
I HAVE A PROVEN RECORD FIGHTING
THE 2nd AMENDMENT, THERE'S A
REASON THE GOVERNMENT OF
AMERICA ENDORSED ME IN THIS
CASE.
THERE'S A REASON THE NRA GAVE
ME FREEDOM CARD AWARD.
AND A REASON WHEN BARACK OBAMA
AND CHUCK SCHUMER CAME AFTER
RIGHT TO BEAR ARMS I LED THE
OPPOSITION ALONG WITH MILLIONS
OF AMERICANS, WE DEFEATED THAT
GUN CONTROL LEGISLATION, AND I
WOULD NOTE THE OTHER
INDIVIDUALS ON THIS STAGE WERE
NOWHERE TO BE FOUND IN THAT
FIGHT.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: SENATOR, LET ME
FOLLOW UP AND SWITCH GEARS.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU SUGGESTED
MR. TRUMP, QUOTE, EMBODIES NEW
YORK VALUES.
COULD YOU EXPLAIN WHAT YOU MEAN
BY THAT?
>> I THINK MOST PEOPLE KNOW
EXACTLY WHAT NEW YORK VALUES
ARE.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> I AM FROM NEW YORK.
>> YOU'RE FROM NEW YORK?
YOU MIGHT NOT.
BUT I PROMISE YOU IN THE STATE
OF SOUTH CAROLINA --
[LAUGHTER]
>> THEY DO.
AND LISTEN, THERE ARE MANY,
MANY WONDERFUL, WONDERFUL
WORKING MEN AND WOMEN IN THE
STATE OF NEW YORK.
BUT EVERYONE UNDERSTANDS THAT
THE VALUES IN NEW YORK CITY ARE
SOCIALLY LIBERAL OR
PRO-ABORTION OR PRO-GAY
MARRIAGE.
FOCUS AROUND MONEY AND THE
MEDIA.
AND I WOULD NOTE INDEED, THE
REASON I SAID THAT IS I WAS
ASKED, MY FRIEND DONALD HAS
TAKEN TO IT AS ADVANCE PLAYING
BRUCE SPRINGSTEEN'S BORN IN THE
USA.
AND I WAS ASKED WHAT I THOUGHT
OF THAT?
AND I SAID IF HE WANTED TO PLAY
A SONG?
MAYBE HE COULD PLAY NEW YORK,
NEW YORK?
AND THE CONCEPT OF NEW YORK
VALUES IS NOT THAT COMPLICATED
TO FIGURE OUT.
NOT TOO MANY YEARS AGO, DONALD
DID A LONG INTERVIEW WITH TIM
RUSSERT.
AND IN THAT INTERVIEW HE
EXPLAINED HIS VIEWS ON A WHOLE
HOST OF ISSUES THAT WERE VERY,
VERY DIFFERENT FROM THE VIEWS
HE'S DESCRIBING NOW.
AND HIS EXPLANATION, HE SAID,
LOOK, I'M FROM NEW YORK, THAT'S
WHAT WE BELIEVE IN NEW YORK.
THOSE AREN'T IOWA VALUES BUT
THIS IS WHAT WE BELIEVE IN NEW
YORK.
THAT WAS HIS EXPLANATION, AND I
GUESS I CAN FRAME IT ANOTHER
WAY.
NOT A LOT OF CONSERVATIVES COME
OUT OF MANHATTAN.
I'M JUST SAYING.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> ARE YOU SURE ABOUT THAT?
MODERATOR: MARIA, SO
CONSERVATIVES ACTUALLY DO COME
OUT OF MANHATTAN.
>> INCLUDING WILLIAM F. BUCKLEY
AND OTHERS, JUST SO YOU
UNDERSTAND.
AND JUST SO -- IF I COULD,
BECAUSE HE INSULTED A LOT OF
PEOPLE.
I'VE HAD MORE CALLS ON THAT
STATEMENT THAT TED MADE.
NEW YORK IS A GREAT PLACE, IT'S
GOT GREAT PEOPLE, IT'S GOT
LOVING PEOPLE, WONDERFUL
PEOPLE.
WHEN THE WORLD TRADE CENTER
CAME DOWN, I SAW SOMETHING THAT
NO PLACE ON EARTH COULD HAVE
HANDLED MORE BEAUTIFULLY, MORE
HUMANELY THAN NEW YORK.
YOU HAD TWO --
[APPLAUSE]
>> YOU HAD TWO 110-STORY
BUILDINGS COME CRASHING DOWN.
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE KILLED AND
THE CLEANUP STARTED THE NEXT
DAY, AND IT WAS THE MOST
HORRIFIC CLEANUP PROBABLY IN
THE HISTORY OF DOING THIS, AND
IN CONSTRUCTION, I WAS DOWN
THERE.
AND I'VE NEVER SEEN ANYTHING
LIKE IT.
AND THE PEOPLE IN NEW YORK
FOUGHT AND FOUGHT AND FOUGHT,
AND WE SAW MORE DEATH AND EVEN
THE SMELL OF DEATH NOBODY
UNDERSTOOD IT.
AND IT WAS WITH US FOR MONTHS.
THE SMELL.
THE AIR.
AND WE REBUILT DOWNTOWN
MANHATTAN, AND EVERYBODY IN THE
WORLD WATCHED, AND EVERYBODY IN
THE WORLD LOVED NEW YORK AND
LOVED NEW YORKERS, AND I HAVE
TO TELL YOU, THAT WAS A VERY
INSULTING STATEMENT THAT TED
MADE.
[APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR BUSH, FOR
THE THIRD TIME IN AS MANY
MONTHS, THE IRANIANS HAVE
PROVOKED US, AS WE'VE BEEN
DISCUSSING THE TEN NAVY SAILORS
STRAIGHT INTO THE WATERS, THE
SAILORS WERE RELEASED ONLY
AFTER SHOWN ON VIDEO
APOLOGIZING FOR THE INCIDENT.
THIS OCCURRING ONLY WEEKS AFTER
IRAN FIRED MULTIPLE ROCKETS
WITHIN 1500 YARDS OF A U.S.
AIRCRAFT CARRIER AND CONTINUED
TO TEST MEDIUM RANGE MISSILES.
NOW YOU CLAIM THAT SUCH ACTIONS
INDICATE TEHRAN HAS LITTLE TO
FEAR FROM A PRESIDENT OBAMA.
I WONDER, SIR, WHAT WOULD
CHANGE IF THEY CONTINUED DOING
THIS SORT OF THING UNDER A
PRESIDENT JEB BUSH?
>> FIRST OF ALL, UNDER
PRESIDENT JEB BUSH, WE WOULD
RESTORE THE STRENGTH OF THE
MILITARY.
LAST WEEK, SECRETARY CARTER
ANNOUNCED THAT THE NAVY'S GOING
TO BE CUT AGAIN.
IT'S NOW HALF THE SIZE OF WHAT
IT WAS PRIOR TO OPERATION
DESERT STORM.
THE DEPLOYMENTS ARE TOO HIGH
FOR THE MILITARY PERSONNEL.
WE DON'T HAVE PROCUREMENT DONE
FOR REFRESHING THE EQUIPMENT.
B-52 IS STILL OPERATIONAL AS
THE LONG RANGE BOMBER,
INAUGURATED IN THE AGE OF HARRY
TRUMAN.
THE PLANES ARE OLDER THAN THE
PILOTS.
WE'RE GUTTING OUR MILITARY AND
SO THE IRANIANS AND THE CHINESE
AND THE RUSSIANS AND MANY OTHER
COUNTRIES LOOK AT UNITED STATES
NOT AS SERIOUS AS WE ONCE WERE.
WE HAVE TO ELIMINATE THE
SEQUESTER, REBUILD THE MILITARY
IN A WAY THAT MAKES IT CLEAR
THAT WE'RE BACK IN THE GAME.
SECONDLY, AS IT RELATES TO
IRAN, WE NEED TO CONFRONT
AMBITIONS ACROSS THE BOARD.
REIMPOSE SANCTIONS, THEY
VIOLATED SANCTIONS AFTER THE
AGREEMENT WAS SIGNED BY TESTING
MEDIUM-RANGE MISSILES.
THIRDLY, WE NEED TO MOVE OUR
EMBASSY FROM TEL AVIV TO
JERUSALEM TO SEND A SERIOUS
SIGNAL WE'RE BACK IN THE GAME
WITH ISRAEL --
[APPLAUSE]
>> AND SIGN AN AGREEMENT TO
MAKE SURE THE WORLD KNOWS THEY
WILL HAVE TECHNOLOGICAL
SUPERIORITY.
WE NEED TO GET BACK IN THE GAME
AS IT RELATES TO OUR ARAB
NATIONS.
REST OF THE WORLD IS MOVING
AWAY FROM US, TOWARDS OTHER
ALLIANCES BECAUSE WE'RE WEAK.
THIS PRESIDENT AND JOHN KERRY
AND HILLARY CLINTON ALL HAVE
MADE IT HARDER FOR THE NEXT
PRESIDENT TO ACT, BUT HE MUST
ACT TO CONFRONT THE AMBITIONS
OF IRAN.
WE CAN GET BACK IN THE GAME TO
RESTORE ORDER AND SECURITY FOR
OUR OWN COUNTRY.
[APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
GOVERNOR KASICH, WHILE EVERYONE
IS FOCUSING ON IRAN'S
PROVOCATIONS, WONDERING WHAT
YOU MAKE OF WHAT SAUDI ARABIA
IS DOING AND RECENT MOVES IN
THE REGION, INCLUDING EXECUTION
OF A WELL-KNOWN SHIITE CLERIC
AND MOVE TO DRAMATICALLY
INCREASE OIL PRODUCTION.
SOME SAY AN EFFORT TO DRIVE
DOWN OIL PRICES AND FORCE A LOT
OF U.S. OIL PRODUCERS OUT OF
BUSINESS.
SURE ENOUGH OIL PRICES TUMBLED.
ONE BROKERAGE HOUSE IS
PREDICTING A THIRD OR MORE OF
AMERICAN OIL PRODUCERS AND
THOSE HEAVILY INVESTED IN
FRACKING WILL GO BANKRUPT, AND
SOON SAUDI ARABIA AND OPEC WILL
BE BACK IN THE DRIVER'S SEAT.
U.S. ENERGY PLAYER HAROLD
HAMRIE SAID WITH FRIENDS LIKE
THESE, WHO NEEDS ENEMYS?
>> I SERVED ON THE DEFENSE
COMMITTEE FOR 18 YEARS, AND BY
THE WAY, ONE OF THE MEMBERS OF
THE COMMITTEE WAS SENATOR STROM
THURMOND FROM SOUTH CAROLINA.
AFTER THE 9/11 ATTACKS,
SECRETARY RUMSFELD INVITED ME
TO THE PENTAGON WITH A MEETING
WITH THE FOUR FORMERS
SECRETARIES OF DEFENSE.
I SUGGESTED WE HAD A PROBLEM
WITH TECHNOLOGY, AND THEY
WANTED TO INVOLVE SILICON
VALLEY INTO THE PENTAGON TO
SOLVE OUR MOST SIGNIFICANT
PROBLEMS.
I NOT ONLY HAD THE OPPORTUNITY
TO GO THROUGH THE COLD WAR
STRUGGLES IN CENTRAL AMERICA,
AND EVEN AFTER 9/11 TO BE
INVOLVED, WITH SAUDI ARABIA AND
OIL PRODUCTION, FIRST OF ALL,
IT'S SO CRITICAL FOR US TO BE
ENERGY DEPENDENT AND GETTING
THERE BECAUSE OF FRACKING AND
WE OUGHT TO EXPLORE, ENERGY
INDEPENDENCE GIVES US LEVERAGE
AND FLEXIBILITY, AND SECONDLY,
IF YOU WANT TO BRING JOBS BACK
TO THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
AND INDUSTRY, LOW PRICES MAKE
THE DIFFERENCE.
WE'RE SEEING IT IN MY STATE AND
SEE IT IN THIS COUNTRY.
THAT'S WHY WE MUST MAKE SURE WE
CONTINUE TO FRACK.
IN TERMS OF SAUDI ARABIA, LOOK,
MY BIGGEST PROBLEM WITH THEM IS
FUNDING RADICAL CLERICS THROUGH
THEIR MEDROCES, THAT IS A BAD
DEAL.
WHETHER I'M PRESIDENT OR NOT,
MAKE IT CLEAR TO THE SAUDIS,
WE'RE GOING TO SUPPORT YOU,
WE'RE IN RELATION WITH YOU JUST
LIKE THE FIRST GULF WAR, BUT
YOU GOT TO KNOCK OFF THE
FUNDING AND TEACHING OF RADICAL
CLERICS WHO ARE THE VERY PEOPLE
WHO TRY TO DESTROY US AND WILL
TURN AROUND AND DESTROY THEM.
SO LOOK, IN FOREIGN POLICY, IN
FOREIGN POLICY, IT'S STRENGTH,
BUT YOU GOT TO BE COOL, YOU GOT
TO HAVE A CLEAR VISION OF WHERE
YOU WANT TO GO, AND I'M GOING
TO TELL YOU THAT I'M GOING TO
SUGGEST TO YOU HERE TONIGHT,
THAT YOU CAN'T DO ON-THE-JOB
TRAINING.
I'VE SEEN SO MUCH OF IT, SOVIET
UNION, COMING DOWN OF THE WALL.
ISSUES WE SAW AROUND THE WORLD
IN CENTRAL AMERICA, THE
POTENTIAL SPREAD OF COMMUNISM
AND EVEN IN AND THE GULF WAR.
YOU SEE WITH THE SAUDIS DELIVER
THEM A STRONG MESSAGE, BUT AT
THE END OF THE DAY, KEEP OUR
COOL BECAUSE MOST OF THE TIME
THEY'RE GOING RIGHT WITH US AND
THEY MUST BE PART OF OUR
COALITION TO DESTROY ISIS, AND
I BELIEVE WE CAN GET THAT DONE.
THANK YOU.
[APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
MUCH MORE AHEAD INCLUDING THE
FIGHT AGAINST ISIS, MORE FROM
CHARLESTON, SOUTH CAROLINA WHEN
WE COME RIGHT BACK.
.
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
RIGHT BACK TO THE QUESTIONS.
CANDIDATES, THE MAN WHO MADE
FIGHTING ISIS THE CORNERSTONE
OF HIS CAMPAIGN, SOUTH CAROLINA
SENATOR LINDSEY GRAHAM IS OUT
OF THE RACE, BUT HE JOINS US
TONIGHT IN THE AUDIENCE.
[APPLAUSE]
>> HE SAYS, HE SAYS THE
AIRSTRIKES NOW IN THEIR 16th
MONTH HAVE BEEN INEFFECTIVE.
DR. CARSON --
>> WAIT A MINUTE, WHO IN THE
16th MONTH.
MODERATOR: THE AIRSTRIKES.
NOW IN THE 16th MONTH ARE
INEFFECTIVE.
DR. CARSON, DO YOU THINK
SENATOR GRAHAM IS RIGHT IN
WANTING TO SEND 20,000 TROOPS,
GROUND TROOPS TO IRAQ AND SYRIA
TO TAKE OUT ISIS?
>> WELL, THERE'S NO QUESTION
THAT ISIS IS A VERY SERIOUS
PROBLEM, AND I DON'T BELIEVE
THAT THIS ADMINISTRATION
RECOGNIZES HOW SERIOUS IT IS.
I THINK WE NEED TO DO A LOT
MORE THAN WE'RE DOING.
RECOGNIZE THAT THE CALIPHATE IS
WHAT GIVES THEM LEGITIMACY TO
GO OUT ON A JIHADIST MISSION
WEEK NEED TO TAKE THAT AWAY
FROM THEM, THE WAY IS TO TALK
TO MILITARY OFFICIALS AND ASK
THEM WHAT DO YOU NEED IN ORDER
TO ACCOMPLISH THIS GOAL?
OUR DECISION IS THEN DO WE GIVE
THEM WHAT WE NEED.
I SAY YES, NOT ONLY DO WE GIVE
THEM WHAT THEY NEED, BUT DON'T
TIE THEIR HANDS BEHIND THEIR
BACKS SO THEY CAN GET THE JOB
DONE.
[APPLAUSE]
>> IN ADDITION TO THAT, WE GO
AHEAD AND WE TAKE THE OIL FROM
THEM, THEIR SOURCE OF REVENUE.
YOU KNOW, SOME OF THESE
ENGAGEMENT RULES THAT THE
ADMINISTRATION HAS WERE NOT
GOING TO BOMB A TANKER COMING
OUT OF THERE BECAUSE THERE
MIGHT BE A PERSON IN IT.
GIVE ME A BREAK.
JUST TELL THEM, YOU PUT PEOPLE
IN THERE, WE'RE GOING TO BOMB
THEM.
DON'T PUT PEOPLE IN THERE IF
YOU DON'T WANT THEM BOMBED.
WE NEED TO SHUT DOWN THE
MECHANISM FOR FUNDING AND
ATTACK THEIR COMMAND AND
CONTROL CENTERS.
WHY SHOULD WE LET THEIR PEOPLE
SMOKING THEIR CIGARS, SITTING
IN COMFORTABLE CHAIRS IN RAQAA.
WE NEED TO SHUT OFF THE SUPPLY
ROUTES AND SEND IN SPECIAL OPS
AT 2:00 A.M. AND ATTACK THEM
EVERYWHERE THEY GO.
THEY SHOULD BE RUNNING ALL THE
TIME, THEN THEY WON'T HAVE TIME
TO PLAN ATTACKS AGAINST US.
[APPLAUSE]
>> THANK YOU, SIR, SENATOR
GRAHAM HAS ALSO SAID THAT THE
U.S. WILL FIND ARAB SUPPORT FOR
ITS COALITION IF IT REMOVES
SYRIAN PRESIDENT BASHAR
AL-ASSAD AND I QUOTE, THE NOW
KING OF SAUDI ARABIA TOLD US
YOU CAN HAVE OUR ARMY, YOU JUST
GOT TO DEAL WITH ASSAD.
AMIR OF QATAR SAID I'LL PAY FOR
THE OPERATION BUT THEY ARE NOT
GOING TO FIGHT ISIS AND LET
DAMASCUS FALL INTO THE HANDS OF
THE IRANIANS.
ASSAD HAS TO GO.
GOVERNOR CHRISTY, HOW IMPORTANT
IS IT TO REMOVE ASSAD FROM
POWER AND HOW WOULD YOU DO IT?
>> YOU LOOK AT WHAT THE
PRESIDENT AND SECRETARY CLINTON
HAS DONE, THIS IS THE PRESIDENT
WHO SAID ALONG WITH THE
SECRETARY OF STATE THROUGH A
RED LINE IN SYRIA, IF ASSAD
USES CHEMICAL WEAPONS AGAINST
HIS PEOPLE, WE'RE GOING TO
ATTACK.
HE USED CHEMICAL WEAPONS, HE'S
KILLED A QUARTER OF A MILLION
OF HIS OWN PEOPLE AND THIS
PRESIDENT HAS DONE NOTHING.
HE'S DONE WORSE THAN NOTHING.
THIS PRESIDENT, AND BY THE WAY
SECRETARY CLINTON WHO CALLED
ASSAD A REFORMER, SHE CALLED
ASSAD A REFORMER.
NOW THE FACT IS WITH THIS
PRESIDENT HAS DONE IS INVITED
RUSSIA TO BRING IN VLADIMIR
PUTIN TO NEGOTIATE GIVING THE
CHEMICAL WEAPONS BACK FROM
ASSAD, YET WHAT DO WE HAVE
TODAY?
WE HAVE THE RUSSIANS AND
IRANIANS WORKING TOGETHER, NOT
TO FIGHT ISIS BUT TO PROP UP
ASSAD.
FACT OF THE MATTER IS WE'RE NOT
GOING TO HAVE PEACE.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE PEACE
IN SYRIA.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO BE ABLE TO
REBUILD UNLESS WE PUT IN A
NO-FLY ZONE, MAKE IT SAFE TR
THE FOLKS SO WE DON'T HAVE TO
TALK ABOUT REFUGEES ANYMORE.
THE SYRIANS SHOULD STAY IN
SYRIA.
SHOULDN'T BE GOING TO EUROPE.
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE PEACE
IN SYRIA WITH ASSAD IN CHARGE.
SENATOR GRAHAM IS RIGHT ABOUT
THIS.
IF WE WANT TO TRY TO REBUILD A
COALITION AS GOVERNOR KASICH
WAS SAYING BEFORE, WHAT WE
BETTER DO IS TO GET TO THE ARAB
COUNTRIES THAT BELIEVE THAT
ISIS IS A THREAT NOT ONLY TO
THEM BUT TO US AND TO WORLD
PEACE AND BRING THEM TOGETHER,
AND BELIEVE ME, ASSAD IS NOT
WORTH IT.
AND IF YOU GOING TO LEAVE THIS
TO HILLARY CLINTON, THE PERSON
WHO GAVE US THIS FOREIGN
POLICY, THE ARCHITECT OF IT,
AND GIVE HER ANOTHER FOUR
YEARS, THAT'S WHY I'M SPEAKING
OUT AS STRONGLY AS I AM ABOUT
THAT.
HILLARY CLINTON CANNOT BE
PRESIDENT.
IT WILL LEAD TO GREATER WAR IN
THIS WORLD, AND REMEMBER THIS,
AFTER HILLARY CLINTON AND
BARACK OBAMA HAD NEARLY 8
YEARS, WE HAVE FEWER
DEMOCRACIES IN THE WORLD THAN
WHEN THEY STARTED.
THAT MAKES THE WORLD LESS
PEACEFUL, LESS SAFE.
IN MY ADMINISTRATION, WE WILL
HELP TO MAKE SURE WE BRING
PEOPLE TOGETHER IN THE MIDDLE
EAST, AND WE WILL FIGHT ISIS
AND DEFEAT THEM.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SIR.
MR. TRUMP, YOUR COMMENT ABOUT
BANNING MUSLIMS FROM ENTERING
THE COUNTRY CREATED A
FIRESTORM.
ACCORDING TO FACEBOOK, IT WAS
THE MOST TALKED ABOUT MOMENT
ONLINE OF YOUR ENTIRE CAMPAIGN.
WITH MORE THAN 10 MILLION
PEOPLE TALKING ABOUT THE ISSUE,
IS THERE ANYTHING YOU'VE HEARD
THAT MAKES YOU WANT TO RETHINK
THIS POSITION?
>> NO.
[ LAUGHTER ]
LOOK, WE HAVE TO STOP WITH
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS.
WE HAVE TO GET DOWN TO CREATING
A COUNTRY THAT'S NOT GOING TO
HAVE THE KIND OF PROBLEMS THAT
WE'VE HAD WITH PEOPLE FLYING
PLANES INTO THE WORLD TRADE
CENTERS, WITH THE SHOOTINGS IN
CALIFORNIA.
WITH ALL THE PROBLEMS ALL OVER
THE WORLD.
I JUST LEFT INDONESIA, BOMB,
BOMB, BOMB, BOMB.
WE HAVE TO FIND OUT WHAT'S
GOING ON.
I SAID TEMPORARILY.
I DIDN'T SAY PERMANENTLY.
I SAID TEMPORARILY, AND I HAVE
MANY GREAT MUSLIM FRIENDS, AND
SOME OF THEM, I WILL SAY NOT
ALL, HAVE CALLED ME AND SAID
DONALD, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
YOU'RE EXPOSING AN UNBELIEVABLE
PROBLEM, AND WE HAVE TO GET TO
THE BOTTOM OF IT.
AND UNLIKE PRESIDENT OBAMA,
WHERE HE REFUSES TO USE THE
TERM OF WHAT'S GOING ON.
HE CAN'T USE THE TERM FOR
WHATEVER REASON, AND IF YOU
CAN'T USE THE TERM, YOU'RE
NEVER GOING TO SOLVE THE
PROBLEM.
MY MUSLIM FRIENDS, SOME, SAID
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
WE'LL GET TO THE BOTTOM OF IT,
BUT WE HAVE A SERIOUS PROBLEM,
AND WE CAN'T BE THE STUPID
COUNTRY ANYMORE.
WE'RE LAUGHED AT ALL OVER THE
WORLD.
>> DONALD, DONALD, I HOPE YOU
RECONSIDER THIS, BECAUSE THIS
POLICY IS A POLICY THAT MAKES
IT IMPOSSIBLE TO BUILD THE
COALITION NECESSARY TO TAKE OUT
ISIS.
THE KURDS ARE OUR STRONGEST
ALLIES, THEY'RE MUSLIM.
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO ALLOW THEM
TO COME TO OUR COUNTRY?
THE OTHER ARAB COUNTRIES HAVE A
ROLE IN THIS.
WE CAN'T BE THE WORLD'S
POLICEMEN, WE CAN'T DO IT
UNILATERALLY.
WE HAVE TO DO IT IN UNISON WITH
THE ARAB WORLD.
WE HAVE TO BE SERIOUS ABOUT
TAKING OUT ISIS AND RESTORING
DEMOCRACY IN SYRIA.
I HOPE YOU'LL RECONSIDER.
THE BETTER WAY OF DEALING WITH
THIS IS RECOGNIZING THAT THERE
ARE PEOPLE IN THE ISLAMIC
TERRORIST EMBEDDED REFUGEE
POPULATIONS, WE OUGHT TO
TIGHTEN UP OUR EFFORTS TO BEEF
UP THE ENTRY VISA PROGRAM SO A
CITIZEN FROM EUROPE, IT'S HARD
FER THEY'RE TRAVELING TO SYRIA
OR OTHER PLACES WHERE THERE IS
ISLAMIC TERRORISM, MAKE THE
SCREENING TAKE PLACE.
WE DON'T HAVE TO HAVE REFUGEES
COME TO THE COUNTRY, BUT ALL
MUSLIMS?
SERIOUSLY!
WHAT KIND OF SIGNAL DOES THAT
SEND TO THE REST OF THE WORLD
THAT THE UNITED STATES IS A
SERIOUS PLAYER IN CREATING
PEACE.
MODERATOR: YOU SAID IT
REPRESENTED HIM BEING UNHINGED.
>> THEY ARE UNHINGED.
MODERATOR: WELL, AFTER HE MADE
THEM.
POLL NUMBERS WENT UP 8 POINTS
IN SOUTH CAROLINA.
>> NO, NO, 11 POINTS TO BE
EXACT.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> ARE YOU SAYING THAT ALL
THOSE PEOPLE WHO AGREE WITH
MR. TRUMP ARE UNHINGEED?
>> NO, NOT AT ALL.
ABSOLUTELY NOT.
I CAN SEE WHY PEOPLE ARE ANGRY
AND SCARED BECAUSE THIS
PRESIDENT HAS CREATED A
CONDITION WHERE OUR NATIONAL
SECURITY HAS WEAKENED
DRAMATICALLY, I TOTALLY GET
THAT.
BUT WE'RE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENCY OF THE UNITED STATES
HERE.
THIS ISN'T -- THIS ISN'T A
DIFFERENT KIND OF JOB, YOU HAVE
TO LEAD.
YOU CANNOT MAKE RASH STATEMENTS
AND EXPECT THE REST OF THE
WORLD TO RESPOND AS THOUGH,
WELL, IT'S JUST POLITICS.
EVERY TIME WE SEND SIGNALS
LIKE, THIS WE SEND A SIGNAL OF
WEAKNESS, NOT STRENGTH.
IT WAS AN UNHINGED STATETETENT,
WHICH IS WHY I'M ASKING HIM TO
CONSIDER CHANGING HIS VIEWS.
[APPLAUSE]
>> I WOULD SECURITY FOR THIS
COUNTRY.
OKAY?
I WANT SECURITY.
I'M TIRED OF SEEING WHAT'S
GOING ON BETWEEN THE BORDER
WHERE THE PEOPLE FLOW OVER,
PEOPLE COME IN, THEY LIVE, THEY
SHOOT.
I WANT SECURITY FOR THIS
COUNTRY.
WE HAVE A SERIOUS PROBLEM WITH,
AS YOU KNOW, WITH RADICAL
ISLAM.
WE HAVE A TREMENDOUS PROBLEM.
NOT ONLY A PROBLEM HERE, IT'S A
PROBLEM ALL OVER THE WORLD.
I WANT TO FIND OUT WHY THOSE
TWO YOUNG PEOPLE, THOSE TWO
HORRIBLE YOUNG PEOPLE IN
CALIFORNIA WHEN THEY SHOT THE
14 PEOPLE, KILLED THEM.
PEOPLE THEY KNEW.
PEOPLE THAT HELD A WEDDING
RECEPTION FOR THEM.
I WANT TO FIND OUT, MANY PEOPLE
SAW PIPE BOMBS AND ALL SORTS OF
THINGS ALL OVER THEIR
APARTMENT.
WHY WEREN'T THEY VIGILANT?
WHY DIDN'T THEY CALL?
WHY DIDN'T THEY CALL THE
POLICE?
AND BY THE WAY, THE POLICE ARE
THE MOST MISTREATED PEOPLE IN
THIS COUNTRY.
I WILL TELL YOU THAT.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
>> THE MOST MISTREATED PEOPLE.
WE NEED -- WAIT A MINUTE, WE
NEED VIGILANCE.
WE NEED TO FIND OUT.
MANY PEOPLE KNEW ABOUT WHAT WAS
GOING ON.
WHY DIDN'T THEY TURN THE TWO
PEOPLE IN SO YOU WOULDN'T HAVE
HAD ALL THE DEATH?
THERE'S SOMETHING GOING ON AND
IT'S BAD.
AND I'M SAYING WE HAVE TO GET
TO THE BOTTOM OF IT.
THAT'S ALL I'M SAYING.
WE NEED SECURITY.
MODERATOR: WE WANT TO HEAR FROM
ALL OF YOU ON THIS.
ACCORDING TO PEW RESEARCH, THE
U.S. ADMITS MORE THAN 100,000
MUSLIM IMMIGRANTS EVERY SINGLE
YEAR ON A PERMANENT LIFETIME
BASIS.
I WANT TO ASK THE REST OF YOU
TO COMMENT ON THIS.
DO YOU AGREE THAT WE SHOULD
PAUSE MUSLIM IMMIGRATION UNTIL
WE GET A BETTER HANDLE ON OUR
HOMELAND SECURITY SITUATION, AS
MR. TRUMP SAID, BEGINNING WITH
YOU, GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> I'VE BEEN FOR PAUSING ON
ADMITTING THE SYRIAN REFUGEES.
AND THE REASON WHY I'VE DONE IS
I DON'T BELIEVE WE HAVE A GOOD
BE PROCESS OF BEING ABLE TO VET
THEM.
WE DON'T WANT TO PUT EVERYBODY
IN THE SAME CATEGORY.
AND GO BACK TO SOMETHING
MENTIONED A FEW MINUTES AGO.
IF WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A
COALITION, WE'RE GOING TO HAVE
TO HAVE A COALITION NOT JUST OF
PEOPLE IN THE WESTERN PART OF
THE WORLD, OUR EUROPEAN ALLIES,
BUT WE NEED THE SAUDIS, WE NEED
THE EGYPTIANS, WE NEED THE
JORDANIANS, WE NEED THE GULF
STATES.
WE NEED JORDAN.
WE NEED ALL OF THEM TO BE PART
OF EXACTLY WHAT THE FIRST
GEORGE BUSH PUT TOGETHER IN THE
FIRST GULF WAR.
IT WAS A COALITION MADE UP OF
ARABS AND AMERICANS AND
WESTERNERS AND WE'RE GOING TO
NEED IT AGAIN, AND IF WE TRY TO
PUT EVERYBODY IN THE SAME --
CALL EVERYBODY THE SAME THING,
WE CAN'T DO IT.
AND THAT'S JUST NOT ACCEPTABLE.
BUT I THINK A PAUSE ON SYRIAN
REFUGEES HAS BEEN EXACTLY RIGHT
FOR ALL THE GOVERNORS THAT HAVE
CALLED FOR IT, AND ALSO, OF
COURSE, FOR MESA THE GOVERNOR
OF OHIO.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SIR, WE
WANT TO HEAR FROM THE REST OF
YOU, GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, YOUR
TAKE.
>> MARIA, I SAID FROM THE
BEGINNING WE SHOULD TAKE NO
SYRAN REFUGEES OF ANY KIND.
THAT'S THE END OF THE
CONVERSATION, I CAN TELL YOU
AFTER SPENDING SEVEN YEARS AS A
FORMER FEDERAL PROSECUTOR,
RIGHT AFTER 9/11, DEALING WITH
THIS ISSUE, HERE'S THE WAY YOU
NEED TO DEAL WITH IT.
YOU CAN'T JUST BAN ALL MUSLIMS.
YOU HAVE TO BAN RADICAL ISLAMIC
JIHADISTS, BAN THE PEOPLE
TRYING TO HURT US.
THE ONLY WAY TO FIGURE THAT OUT
IS TO GO BACK TO GETTING THE
INTELLIGENCE COMMUNITY THE
FUNDING AND THE TOOLS THAT IT
NEEDS TO BE ABLE TO KEEP
AMERICA SAFE.
AND THIS SUMMER, WE TOOK IT
AWAY FROM THE NSA, IT WAS A BAD
DECISION BY THE PRESIDENT.
BAD BY THOSE IN THE SENATE WHO
VOTED FOR IT.
IF I'M PRESIDENT WE'LL MAKE OUR
INTELLIGENCE COMMUNITY STRONG,
AND WE'RE JUST GOING TO KEEP
THE BAD FOLK OUT AND MAKE SURE
THEY DON'T HARM US.
MODERATOR: SENATOR RUBIO, WHERE
DO YOU STAND.
>> LET'S FIND OUT WHY WE ARE
SEE ANGERED, THIS ISSUE HAS
CONSISTENTLY UNDERESTIMATED THE
THREAT OF ISIS.
IF YOU LISTEN TO THE STATE OF
THE UNION THE OTHER NIGHT, HE
DESCRIBED THEM AS A BUNCH OF
GUYS WITH LONG BEARDS ON THE
BACK OF A PICKUP TRUCK.
THEY ARE MUCH MORE THAN THAT.
THEY ENSLAVE WOMEN AND SELL
THEM AS BRIDES.
THIS IS A GROUP OF PEOPLE THAT
BURNS PEOPLE IN CAGES, THAT IS
CONDUCTING GENOCIDE AGAINST
CHRISTIANS AND YAZIDIS IN THE
REGION, THIS IS NOT A SMALL
SCALE GROUP, THEY ARE
RADICALIZING PEOPLE IN THE
UNITED STATES, CONDUCTING
ATTACKS AROUND THE WORLD.
WHAT NEEDS TO HAPPEN, IT'S A
VERY SIMPLE EQUATION, AND WILL
HAPPEN WHEN I'M PRESIDENT.
IF WE DO NOT KNOW WHO YOU ARE,
WHEN I AM PRESIDENT, YOU ARE
NOT GETTING INTO THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
[APPLAUSE]
>> SENATOR CRUZ, WHERE DO YOU
STAND?
SENATOR CRUZ?
>> YOU KNOW I UNDERSTAND WHY
DONALD MADE THE COMMENTS HE DID
AND I UNDERSTAND WHY AMERICANS
ARE FEELING FRUSTRATED AND
SCARED AND ANGRY WHEN WE HAVE A
PRESIDENT WHO REFUSES TO
ACKNOWLEDGE THE THREATS WE FACE
AND WORSE WHO ACTS AS AN
APOLOGIST FOR RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM.
I THINK WHAT WE NEED IS A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF FOCUSED LIKE
A LASER ON KEEPING THIS COUNTRY
SAFE AND ON DEFEATING RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
WHAT SHOULD WE DO?
FIRST, PASS THE EXPATRIATE
TERRORIST ACT, LEGISLATION I'VE
INTRODUCED THAT SAYS IF AN
AMERICAN GOES AND JOINS ISIS
AND WAGES JIHAD AGAINST
AMERICA, THAT YOU FORFEIT YOUR
CITIZENSHIP AND YOU NOT COME IN
ON A PASSPORT.
[APPLAUSE]
>> AND SECONDLY, WE SHOULD PASS
THE LEGISLATION THAT I'VE
INTRODUCED THAT SUSPENDS ALL
REFUGEES FROM NATIONS OR AL
QAEDA CONTROLS SIGNIFICANT
TERRITORY, JUST LAST WEEK, SEE
SAW TWO IRAQI REFUGEES VETTED
USING THE SAME PROCESS THE
PRESIDENT SAYS WILL WORK THAT
WERE ARRESTED FOR BEING ALLEGED
ISIS TERRORISTS, IF I'M ELECTED
PRESIDENT, WE WILL NOT LET IN
REFUGEES FROM COUNTRIES
CONTROLLED BY ISIS OR AL QAEDA.
WHEN IT COMES TO ISIS, WE WILL
NOT WEAKEN OR DEGRADE THEM, WE
WILL UTTERLY AND COMPLETELY
DESTROY ISIS.
>> WE NEED TO GET A GROUP OF
EXPERTS TOGETHER.
INCLUDING PEOPLE FROM OTHER
COUNTRIES, FROM ISRAEL, WHO
HAVE HAD EXPERIENCE SCREENING
THESE PEOPLE, COME UP WITH NEW
GUIDELINES FOR IMMIGRATION,
AND VISAS, THAT IS THING THAT
MAKES SENSE, WE CAN DO, THAT
AS FAR AS THIS SYRIANS,
PROVINCE, PERFECT PLACE.
THEY HAVE INFRASTRUCTURE.
ALL WE NEED IS PROTECT THEM,
THEY WILL BE IN OWN COUNTRY.
I WAS IN JORDAN IN NOVEMBER.
MODERATOR: YOU DO NOT AGREE?
>> ARE WE BANNING MUSLIMS FROM
INDIA?
FROM INDONESIA?
FROM COUNTRIES THAT ARE STRONG
ISIS, OF COURSE, NOT, I LAID
OUT A PLAN AT CIDA DELL TO DO
THAT WE NEED A FORCE, A SUNNI
LED FORCE IN SYRIA, WE NEED TO
EMBED WITH THE IRAQI MILITARY,
ARM THE CURS DIRECTLY, WE NEED
LAWYERS OFF THE BACK OF THE
WAR FIGHTERS, THAT IS HOW YOU
SOLVE THE PROBLEMS.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU GOVERNOR.
>> MR. TRUMP, SOMETIMES, MAYBE
IN HEAT OF CAMPAIGN, YOU SAY
THINGS AND HAVE TO DEAL THEM
BACK, LAST WEEK YOU WERE
QUOTED AS SAYING IMPOSING A
TARIFF ON CHINESE GOODS.
>> THEY ARE WRONG, THEY WERE
WRONG, IT IS THE "NEW YORK
TIMES," THEY ARE ALWAYS WRONG.
MODERATOR: YOU NEVER SAID?
>> I SAID THEY WERE ASKING ME
WHAT TO DO ABOUT NORTH KOREA,
CHINA, THEY DON'T LIKE TO TELL
US BUT THEY HAVE TOTAL CONTROL
JUST ABOUT OF NORTH KOREA.
THEY CAN SOLVE
PROBLEM OF NORTH KOREA IF THEY
WANTED TO, BUT THEY TAUNT US,
CHINA IS RIPPING US ON TRADE,
THEY ARE DEVALUING THEIR
CURRENCY AND KILLING OUR
COMPANIES, THOUSANDS -- YOU
LOOK AT NUMBER OF COMPANIES
AND NUMBER IN TERMS OF
MANUFACTURING OF PLANS, THAT
WE LOST, 50,000 BECAUSE OF
CHINA.
-- ANYWHERE BETWEEN 4 AND 7
MILLION JOBS, BECAUSE OF
CHINA, I SAID THIS.
WE HAVE VERY UNFAIR TRADE WITH
CHINA.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A TRADE
DEFICIT OF $505 BILLION THIS
YEAR WITH CHINA.
A LOT IS PAUSE THEY DEVALUED
THEIR CURRENCY.
WHAT I SAID TO THE "NEW YORK
TIMES" IS WE HAVE GREAT
ECONOMIC POWER OVER CHINA, IF
WE WANTED TO USE THAT AND THE
AMOUNT WITH 45% COMES IN, THAT
WOULD BE THE AMOUNT BASED ON
THEIR DEVALUATIONS, THAT WE
SHOULD GET, THAT WE SHOULD
GET, I'M SAYING, IF THEY DON'T
START TREATING US FAIRLY AND
STOP DEVALUES AND LET THEIR
CURRENCY RISE SO OUR COMPANIES
COME PETE, AND WE DON'T LOSE
MILLIONS OF JOBS WE'RE LOSING
I WOULD TAX GOODS THAT COME IN
FROM CHINA, WHO THE HELL HAS
TO LOSE $505 BILLION A YEAR.
MODERATOR: YOU LOST ME.
>> IT'S NOT THAT COMPLICATED.
MODERATOR: I APOLOGIZE.
IF YOU DON'T WANT A 45 PERCENT
TARIFF.
WOULD YOU BE OPEN ARE YOU OPEN
TO SLAPPING A HIGHER TARIFF ON
CHINESE GOODS OF ANY SORT TO
GO BACK.
>> JUST SO YOU UNDERSTAND, I
KNOW SO MUCH ABOUT TRADE WITH
CHINA, CARL ICAHN ENDORSED ME.
HE IS SOMEBODY -- THESE ARE
PEOPLE THAT WE SHOULD USE TO
NEGOTIATE.
NOT THE KIND OF PEOPLE WE
HAVE, WHO ARE POLITICAL HACKS
WHO DON'T KNOW WHAT THEY ARE
DOING, WE HAVE PROBLEMS LIKE
THIS.
WE SHOULD USE OUR BEST AND OUR
FINEST.
MODERATOR: ON THAT TARIFF.
>> HERE IS WHAT I'M SAYING,
CHINA THEY SEND THEIR GOODS WE
DON'T TAX THEY DO WHATEVER
THEY WANT.
OKAY.
WHAT WHEN WE DO BUSINESS WITH
CHINA, THEY TAX US, YOU DON'T
KNOW IT THEY TAX US, I HAVE
MANY FRIENDS THAT DEAL WITH
CHINA, THEY CAN'T DEAL, NUMBER
ONE THEY DON'T WANT THE
PRODUCT, WHEN THEY GET THE
PRODUCT IT TAXED, YOU LOOK AT
BOEING COULD AND WITH SO MANY
COMPANIES, THAT DEAL, WE DON'T
HAVE AN EQUAL PLAYING FIELD, I
AM SAYING, WE COACH HAVE TO
CONTINUE TO LOSE $5005 BILLION
AS A TRADE DEFICIT FOR
PRIVELAGE OF DEALING WITH
CHINA, I AM A FREE TRADER, WE
HAVE TO BE SMART, AND USE
SMART PEOPLE TO NEGOTIATE, I
HAVE THE LARGEST BANK IN THE
WORLD, I SELL TENS OF
MILLIONS, I LOVE CHINA, I LOVE
THE CHINESE PEOPLE.
BUT THEY LAUGH THEMSELVES,
THEY CAN'T BELIEVE HOW STUPID
THE AMERICAN LEADERSHIP IS.
MODERATOR: YOU ARE OPEN TO A
TARIFF?
>> I AM TOTALLY OPEN TO A
TARIFF.
IF THEY DON'T TREAT US FAIRLY.
THEIR WHOLE TRADE THING IS
TARIFF, YOU CAN'T DEAL IN
CHINA OUT TARIFF, THEY DO IT
TO US, WE DON'T DO IT IT IS
NOT FAIR TRADE.
>> NEIL, LET'S ME SAY, I AM A
FREE TRADER.
I SUPPORTED NAFTA, IT IS
IMPORTANT THOSE COUNTRIES IN
ASIA OR A INTERFACE IN CHINA,
WE DO NEED CHINA.
DONALD IS RIGHT ABOUT NORTH
KOREA, THEY DO NEED TO PUT
PRESSURE ON, WE NEED TO
INTERCEPT TRIPS COMING OUT OF
NORTH KOREA.
BUT I THINK WHAT HE IS TALKING
ABOUT HAS MERIT.
>> I LIKE HIM TONIGHT.
>> FOR TOO LONG, WHAT HAPPEN
IS, SOMEBODY DUMPS THEIR
PRODUCT IN OUR COUNTRY.
TAKES OUR PEOPLE'S JOBS, WE GO
TO A INTERNATIONAL COURT, IT
TAKES A YEAR OR TWO TO FIGURE
OUT THEY WERE CHEATING US.
GUESS WHAT?
THE WORKER IS OUT OF A JOB,
WHEN IT IS FOUND AGAINST THAT
COUNTRY SELLING PRODUCTS IN
HERE LOWER THAN THE COST TO
PRODUCE THEM, WHAT DO WE TELL
THE WORKER, OH,WELL, IT DONE
WORK OUT FOR YOU.
WE SHOULD BE FOR FREE TRADE
BUT FAIR TRADE, WHEN COUNTRIES
VIOLATE TRADE AGREEMENTS OR
DUMP PRODUCTSES HERE TO
STAND UP AGAINST THOSE
COUNTRIES THAT DO THAT,
WITHOUT MAKING THEM AN ENEMY.
HOW DO I KNOW THIS?
SO MANY PEOPLE IN MY FAMILY
WORKED IN STEEL MILLS, THEY
DID NOT WORK WITH THE WHITE
COLLAR THEY WORKED IN BLUE
COLLAR, THOSE -- JOBS ARE
CRITICAL THEY ARE HARD WORKING
MEMBERS OF THE MIDDLE CLASS,
THEY NEED TO BE PAID ATTENTION
TO, THEY ARE AMERICANS THEY
CARRY THE LOAD, DEMAND
OPEN TRADE BUT FAIR TRADE.
>> ON THIS POINT, IF I MAY
ADD.
WE'RE ALL FRUSTRATED WITH
CHINA, WE NEED TO BE CAREFUL
WITH TARIFF, CHINA DID NOT PAY
TARIFFS, THE BUYER PAYS THE
TARIFF, IF YOU SEND A TIE OR
SHIRT ON U.S., IT GETS PASSED
ON TO PRICE OF THE CONSUMER,
BEST THING TO PROTECT AGAINST
CHINA ECONOMY LIKE IS TO MAKE
OUR ECONOMY STRONGER THAT
MEANS PREVERSING COURSE FROM
ALL OF THE -- REVERSING COURSE
FROM ALL OF THE DAMAGE THAT
BARACK OBAMA DOING TO THIS
ECONOMY.
LET'S, LOW COMPANIES TO
IMMEDIATELY -- CONTINUES A
REGULATORY REFORM, REGULATION
IS OUT OF CONTROL.
ESPECIALLY THE EPA, AND ALL OF
THE RULES THEY IMPOSE ON OUR
ECONOMY AND HURTING US,
OBAMACARE?
A CERTIFIEDED JOB KILLER THAT
NEEDED TO BE REPEALED AND
REPLACED.
WE NEED TO MAKE OUR ECONOMY
STRONGER.
THAT IS THE WAY TO DEAL WITH
CHINA.
>> THE PROBLEM IS WHAT MARCO
SAID, IT TAKES TOO LONG, THEY
ARE SUCKING US DRY, YOU
ABSOLUTELY HAVE TO GET
INVOLVED WITH CHINA, THEY ARE
TAKING SO MUCH OF WHAT WE HAVE
IN TERMS OF JOBS IN
TERPS OF MONEY.
MODERATOR: HE IS RIGHT, THE
AMERICANS PAY.
>> YOU LOOKING AT ME.
>> PRICES GO HIGHER.
>> CAN I TELL YOU, IT WILL
NEVER HAPPEN, THEY WILL LET
THEIR CURRENCY GO UP, JAPAN
THE SAME THING, THEY ARE
DEVALUING, SO IMPOSSIBLE FOR
-- YOU LOOK AT CATERPILLAR
TRACTOR.
FRIENDS OF MINE ARE ORDERS
KAMATZU TRACTORS NOW, YOU
CAN'T BUY A CATERPILLAR
TRACTOR, WE'RE LETTING THEM
GET AWAY WITH IT, THAT IS WHY
WE HAVE TO USE CARL AND OUR
GREAT BUSINESS PEOPLE NOT
POLITICAL HACKS TO NEGOTIATE
WITH THESE GUYS.
>> APART FROM THE HIGHER
PRICES ON CONSUMERS, PEOPLE
LIVING PAYCHECK TO
PAYCHECK, THERE WILL BE
RETALIATION, SOYBEAN SALES
FROM IOWA, TO GOES TO CHINA OR
BOEING HERE WITHIN A MILE, YOU
THINK THAT CHINESE IF THEY HAD
A 45 PERCENT TARIFF ON THEIR
IMPORTS WOULD NOT BUY AIRBUS,
THEY WOULD, THIS WOULD BE
DEVASTATING FOR THE ECONOMY.
WE NEED SOMEONE WITH A STEADY
HAPPENED TO BE PRESIDENT OF
THE U.S.
>> SENATOR, GO AHEAD, THEN TAX
REFORM.
MODERATOR: WE DON'T NEED A
WEAK PERSON BEING PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES THAT IS -- I
TELL YOU WHAT -- WE DON'T NEED
THAT THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE NOW.
WE DON'T NEED THAT.
THAT IS WHY WE'RE IN THE
TROUBLE THAT WE'RE NOW -- BY
THE WAY JEB YOU MENTIONED
BOEING, LOOK.
THEY ORDER PLANES THEY MAKE
BOEING BUILD THEIR PLANT IN
CHINA.
>> THANK YOU, MR. TRUMP.
>> BRIEFLY.
>> MY NAME WAS MENTIONED.
THE PLANE THAT IS BEING BUILD
HERE IS SOLD TO CHINA.
YOU FLEW IN WITH YOUR 767.
>> THE NEW PLANTS NOT NOW IN
THE FUTURE THEY ARE BUILDING
MASSIVE PLANTS IN CHINA.
BECAUSE CHINA DOES NOT WANT
BOEING BUILDING THEIR PLANES
HERE THEY WANT THEM BUILT IN
CHINA, BECAUSE CHINA IS SMART
THE WAY THEY DO IT.
>> YOU HEAD BACK TO AIRPORT
CHECK.
>> I'LL CHECK.
>> CHECK IT OUT.
>> SENATOR.
>> THANK YOU FOR COMING BACK
TO ME.
BOTH DONALD AND JEB HAVE GOOD
POINTS THERE IS A MIDDLE
GROUND, DONALD IS RIGHT, CHINA
IS RUN OVER PRESIDENT OBAMA
LIKE HE IS A CHILD, PROBE IS
NOT PROTECTING AMERICAN
WORKERS, WE'RE GETTING
HAMMERED.
A SAT DOWN WITH SENIOR
LEADERSHIP OF JOHN DEERE THEY
DISCUSS HOW HARD IT IS TO SELL
TRACTORS IN CHINA, BUT JEB
ALSO RIGHT, IF WE JUST IMPOSE
A TARIFF THEY WILL PUT
RECIPROCAL TARIFFS THAT WILL
HURT THE IOWA FORMERS, YOU
PASS A TAX PLAN LIKE THE TAX
PLAN, A SIMPLE FLAT TAX, 10%
FOR INDIVIDUALS, 16% FLAT TAX,
YOU ABOLISH THE IRS.
HERE IS CRITICAL POINT, MARIA,
THE BUSINESS FLAT TAX ENABLES
US TO ABOLISH CORPORATE INCOME
TAX, DATE TAX,
OBAMACARE TAX, AND PAYROLL
TAX, A HUGE ADVANTAGE FOR
FORMERS, AND MANUFACTURERS,
EVERY IMPORT PAYS THE 16%
BUSINESS FLAT TAX, LIKE A
TARIFF.
BUT IF WE IMPOSE A TARIFF,
CHINA RESPONDS THE BUSINESS
FLAT TAX THEY ALREADY IMPOSE
THEIR TAX ON US.
IT PUTS US ON A LEVEL EVEN
PLAYING FIELD THAT BRINGS JOBS
HERE AT HOME, AS PRESIDENT I
WILL FIGHT FOR THE WORKING MAN
AND WOMEN.
MODERATOR: WE HAVE TO GET TO
TAX REFORM.
NATIONAL DEBT AS WELL, UP
NEXT, GROWING NATIONAL DEBT,
WAR ON CRIME ATTACK REFORM.
MORE FROM NORTH CHARLESTON,
SOUTH CAROLINA, WHEN WE
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
HERE IN NORTH CHARLESTON,
RIGHT BACK TO THE QUESTION,
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE WE'VE SPOKEN
ABOUT CUTTING SPENDING.
ACCORDING TO A REPORT,
AMERICAN NEEDS $3.6 TRILLION
IN INFRASTRUCTURE SPENDING BY
2020, HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA,
11% OF BRIDGES ARE CONSIDERED
STRUCTURAL DEFICIENT.
WHAT IS YOUR PLAN TO FIX THE
AILING ROADS AND BRIDGES
WITHOUT BREAKING THE BANK?
>> HERE IS OUR PLAN.
WE HAVE ALL BEEN TALKING ABOUT
TAX REFORM.
IF YOU REFORM CORPORATE TAX,
WHICH HAS MENTIONED BEFORE IS
HIGHEST RATE IN THE WORLD, WE
DOUBLE TAX, THAT LED TO OVER
$2 TRILLION OF AMERICAN
COMPANY'S MONEYS THAT ARE KEPT
OFFSHORE BECAUSE THEY DON'T
WANT TO PAY THAT SECOND TAX.
THEY PAY TAX ONCE OVERSEAS
THEY DON'T WANT TO PAY 35% TAX
ON THE WAY BACK.
BESIDE REFORMING THAT TAX TO
BRING IT DOWN TO 25 PERCENT,
AND ELIMINATING LOOPHOLES, BUT
ALSO, A ONE-TIME REPATRIATION
OF THE MONEY, BRIDGE THAT
MONEY BACK TO U.S., WE'LL TAX
8.75%.
I WOULD DEDICATE THAT MONEY TO
REBUILDING INFRASTRUCTURE
HERE.
IT WOULD BRIDGE THE MONEY BACK
INTO THE UNITED STATES TO HELP
BUILD JOBS BY AMERICAN
COMPANIES GET OUR ECONOMY
MOVING AND GROWING AS A HIGHER
RATE, AND REBUILD THE ROADS,
BRIDGES AND TUNNELS, THE LAST
PIECE.
THIS PRESIDENT, HAS PENALIZED
CORPORATIONS IN AMERICA.
HE DOES NOT UNDERSTAND, THAT
HURTS HARD WORKING TAXPAYERS.
YOU HAVE SEEN MIDDLE CLASS
WAGES GO BACKWARDS WITH THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION, THAT IS
WRONG FOR HARD WORKING TAX
PAYER, WE WOULD REBUILD
INFRASTRUCTURE TO CREATE JOBS,
AND WORK WITH THE STATES TO DO
IT THE RIGHT WAY, REMEMBER
THAT.
I AM CREDIBLE TO THIS FOR THIS
REASON, AMERICANS FOR TAX
REFORM SAID I VETOES MORE TAX
INCREASES THAN ANY GOVERNOR IN
AMERICAN HISTORY.
WE DON'T NEED TO RAISE TAXES
TO GET THIS DONE.
WE NEED TO GET SMARTER, REFORM
THE TAX SYSTEM, BRING
THE MONEY BACK TO U.S., ALL
THESE ARE IMPORTANT.
MODERATOR: DR. CARSON, IT IS
TRUE, U.S. COMPANIES HAVE $2
TRILLION IN CASH SITTING
OVERSEAS RIGHT NOW, THAT COULD
BE USED FOR INVESTMENT AND
JOBS IN AMERICA, ALSO.
SEVERAL COMPANIES RIGHT NOW,
ARE PURSUING MERGERS TO MOVE
THEIR CORPORATE HEADQUARTERS
ABROAD, AND TAKE ADVANTAGE OF
MUCH LOWER TAXES.
WHAT WILL YOU DO TO STOP THE
FLOW OF COMPANIES MOVING CASH
AWAY FROM AMERICA, AND THOSE
LEAVING AMERICA?
>> I WOULD SUGGEST A FAIR TAX
SYSTEM, THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE
PROPOSED.
A FLAT TAX, FOR EVERYONE, NO
EXEMPTIONS, NO DEDUCTTIONS, NO
SHELTERS, SOME PEOPLE HAVE A
BETTER CAPABILITY OF TAKING
ADVANTAGE OF THOSE THAN
OTHERS, OTHER THING IS STOP
SPENDING SO MUCH MONEY.
YOU KNOW, MY MOTHER TAUGHT ME
THIS, SHE HAD A THIRD GRADE
EDUCATION, SHE KNEW HOW TO
STRETCH A DOLLAR, SHE WOULD
DRIVE A CAR UNTIL IT WOULD NOT
MAKE A SOUND, GATHER HER COINS
AND BUY A NEW CAR.
IF MY MOTHER WERE SECRETARY OF
TREASURY WE WOULD NOT BE IN A
DEFICIT SITUATION.
BUT, YOU KNOW IF WE FIX THE
TAXATION SYSTEM, MAKE IT FAIR,
AND GET RID OF THE INCREDIBLE
REGULATIONS.
EVERY REGULATION IS A TAX.
ON GOODS AND SERVICES, IT IS
THE MOST REGRESSIVE TAX THERE.
IS YOU KNOW YOU GO TO THE
STORE, BUY A BOX OF LAUNDRY
DETERGENT, AND THE PRICE IS UP
50 CENTS BECAUSE OF
REGULATION, A POOR PERSON
NOTICES THAT, A POOR PERSON
DID YOU NOT, MIDDLE CLASS
NOTICES IT AT CASH REGISTER,
EVERYTHING IS COSTING MORE
MONEY.
WE'RE KILLING OUR PEOPLE LIKE
THIS BERNIE SANDERS AND
HILLARY CLINTON WILL SAY, IT
IS THE EVIL RICH PEOPLE, IT IS
NOT THE EVIL RICH PEOPLE, IT
IS THE EVIL GOVERNMENT THAT IS
PUTTING THESE REGULATIONS ON
US.
>> YOU WERE TALKING ABOUT
CORPORATE INVERSION,
CORPORATIONS BY THE THOUSANDS
ARE THINKING OF LEAVING THE
COUNTRY BECAUSE OF TAXES, BUT
THEY ARE ALSO LEAVING BECAUSE
THEY CAN'T GET THEIR MONEY
BACK IN EVERYONE AGREES IT
SHOULD COME BACK IN, BUT THEY
CAN'T GET ALONG.
HERE IS THE CASE THEY AGREE,
THEY CAN'T MAKE A DEAL, WE
HAVE TO DO SOMETHING,
CORPORATE INVERSION IS ONE OF
THE BIGGEST PROBLEMS WE HAVE.
SO MANY COMPANIES, ARE GOING
TO LEAVE OUR COUNTRY.
MODERATOR: THAT IS WHY WE
RAISED IT, THANK YOU, MR.
TRUMP.
>> ONE OF THE BIGGEST FISCAL
CHALLENGES IS OUR ENTITLEMENT
PROGRAM IN PARTICULAR SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE, WHAT
POLICIES WILL YOU PUT FORWARD
TO MAKE SURE THESE PROGRAMS
ARE MORE FINANCIALLY SECURE.
>> LET ME ADDRESS THE TAX
ISSUE.
I WOULD LIKE TO THANK YOU TO
HAVE SUBSTANTIVE DEBATES.
HERE IS ONE THING I'M NOT
DOING, I WILL NOT HAVE
SOMETHING THAT TED DESCRIBED
THE VALUE ADDED TAX, YOU FIND
THAT TAX IN MANY COMPANIES IN
EUROPE.
WHERE BUSINESSES PAY A TAX ON
MONEY THEY MAKE AND ALSO ON
MONEY THEY PAY THEIR
EMPLOYEES, IT IS A WAY TO
BLINDFOLDED THE PEOPLE, RONALD
REAGAN OPPOSED IT SAID IT WAS
A WAY TO BLIND FOAL THE
PEOPLE, SO TRUE COST OF
GOVERNMENT WAS THERE THERE FOR
THEM.
WHAT IS TO PREVENT A FUTURE
LIBERAL PRESIDENT OR CONGRESS
FROM COMING BACK NOT JUST
RAISING INCOME TAX BUT ALSO
THE VAT TAX, THAT IS ALSO BAD
FOR SENIORS, SENIORS, IF THEY
ARE RETIRED ARE NO LONGER
EARNING AN INCOME FROM A JOB,
THEY DO NOT GET THAT INCOME
TAX BREAK BUT THE PRICES WILL
BE HIGHER.
WHEN I AM PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, I AM SIDES WITH
RONALD REAGAN ON THIS, NOT
NANCY PELOSI, WE'RE NOT HAVING
A VAT TAX.
>> MARIA, MARCO HAS BEEN
FLOATING THIS TAX FOR A FEW
WEEKS NOW, BUT PROBLEM IS THAT
BUSINESS FLAT TAX IN MY
PROPOSAL IS NOT A VAT, A VAT
IS A SALES TAX WHEN YOU BUY A
GOODS, THIS IS A BUSINESS FLAT
TAX, IMPOSED ON THE
BUSINESSES, A CRITICAL PIECE
THAT MARCO IS MISSING THIS 16%
BUSINESS FLAT TAX ENABLES TO
US ELIMINATE CORPORATE INCOME
TAX, IT ELIMINATES THE DEATH
TAX IF YOU ARE A FARMER OR
RANCHER, THE DEATH TAX IS
GONE.
WE ELIMINATE PAYROLL TAX, THE
OBAMACARE TAX, AND THERE IS A
REAL DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
MARCO'S TAX PLAN AND MINE,
MINE GIVES EVERY AMERICAN A
FLAT TAX OF 10%.
MARCO'S TAX RATE IS 35%.
MY TAX PLAN ENABLES TO FILL
OUT YOUR TAXES ON A POST CARD
TO ABOLISH THE IRS, WE NEED TO
BREAK WASHINGTON CARTEL, ONLY
WAY TO DO IT IS END SUBSIDIES
AND MANDATES, FINAL
OBSERVATION, INVOKE RONALD
REAGAN, I WOULD NOTE ART
LAFFER HAS WRITTEN MY SIMPLE
FLAT TAX IS THE BEST TAX PLAN
OF ANY OF THE INDIVIDUALS ON
THIS STAGE, IT HELPS EVERYONE
FROM THE POOREST TO THE
RICHEST.
>> THAT NOT AN ACCURATE
DESCRIPTION OF THE PLAN, YOU
MAY RENAME THE IRS BUT YOU ARE
NOT ABOLISHES THE IRS, KNOW
WHAT WILL COLLECT OUR VAT TAX,
RONALD REAGAN'S TREASURY, WHEN
IT LOOKED AT VAT TAX THEY
FOUND THEY WOULD HAVE TO HIRE
20,000 NEW IRS AGENCIES TO
COLLECT IT IT DOES NOT
ELIMINATE CORPORATE TAX OR
PAYROLL TAX, BUSINESSES PAY
16% ON MONEY THEY MAKE, AND
16% ON MONEY THEY PAY THEIR
EMPLOYS, THERE ARE PEOPLE
WATCHING IN BUSINESS IF YOU
ARE NOW ON A 60% TAX ON INCOME
AND WAGES YOU PAY YOUR
EMPLOYS, WHERE YOU ARE GETTING
THAT MONEY FROM?
BY PAYING OUR EMPLOYS NEXT,
CHARGING YOUR CUSTOMERS MORE,
THE DIFFERENCE IS YOU DON'T
SEE IF ON THE BILL, YOU BLIND
FOAL THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, 16%
IS WHAT RATE THAT TED WANTS,
WHAT HAPPENS IF GOD FORBID THE
NEXT BARACK OBAMA TAKES OVER,
AND NANCY PELOSI, AND HARRY
REID, AND THEY SAY WE'LL RAISE
IT TO 30%, NOW YOU HAVE
EUROPE.
MODERATOR: I HAVE TO GET TO A
QUESTION.
>> MARIA --
>> DEBATE ON THE FLOOR OF
SENATE, TO ANSWER THE QUESTION
YOU ASK.
A ENTITLEMENT, DO YOU REMEMBER
THAT?
THERE WAS A QUESTION ON
ENTITLEMENTS, THE REASON --
YOU HAD YOUR CHANCE.
HERE IS THE THING.
REASON WHY THAT NO ONE WANTS
TO ANSWER ENTITLEMENT BECAUSE
IT IS HARD, A HARD PROBLEM IMF
-- I'M ONLY ONE IN APRIL THAT
PUT FORWARD A DETAIL
ENTITLEMENT REFORM PLAN.
THAT WOULD AVOID THIS, AVOID
WHAT HILLARY CLINTON WILL DO
TO YOU, BECAUSE WHAT SHE WILL
DO IS COME IN, SHE WILL RAISE
SOCIAL SECURITY TAXES, BERNIE
SANDERS SAID IT, SHE ONE OR
TWO MORE POLL DROPS DOWN, FROM
MOVING FURTHER LEFT THAN SHE
HAS ALREADY MOVES.
WE HAVE SENIORS OUT THERE WHO
ARE SCARED TO DATE, BECAUSE
THIS CONGRESS, THIS ONE THAT
WE HAVE RIGHT NOW, JUST STOLE
$150 BILLION FROM SOCIAL
SECURITY RETIREMENT
FUND TO GIVE IT SO SOCIAL
SECURITY DISABILITY FUND, THAT
IS WRONG, WE NEED TO REFORM
SOCIAL SECURITY.
MINE IS ONLY PLAN THAT SAVES
OVER A TRILLION DOLLARS, THAT
IS WHY I'M ANSWERING YOUR
QUESTIONS.
>> ONE THING, I WANT TO SAY.
YOU KNOW, LAST WEEK, WE
RELEASE OUR TAX PLAN, AND
MULTIPLE REPUTABLE JOURNALS
INCLUDING "WALL STREET
JOURNAL" SAY OURS IS THE BEST,
I JUST WANT TO GET THAT OUT
THEIR.
MODERATOR: COMING UP, HOW WILL
THE CANDIDATES PROTECT
AMERICA.
AND ANOTHER TERROR ATTACK, IF
WE WERE TO SEE IT, YOU CAN
JOIN US LIVE ONSTAGE DURING
THE COMMERCIAL BREAK FROM
HOME, WE'LL BE STREAMING LIVE
AND ANSWERING YOUR QUESTIONS,
DURING THE BREAK, MORE FROM
SOUTH CAROLINA COMING UP, STAY
WITH US.
.
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
RIGHT HERE IN NORTH CHARLESTON,
SOUTH CAROLINA.
LET'S GET RIGHT TO THE
QUESTION, MARIA?
>> MR. TRUMP, YOUR NET WORTH IS
IN THE MULTIBILLIONS OF
DOLLARS, AND HAVE AN ONGOING
THRIVING HOTEL AND REAL ESTATE
BUSINESS, ARE YOU PLANNING ON
PUTTING YOUR ASSETS IN A BLIND
TRUST YOU SHOULD BECOME
PRESIDENT.
WITH SUCH VAST WEALTH, HOW
DIFFICULT WILL IT TO BE TO
DISENTANGLE YOURSELF FROM YOUR
BUSINESS AND MONEY AND
PRIORITIZE AMERICA'S INTERESTS
FIRST?
>> WELL, IT'S AN INTERESTING
QUESTION BECAUSE I'M VERY PROUD
OF MY COMPANY, AS YOU, TOO KNOW
I BUILT A GREAT COMPANY.
IF I BECOME PRESIDENT, I
COULDN'T CARE LESS ABOUT MY
COMPANY.
IT'S PEANUTS.
I WANT TO USE THE SAME, UP
HERE, WHATEVER IT MAY BE, TO
MAKE AMERICA RICH AGAIN AND
MAKE AMERICA GREAT AGAIN.
I HAVE IVANKA AND ERIC AND DON
SITTING THERE, RUN THE COMPANY,
HAVE A GOOD TIME, I'M GOING TO
DO IT FOR AMERICA.
I WOULD BE WILLING TO DO IT.
MODERATOR: YOU WOULD PUT YOUR
ASSETS IN A BLIND TRUST?
>> I WOULD PUT IT IN A BLIND
TRUST.
I DON'T KNOW IF IT'S A BLIND
TRUST IF IVANKA AND DON AND
ERIC RUN IT.
I WOULD HAVE MY CHILDREN RUN IT
WITH EXECUTIVES AND WOULDN'T
EVER BE INVOLVED BECAUSE I
WOULDN'T CARE ABOUT ANYTHING
BUT OUR COUNTRY.
ANYTHING.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, SIR?
>> THANK YOU.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRISTIE,
GOING BACK TO U.S. ATTORNEY
DAYS, YOU HAVE BEEN PRAISED BY
BOTH PARTIES AS CERTAINLY A
TOUGH LAW AND ORDER GUY.
I WONDER WHAT YOU MAKE OF
RECENT STATISTICS, SIR, THAT
SHOW VIOLENT CRIME SPIKING
SOMETIMES BY DOUBLE DIGIT RATE
IN 30 CITIES ACROSS THE
COUNTRY.
MILWAUKEE'S POLICE CHIEF ED
FLYNN SAID MOST LOCAL LAW
ENFORCEMENT OFFICIALS FEEL
ABANDONED BY WASHINGTON.
FORMER NYC POLICE CHIEF RAY
KELLY SAYS POLICE ARE BEING
LESS PRO ACTIVE BECAUSE THEY
ARE OVERLY SCRUTINIZED AND
SECOND-GUESSED AND AFRAID OF
BEING SUED OR THROWN IN JAIL.
WHAT WOULD YOU DO AS PRESIDENT
TO ADDRESS THAT?
>> WELL, FIRST OFF, LET'S FACE
IT, THE FBI DIRECTOR JIM COMEY,
A FRIEND OF MINE WHO I WORKED
WITH AS U.S. ATTORNEY IN NEW
JERSEY HERE, WAS U.S. ATTORNEY
IN MANHATTAN.
HE SAID IT, THERE'S A CHILL
BLOWING THROUGH LAW ENFORCEMENT
IN THIS COUNTRY.
THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES AND BOTH ATTORNEYS
GENERAL GIVE THE BENEFIT OF THE
DOUBT TO THE CRIMINAL, NOT TO
THE POLICE OFFICER.
THAT'S THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER.
AND YOU SEE IT EVERY TIME WITH
THIS PRESIDENT.
EVERY TIME HE'S GOT A CHANCE,
GOING ALL THE WAY BACK TO
REMEMBER THE GREAT BEER SUMMIT
HE HAD AFTER HE MESSED UP THAT
TIME.
THIS IS A GUY WHO JUST BELIEVED
THAT LAW ENFORCEMENT ARE THE
BAD GUYS.
NOW I, FOR SEVEN YEARS, WAS THE
U.S. ATTORNEY IN NEW JERSEY.
I WORKED HARD WITH NOT ONLY
FEDERAL AGENTS BUT WITH POLICE
OFFICERS, AND HERE'S THE
PROBLEM, SANCTUARY CITIES IS
PART OF THE PROBLEM IN THIS
COUNTRY.
THAT'S WHERE CRIME IS HAPPENING
IN THE CITIES WHERE THEY DON'T
ENFORCE THE IMMIGRATION LAW,
AND THIS PRESIDENT TURNS HIS
BACK.
THIS PRESIDENT DOESN'T ENFORCE
THE MARIJUANA LAWS IN THIS
COUNTRY BECAUSE HE DOESN'T
AGREE WITH THEM, AND ALLOWS
STATES TO DO WHATEVER THEY WANT
ON A SUBSTANCE THAT IS ILLEGAL.
HERE'S WHAT I WOULD DO, NEIL, I
WOULD APPOINT ATTORNEY GENERAL
AND HAVE ONE VERY BRIEF
CONVERSATION WITH THAT ATTORNEY
GENERAL.
I SAY, GENERAL, ENFORCE THE LAW
AGAINST EVERYONE JUSTLY,
FAIRLEY AND AGGRESSIVELY, MAKE
OUR STREETS SAFE AGAIN, MAKE
OUR POLICE OFFICERS PROUD OF
WHAT THEY DO, MORE IMPORTANT
THAN, THAT LET THEM KNOW HOW
PROUD WE ARE OF THEM.
WE DO THAT, THIS COUNTRY WILL
BE SAFE AND SECURE AGAIN, NOT
ONLY FROM CRIMINALS BUT
TERRORISTS WHO THREATEN US AS
WELL.
I'M THE ONLY PERSON ON THE
STAGE THAT'S DONE THAT, AND WE
WILL GET IT DONE AS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES.
MODERATOR: THANK YOU, GOVERNOR,
GOVERNOR KASICH, AS SOMEONE WHO
HAS TO DEAL WITH CONTROVERSIAL
--
[CHANTING]
.
MODERATOR: ALL RIGHT!
YOU GUYS DEAL WITH CONTROVERSY.
>> THAT'S WHY YOU WORE A RED
TIE.
MODERATOR: DEAL WITH
CONTROVERSIAL SHOOTINGS IN YOUR
OWN STATE.
WHAT DO YOU MAKE OF CHICAGO'S
MOVE TO RETRAIN POLICE, MAYBE
MAKE THEM NOT SO QUICK TO USE
THEIR GUNS?
>> I CREATED A TASK FORCE WELL
OVER A YEAR AGO, AND THE
PURPOSE WAS TO BRING LAW
ENFORCEMENT, COMMUNITY PEOPLE,
CLERGY AND THE PERSON THEY
NAMED AS ONE OF THE COCHAIRMAN
IS A LADY BY THE NAME OF NINA
TURNER, FORMER STATE SENATOR,
LIBERAL DEMOCRAT, RAN AGAINST
ONE OF MY FRIENDS, AND HEAD OF
PUBLIC SAFETY.
AND THEY SAT DOWN AS A GROUP
TRYING TO MAKE SURE WE CAN
BEGIN TO HEAL SOME OF THESE
PROBLEMS THAT WE SEE BETWEEN
COMMUNITY AND POLICE, AND THEY
CAME BACK WITH 23
RECOMMENDATIONS.
ONE IS A STATEWIDE USE OF
DEADLY FORCE, AND IT IS NOW
BEING PUT INTO PLACE EVERYPLACE
ACROSS THE STATE OF OHIO.
SECONDLY, A POLICY ON
RECRUITING, AND HIRING, AND
MORE RESOURCES FOR TRAINING.
BUT LET ME ALSO TELL YOU ONE OF
THE ISSUES HAS GOT TO BE THE
INTEGRATION OF BOTH COMMUNITY
AND POLICE.
COMMUNITY HAS TO UNDERSTAND
THAT THAT POLICE OFFICER WANTS
TO GET HOME AT NIGHT AND NOT TO
LOSE THEIR LIFE.
THEIR FAMILY IS WAITING FOR
THEM.
AT THE SAME TIME, LAW
ENFORCEMENT UNDERSTANDS THERE
ARE PEOPLE IN THE COMMUNITY WHO
NOT ONLY THINK THAT THE SYSTEM
DOESN'T WORK FOR THEM, BUT
WORKS AGAINST THEM.
SEE, IN OHIO, WE'VE HAD
CONTROVERSIAL DECISIONS BUT THE
LEADERS HAVE COME FORWARD TO
REALIZE THAT PROTEST IS FINE,
BUT VIOLENCE IS WRONG, AND IT
HAS BEEN A REMARKABLE SITUATION
IN OUR STATE, AND AS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, IT'S ALL
ABOUT COMMUNICATION, FOLKS.
IT'S ALL ABOUT GETTING PEOPLE
TO LISTEN TO ONE ANOTHER'S
PROBLEMS, AND WHEN YOU DO THAT,
YOU WILL BE AMAZED AT HOW MUCH
PROGRESS YOU CAN MAKE AND HOW
MUCH HEALING WE CAN HAVE
BECAUSE, FOLKS, AT THE END OF
THE DAYS, THE COUNTRY NEEDS
HEALED.
I HEARD A LOT OF HOT RHETORIC
HERE TONIGHT.
I GOT TO TELL YOU AS SOMEBODY
WHO ACTUALLY PASSED A BUDGET
THAT PAID DOWN A HALF A
TRILLION DOLLARS OF OUR
NATIONAL DEBT, YOU CAN'T DO IT
ALONE.
YOU GOT TO BRING PEOPLE
TOGETHER, YOU GOT TO GIVE
PEOPLE HOPE, AND TOGETHER, WE
CAN SOLVE THESE PROBLEMS THAT
HURT US AND HEAL AMERICA, AND
THAT IS WHAT IS SO CRITICAL FOR
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS, OUR
FAMILIES, OUR CHILDREN AND OUR
GRANDCHILDREN.
[APPLAUSE]
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
UNDER CURRENT LAW, THE U.S. IS
ON TRACK TO ISSUE MORE NEW
PERMANENT IMMIGRANTS ON GREEN
CARDS OVER THE NEXT FIVE YEARS
THAN THE ENTIRE POPULATION OF
SOUTH CAROLINA.
THE CBO SAYS YOUR 2013
IMMIGRATION BILL WOULD HAVE
INCREASED GREEN CARD HOLDERS BY
ANOTHER 10 MILLION OVER 10
YEARS.
WHY ARE YOU SO INTERESTED IN
OPENING UP BORDERS TO
FOREIGNERS WHEN AMERICAN
WORKERS HAVE A HARD ENOUGH TIME
FINDING WORK?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THIS SAN ISSUE
THAT'S BEEN DEBATED FOR 30
YEARS, AND FOR 30 YEARS, THE
ISSUE OF IMMIGRATION HAS BEEN
ABOUT SOMEONE IN THIS COUNTRY,
MAYBE HERE ILLEGALLY, BUT
LOOKING FOR A JOB.
THIS ISSUE IS NOT ABOUT THAT
ANYMORE.
FIRST AND FOREMOST, THIS ISSUE
HAS TO BE MORE THAN ANYTHING
ELSE ABOUT KEEPING AMERICA
SAFE.
AND HERE'S WHY, THERE'S A
RADICAL JIHADIST GROUP
MANIPULATING OUR IMMIGRATION
SYSTEM, AND NOT JUST GREEN
CARDS, THEY'RE RECRUITING
PEOPLE THAT ENTER AS DOCTORS,
AND ENGINEERS, AND EVEN
FIANCEES, THEY UNDERSTAND THE
VULNERABILITIES WE HAVE ON THE
SOUTHERN BORDER, THEY'RE
LOOKING TO MANIPULATE THE VISA
WAIVER COUNTRIES TO GET PEOPLE
INTO THE UNITED STATES.
SO OUR NUMBER ONE PRIORITY MUST
NOW BECOME ENSURING THAT ISKISS
NOT GET KILLERS INTO THE UNITED
STATES.
WHETHER IT'S GREEN CARDS OR ANY
OTHER FORM OF ENTRY INTO
AMERICA, WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, IF
WE DO NOT KNOW WHO YOU ARE OR
WHY YOU ARE COMING, YOU ARE NOT
GOING TO GET INTO THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
MODERATOR: SO YOUR THINKING HAS
CHANGED?
>> THE ISSUE IS A DRAMATICALLY
DIFFERENT ISSUE THAN 24 MONTHS
AGO.
24 MONTHS AGO, 36 MONTHS AGO,
DID YOU NOT HAVE A GROUP OF
RADICAL CRAZIES NAMED ISIS
BURNING PEOPLE IN CAGES AND
RECRUITING PEOPLE TO ENTER OUR
COUNTRY LEGALLY.
THEY HAVE A SOPHISTICATED
UNDERSTANDING OF OUR LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM, AND WE NOW
HAVE AN OBLIGATION TO ENSURE
THAT THEY ARE NOT ABLE TO USE
THAT SYSTEM AGAINST US.
THE ENTIRE SYSTEM OF LEGAL
IMMIGRATION MUST NOW BE
REEXAMINED FOR SECURITY FIRST
AND FOREMOST WITH AN EYE ON
ISIS.
BECAUSE THEY'RE RECRUITING
PEOPLE ENTER TO THIS COUNTRY AS
ENGINEERS, POSING AS DOCTORS,
POSING AS REFUGEES.
WE KNOW THIS FOR A FACT.
THEY CONTACTED TRAFFICKING
NETWORKS IN THE WESTERN
HEMISPHERE TO GET PEOPLE IN
THROUGH THE SOUTHERN BORDER.
THEY GOT A KILLER IN SAN
BERNARDINO POSING AS A FIANCEE.
THIS ISSUE HAS TO BE STOPPING
ISIS ENTERING THE UNITED
STATES, WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE
WILL.
>> MARIA?
[APPLAUSE]
>> RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM
WAS NOT INVENTED 24 MONTHS AGO.
24 MONTHS AGO, WE HAD AL QAEDA,
BOKO HARAM, HEZBOLLAH, IRAN
PUTTING OPERATIVES IN CENTRAL
AMERICA, IT'S THE REASON WHY I
STOOD WITH JEFF SESSIONS AND
STEVE KING AND LED THE FIGHT TO
STOP THE GANG OF EIGHT AMNESTY
BILL.
IT WAS CLEAR THEN LIKE IT'S
CLEAR NOW THAT BORDER SECURITY
IS NATIONAL SECURITY.
[APPLAUSE]
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> IT IS ALSO THE CASE THAT
THAT RUBIO-SCHUMER AMNESTY
BILL, IT EXPANDED BARACK
OBAMA'S POWER TO LET IN SYRIAN
REFUGEES, ENABLED THE PRESIDENT
TO CERTIFY THEM EN MASSE
WITHOUT MANDATING MEANINGFUL
BACKGROUND CHECKS.
I THINK THAT'S A MISTAKE.
THAT'S WHY I'M LEADING THE
FIGHT TO STOP IT, AND I WOULD
NOTE, THE SENATE A FEW WEEKS
AGO VOTED TO SUSPEND REFUGEES
FROM MIDDLE EASTERN COUNTRIES.
I VOTED YES TO SUSPEND THAT.
MARCO VOTED ON THE OTHER SIDE.
YOU CAN'T SAY WE NEED TO SECURE
THE BORDERS AND GIVE BARACK
OBAMA MORE AUTHORITY TO ALLOW
MIDDLE EASTERN REFUGEES COMING
IN WHEN THE HEAD OF THE FBI
TELLS US THEY CANNOT VET THEM
TO DETERMINE IF THEY ARE ISIS
TERRORISTS.
>> MARIA, LET ME CLEAR
SOMETHING UP HERE.
THIS SAN INTERESTING POINT WHEN
YOU TALK ABOUT IMMIGRATION.
TED CRUZ, YOU USED TO SAY YOU
SUPPORTED DOUBLING THE NUMBER
OF GREEN CARDS, NOW YOU SAY
YOU'RE AGAINST IT.
YOU USED TO SUPPORT 500%
INCREASE IN THE NUMBER OF GUEST
WORKERS, NOW AGAINST IT.
YOU USED TO SUPPORT LEGALIZING
PEOPLE HERE ILLEGALLY.
NOW AGAINST IT.
YOU USED TO SAY YOU WERE IN
FAVOR OF BIRTHRIGHTS CITIZEN
SHIP.
NOW YOU ARE AGAINST IT.
NOT JUST ON IMMIGRATION, YOU
USED TO SUPPORT TPA, NOW YOU
ARE AGAINST IT.
I SAW YOU ON THE SENATE FLOOR
FLIP YOUR VOTE ON CROP
INSURANCE BECAUSE THEY TOLD YOU
IT WOULD HELP YOU IN IOWA.
AND LAST WEEK WE SAW YOU FLIP
THE VOTE ON IOWA FOR THE SAME
REASON.
THAT IS NOT CONSISTENT
CONSERVATISM.
THAT IS POLITICAL CALCULATION.
WHEN I AM PRESIDENT, I WILL
WORK TO KEEP THIS COUNTRY SAFE,
NOT CALL EVERYONE SNOWDEN, AS
YOU DID, A GREAT PUBLIC SERVANT
AS YOU DID.
EDWARD SNOWDEN IS A TRAITOR.
IF I GET MY HANDS ON HIM, HE IS
STANDING TRIAL FOR TREASON.
EVERY SINGLE TIME THERE HAS
BEEN A DEFENSE BILL IN THE
SENATE, THREE PEOPLE TEAM UP TO
VOTE AGAINST IT.
BERNIE SANDERS, RAND PAUL AND
TED CRUZ.
IN FACT, THE ONLY BUDGET YOU
HAVE EVER VOTED FOR, TED, IN
ENTIRE TIME IN THE SENATE IS A
BUDGET FROM RAND PAUL THAT
BRAGS ABOUT OR CUTS DEFENSE.
HERE'S THE BOTTOM LINE, IF I'M
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
AND CONGRESS TRIES TO CUT THE
MILITARY, I WILL VETO THAT IN A
MILLISECOND.
MODERATOR: GENTLEMEN,
GENTLEMEN --
>> I'M GOING TO GET A RESPONSE
TO THAT NEIL.
THERE'S NO WAY HE'S GOING TO
LAUNCH THAT.
HE HAD NO FEWER THAN 11 ATTACKS
THERE.
I APPRECIATE YOUR DUMPING YOUR
RESEARCH FOLDER ON THE DEBATE
STAGE.
>> IT'S YOUR RECORD.
>> I WILL SAY AT LEAST HALF OF
THE THINGS MARCO SAID ARE
FLAT-OUT FALSE.
[BOOING]
.
>> ABSOLUTELY FALSE.
START WITH IMMIGRATION.
LET'S START WITH IMMIGRATION
AND HAVE A LITTLE CLARITY.
MARCO STOOD WITH CHUCK SCHUMER
AND BARACK OBAMA ON AMNESTY.
I STOOD WITH JEFF SESSIONS AND
STEVE KING.
MARCO STOOD TODAY, STAND ON
THIS STAGE MARCO SUPPORTS
LEGALIZATION AND CITIZENSHIP
FOR 12 MILLION ILLEGALS.
I OPPOSED AND OPPOSE
LEGALIZATION AND CITIZENSHIP.
AND BY THE WAY, THE ATTACK HE
KEEPS THROWING OUT ON THE
MILITARY BUDGET, MARCO KNOWS
FULL WELL, I VOTED FOR HIS
AMENDMENT TO INCREASE MILITARY
SPENDING TO $697 BILLION.
WHAT HE SAID AND SAID IT IN THE
LAST DEBATE, IT'S SIMPLY NOT
TRUE.
AND AS PRESIDENT, I WILL
REBUILD THE MILITARY AND KEEP
THIS COUNTRY SAFE.
MODERATOR: WE HAVE TO STOP YOU,
I KNOW YOU ARE PASSIONATE ABOUT
THAT.
GOVERNOR BUSH, FEARS HAVE
GRIPPED THIS COUNTRY OBVIOUSLY,
AND YOU TOUCHED ON IT EARLIER
SINCE THE SAN BERNARDINO
ATTACKS.
SINCE OUR LAST DEBATE, IT HAS
CHANGED ACCORDING TO FACEBOOK
DATA AS WELL.
THIS ISSUE GRIPS PEOPLE RIGHT
BEFORE THE ATTACKS AND NOW
AFTER, THE INTEREST OF ISLAM,
HOMELAND SECURITY AND ISIS LOOM
VERY LARGE.
THE FBI SAYS ISLAMIC RADICALS
ARE USING SOCIAL MEDIA TO
COMMUNICATE AND IT NEEDS BETTER
ACCESS TO COMMUNICATION.
NOW THE CEO OF APPLE, GOVERNOR,
TIM COOK SAID UNLESS SERVED
WITH A WARRANT PRIVATE
COMMUNICATION IS PRIVATE,
PERIOD, DO YOU AGREE, OR WOULD
YOU CONVINCE HIM OTHERWISE?
>> I WOULD TRY TO CONVINCE HIM
OTHERWISE.
THE LAST BACK AND FORTH
EXPLAINS WHY WE HAVE THE MESS
IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT THAT WILL
FIX OUR IMMIGRATION LAWS AND
STICK WITH IT.
NOT BEND WITH THE WIND.
THE SIMPLE FACT IS ONE OF THE
WAYS MARIA TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM
YOU DESCRIBED IS NARROW THE
NUMBER OF PEOPLE COMING BY
FAMILY PETITIONING TO WHAT
EVERY OTHER COUNTRY HAS SO WE
HAVE THE BEST AND THE BRIGHTEST
IN OUR COUNTRY.
WE NEED TO CONTROL THE BORDER,
NOT JUST GO BACK AND FORTH.
MODERATOR: WOULD YOU ANSWER
THIS QUESTION.
>> I'LL TALK ABOUT THAT, TOO.
YOU HAVEN'T ASKED ME A QUESTION
IN A WHILE, NEIL, I THOUGHT I'D
GET THAT OFF MY CHEST.
[LAUGHTER]
[APPLAUSE]
>> FAIR ENOUGH.
TIM COOK, IS HE GOING TO KEEP
IT PRIVATE?
>> THERE IS NO CONFIDENCE IN
WASHINGTON, D.C.
THERE NEEDS TO BE MORE THAN ONE
MEETING, COMPLETE DIALOGUE WITH
THE LARGE TECHNOLOGY COMPANIES.
THEY UNDERSTAND THERE IS A
NATIONAL SECURITY RISK.
WE OUGHT TO GIVE THEM A LITTLE
LIABILITY RELEASE, SO THEY
SHARE DATA WITH THEMSELVES AND
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, THEY'RE
NOT FEARFUL OF THE LAWSUIT.
WE NEED TO KEEP THE COUNTRY
SAFE.
THIS IS THE FIRST PRIORITY.
CYBERSECURITY CHALLENGES WE
FACE, THIS ADMINISTRATION
FAILED US COMPLETELY,
COMPLETELY.
NOT JUST THE HACKING OF OPM,
BUT THAT IS JUST SHAMEFUL.
23 MILLION FILES IN THE HANDS
OF THE CHINESE?
IT'S NOT JUST THE GOVERNMENT,
THE PRIVATE SECTOR COMPANIES,
IT'S OUR OWN GOVERNMENT THAT
NEEDS TO RAISE THE LEVEL OF OUR
GAME.
PUT THE NSA IN CHARGE OF THE
CIVILIAN SIDE OF THIS AS WELL,
THAT EXPERTISE NEEDS TO SPREAD
ACROSS THE GOVERNMENT AND THERE
NEEDS TO BE MUCH MORE
COOPERATION.
MODERATOR: TIM COOK IS TELLING
YOU NO MR. PRESIDENT.
>> YOU GOT TO KEEP ASKING.
THIS IS A HUGELY IMPORTANT
ISSUE.
IF YOU CAN ENCRYPT MESSAGES,
ISIS CAN, OVER THE PLATFORMS,
AND WE HAVE NO ABILITY?
MODERATOR: DO YOU ASK OR
DEMAND?
>> THE LAW HAS TO CHANGE.
IF WE ARE TOO PUNITIVE, YOU
WILL GO TO OTHER TECHNOLOGY
COMPANIES OUTSIDE THE UNITED
STATES.
AND WHAT WE WANT TO DO IS TO
CONTROL.
THIS WE ALSO WANT TO DOMINATE
THIS FROM A COMMERCIAL SIDE.
THERE IS A LOT OF BALANCED
INTEREST.
THE PRESIDENT LEADS IN THIS
REGARD.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED.
WE NEED LEADERSHIP, SOMEONE WHO
HAS A BACK BONE AND STICKS WITH
THINGS RATHER THAN TALKS ABOUT
THEM AS THOUGH ANYTHING MATTERS
WHEN YOU ARE TALKING ABOUT
AMENDMENTS THAT DON'T -- ARE
PART OF A BILL THAT EVER
PASSED.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
WHEN WE COME BACK, CLOSING
STATEMENTS.
STAY WITH US.
.
MODERATOR: WELCOME BACK.
CANDIDATES, IT IS TIME FOR YOUR
CLOSING STATEMENTS.
YOU GET 60 SECONDS EACH.
GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH, WE BEGIN
WITH YOU.
>> IN OUR COUNTRY, THERE ARE A
LOT OF PEOPLE WHO FEEL AS
THOUGH THEY JUST DON'T HAVE THE
POWER.
YOU KNOW THEY FEEL LIKE IF THEY
DON'T HAVE A LOBBYIST, IF
THEY'RE NOT WEALTHY, THAT
SOMEHOW THEY DON'T GET TO PLAY.
BUT ALL OF MY CAREER, YOU KNOW,
HAVING BEEN RAISED IN A -- BY A
MAILMAN FATHER WHOSE FATHER WAS
A COALMINER WHO DIED OF BLACK
LUNG AND LOSING EYE SIGHT OR A
MOTHER WHOSE MOTHER BARELY
SPOKE ENGLISH.
ALL OF MY CAREER I THOUGHT
ABOUT GIVING VOICE TO THE
PEOPLE WHO ELECTED ME.
WHETHER IT'S WELFARE REFORM AND
GETTING SOMETHING BACK FOR THE
HARD EARNED TAXPAYERS.
WHETHER IT'S ENGAGING IN
PENTAGON REFORM AND TAKING ON
THE BIG CONTRACTORS THAT WERE
CHARGING THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS
FOR HAMMERS AND SCREWDRIVERS
AND RIPPING US OFF.
OR WHETHER IT'S TAKING ON THE
SPECIAL INTERESTS IN THE
NURSING HOME INDUSTRY IN OHIO
SO THAT MOM AND DAD HAVE THE
ABILITY TO STAY IN THEIR OWN
HOME RATHER THAN BEING FORCED
IN A NURSING HOME.
THAT'S WHO I STAND UP FOR,
THAT'S WHO'S IN MY MIND'S EYE.
IF YOU WANT TO BELIEVE YOU CAN
GET YOUR VOICE BACK, I WILL
CONTINUE TO FIGHT FOR YOU,
BECAUSE YOU'RES ONES THAT BUILT
THIS COUNTRY AND WILL CARRY IT
INTO THE FUTURE.
THANK YOU.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR BUSH?
>> WHO CAN YOU COUNT ON TO KEEP
US SAFER, STRONGER AND FREER?
RESULTS COUNT, AND AS GOVERNOR
I PUSHED FLOORED UP A TO THE
TOP IN TERMS OF JOBS, INCOME
AND SMALL BUSINESS GROWTH.
DETAILS PLANS COUNT AND I
BELIEVE THE PLAN I LAID OUT TO
DESTROY ISIS BEFORE THE
TRAGEDIES OF SAN BERNARDINO AND
PARIS ARE THE RIGHT ONES.
CREDIBILITY COUNTS.
THERE WILL BE PEOPLE HERE THAT
WILL TALK ABOUT WHAT THEY'RE
GOING TO DO, I'VE DONE IT.
I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT TO BUILD
TOGETHER A SAFER AND STRONGER
AMERICA.
[APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: GOVERNOR CHRIS
CHRISTIE?
>> MARIA, NEIL, THANK YOU FOR A
GREAT DEBATE TONIGHT.
WHEN I THINK OF THE FOLKS OUT
THERE TONIGHT WATCHING, AND
THINK ABOUT WHAT THEY HAD TO
WATCH THIS WEEK, THE SPECTACLE
AT THE FLORIDA HOUSE OF
REPRESENTATIVES WITH THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
WHO TALKED A FANTASY LAND ABOUT
THE WAY THEY'RE FEELING.
THEY KNOW THAT THIS COUNTRY IS
NOT RESPECTED AROUND THE WORLD
ANYMORE.
THEY KNOW THAT THIS COUNTRY IS
PUSHING THE MIDDLE CLASS, THE
HARD WORKING TAXPAYERS
BACKWARDS, AND SAW A PRESIDENT
WHO DOESN'T UNDERSTAND THEIR
PAIN, AND DOESN'T HAVE ANY PLAN
FOR GETTING AWAY FROM IT.
I LOVE THIS COUNTRY.
THE MOST EXCEPTIONAL COUNTRY
THE WORLD HAS EVER KNOWN.
WE NEED SOMEONE TO FIGHT FOR
THE PEOPLE.
WE NEED A FIGHTER FOR THIS
COUNTRY AGAIN.
I LIVED MY WHOLE LIFE FIGHTING
FOR THINGS I BELIEVE IN,
FIGHTING FOR JUSTICE AND
PROTECT PEOPLE FROM CRIME AND
TERRORISM, FIGHTING TO STAND UP
FOR FOLKS WHO HAVE NOT HAD
ENOUGH AND NEED AN OPPORTUNITY
TO GET MORE AND TO STAND UP AND
FIGHT AGAINST THE SPECIAL
INTERESTS.
BUT HERE'S THE BEST WAY WE'RE
GOING TO MAKE AMERICA MUCH MORE
EXCEPTIONAL, IT IS TO MAKE SURE
WE PUT SOMEONE ON THE STAGE IN
SEPTEMBER WHO WILL FIGHT
HILLARY CLINTON AND MAKE SURE
SHE NEVER, EVER GETS IN THE
WHITE HOUSE AGAIN, I AM THE MAN
TO BRING US TOGETHER TO DO
THAT, AND I ASK FOR YOUR VOTE.
MODERATOR: DR. BEN CARSON?
>> YOU KNOW, IN RECENT TRAVELS
AROUND THIS COUNTRY, I'VE
ENCOUNTERED SO MANY AMERICANS
WHO ARE DISCOURAGED AND ANGRY
AS THEY WATCH OUR FREEDOM, OUR
SECURITY, AND THE AMERICAN
DREAM SLIPPING AWAY.
UNDER AN UNRESPONSIVE
GOVERNMENT THAT IS POPULATED BY
BUREAUCRATS AND SPECIAL
INTEREST GROUPS.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO SOLVE THIS
PROBLEM WITH TRADITIONAL
POLITICS.
THE ONLY WAY WE'RE GOING TO
SOLVE THIS PROBLEM IS WITH WE,
THE PEOPLE.
AND I ASK YOU TO JOIN ME IN
TRUTH AND HONESTY AND
INTEGRITY.
BEN CARSON.COM, WE WILL HEAL,
INSPIRE AND REVIVE AMERICA FOR
OUR CHILDREN.
[APPLAUSE]
>> SENATOR MARCO RUBIO?
>> YOU KNOW, 200 YEARS AGO
AMERICA WAS FOUNDED ON THE
POWERFUL PRINCIPLE THAT OUR
RIGHTS DON'T COME FROM
GOVERNMENT.
OUR RIGHTS COME FROM GOD.
THAT'S WHY WE EMBRACE FREE
ENTERPRISE AND MADE US THE MOST
PROSPEROUS PEOPLE IN THE
HISTORY OF THE WORLD.
THAT'S WHY WE EMBRACED
INDIVIDUAL LIBERTY AND BECAME
THE FREEST PEOPLE EVER, AND THE
RESULT WAS THE AMERICAN
MIRACLE.
NOW AS I TRAVEL THE COUNTRY
PEOPLE SAY WHAT I FEEL.
THIS COUNTRY IS CHANGING, IT
FEELS DIFFERENT.
WE FEEL WE'RE LEFT BEHIND AND
LEFT OUT AND THE REASON IS
SIMPLE, BECAUSE IN 2008 WE
ELECTED AS PRESIDENT SOMEONE
WHO WASN'T INTERESTED IN FIXING
AMERICA.
WE ELECTED SOMEONE WHO WANTS TO
CHANGE AMERICA, WHO WANTS TO
MAKE IT MORE LIKE THE REST OF
THE WORLD SO HE UNDERMINES THE
CONSTITUTION, AND UNDERMINES
FREE ENTERPRISE BY EXPANDING
GOVERNMENT, AND BETRAYS OUR
ALLIES AND GUTS OUR MILITARY.
THAT'S WHY 2016 IS A TURNING
POINT IN OUR HISTORY.
IF WE ELECT HILLARY CLINTON,
THE NEXT FOUR YEARS WILL BE
WORSE THAN THE LAST EIGHT AND
CHILDREN WILL BE THE FIRST
AMERICANS EVER TO INHERIT A
DIMINISHED COUNTRY.
IF YOU ELECT ME, WE WILL TURN
THIS COUNTRY AROUND, WE WILL
RECLAIM THE AMERICAN DREAM AND
THIS NATION WILL BE STRONGER
AND GREATER THAN IT HAS EVER
BEEN.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: SENATOR TED CRUZ?
>> 13 HOURS, TOMORROW MORNING A
NEW MOVIE WILL DEBUT ABOUT THE
INCREDIBLE BRAVERY OF THE MEN
FIGHTING FOR THEIR LIVES IN
BENGHAZI AND THE POLITICIANS
THAT ABANDONED THEM.
I WANT TO SPEAK TO ALL OUR
FIGHTING MEN AND WOMEN.
I WANT TO SPEAK TO ALL THE MOMS
AND DADS WHOSE SONS AND
DAUGHTERS ARE FIGHT FOR THIS
COUNTRY AND THE INCREDIBLE
SENSE OF BETRAYAL WHEN YOU HAVE
A COMMANDER IN CHIEF WHO WILL
NOT SPEAK THE NAME OF OUR
ENEMY, RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM, WHEN YOU HAVE A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF WHO SENDS
150 BILLION DOLLARS TO THE
AYATOLLAH KHAMENEI.
I WANT TO SPEAK TO ALL OF THOSE
MADENED BY POLITICAL
CORRECTNESS WHERE HILLARY
CLINTON APOLOGIZES FOR SAYING
ALL LIVES MATTER.
THIS WILL END.
IT WILL END ON JANUARY 2017.
IF I AM ELECTED PRESIDENT TO
EVERY SOLDIER AND SAILOR AND
AIRMEN AND MARINE AND EFFORT
FIREFIGHTER AND LAW ENFORCEMENT
OFFICER WHO RISK THEIR LIVES TO
KEEP US SAFE, I WILL HAVE YOUR
BACK.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: MR. DONALD TRUMP?
>> I STOOD YESTERDAY WITH 75
CONSTRUCTION WORKERS.
THEY'RE TOUGH, THEY'RE STRONG,
THEY'RE GREAT PEOPLE.
HALF OF THEM HAD TEARS POURING
DOWN THEIR FACE.
THEY WERE WATCHING THE
HUMILIATION OF OUR YOUNG TEN
SAILORS, SITTING ON THE FLOOR
WITH THEIR KNEES IN A BEGGING
POSITION, THEIR HANDS UP, AN
IRANIAN WISE GUYS HAVING GUNS
TO THEIR HEADS.
IT WAS A TERRIBLE SIGHT.
A TERRIBLE SIGHT.
AND THE ONLY REASON WE GOT THEM
BACK IS BECAUSE WE OWED THEM
WITH A STUPID DEAL, $150
BILLION.
IF I'M PRESIDENT, THERE WON'T
BE STUPID DEALS ANYMORE.
WE WILL MAKE AMERICA GREAT
AGAIN.
WE WILL WIN ON EVERYTHING WE
DO.
THANK YOU.
[CHEERING AND APPLAUSE]
.
MODERATOR: CANDIDATES, THANK
YOU.
GENTLEMEN, THANK YOU ALL.
ALL OF YOU.
THAT WRAPS UP OUR DEBATE.
WE WENT A LITTLE BIT OVER HERE.
WE WANTED TO MAKE SURE EVERYONE
WAS ABLE TO SAY THEIR DUE.
HE'S UPSET.
THANK YOU FOR JOINING US.
MUCH MORE TO COME IN THE SPIN
ROOM AHEAD.
>> OUR SPECIAL COVERAGE OF THE
SIXTH REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE CONTINUES LIVE FROM
NORTH CHARLESTON ON THE FOX
BUSINESS NETWORK.