[ APPLAUSE ]
8:00 HERE IN DES MOINES, IOWA.
I'M BRET BAIER, WITH MEGYN KELLY
AND CHRIS WALLACE.
>> TONIGHT, WE ARE COMING TO YOU
LIVE FROM THE IOWA EVENT CENTER
IN DOWNTOWN DES MOINES IN THE
SHADOW OF THE IOWA STATE
CAPITAL.
IN JUST FOUR DAYS, PEOPLE HERE
IN THE HAWKEYE STATE WILL CAUCUS
AND CAST THE FIRST VOTES OF THE
2016 ELECTION.
>> TONIGHT, WE'RE PARTNERING
WITH GOOGLE FOR AN EXCLUSIVE
SECOND SCREEN EXPERIENCE.
SEARCH FOX NEWS DEBATE ON GOGGLE
ANY TIME IN THE NEXT TWO HOURS
TO ACCESS EXCLUSIVE CONTENT.
YOU CAN SEE THE CAMPAIGNS
RESPOND TO THE DEBATE IN
REALTIME AND YOU CAN WEIGH IN BY
VOTING ON THE TOPICS BEING
DISCUSSED.
JUST GO TO GOOGLE.COM.
>> GOOGLE SEES POLITICAL
SEARCHES SPIKE DURING TELEVISED
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATES, NO
SURPRISE THERE.
BUT THEY SPIKE BY MORE THAN 440%
ON AVERAGE, AS VOTERS ACROSS
AMERICA SEEK TO LEARN MORE ABOUT
WHAT'S HAPPENING ON THE LIVE
DEBATE STAGE.
>> SEVEN CANDIDATES ARE ON THAT
STAGE TONIGHT.
THEIR POSITION ON THE STAGE
DETERMINED BY THEIR STANDING IN
THE LATEST NATIONAL POLLS.
AS WELL AS POLLS IN IOWA AND NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
AND HERE THEY ARE.
TEXAS SENATOR TED CRUZ.
[ APPLAUSE ]
FLORIDA SENATOR MARCO RUBIO.
>> DR. BEN CARSON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
FORMER FLORIDA GOVERNOR JEB
BUSH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR CHRIS
CHRISTIE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
OHIO GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH.
>> AND KENTUCKY SENATOR RAND
PAUL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> APPARENTLY IOWA IS NEAR
KENTUCKY.
>> TONIGHT'S RULES ARE SIMPLE.
UP TO 60 SECONDS FOR EACH
ANSWER, 30 SECONDS FOR EACH
FOLLOWUP RESPONSE.
IF A CANDIDATE GOES OVER THE
ALLOTTED TIME, YOU WILL HEAR
THIS.
I THINK THE DOUBLE IS THE ONE WE
WANT.
VERY PLEASING.
WE HAVE A CROWD OF ABOUT 1600
HERE, AND WHILE THEY HAVE AGREED
TO RESPECT THE CANDIDATES AND
LISTEN INTENTLY, WE CAN TELL YOU
THEY ARE VERY EXCITED TO BE
HERE.
AM I RIGHT?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> LET'S GET STARTED.
SENATOR CRUZ, BEFORE WE GET TO
THE ISSUES, LET'S ADDRESS THE
ELEPHANT NOT IN THE ROOM
TONIGHT.
[ LAUGHTER ]
DONALD TRUMP HAS CHOSEN NOT TO
ATTEND THIS EVENING'S
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
WHAT MESSAGE DO YOU THINK THAT
SENDS TO THE VOTERS OF IOWA?
>> MEGYN, LET ME SAY AT THE
OUTSET TO THE MEN AND WOMEN OF
IOWA, THANK YOU FOR THE
INCREDIBLE HOSPITALITY OVER THIS
PAST YEAR.
BY MONDAY, YOU WILL HAVE
WELCOMED ME IN ALL 99 COUNTIES
IN IOWA.
YOU WILL HAVE WELCOMED MY DAD TO
PREACH AT YOUR CHURCHES.
YOU WILL HAVE WELCOMED HEIDI AND
OUR GIRLS, CAROLINE AND
CATHERINE INTO YOUR HOMES.
AND I'M SO GRATEFUL FOR THE
DILIGENCE, FOR THE SERIOUSNESS
WHICH THE MEN AND WOMEN OF IOWA
APPROACH THIS PROCESS.
IF I AM ELECTED PRESIDENT, KEEP
AN EYE ON THE TARMAC BECAUSE
I'LL BE BACK.
BECAUSE IOWA IN 2017 WILL NOT BE
FLY-OVER COUNTRY.
IT WILL BE FLY-TO COUNTRY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW, SECONDLY, LET ME SAY I'M A
MANIAC AND EVERYONE ON THIS
STAGE IS STUPID, FAT, AND UGLY.
AND BEN, YOU'RE A TERRIBLE
SURGEON.
NOW THAT WE'VE GOTTEN THE DONALD
TRUMP PORTION OUT OF THE WAY --
[ LAUGHTER ]
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WANT TO THANK EVERYONE HERE
FOR SHOWING THE MEN AND WOMEN OF
IOWA THE RESPECT TO SHOW UP AND
MAKE THE CASE TO THE PEOPLE OF
THIS STATE AND THE PEOPLE OF THE
COUNTRY WHY EACH OF US BELIEVE
WE WOULD MAKE THE BEST COMMANDER
IN CHIEF.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THE DIVIDE BETWEEN YOU AND
MR. TRUMP HAS TURNED INTO ONE OF
THE BIGGEST STORIES IN THE
COUNTRY.
AND FOR SIX MONTHS, YOU PRAISED
MR. TRUMP AS SOMEBODY WHO YOU
THOUGHT WAS AN EFFECTIVE VOICE
AGAINST THE WASHINGTON CARTEL.
YOU SAID YOU WERE GLAD THAT HE
WAS RUNNING AS A REPUBLICAN.
BUT WHEN HE STARTED TO CRITICIZE
YOU, YOUR MESSAGE CHANGED.
AND YOU SUDDENLY STARTED TO
PORTRAY HIM AS THE VOICE OF THE
WASHINGTON CARTEL AND SUGGESTED
HE WOULD DO THE DEMOCRAT'S
BIDDING.
WHICH IS IT?
>> WELL, LET ME BE CLEAR, IF
DONALD ENGAGES IN INSULTS OR
ANYBODY ELSE, I DON'T INTEND TO
RECIPROCATE.
I HAVE NOT INSULTED DONALD
PERSONALLY AND I DON'T INTEND
TO.
I'M GLAD HE'S RUNNING AND
PRODUCED ENORMOUS ENTHUSIASM AND
EVERY DONALD TRUMP VOTER OR
POTENTIAL VOTER, I HOPE TO EARN
YOUR SUPPORT.
I KNOW EVERYONE ELSE ON THIS
STAGE HOPES TO EARN YOUR
SUPPORT.
THERE'S A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
GOING INTO THE MUD WITH
ADHOMONYMS.
POLICY AND VISION AND RECORD
SHOULD BE THE MEAT OF POLITIC.
THAT'S FAIR GAME BUT THAT'S
WHERE I'M GOING TO FOCUS.
THAT'S HOW I FOCUSSED FROM THE
BEGINNING OF THE CAMPAIGN AND
HOW I PLAN TO CONTINUE GOING
FORWARD.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR RUBIO, I WANT TO
EXPLORE THIS LARGER ISSUE.
THE CAMPAIGN HAS IN A SENSE
TURNED INTO A BATTLE FOR THE
SOUL OF THE REPUBLICAN PARTY,
ESTABLISHMENT VERSUS GRASSROOTS,
PRAGMATIC VERSUS PRINCIPLE.
YOU CAN SAY YOU CAN UNITE ALL OF
THE FACTIONS INSIDE THE GOP.
HOW?
>> CHRIS, LET'S BE CLEAR WHAT
THIS IS ABOUT.
IT'S NOT ABOUT DONALD TRUMP.
HE'S THE GREATEST SHOW ON EARTH.
BUT THIS CAMPAIGN ISN'T THE
GREATEST COUNTRY IN THE WORLD
AND A PRESIDENT WHO HAS
SYSTEMATICALLY DESTROYED MANY OF
THE THINGS THAT MADE AMERICA
SPECIAL.
YOU SEE, WE USUALLY ELECT
PRESIDENTS IN AMERICA THAT WANT
TO CHANGE THE THINGS THAT ARE
WRONG IN AMERICA.
BARACK OBAMA WANTS TO CHANGE
AMERICA.
BARACK OBAMA WANTS AMERICA TO BE
MORE LIKE THE REST OF THE WORLD.
WE DON'T WANT TO BE LIKE THE
REST OF THE WORLD.
WE WANT TO BE THE UNITED STATES
OF AMERICA.
THAT IS WHY HILLARY CLINTON
CANNOT WIN THIS ELECTION.
HILLARY CLINTON THIS WEEK SAID
BARACK OBAMA WOULD MAKE A GREAT
SUPREME COURT JUSTICE.
THE GUY WHO SYSTEMATICALLY
VIOLATES THE CONSTITUTION ON THE
SUPREME COURT?
I DON'T THINK SO.
IF I'M THE NOMINEE, I WILL UNITE
THIS PARTY AND WE'LL DEFEAT
HILLARY CLINTON AND TURN THIS
COUNTRY AROUND AFTER SERVE YEARS
OF THE DISASTER THAT IS BARACK
OBAMA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, IT'S HARD FOR
ANYONE OF YOUR PEDIGREE TO AVOID
BEING CALLED ESTABLISHMENT.
BUT ISN'T THAT PART OF THE
PROBLEM, THAT THREE OTHERS ON
THIS STAGE ARE SPLITTING THE
MAIN STREAM REPUBLICAN VOTE AND
THERE BY POSSIBLY HAND THING
NOMINATION OVER TO AN
ANTI-ESTABLISHMENT CANDIDATE?
>> BRET, WE'RE JUST STARTING.
LET'S LET THE PROCESS WORK.
I TRUST IOWAENS, PEOPLE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA AND NEVADA TO START
THIS PROCESS OUT.
I KIND OF MISS DONALD TRUMP.
HE WAS A LITTLE TEDDY BEAR TO
ME.
WE ALWAYS HAD SUCH A LOVING
RELATIONSHIP IN THESE DEBATES
AND IN BETWEEN AND THE TWEETS.
I WISH HE WAS HERE.
EVERYBODY ELSE WAS IN THE
WITNESS PROTECTION PROGRAM WHEN
I WENT AFTER HIM ON BEHALF OF
WHAT THE REPUBLICAN CAUSE SHOULD
BE, CONSERVATIVE PRINCIPLES,
BELIEVING IN LIMITED GOVERNMENT
AND ACCOUNTABILITY.
LEADING BY FIXING THE THINGS
THAT ARE BROKEN.
MY DAD AND BROTHER WHO WERE
PRESIDENTS OF THE UNITED STATES.
FINE, I'LL TAKE IT.
I GUESS I'M PART OF THE
ESTABLISHMENT BECAUSE BARBARA
BUSH IS MY MOM.
I'LL TAKE THAT, TOO.
BUT THIS ELECTION IS NOT ABOUT
OUR PEDIGREE, THIS IS ABOUT
PEOPLE WHO ARE HURTING.
WE NEED A LEADER WHO WILL FIX
THINGS AND HAVE A PROVEN RECORD
TO DO IT.
AND WE NEED SOMEONE WHO WILL
TAKE ON HILLARY CLINTON IN
NOVEMBER.
SOMEONE WHO HAS A PROVEN RECORD,
WHO HAS BEEN TESTED AND IS
TRANSPARENT.
I RELEASED 34 YEARS OF TAX
RETURNS AND 300,000 E-MAILS TO
GET THE INFORMATION FROM HILLARY
CLINTON, YOU NEED TO GET A
SUBPOENA FROM THE FBI.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR CHRISTIE, YOU BEGAN
THIS CAMPAIGN TOUTING YOUR
RECORD AS A REPUBLICAN FROM A
BLUE STATE WHO KNOWS HOW TO GET
THINGS DONE AND REACH ACROSS THE
AISLE.
HOWEVER, MANY REPUBLICANS FEEL
THAT REACHING ACROSS THE AISLE
AND GETTING THINGS DONE ISN'T
GREAT IF YOU GET THE WRONG
THINGS DONE.
AND THEY PREFER TO STAND ON
PRINCIPLE RATHER THAN
COMPROMISE.
WHY ARE THEY WRONG AND YOU'RE
RIGHT?
>> THEY'RE NOT WRONG.
BUT WHAT'S WRONG IS YOUR PREMISE
IN THE QUESTION.
YOU CAN DO BOTH.
THERE IS NO REASON WHY YOU CAN'T
STAND FOR PRINCIPLES, GO AND
FIGHT FOR THEM, AND BE ABLE ALSO
TO HAVE TO GET THINGS DONE IN
GOVERNMENT.
YOU KNOW, WHAT PEOPLE ARE
FRUSTRATED ABOUT IN WASHINGTON,
D.C., AND I KNOW THE FOLKS OUT
THERE TONIGHT ARE FRUSTRATED
BECAUSE WHAT THEY SEE IS A
GOVERNMENT THAT DOESN'T WORK FOR
THEM.
FOR THE 45-YEAR-OLD CONSTRUCTION
WORKER OUT THERE HAVING A HARD
TIME MAKING THINGS MEET.
HE DOESN'T WANT TO HEAR THE TALK
ABOUT POLITICS AND WHO IS
GRASSROOTS AND ESTABLISHMENT.
WHAT HE WANTS IS SOMETHING DONE.
THAT'S THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
BEING A GOVERNOR AND HAVING DONE
THAT FOR SIX YEARS IN NEW JERSEY
AND BEING SOMEONE WHO HAS NEVER
HAD TO BE RESPONSIBLE FOR ANY OF
THOSE DECISIONS.
BARACK OBAMA WAS NEVER
RESPONSIBLE FOR THOSE DECISIONS.
HILLARY CLINTON HAS NEVER BEEN
RESPONSIBLE FOR THOSE KIND OF
DECISIONS WHERE THEY WERE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE.
I'VE BEEN HELD ACCOUNTABLE FOR
SIX YEARS AS THE GOVERNOR OF NEW
JERSEY AND WITH A DEMOCRATIC
LEGISLATURE, I'VE GOTTEN
CONSERVATIVE THINGS DONE.
THAT'S WHAT I'LL DO AS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR PAUL, YOU ARE
DEFINITELY NOT IN THE
ESTABLISHMENT CATEGORY.
BUT AT THE BEGINNING OF THIS
CAMPAIGN, YOU SAID YOU WERE YOUR
OWN MAN WHEN ASKED ABOUT YOUR
FATHER, FORMER TEXAS CONGRESSMAN
AND THREE-TIME PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATE RON PAUL.
SENATOR CRUZ IS OUT WITH A VIDEO
SAYING CRUZ IS THE POLITICAL
HEIR TO YOUR FATHER'S 2012
CAMPAIGN AND THE LIBERTY
MOVEMENT AND YOUR FATHER NOW
SAYS IT'S REALISTIC THAT DONALD
TRUMP WILL BE YOUR PARTY'S
NOMINEE.
DID YOU MAKE A MISTAKE BY NOT
MORE FULLY EMBRACING YOUR FATHER
POLITICALLY AT THE BEGINNING OF
THIS CAMPAIGN?
>> YOU KNOW, I'VE ALWAYS HAD A
GREAT DEAL OF RESPECT, PROBABLY
NO PERSON I RESPECT MORE IN THE
COUNTRY THAN MY FATHER.
I THINK HE WAS PROBABLY THE MOST
HONEST MAN IN POLITICS WE'VE
EVER SEEN IN A GENERATION.
SO IN NO WAY HAVE I EVER SAID I
DON'T EMBRACE MY FATHER OR
APPRECIATE EVERYTHING HE'S DONE
FOR THE COUNTRY.
I THINK WHAT'S INTERESTING WHERE
THAT LIBERTY VOTE GOES THAT MY
FATHER BROUGHT TO THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY, I DON'T THINK THEY'RE
NECESSARILY GOING TO GO FOR TED.
TED DIDN'T SHOW UP.
WE HAD A VOTE, THE BIGGEST THING
MY DAD HAD BEEN ADVOCATING FOR,
FOR 30 YEARS, TED WAS THE ONLY
REPUBLICAN THAT DIDN'T SHOW UP
FOR IT.
SO THAT VOTE IS GOING TO STAY IN
THE PAUL HOUSEHOLD.
I THINK MORE IS COMING AND WILL
GROW.
THE NSA IS ANOTHER BIG ISSUE.
TED SAI NSA REFORM,
BUT THEN HE TOLD MARCO RUBIO,
NO, I VOTED FOR THE BILL BECAUSE
I'M FOR THE GOVERNMENT
COLLECTING 100% OF YOUR CELL
PHONE RECORDS.
I DON'T THINK TED CAN HAVE IT
BOTH WAYS.
THEY WANT TO SAY THEY'RE GETTING
SOME OF THE LIBERTY VOTE.
BUT WE THINK WE'LL DO VERY WELL
IN IOWA WITH THE LIBERTY VOTE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOUR RESPONSE
TO THAT?
>> WELL, I AGREE WITH RAND THAT
I VERY MUCH RESPECT RON PAUL AND
I THINK ANYONE WHO IS GOING TO
WIN IN THE REPUBLICAN PARTY HAS
TO BRING TOGETHER THE DISPARATE
ELEMENTS OF THE REAGAN
COALITION, BRING TOGETHER
CONSERVATIVES AND LIBERTARIANS
AND EVANGELICALS AND STITCH
TOGETHER A WINNING MAJORITY.
WHEN IT COMES TO THE AUDIT OF
THE FED BILL, I WAS AN ORIGINAL
SPONSOR OF THE BILL, I'M
SUPPORTIVE OF IT.
IT DIDN'T HAVE THE VOTES TO PASS
AND I HAD COMMITMENTS TO BE IN A
TOWN HALL IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
BUT I LOOK FORWARD TO SIGNING
THAT BILL INTO LAW AS PRESIDENT
AND AUDITING THE FED AND
PROVIDING NEEDED ACCOUNTABILITY
AT THE FEDERAL RESERVE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> I THINK, YOU KNOW, RAND AND I
HAVE SOME SIGNIFICANT ISSUES ON
POLICY, BUT I RESPECT RAND.
HE BELIEVES EVERYTHING HE STANDS
FOR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WANT TO BE FRANK ABOUT WHAT I
STAND FOR.
I BELIEVE THE WORLD IS A SAFER
AND BETTER PLACE WHEN AMERICA IS
THE STRONGEST POWER IN THE
WORLD.
I BELIEVE ONLY WITH A STRONG
AMERICA WILL WE DEFEAT THIS
RADICAL GROUP CALLED ISIS.
THAT'S WHY WHEN I'M PRESIDENT
WE'RE GOING TO REBUILD OUR
INTELLIGENCE CAPABILITIES AND A
REBUILT U.S. MILITARY IS GOING
TO DESTROY THESE TERRORISTS.
IF WE CAPTURE ANY OF THESE ISIS
KILLERS ALIVE, THEY ARE GOING TO
GUANTANAMO BAY, CUBA AND WE'LL
FIND OUT EVERYTHING THEY KNOW.
BECAUSE WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE
WILL KEEP THIS COUNTRY SAFE,
UNLIKE BARACK OBAMA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> MAY I RESPOND?
>> WE'LL COME BACK --
>> JUST VERY QUICKLY, I WOULD
LIKE TO RESPOND.
THE BULK COLLECTION OF YOUR
PHONE DATA, THE INVASION OF YOUR
PRIVACY DID NOT STOP ONE
TERRORIST ATTACK.
I DON'T THINK YOU HAVE TO GIVE
UP YOUR LIBERTY FOR A FALSE
SENSE OF SECURITY.
WHEN WE LOOK AT THIS BULK
COLLECTION, THE COURT HAS LOOKED
AT THIS.
EVEN THE COURT DECLARED IT TO BE
ILLEGAL.
IF WE WANT TO COLLECT THE
RECORDS OF TERRORISTS, LET'S DO
IT THE OLD FASHIONED WAY.
LET'S USE THE FOURTH AMENDMENT.
LET'S PUT A NAME ON A WARRANT,
LET'S RESPECT THE HISTORY OF OUR
COUNTRY.
JOHN ADAMS SAID WE FOUGHT A WAR
FOR INDEPENDENCE BECAUSE WE
WANTED TO FIGHT AGAINST
GENERALIZED WARRANTS.
LET'S DON'T FORGET THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, I WANT TO
GET BACK TO THIS QUESTION OF
WHERE CONSERVATIVES ARE THIS
YEAR.
YOU CALL YOURSELF A "INSIDE
OUTSIDE GUY, A REFORMER WHO
KNOWS HOW TO GET THINGS DONE,"
BUT YOU REJECT THE ESTABLISHMENT
LABEL.
THE FIRST QUESTION IS WHY DO YOU
REJECT IT?
AND SECONDLY, WHAT DO YOU SAY TO
REPUBLICAN VOTERS THIS YEAR WHO
VIEW PRACTICAL GOVERNMENT
EXPERIENCE AS A LIABILITY AND
NOT AN ASSET?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I HAD A
NATIONAL REPORTER SAY THERE'S
THREE LANES.
THERE'S THE ESTABLISHMENT LANE,
THE ANTI-ESTABLISHMENT LANE AND
THEN THE KASICH LANE.
THE REASON IS, I'VE BEEN A
REFORMER ALL MY CAREER, FIGHTING
TO REFORM WELFARE, FIGHTING TO
REFORM THE PENTAGON.
ALSO BEING IN A POSITION TO
BALANCE THE BUDGET.
BECAUSE THAT IS VERY HARD TO DO.
AND THEN IN OHIO, I HAD TO BRING
ABOUT BIG REFORM, AGAIN, BECAUSE
WE WERE SO FAR IN THE HOLE AND
NOW WE JUST FOUND OUT WE WERE UP
OVER 400,000 JOBS SINCE I TOOK
OVER AS GOVERNOR.
YOU KNOW, THE SITUATION IS THIS,
WE CANNOT FIX THE THINGS IN THIS
COUNTRY, THE SOCIAL SECURITY,
THE BORDER, BALANCING THE
BUDGET, GETTING WAGES TO GROW
FASTER, UNLESS WE LEAD AS
CONSERVATIVES BUT WE ALSO INVITE
PEOPLE FROM THE OTHER PARTY.
WE HAVE TO COME TOGETHER AS A
COUNTRY AND STOP THE DIVISION.
THAT'S BEEN MY MESSAGE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
I JUST RECEIVED THE SUPPORT OF 7
OUT OF 8 OF THE NEWSPAPERS IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE, BECAUSE THEY SEE
POSITIVE, THEY SEE UNITY AND
COMING TOGETHER AND THEY SEE A
RECORD OF CHANGE AND
ACCOMPLISHMENT.
IT'S NOT BECAUSE I'M THAT GREAT,
IT'S BECAUSE I'VE BEEN
ASSEMBLING A TEAM OF PEOPLE WHO
WANT TO BE INVOLVED IN SOMETHING
BIGGER THAN THEMSELVES.
I'LL KEEP HEADING IN THAT
DIRECTION, BELIEVE ME.
>> DR. CARSON, I WANT TO PICK UP
ON THAT WITH YOU.
GOVERNOR KASICH LIKES TO SAY HE
KNOWS HOW TO LAND THE PLANE.
YOU'VE LANDED A LOT OF PLANES IN
THE O.R.
BUT WHAT ABOUT THE IDEA OF
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT WITH NO
EXPERIENCE IN GOVERNMENT AT ALL?
>> WELL, I WILL GLADLY CONFESS
THAT I'M THE ONLY ONE ON THIS
STAGE WITH NO POLITICAL TITLE.
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO HEAR A LOT
OF POLISHED, POLITICAL SPEECH
FROM ME.
BUT YOU WILL HEAR THE TRUTH.
AND I DON'T THINK YOU HAVE TO BE
A POLITICIAN TO TELL THE TRUTH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IN FACT, SOMETIMES IT'S NOT THAT
WAY.
I'VE HAD MORE 2:00 A.M. PHONE
CALLS THAN EVERYBODY HERE PUT
TOGETHER, MAKING LIFE AND DEATH
DECISIONS, PUT TOGETHER VERY
COMPLEX TEAMS TO ACCOMPLISH
THINGS THAT HAVE NEVER BEEN DONE
BEFORE.
AND WE ARE IN A SITUATION RIGHT
NOW IN OUR COUNTRY WE'VE NEVER
BEEN IN BEFORE.
WE NEED PEOPLE WHO THINK OUT OF
THE BOX AND CAN SOLVE PROBLEMS.
CAN UTILIZE THE RESOURCES AROUND
THEM, VERY SMART PEOPLE, TO
FOCUS ON THE PROBLEM AND SOLVE
THE PROBLEM.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE
TERRIFIED.
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE THIS ABNORMAL
SITUATION GOING ON RIGHT NOW.
WE DON'T NEED MORE OF THE SAME
SOLUTIONS.
WE NEED DIFFERENT SOLUTIONS TO
SOLVE THE PROBLEMS, AND TO SAVE
OUR NATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GENTLEMEN, WE'RE NOW GOING TO
GO TO SPECIFIC ISSUES AND START
WITH ONE OF THE BIGGEST ONES,
WHICH IS FOREIGN TERROR.
ACCORDING TO GOOGLE, ISIS WAS BY
FAR THE MOST SEARCHED FOREIGN
POLICY TOPIC OVER THE LAST YEAR.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU TALK TOUGH
ABOUT FIGHTING TERRORISM.
YOU TALK ABOUT CARPET BOMBING
INTO OBLIVION.
YOU TALK ABOUT SEEING IF THE
SAND WILL GLOW AT NIGHT.
BUT CRITICS SAY THAT YOUR RECORD
DOES NOT MATCH UP TO THAT.
YOU OPPOSED GIVING PRESIDENT
OBAMA AUTHORITY TO ENFORCE HIS
RED LINE IN SYRIA.
YOU HAVE VOTED AGAINST THE
DEFENSE AUTHORIZATION ACT THREE
YEARS.
HOW DO YOU SQUARE YOUR RHETORIC
WITH YOUR REPORT, SIR?
>> I APOLOGIZE TO NOBODY FOR THE
VIGOROUSNESS TO WITH WHICH I
WILL FIGHT TERRORISM, GO AFTER
ISIS, HUNT THEM DOWN WHEREVER
THEY ARE AND UTTERLY AND
COMPLETELY DESTROY ISIS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU KNOW, YOU CLAIM IT IS TOUGH
TALK TO DISCUSS CARPET BOMBING.
IT IS NOT TOUGH TALK, IT IS A
DIFFERENT FUNDAMENTAL MILITARY
STRATEGY THAN WHAT WE'VE SEEN
FROM BARACK OBAMA.
BARACK OBAMA RIGHT NOW, NUMBER
ONE, OVER SEVEN YEARS HAS
DRAMATICALLY DEGRADED OUR
MILITARY.
JUST TWO WEEKS AGO WAS THE 25th
ANNIVERSARY OF THE FIRST PERSIAN
GULF WAR.
WHEN THAT WAR BEGAN, WE HAD
8,000 PLANES.
TODAY, WE HAVE ABOUT 4,000.
WHEN THAT WAR BEGAN, WE HAD 529
SHIPS.
TODAY, WE HAVE 272.
YOU WANT TO KNOW WHAT CARPET
BOMBING IS?
IT'S WHAT WE DID IN THE FIRST
PERSIAN GULF WAR.
1100 AIR ATTACKS A DAY,
SATURATION BOMBING THAT
DESTROYED THE ENEMY.
RIGHT NOW BARACK OBAMA IS
LAUNCHING BETWEEN 15 AND 30 AIR
ATTACKS A DAY.
HE'S NOT ARMING THE KURDS.
WE NEED TO DEFINE THE ENEMY,
REBUILD THE MILITARY TO DEFEAT
THE ENEMY, AND WE NEED TO BE
FOCUSED AND LIFT THE RULES OF
ENGAGEMENT SO WE'RE NOT SENDING
OUR FIGHTING MEN AND WOMEN INTO
COMBAT WITH THEIR ARMS TIED
BEHIND THEIR BACK.
>> DOES HIS RHETORIC MATCH
HIS --
>> I THINK THAT'S A BAD IDEA FOR
THE FOLLOWING REASON.
ISIS IS THE MOST DANGEROUS GROUP
IN THE HISTORY OF MAN KIND.
ISIS BURNS PEOPLE ALIVE IN
CAGES, THAT SELLS OFF LITTLE
GIRLS AS BRIDES.
ISIS WANTS TO TRIGGER AN
APOCALYPTIC SHOWDOWN IN SYRIA.
THEY WANT TO TRIGGER AN
ARMAGEDDON SHOWDOWN.
THEY NEED TO BE DEFEATED.
THEY ARE NOT GOING TO GO AWAY ON
THEIR OWN.
THEY ARE NOT GOING TO TURN INTO
STOCKBROKERS OVERNIGHT.
THEY NEED TO BE DEFEATED
MILITARILY AND THAT WILL TAKE
OVERWHELMING U.S. FORCE.
TODAY, WE ARE ON PACE TO HAVE
THE SMALLEST ARMY SINCE THE END
OF WORLD WAR II.
THE SMALLEST NAVY IN 100 YEARS.
THE SMALLEST AIR FORCE IN OUR
HISTORY.
YOU CANNOT DESTROY ISIS WITH A
MILITARY THAT'S BEEN DIMINISHED.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE ARE
REBUILDING THE U.S. MILITARY,
BECAUSE THE WORLD IS A SAFER AND
BETTER PLACE WHEN AMERICA IS THE
STRONGEST MILITARY IN THE WORLD.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, 30 SECONDS.
>> CHRIS, IN 1981, WHEN RONALD
REAGAN CAME TO THE OVAL OFFICE,
HE ENCOUNTERED A MILITARY THAT
HAD BEEN DEBILITATED JUST AS THE
CURRENT MILITARY HAS, JUST LIKE
JIMMY CARTER WEAKENED OUR
READINESS, UNDERMINED OUR
ABILITY TO DEFEND THIS COUNTRY,
SO TOO HAS BARACK OBAMA.
JUST AS MORALE HAS PLUMMETED IN
THE LAST SEVEN YEARS, SO IT HAD
THEN.
REAGAN BEGAN WITH REGULATORY
REFORM, UNLEASHING THE ENGINE OF
THE AMERICAN FREE ENTERPRISE
SYSTEM AND BROUGHT BOOMING
ECONOMIC GROWTH AND THAT GROWTH
FUELED REBUILDING THE MILITARY.
I INTEND TO DO THE EXACT SAME
THING TO DEFEAT RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM AND TO DEVOTE THE
RESOURCES FROM THE BOOMING
ECONOMY TO REBUILDING OUR NAVY,
OUR AIR FORCE, OUR ARMY.
AND ENSURING WE HAVE THE
CAPACITY TO KEEP THIS COUNTRY
SAFE.
[ OVERLAPPING SPEAKERS ]
>> MAY I JUST SAY, WE ARE GOING
TO CONTINUE THE QUESTIONS ABOUT
FOREIGN TERROR, GENTLEMEN, RIGHT
AFTER THIS BREAK.
>> BUT FIRST, YOU CAN JOIN
TONIGHT'S CONVERSATION RIGHT
FROM HOME GO.
TO GOOGLE.COM OR OPEN YOUR
GOOGLE SEARCH APP AND SEARCH FOX
NEWS DEBATE TO VOTE ON WHICH
CANDIDATE YOU THINK HAS THE BEST
PLAN TO DEFEAT ISIS.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK.
LET'S GET RIGHT BACK TO THE
QUESTIONS.
CHRIS?
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, YOU HAVE
COMPARED BOTH SENATORS CRUZ AND
RUBIO TO BARACK OBAMA SAYING WE
CANNOT AFFORD ANOTHER
INEXPERIENCED PRESIDENT AND THAT
SENATOR CRUZ'S VOTE TO CURTAIL
THE NSA SURVEILLANCE PROGRAM
MADE AMERICA LESS SAFE.
IS EITHER READY TO BE COMMANDER
IN CHIEF?
>> I DO BELIEVE THAT THE VOTE ON
NSA MADE THE COUNTRY LESS SAFE.
I WATCHED THAT TOWN HALL MEETING
WITH THE DEMOCRATS THE OTHER
NIGHT, AND I HEARD HILLARY
CLINTON ASKED A DIRECT QUESTION
BY AN IOWAEN.
THEY ASKED ABOUT HER E-MAIL
SITUATION, AND HERE'S WHAT SHE
SAID TO THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
SHE DID IT FOR CONVENIENCE, FOR
HER CONVENIENCE.
SHE PUT AMERICA'S SECRETS AT
RISK FOR HER CONVENIENCE.
SHE PUT AMERICAN INTELLIGENCE
OFFICERS AT RISK FOR HER
CONVENIENCE.
SHE PUT AMERICAN STRATEGY AT
RISK FOR HER CONVENIENCE.
LET ME TELL YOU WHO'S NOT
QUALIFIED TO BE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, HILLARY RODHAM
CLINTON DID THAT TO OUR COUNTRY.
SHE'S NOT QUALIFIED TO BE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THE FACT IS, WHAT WE NEED IS
SOMEONE ON THAT STAGE WHO HAS
BEEN TESTED, WHO HAS BEEN
THROUGH IT, WHO HAS MADE
DECISIONS, WHO WILL SIT IN THE
CHAIR OF CONSEQUENCE AND CAN
PROSECUTE THE CASE AGAINST
HILLARY CLINTON ON THAT STAGE.
THAT'S WHAT I'M READY TO DO.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH --
>> CHRIS, I WAS MENTIONED IN
THAT QUESTION.
>> I DON'T THINK YOUR NAME WAS
MENTIONED.
>> YOUR QUESTION SAID --
>> I THINK -- THE QUESTION WAS
ABOUT -- IT'S NOT MY QUESTION
YOU GET A CHANCE TO RESPOND TO,
IT'S HIS ANSWER.
>> YOUR QUESTION WAS --
>> YOU DON'T GET 30 SECONDS --
SIR, I KNOW YOU LIKE TO ARGUE
ABOUT THE RULES, BUT WE'RE GOING
TO CONDUCT THE DEBATE.
GOVERNOR BUSH, HERE'S A
QUESTION.
YOU CRITICIZED SEVERAL
CANDIDATES IN THIS FIELD ON THIS
DAY FOR WHAT YOU CALL
UNREALISTIC IDEAS ABOUT HOW TO
FIGHT TERRORISTS, INCLUDING
RUBIO AND CRUZ ON THE ISSUE OF
THEIR REFUSING TO GIVE THE
PRESIDENT AUTHORITY TO ENFORCE
THE RED LINE IN SYRIA.
GIVEN THE FACT THAT YOUR BROTHER
GOT US INTO TWO WARS IN IRAQ AND
AFGHANISTAN THAT'S STILL NOT
ENDED --
[ CROWD BOOS ]
-- WHAT LESSONS HAVE YOU LEARNED
FROM HIS MISTAKES?
>> I WAS CRITICAL OF THE
SENATORS NOT GIVING THE
PRESIDENT AUTHORIZATION TO USE
MILITARY FORCE.
WE SHOULDN'T HAVE THE WAR
FIGHTERS HAVE THEIR ARMS TIED
BEHIND THEIR BACK AS PRESIDENT
OBAMA WANTED TO DO.
BUT THEY HAD A CHANCE TO SHOW
SUPPORT.
AND IT WASN'T POPULAR AT THE
TIME.
IT BECAME POPULAR AFTER THE
ATTACK IN PARIS AND SAN
BERNARDINO.
PRIOR TO THAT, IN THE REAGAN
LIBRARY, I GAVE A DETAILED PLAN
RELATED TO ISIS.
IT IS FROM THE LESSONS FROM
HISTORY THAT WE DO THIS.
IF WE ALLOW THIS TO FESTER,
WE'LL HAVE GENERATIONS OF IT.
THE CALIPHATE OF ISIS NEEDS TO
BE DESTROYED, WHICH MEANS WE
NEED TO ARM THE KURDS, REENGAGE
WITH THE SUNNI TRIBAL LEADERS,
GET THE YOU LAWYERS OFF THE
BACKS OF OUR SOLDIERS AND TAKE
OUT ISIS ON THE GROUND AND AIR.
I LAID THAT OUT PRIOR TO THE
CHRIS WHICH IS THE ADVICE OF A
LOT OF PEOPLE, INCLUDING 12
MEDAL OF HONOR RECIPIENTS THAT
I'M PROUD ARE SUPPORTING MY
CAMPAIGN.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, NOW YOU GET A
CHANCE TO RESPOND.
>> CHRIS, I WOULD NOTE THAT THE
LAST FOUR QUESTIONS HAVE BEEN
RAND, PLEASE ATTACK TED, JEB,
PLEASE ATTACK TED --
[ CROWD BOOS ]
>> LET ME JUST SAY THIS.
>> IT IS A DEBATE, SIR.
>> NO, A DEBATE IS A POLICY
ISSUE, BUT I WILL SAY THIS,
GOSH, IF YOU GUYS ASK ONE MORE
MEAN QUESTION, I MAY HAVE TO
LEAVE THE STAGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
CHRIS, THE MOST IMPORTANT
DETERMINATION ANY VOTER IS GOING
TO MAKE IN THIS ELECTION IS WHO
IS BEST PREPARED TO BE COMMANDER
IN CHIEF.
WHO HAS THE EXPERIENCE, WHO HAS
THE KNOWLEDGE, WHO HAS THE
JUDGMENT, WHO HAS THE CLARITY,
VISION, AND STRENGTH TO KEEP
THIS COUNTRY SAFE.
ATE IS ALL
ABOUT.
I WOULD SUGGEST LET'S STAY
FOCUSED ON THOSE ISSUES RATHER
THAN JUST ATTACKS DIRECTED AT
EACH OTHER.
>> I THINK THE QUESTIONS WERE
ABOUT ISSUES.
BUT SENATOR RUBIO --
>> I WAS MENTIONED IN THAT
QUESTION AND I WOULD LIKE TO
RESPOND.
>> LET ME GO FIRST AND THEN YOU
CAN PLEASE RECOGNIZE RAND AFTER.
[ LAUGHTER ]
FIRST OF ALL, DON'T WORRY, I'M
NOT LEAVING THE STAGE NO MATTER
WHAT YOU ASK ME.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THE AUTHORIZATION THAT BARACK
OBAMA ASKED FOR WAS NOT AGAINST
ISIS, IT WAS AGAINST ASSAD.
JOHN KERRY DESCRIBED IT AS
ATTACKS THAT WOULD BE
UNBELIEVABLY SMALL.
I DON'T THINK THE UNITED STATES
SHOULD BE ENGAGED IN SYMBOLIC
MILITARY ACTIVITY.
IT WAS NOT AGAINST ISIS, IT WAS
AGAINST ASSAD.
I THINK THE UNITED STATES
MILITARY IS OPERATING UNDER
RULES OF ENGAGEMENT TOO STRICT
AND DO NOT ALLOW US TO PURSUE
VICTORY.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, THAT WILL
CHANGE.
>> SENATOR PAUL, GO AHEAD.
>> THANK YOU.
THE ISSUE IN SYRIA IS A VERY
IMPORTANT ONE, AND ONE THAT WE
NEED TO GET RIGHT.
THE QUESTION IS, SHOULD WE BE
BOMBING BOTH SIDES OF THE WAR?
SOMEONE TO TOPPLE ASSAD.
THEY WANT TO BOMB ISIS AND ASSAD
SIMULTANEOUSLY.
I THINK THAT'S A REALLY BAD
IDEA.
I SAID THAT ARMING THE ALLIES OF
ISIS WILL MAKE THE SITUATION
WORSE.
THAT WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS
DEFEAT ISIS, BUT IF YOU DEFEAT
ASSAD, WHAT YOU WILL WIND UP
WITH IS A LARGER AND MORE
POWERFUL ISIS THAT OCCUPIES THAT
SPACE.
YOU MAY SEE AN ISIS THAT TAKES
OVER ALL OF SYRIA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THERE WAS A QUESTION ABOUT
FOREIGN POLICY, BY THE WAY, AND
EXPERIENCE.
I THOUGHT IF I DIDN'T JUMP IN, I
MIGHT NOT BE ABLE TO TELL
EVERYBODY THIS.
LOOK, I SERVED ON --
>> WE HAVE A LOT TO COVER.
>> WAIT A MINUTE, THE ONLY --
>> WE WANT TO TURN THE PAGE TO
DOMESTIC TERROR AND LET ME TELL
YOU WHY.
WE'RE PARTNERING WITH GOOGLE AND
THEY'RE TELLING US THEIR SEARCH
RESULTS HAVE GONE THROUGH THE
ROOF --
>> GO AHEAD, MEGYN.
>> YOU'RE A GOOD MAN, GOVERNOR
KASICH.
THE SEARCHES FOR TERROR ISSUES,
FOR SAFETY ISSUES IN AMERICA
HAVE GONE THROUGH THE ROOF,
INCREASED OF 400% SINCE 2008.
PEOPLE ARE WORIED ABOUT WHAT'S
HAPPENING IN THE COUNTRY AND A
DOMESTIC TERRORIST ATTACK.
WHEN COMBATTING THIS ATTACK,
SENATOR RUBIO, YOU ADVOCATED
CLOSING DOWN MOSQUES, DINERS,
ANY PLACE WHERE RADICALIZATION
IS OCCURRING.
YOU TOLD ME THAT.
BUT THE SUPREME COURT MADE CLEAR
THAT HATEFUL SPEECH IS GENERALLY
PROTECTED BY THE FIRST
AMENDMENT.
IN OTHER WORDS, IF RADICAL
MUSLIMS HAVE THE RIGHT TO BE
RADICAL MUSLIMS UNLESS THEY TURN
TO TERROR.
DOESN'T YOUR POSITION RUN AFOUL
OF THE FIRST AMENDMENT?
>> RADICAL ISLAM IS NOT JUST
HATE TALK, IT'S HATE ACTION.
THEY BLOW PEOPLE UP.
LOOK AT SAN BERNARDINO.
LOOK AT THE INCIDENT IN
PHILADELPHIA WHERE A GUY SHOT A
POLICE OFFICERS THREE TIMES.
HE SAID I DID IT BECAUSE I WAS
INSPIRED BY ISIS AND THE WHITE
HOUSE ACKNOWLEDGES IT HAD
ANYTHING TO DO WITH TERROR.
THE THREAT WE FACE FROM ISIS IS
UNPRECEDENTED.
THERE'S THEY HAVE BEEN A
JIHADIST GROUP LIKE THIS.
THEY HAVE AFFILIATES IN A DOZEN
COUNTRIES.
THEY'RE THE BEST FUNDED RADICAL
GROUP IN THE HISTORY OF THE
WORLD AND HAVE SHOWN A
SOPHISTICATED UNDERSTANDING OF
THE LAWS OF OTHER COUNTRIES AND
ARE PLANNING TO ATTACK US HERE
AT HOME AND AROUND THE WORLD.
WE MUST KEEP AMERICA SAFE FROM
THIS THREAT.
YES, WHEN I AM PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, IF THERE IS SOME
PLACE IN THISISTS ARE PLANNING
ATTACK, WE WILL GO AFTER THEM
AND IF CAPTURED, THEY WILL GO TO
GUANTANAMO.
>> SENATOR PAUL, DO YOU AGREE
WITH THAT?
>> I THINK THAT'S A HUGE MISTAKE
TO CLOSE DOWN MOSQUES.
BUT IF YOU WANT TO DEFEND THE
COUNTRY, IT BEGINS WITH BORDER
SECURITY.
WHEN SENATOR RUBIO BROUGHT
FORWARD THE GANG OF EIGHT BILL
TO GIVE CITIZENSHIP TO THOSE WHO
CAME HERE ILLEGALLY, I HAD AN
AMENDMENT THAT SAYS WE SHOULD
HAVE MORE SCRUTINY ON THOSE WHO
ARE COMING AS STUDENTS,
IMMIGRANTS AND REFUGEES.
WE HAD TWO REFUGEES COME TO
BOWLING GREEN AND TRIED TO
ATTACK US.
HE OPPOSED THIS BECAUSE HE MADE
A DEAL WITH CHUCK SCHUMER THAT
HE WOULD OPPOSE ANY CONSERVATIVE
AMENDMENT.
YOU CAN'T DEFEND US AGAINST
ISLAM IF YOU'RE NOT FOR BORDER
SECURITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> LET ME RESPOND.
THE FIRST THING, I DON'T KNOW OF
ANYONE WHO IS NOT IN FAVOR OF
FULLY VETTING PEOPLE TRYING TO
COME TO THIS COUNTRY OTHER THAN
PERHAPS BARACK OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON.
I THINK WE ALL SUPPORT THAT.
I DO BELIEVE PEOPLE COMING TO
THE UNITED STATES, THIS COUNTRY
HAS A RIGHT TO KNOW WHO THEY ARE
AND WHY THEY ARE COMING.
THAT'S WHY I'VE BEEN CLEAR, WHEN
I AM PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA, WE DON'T KNOW
WHO YOU ARE, AND WE DON'T KNOW
WHY YOU'RE TRYING TO COME TO THE
UNITED STATES, YOU ARE NOT GOING
TO GET IN.
BECAUSE THE RADICAL THREAT THAT
WE NOW FACE FROM ISIS IS
EXTRAORDINARY AND UNPRECEDENTED
AND WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE ARE
KEEPING ISIS OUT OF AMERICA.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, LET'S TALK
ABOUT PROFILING.
IN DECEMBER, TWO RADICAL MUSLIMS
KILLED 14 PEOPLE IN SAN
BERNARDINO, CALIFORNIA.
NEIGHBORS OF THE TERRORISTS SAID
THEY DID NOT REPORT THE COUPLE
TO LAW ENFORCEMENT PRIOR TO THE
CRIME BECAUSE THEY WERE AFRAID
THEY WOULD BE ACCUSED OF
PROFILING.
YOU HAVE SAID WE SHOULD NOT
PROFILE.
HOW DO YOU SQUARE THAT WITH THE
SAN BERNARDINO CASE?
>> BECAUSE YOU CAN DO IT WITHOUT
PROFILING.
YOU DO IT ON THE FACTS.
WHAT THOSE FACTS KNEW WAS THAT
THESE FOLKS HAD WEAPONS, THEY
KNEW THAT THEY WERE TALKING
ABOUT TRYING TO TAKE OUR COUNTRY
AND ATTACK IT.
THAT'S NOT PROFILING, THAT'S LAW
ENFORCEMENT.
THAT'S THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
SOMEBODY WHO KNOWS HOW TO DO
THIS AND SOMEBODY WHO HAS DONE
THIS BEFORE.
>> THEY DIDN'T KNOW THEY WERE
GOING TO ATTACK THE COUNTRY.
>> THEY KNEW THEY WERE TALKING
ABOUT ATTACKING PEOPLE.
>> NEIGHBORS SAID THEY SAW MEN
GOING IN AND OUT OF THE GARAGE.
THEY SAW PACKAGES BEING
DELIVERED.
THEY SAW MUSLIMS AND THEY DID
NOT THINK THAT WAS ENOUGH TO
CALL THE COPS.
DO YOU?
>> LISTEN, I THINK WHAT PEOPLE
SHOULD DO IS USE COMMON SENSE.
AND THE FACT IS, LET LAW
ENFORCEMENT MAKE THOSE
DECISIONS.
I TOLD PEOPLE THAT FROM THE TIME
I WAS U.S. ATTORNEY 13 YEARS
AGO.
YOU SEE SOMETHING THAT'S
SUSPICIOUS, YOU CALL LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND LET LAW
ENFORCEMENT MAKE THOSE
DECISIONS.
THAT'S WHAT SHOULD BE DONE AND
CAN BE DONE.
THAT CAN BE DONE WITHOUT
PROFILING PEOPLE.
WHAT THAT IS, IT'S COMMON SENSE.
THEY THOUGHT SOMETHING WAS
WRONG.
HERE'S THE PROBLEM IN THIS
COUNTRY RIGHT NOW.
THE PROBLEM IS, BARACK OBAMA HAS
MADE LAW ENFORCEMENT THE ENEMY,
HILLARY CLINTON HAS MADE LAW
ENFORCEMENT THE ENEMY.
THEY'RE NOT SUPPORTING LAW
ENFORCEMENT, IT'S MAKING
EVERYBODY NERVOUS TO GET OUT OF
YOUR CARS IF YOU'RE A LAW
ENFORCEMENT OFFICER.
IT'S MAKING PEOPLE NERVOUS TO GO
TO LAW ENFORCEMENT.
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL SUPPORT LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND WE'LL STOP
RADICAL TERRORIST ATTACKS IN
THIS COUNTRY BY SUPPORTING OUR
INTELLIGENCE AND LAW ENFORCEMENT
COMMUNITY.
>> DR. CARSON, THIS WEEK A
FEMALE MUSLIM WHO SERVED IN THE
U.S. AIR FORCE ASKED HILLARY
CLINTON THE QUESTION, WHETHER
THE UNITED STATES IS STILL THE
BEST PLACE IN WHICH TO RAISE HER
THREE MUSLIM CHILDREN.
GIVEN WHAT SHE PERCEIVES AS A
RISE IN ISLAMAPHOBIA IN THIS
COUNTRY.
DO YOU THINK THE GOP MESSAGING
ON MUSLIMS HAS STOKED THE FLAMES
OF BIAS ON THIS AS THE DEMOCRATS
SUGGEST AND HOW WOULD YOU ANSWER
THIS VETERAN?
>> WELL, I DON'T KNOW ABOUT THE
GOP MESSAGING, BUT I CAN TELL
YOU ABOUT MY MESSAGING.
WE NEED TO STOP ALLOWING
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS TO DICTATE
OUR POLICIES, BECAUSE IT'S GOING
TO KILL US IF WE DON'T.
IN THE HOLY LAND FOUNDATION
TRIAL IN 2006 IN TEXAS, THEY HAD
A MEMORANDUM, AN EXPLANATORY
MEMORANDUM THAT TALKED ABOUT THE
FACT THAT AMERICANS WOULD BE
EASY TO OVERCOME AND TO COMMIT
CIVILIZATION JIHAD BECAUSE THEY
WERE GOING TO BE TRYING TO
PROTECT THE RIGHTS OF THE VERY
PEOPLE WHO WERE TRYING TO
SUBVERT THEM.
BUT I BELIEVE IN THE TEDDY
ROOSEVELT PHILOSOPHY.
HE SAID, WE ARE A NATION OF
IMMIGRANTS.
AS SUCH, EVERYBODY IS WELCOME
FROM ANY RACE, ANY COUNTRY, ANY
RELIGION, IF THEY WANT TO BE
AMERICANS.
IF THEY WANT TO ACCEPT OUR
VALUES AND OUR LAWS.
IF NOT, THEY CAN STAY WHERE THEY
ARE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, YOU APPEAR
TO BACK IN ANOTHER DEBATE, A
BACK DOOR TO ENCRYPTED CELL
PHONE TECHNOLOGY, WHICH PROTECTS
MOST SMARTPHONES THAT WE ALL
HAVE FROM HACKING.
AND IT INCLUDES OUR PHONES AND
IT PROTECTS THE CELL PHONES OF
THE TERRORIST.
THE TECH COMPANIES AND A GROUP
OF M.I.T. SCIENTISTS, SMART
GUYS, WARN IF THEY CREATE A WAY
FOR THE FBI TO HAVE A BACK DOOR
INTO OUR ENCRYPTED
COMMUNICATIONS, THE BAD GUYS
WILL EXPLOIT IT AND CAUSE MORE
PROBLEMS THAN IT SOLVES.
ARE THEY WRONG?
>> THE JOINT TERRORISM TASK
FORCE NEED RESOURCES AND TOOLS.
THOSE ARE MADE UP OF THE FBI,
STATE AND LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT.
IT'S BEST NOT TO TALK ANYMORE
ABOUT BACK DOOR ENCRYPTION, IT
WILL BE SOLVED BUT IT NEEDS TO
BE SOLVED IN THE SITUATION OF
THE WHITE HOUSE.
>> THIS IS PUBLIC TESTIMONY.
>> IT'S BEST WITH SOME OF THESE
THINGS NOT BE SAID.
I WANT TO GO BACK SOMETHING.
I WAS THERE WHEN REAGAN REBUILT
THE MILITARY.
I WAS THERE IN '89 WHEN THE WALL
CAME TUMBLING DOWN BECAUSE WE
WERE STRONG AND I WAS THERE WHEN
WE WENT INTO THE GULF CAR.
WE DIDN'T WIN THAT WAR JUST FROM
THE AIR, BUT BY ASSEMBLING A
GROUP OF ARAB LEADERS WHO STOOD
WITH AMERICA.
WE WANT TO DESTROY ISIS, IT HAS
TO BE IN THE AIR, ON THE GROUND,
IT HAS TO BE WITH OUR FRIENDS IN
THE ARAB WORLD AND OUR FRIENDS
IN EUROPE, THE COALITION THAT WE
HAD WHEN WE WENT TO THE FIRST
GULF WAR.
AND THEN WHEN WE WIN THAT, AND
WE WILL WIN THAT AGAINST ISIS AS
IT SETTLES DOWN AND WE SHOULD
LEAVE.
WE SHOULDN'T BE POLICEMEN OF THE
WORLD.
BUT WE NEED TO TURN IT OVER TO
THE REGIONAL POWERS TO HANDLE
THAT.
WE HAVE A UNIQUE TIME IN AMERICA
TO CONNECT WITH PEOPLE AROUND
THE WORLD THAT UNDERSTAND THAT
THERE'S AN THREAT AGAINST ALL OF
THEM, THE ARABS, THE SAUDIS, THE
EGYPTIANS, OUR FRIENDS IN
EUROPE, INCLUDING THE TURKS.
SO WE HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO
BRING EVERYBODY TOGETHER.
I SAW REAGAN DO IT AND OTHER
PRESIDENTS DO IT.
IF YOU WANT TO BE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF, YOU HAVE TO HAVE THE
EXPERIENCE.
AT THE SAME TIME WE'RE DOING ALL
THAT, THE PENTAGON MUST BE
REFORMED SO WE GET WHAT WE NEED
FOR OUR MEN AND WOMEN IN
UNIFORM.
ALL OF THAT TOGETHER, WE'RE
GOING TO BE JUST FINE AND
AMERICA IS GOING TO CONTINUE TO
LEAD THE WORLD.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, JUST TODAY, A
WOUNDED WARRIOR ORGANIZATION
DESIGNED TO HELP WOUNDED
VETERANS AND THEIR FAMILIES IS
COMING UNDER FIRE FOR RAISING
TENS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS, BUT
SPENDING ALMOST HALF OF THAT ON
TRAVEL AND HOTELS AND DINNERS
AND LUXURY, LAVISH CONFERENCES.
IF YOU WERE PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU
POLICE THESE CHARITY
ORGANIZATIONS THAT SAY THEY'RE
HELPING VETS?
>> OF COURSE.
AND THERE'S ALL SORTS OF WAYS
THAT CAN BE DONE TO DO THAT.
BUT THE FIRST DUTY OF THE NEXT
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
IS TO FIX THE MESS AT THE
DEPARTMENT OF VETERANS AFFAIRS.
THAT'S HIS FIRST RESPONSIBILITY.
WE HAVE WAITING LISTS OR
VETERANS THAT ARE WAITING.
WE'RE GUTTING THE MILITARY.
MORE AND MORE MILITARY PERSONNEL
ARE LEAVING, BECOMING VETERANS.
AND THE WAITING LIST GROWS.
THEY'VE GIVEN OUT $140 MILLION
OF BONUSES TO VETERANS
DEPARTMENT EMPLOYEES, INCLUDING
REDUCING THE WAITING LIST,
WITHOUT GIVING VETERANS CARE.
PEOPLE DIED.
AND ONLY THREE PEOPLE HAVE BEEN
FIRED.
I WILL MAKE SURE THAT WE FIRE
THE SHEER INCOMPETENCE INSIDE
THE OFFICE OF VETERANS AFFAIRS
AND GIVE VETERANS A CHOICE CARD
SO THEY CAN GO TO THEIR OPEN
PRIVATE PROVIDER.
YOU WANT TO MAKE THE VETERANS
ADMINISTRATION DO A BETTER JOB,
GET VETERANS CHOICES AND YOU'LL
GET A BETTER CHOICE.
IN HOUSTON, TEXAS, THERE'S AN
ORGANIZATION IN PLACE BECAUSE
SOMEONE ACTED ON THEIR HEART,
WANTED TO MAKE SURE THAT THAT'S
NO HOMELESS VETERANS IN HOUSTON.
THEY'VE COME CLOSE TO THAT.
WITHOUT FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
ASSISTANCE.
WE NEED TO MOBILIZE THE ENTIRE
COUNTRY TO TREAT OUR VETERANS
WITH MUCH MORE RESPECT THAN THEY
GET TODAY.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, THANK YOU.
SPEAKING OF VETERANS, WE HAVE A
QUESTION FROM A VETERAN, ONE OF
THE TOP YOUTUBE CREATORS.
OVER THE COURSE OF THE EVENING,
WE'LL HEAR FROM SOME OF
YOUTUBE'S MOST FOLLOWED STARS.
>> I'M MARK WATSON.
I'M A VETERAN WHO SERVED IN THE
ARMY FOR EIGHT YEARS.
AS AN AFRICAN-AMERICAN LIVING
NEAR FERGUSON, I'VE SEEN THE
STRAIN BETWEEN POLICE OFFICERS
AND THE COMMUNITIES THEY SERVE
FIRSTHAND.
NOW, THERE ARE GREAT TOOLS LIKE
CAMERAS THAT CAN PROTECT
OFFICERS AND CITIZENS, BUT WE
ALL HAVE BETTER CAMERAS IN OUR
POCKETS THAN OUR PRECINCTS.
WHY AREN'T WE USING THE
TECHNOLOGY AVAILABLE TO BETTER
PROTECT OUR COMMUNITIES?
>> SENATOR PAUL, THAT QUESTION
TO YOU?
>> I SUPPORTED LEGISLATION TO
ALLOW BODY CAMERAS.
I'VE BEEN TO FERGUSON.
ONE THING I DISCOVERED IN
FERGUSON WAS THAT A THIRD OF THE
BUDGET FOR THE CITY OF FERGUSON
WAS BEING REAPED BY CIVIL FINES.
PEOPLE WERE JUST BEING FINED TO
DEATH.
YOU AND I, MANY OF THE PEOPLE,
WE GET A $100 FINE, WE CAN
SURVIVE IT.
IF YOU'RE ON THE EDGE OF POVERTY
AND YOU GET A $100 FINE, YOU CAN
LOSE YOUR JOB.
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THE WAR ON
DRUGS IS EQUAL PROTECTION UNDER
THE LAW AND WE DON'T UNFAIRLY
INCARCERATE UNDER GENERATION OF
AFRICAN-AMERICAN MALES.
IN FERGUSON, FOR EVERY 100
AFRICAN-AMERICAN WOMEN, THERE
ARE ONLY 60 AFRICAN-AMERICAN
MEN.
DRUG USE IS EQUAL BETWEEN WHITE
AND BLACK, BUT THREE OUT OF FOUR
PEOPLE IN PRISON ARE BLACK OR
BROWN.
I THINK IT'S A BIG THING OUR
PARTY NEEDS TO BE PART OF AND
I'VE BEEN A LEADER IN CONGRESS
TRYING TO BRING ABOUT CRIMINAL
JUSTICE REFORM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THIS DEBATE IS JUST GETTING
STARTED.
COMING UP, THE ROLE OFF THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
BUT FIRST, JOIN TONIGHT'S
CONVERSATION RIGHT FROM YOUR
HOME.
GO TO GOOGLE.COM OR HOPE YOUR
GOOGLE SEARCH APP AND SEARCH FOX
NEWS DEBATE TO VOTE ON WHICH
ISSUE IS MOST IMPORTANT TO YOU
IN THIS ELECTION.
MORE FROM THE IOWA EVENT CENTER
AND THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE IN A MOMENT.
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY.
WE ARE LIVE IN DES MOINES, IOWA.
LET'S GET R TO THE
QUESTIONS.
BRET.
>> I'LL ASK SOME QUESTIONS ABOUT
FEDERAL SPENDING.
EVERYBODY ALWAYS SAID THEY WANT
TO CUT FEDERAL SPENDING AND
USUALLY SAY THEY'LL START BY
CUTTING WASTE, FRAUD, OR ABUSE,
BUT THAT NEVER MATERIALIZES.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, YOU TALK
ABOUT ENTITLEMENT REFORM AND SAY
THAT'S WHERE THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT CAN GET SAVINGS TO
BALANCE THE BUDGET.
CAN YOU NAME EVEN ONE THING THAT
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT DOES NOW
THAT IT SHOULD NOT DO AT ALL?
>> YEAH.
YOU WANT ONE?
>> I WANT ONE.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> HOW ABOUT ONE THAT I'VE DONE
IN NEW JERSEY FOR THE LAST SIX
YEARS.
THAT'S GET RID OF PLANNED
PARENTHOOD FUNDING FROM THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ANYTHING BIGGER THAN THAT?
>> BIGGER THAN THAT?
WHEN YOU SEE THOUSANDS UPON
THOUSANDS UPON THOUSANDS OF
AMERICAN BEING MURDERED IN THE
WOMB, I CAN'T THINK OF ANYTHING
BETTER THAN THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I REALIZE EVERYONE OPPOSES
OBAMACARE AND YOU'RE NOT ALONE.
DATA SHOWS THAT IN THE LAST
MONTH WHEN PEOPLE SEARCHED
POLICY REPEALS, THAT THERE WERE
A LOT OF THEM.
OBAMACARE TOOK THE TOP TWO
SPOTS.
BUT TODAY THERE ARE MILLIONS OF
PEOPLE WHO GAINED HEALTH
INSURANCE FROM OBAMACARE AND
THEY NOW RELY ON IT.
SO THE QUESTION, SENATOR CRUZ,
IF YOU REPEAL OBAMACARE, AS YOU
SAY YOU WILL, WILL YOU BE FINE
IF MILLIONS OF PEOPLE DON'T HAVE
HEALTH INSURANCE?
AND WHAT IS YOUR SPECIFIC PLAN
FOR COVERING THE UNINSURED?
>> SURE.
LET'S TAKE IT ONE AT A TIME.
FIRST OF ALL, WE HAVE SEEN NOW
IN SIX YEARS OF OBAMACARE THAT
IT'S BEEN A DISASTER.
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE HAVE LOST
THEIR JOBS, FORCED INTO PART
TIME WORK, HAVE LOST THEIR
INSURANCE, HAVE SEEM THEIR
PREMIUMS SKYROCKET.
IF I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT, WE
WILL REPEAL EVERY WORD OF
OBAMACARE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW, ONCE THAT IS DONE, EVERYONE
AGREES WE NEED HEALTH CARE
REFORM.
IT SHOULD FOLLOW THE PRINCIPLES
OF EXPANDING COMPETITION,
EMPOWERING PATIENTS AND KEEPING
GOVERNMENT FROM GETTING BETWEEN
US AND OUR DOCTORS.
WE SHOULD EXPAND HEALTH SAVINGS
ACCOUNTS SO PEOPLE CAN SAVE IN A
TAX ADVANTAGE WAY FOR MORE
ROUTINE HEALTH CARE NEEDS.
AND NUMBER THREE, WE SHOULD WORK
TO DELINK HEALTH INSURANCE FROM
EMPLOYMENT, SO IF YOU LOSE YOUR
JOB, YOUR HEALTH INSURANCE GOES
WITH YOU, AND IT IS PERSONAL,
PORTABLE AND I THINK THAT'S A
MUCH MORE ATTRACTIVE VISION FOR
HEALTH CARE THAN THE WASHINGTON
DRIVEN TOP DOWN OBAMACARE THAT
IS CAUSING SO MANY MILLIONS TO
HURT.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, YOU'VE
ADVOCATED FOR STATEHOOD FOR
PUERTO RICO.
THE PUERTO RICAN ECONOMY IS
COLLAPSING UNDER UNSUSTAINABLE
DEBT BURDEN.
ONLY ABOUT 1 MILLION OF 4
MILLION RESIDENTS ARE EMPLOYED.
SO SHOULD AMERICAN CITIZENS, WHO
YOU SAY ARE ALREADY OVERTAXED,
BAIL OUT PUERTO RICO, AS WELL IN
>> NO, THEY SHOULDN'T.
I BELIEVE PUERTO RICO OUGHT TO
HAVE THE RIGHT OF
SELF-DETERMINATION.
IF I WAS A PUERTO RICAN, I WOULD
VOTE FOR STATEHOOD.
THEY SHOULD HAVE THE RIGHT OF
SELF-DETERMINATION.
BEFORE YOU GET TO THAT, THOUGH,
PUERTO RICO WILL HAVE TO DEAL
WITH THE STRUCTURAL PROBLEMS
THEY FACE.
IT'S A FACT THAT IF YOU CAN PAY
FOR $79 ONE-WAY TICKET TO
ORLANDO AND ESCAPE CRIME RATES,
YOU MOVE TO ORLANDO.
A LOT OF PEOPLE ARE DOING THAT
AND THE SPIRALING OUT OF CONTROL
REQUIRES PUERTO RICO TO MAKE
REFORMS.
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT CAN ALLOW
THEM TO DO THAT BUT SHOULD
NOT -- THE PROCESS OF STATEHOOD
OR THE STATUS OF PUERTO RICO
WON'T BE SOLVED UNTIL WE GET TO
THE BIGGER ISSUE HOW TO DEAL
WITH THE ECONOMIC PROBLEMS
THEY'RE FACING RIGHT NOW.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, YOU'RE ONE
OF TWO REMAINING GOVERNORS IN
THE RACE.
YOUR COLLEAGUE RICK SNYDER IN
MICHIGAN IS UNDER FIRE FOR THE
FLINT, MICHIGAN WATER CRISIS.
HOW WOULD YOU HAVE HANDLED THAT?
>> YOU HAVE TO BE ON TOP OF IT
RIGHT AWAY.
I KNOW PEOPLE ARE BEING HELD
ACCOUNTABLE, BUT THE FACT IS,
EVERY SINGLE ENGINE OF
GOVERNMENT HAS TO MOVE WHEN YOU
SEE A CRISIS LIKE THAT.
I'VE HAD MANY SITUATIONS IN THE
STATE OF OHIO WHERE WE'VE HAD TO
MOVE, WHETHER IT'S STORMS,
WHETHER IT WAS A HORRIBLE SCHOOL
SHOOTING.
THERE ARE MANY CRISES THAT COME.
THE WATER CRISIS IN TOLEDO.
YOU'VE GOT TO BE ON TOP OF IT
AND GO THE EXTRA MILE.
YOU HAVE TO WORK WITH LOCAL
COMMUNITIES AND THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT.
BECAUSE YOU REALIZE THAT PEOPLE
ARE DEPENDING ON YOU.
SO YOU GO THE EXTRA MILE.
BUT PEOPLE HAVE TO BE ALERT.
AND WHEN YOU SEE A PROBLEM, YOU
MUST ACT QUICKLY TO GET ON TOP
OF IT AND PEOPLE AT HOME ARE
SAYING THEY'VE GOT A PROBLEM.
LISTEN TO THEM.
BECAUSE MOST OF THE TIME THEY'RE
ABSOLUTELY CORRECT.
SO THE FACT IS, WE WORK FOR THE
PEOPLE, THE PEOPLE DON'T WORK
FOR US, AND WE HAVE TO HAVE AN
ATTITUDE WHEN WE'RE IN
GOVERNMENT OF SERVANTHOOD THAT'S
WHAT MATTERS.
WE SERVE YOU, YOU DON'T SERVE
US.
WE LISTEN TO YOU.
AND THEN WE ACT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO --
>>
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> -- ON THE ISSUE OF CLIMATE
CHANGE, IN 2008 YOU WANTED
FLORIDA TO GET AHEAD OF OTHER
STATES AND ESTABLISH A CAP AND
TRADE SYSTEM, A PROGRAM FOR
CARBON EMISSIONS, WHICH MANY
REPUBLICANS THOUGHT AT THE TIME
WOULD HURT THE FLORIDA ECONOMY.
NOW YOU'RE A SKEPTIC OF CLIMATE
CHANGE SCIENCE AND IN FACT, YOU
WARN THAT FEDERAL EFFORTS TO
FIGHT CLIMATE CHANGE WILL U.S.
THE HURT ECONOMY AND COST JOBS.
WHY THE CHANGE?
>> FIRST, THAT'S NOT ENTIRELY
THE STORY.
AT THE TIME, THE LIBERAL
GOVERNOR OF FLORIDA, CHARLIE
CRIST, HE WANTED TO IMPOSE CAP
AND TRADE ON FLORIDA AND I WAS
THE FIRST PERSON OUT OF THE BOX
THAT
THEN WE SAW THE LEADS CANDIDATE
FOR PRESIDENT AT THE TIME BOTH
THE REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS
ALL SUPPORTED IT.
WHAT WE SAID IS THEY'RE GOING TO
IMPOSE THIS ON US, I NEVER
THOUGHT IT WAS A GOOD IDEA.
I WAS CLEAR ABOUT THAT AT THE
TIME.
I DO NOT BELIEVE IT'S A GOOD
IDEA NOW.
I DO NOT BELIEVE WE HAVE TO
DESTROY OUR ECONOMY IN ORDER TO
PROTECT OUR ENVIRONMENT.
AND ESPECIALLY WITH THESE
PROGRAMS THEY'RE ASKING US TO
PASS THAT WILL DO NOTHING TO
HELP THE ENVIRONMENT BUT WILL BE
DEVASTATING FOR OUR ECONOMY.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA, THERE WILL
NEVER BE ANY CAP AND TRADE IN
THE UNITED STATES.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> ALL RIGHT.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON, BECAUSE
COMING UP, IMMIGRATION, AND
SOMETHING YOU'VE NEVER SEEN
BEFORE.
STAY TUNED, RIGHT AFTER THIS
BREAK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYONE, LIVE
IN DES MOINES, IOWA, AND NOW WE
MOVE ON TO THE TOPIC OF
IMMIGRATION.
SENATOR RUBIO, WE START WITH
YOU.
WHEN YOU RAN FOR SENATE IN 2010,
YOU MADE CLEAR YOU OPPOSED
LEGALIZATION AND CITIZENSHIP FOR
ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS.
YOU PROMISED REPEATEDLY THAT YOU
WOULD OPPOSE IT AS A U.S.
SENATOR AS WELL.
HERE ARE JUST A FEW EXAMPLES.
WATCH.
>> NEVER SUPPORT, NEVER HAVE AND
NEVER WILL SUPPORT ANY EFFORT TO
GRANT BLANKET LEGALIZATION
AMNESTY TO FOLKS WHO ENTERED OR
STAYED IN THE COUNTRY EL
LEGALLY.
>> EARNED PATH TO CITIZENSHIP IS
CODE, THE REALITY IS THIS, IT'S
UNFAIR TO THE PEOPLE WHO LEGALLY
ENTERED THIS COUNTRY TO CREATE
AN ALTERNATIVE PATHWAY WHO
ENTERED ILLEGALLY AND KNOWINGLY
DID SO.
YOU CANNOT GRANT AMNESTY.
THEY'LL NEVER AGAIN BELIEVE IN
LEGAL IMMIGRATION, NEVER AGAIN
SUPPORT IT.
THAT'S BAD FOR OUR COUNTRY AND
FUTURE.
>> WITHIN TWO YEARS OF GETTING
ELECTED YOU WERE CO-SPONSORING
LEGISLATION TO CREATE A PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP, IN YOUR WORDS,
AMNESTY.
HAVEN'T YOU ALREADY PROVEN YOU
CANNOT BE TRUSTED ON THIS ISSUE?
>> NO BECAUSE IF YOU LOOK AT THE
QUOTE, IT'S VERY SPECIFIC, IT
SAYS BLANKET AMNESTY.
I DO NOT SUPPORT --
>> YOU SAID MORE THAN THAT, SIR.
>>S I SAID I DO NOT SUPPORT --
>> YOU SAID EARNED PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP IS BASICALLY CODE
FOR AMNESTY.
>> IT WAS.
>> YOU SUPPORTED EARNED PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP.
>> IT ABSOLUTELY HAS BEEN.
AT THE TIME AND CONTEXT OF THAT
WAS IN 2009 AND 2010 WHERE THE
LAST EFFORT FOR LEGALIZATION WAS
AN EFFORT DONE IN THE SENATE, AN
EFFORT LED BY SEVERAL PEOPLE
THAT PROVIDED ALMOST AN INSTANT
PATH, WITH VERY LITTLE OBSTACLES
MOVING FORWARD.
WHAT I'VE ALWAYS SAID IS THIS
ISSUE DOES NEED TO BE SOLVED.
THEY'VE BEEN TALKING ABOUT THIS
ISSUE FOR 30 YEARS AND NOTHING
EVER HAPPENS AND I'M GOING TO
TELL YOU EXACTLY HOW WE'RE GOING
TO DEAL WITH IT WHEN I AM
PRESIDENT.
NUMBER ONE, WE'RE GOING TO KEEP
ISIS OUT OF AMERICA.
IF WE DON'T KNOW WHO YOU ARE OR
WHY YOU'RE COMING, YOU WON'T GET
INTO THE UNITED STATES.
NUMBER TWO, WE'RE GOING TO
ENFORCE IMMIGRATION LAWS.
I AM THE SON AND GRANDSON OF
IMMIGRANTS.
SECURING OUR BORDERS IS NOT
ANTI-IMMIGRANT.
WE'LL HIRE 20,000 NEW BORDER
AGENTS INSTEAD OF 20,000 NEW IRS
AGENTS.
FINISH THE 700 MILES OF FENCING
AND WALLS OUR NATION NEEDS.
WE'LL HAVE MANDATORY E-VERIFY, A
MANDATORY ENTRY/EXIT TRACKING
SYSTEM AND UNTIL ALL OF THAT IS
IN PLACE AND ALL OF THAT IS
WORKING AND WE CAN PROVE TO THE
PEOPLE OF THIS COUNTRY THAT
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION IS UNDER
CONTROL, NOTHING ELSE IS GOING
TO HAPPEN.
WE ARE NOT GOING TO ROUND UP AND
DEPORT 12 MILLION PEOPLE BUT
WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAND OUT
CITIZENSHIP CARDS, EITHER.
THERE WILL BE A PROCESS.
WE WILL SEE WHAT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE ARE WILLING TO SUPPORT.
BUT IT WILL NOT BE
UNCONSTITUTIONAL EXECUTIVE
ORDERS LIKE THE ONES BARACK
OBAMA HAS FORCED ON US.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, DO YOU AGREE
SENATOR RUBIO HAS NOT REVERSED
HIMSELF ON HIS IMMIGRATION
PROMISE?
>> I'M KIND OF CONFUSED BECAUSE
HE WAS THE SPONSOR OF THE GANG
OF EIGHT BILL THAT DID REQUIRE A
BUNCH OF THRESHOLDS BUT
ULTIMATELY ALLOWED FOR
CITIZENSHIP OVER AN EXTENDED
PERIOD OF TIME.
I MEAN, THAT'S A FACT.
AND HE ASKED ME TO SUPPORT THAT.
AND I -- I SUPPORTED HIM BECAUSE
I THINK PEOPLE WHEN YOU'RE
ELECTED YOU NEED TO DO THINGS
AND HE LED THE CHARGE TO FINALLY
FIX THIS IMMIGRATION PROBLEM
THAT HAS EXISTED NOW FOR, AS
MARCO SAYS, FOR 30 YEARS.
THEN HE CUT AND RUN BECAUSE IT
WASN'T POPULAR AMONGST
CONSERVATIVES, I GUESS.
HERE'S WHAT I BELIEVE.
AND I WROTE A BOOK ABOUT THIS
CALLED "IMMIGRATION WARS."
YOU CAN GET IT AT $2.99 ON
AMAZON.
IT'S NOT A BESTSELLER.
I CAN PROMISE YOU, THERE WON'T
BE ANY -- YOU CAN GET IT.
IT'S AFFORDABLE TO EVERYBODY.
WE SHOULD HAVE A MATH TO LEGAL
STATUS FOR THE 12 MILLION PEOPLE
HERE ILLEGALLY.
COME OUT FROM THE SHADOWS, PAY A
FINE, EARN LEGAL STATUS BY
WORKING, PAYING TAXES, LEARNING
ENGLISH, NOT COMMITTING CRIMES
AND EARN LEGAL STATUS, NOT
CUTTING IN FRONT OF THE LINE FOR
PEOPLE THAT ARE PATIENTLY
WAITING OUTSIDE.
THAT IS THE -- I THINK THAT'S
THE CONSERVATIVE CONSENSUS
PRAGMATIC APPROACH TO HOW TO
SOLVE THIS PROBLEM.
>> GO AHEAD, SENATOR.
>> IT'S INTERESTING JEB MENTIONS
THE BOOK, THAT'S THE BOOK WHERE
YOU CHANGED YOUR POSITION ON
IMMIGRATION BECAUSE YOU USED TO
SUPPORT A PATH TO CITIZENSHIP.
>> TO DID YOU.
>> YOU CHANGED --
>> SO DID YOU, MARCO.
>> YOU WROTE A BOOK WHERE YOU
CHANGED YOUR POSITION -- YOU
WROTE A BOOK WHERE YOU CHANGED
YOUR POSITION FROM A PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP TO A PATH TO
LEGALIZATION AND THE BOTTOM LINE
IS THIS, WE ARE NOT GOING TO
ANYTHING ON THIS ISSUE UNTIL WE
FIRST BRING ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION
UNDER CONTROL.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE BEEN
TOLD FOR 30 YEARS THEY'RE GOING
TO ENFORCE THE BORDER, GOING TO
BUILD THE WALL AND IT NEVER GETS
BUILD AND NEVER HAPPENS.
IT IS VERY CLEAR THERE WILL BE
NO PROGRESS ON THIS ISSUE IN ANY
WAY, SHAPE OR FORM UNTIL YOU
PROVE TO THE PEOPLE OF THIS
COUNTRY ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION IS
UNDER CONTROL AND WHEN I'M
PRESIDENT, WE ARE GOING TO BRING
IT UNDER CONTROL ONCE AND FOR
ALL AFTER 30 YEARS OF TALKING
ABOUT IT.
>> MARCO, MARCO -- HE BROUGHT UP
MY NAME.
I HAVE SUPPORTED A CONSENSUS
APPROACH TO SOLVING THIS PROBLEM
WHEREVER IT CAME UP AND IN 2007
IT ALMOST PASSED WHEN MY BROTHER
WAS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
WHEN YOU LED THE CHARGE WITH THE
CHANG OF EIGHT, I SUPPORTED IT
BECAUSE YOU ASKED ME TO.
I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT FOR
PEOPLE IN ELECTED OFFICE TO
FORGE CONSENSUS TO SOLVE
PROBLEMS.
THERE'S NEVER GOING DO BE
PERFECT BILL.
>> ALL RIGHT.
>> WHEN YOU DIDN'T DO THAT AND
ASKED PEOPLE TO SUPPORT, YOU
SHOULDN'T CUT AND RUN.
>> MEGYN --
>> STICK WITH IT, THAT'S EXACTLY
WHAT HAPPENED.
HE CUT AND RUN.
THAT'S A TRAGEDY.
NOW IT'S HARDER AND HARDER TO
SOLVE THIS PROBLEM.
>> THE LAST ONE.
>> THERE'S NOT GOING TO BE
CONSENSUS ON THIS ISSUE UNTIL WE
ENFORCE OUR IMMIGRATION LAWS.
THAT IS ABUNDANTLY CLEAR, YOU'RE
NOT GOING TO BE ABLE TO RAM DOWN
THE THROAT OF THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE YOUR APPROACH.
THE ONLY WAY TO MOVE FORWARD
AFTER TWO MIGRATORY CRISES WITH
MINORS, FIRST BRING ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION UNDER CONTROL.
UNTIL THAT HAPPENS THERE'S NOT
GOING TO BE CONSENSUS ON THIS
ISSUE.
>> LET'S MOVE ON.
SENATOR CRUZ, WHEN SENATOR RUBIO
PROPOSED THAT BILL CREATING A
MATH TO CITIZENSHIP, YOU
PROPOSED AN AMENDMENT.
IT WOULD HAVE ALLOWED FOR
LEGALIZATION BUT NOT
CITIZENSHIP.
YES, IT WOULD.
PRESSED LAST MONTH ON WHY YOU
SUPPORTED LEGALIZATION, YOU
CLAIMED THAT YOU DIDN'T.
RIGHT, LIKE YOU JUST DID.
SAW THAT.
YOU ARGUED THAT THIS WAS JUST A
POISON PILL AMENDMENT, BASICALLY
SOMETHING DESIGNED TO KILL THE
BILL AND NOT ACTUALLY GET IT
THROUGH.
BUT THAT IS NOT, HOWEVER, HOW IT
SOUNDED AT THE TIME.
WATCH.
>> THIS BILL TO BE VOTED DOWN.
I DON'T WANT IMMIGRATION REFORM
TO FAIL.
I WANT IMMIGRATION REFORM TO
PASS.
I BELIEVE IF THIS AMENDMENT WERE
TO PASS, THE CHANCES OF THIS
BILL PASSING INTO LAW WOULD
INCREASE DRAMATICALLY.
I BELIEVE IF THE AMENDMENTS I
INTRODUCED WERE ADOPTED THAT THE
BILL WOULD PASS AND MY EFFORT IN
INTRODUCING THEM WAS TO FIND A
SOLUTION THAT REFLECTED COMMON
GROUND AND THAT FIXED THE
PROBLEM.
IF THE PROPONENTS OF THIS BILL
ACTUALLY DEMONSTRATE A
COMMITMENT NOT TO POLITICS, NOT
TO CAMPAIGNING ALL THE TIME, BUT
TO ACTUALLY FIXING THIS PROBLEM,
TO FINDING A MIDDLE GROUND, THAT
WOULD FIX THE PROBLEM AND ALSO
ALLOW FOR THOSE 11 MILLION
PEOPLE WHO ARE HERE ILLEGALLY A
LEGAL STATUS WITH CITIZENSHIP
OFF THE TABLE.
>> WAS THAT ALL AN ACT?
IT WAS PRETTY CONVINCING.
>> YOU KNOW, THE AMENDMENT
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT IS ONE
SENTENCE, IT'S 38 WORDS.
ANYONE CAN GO ONLINE AT
TEDCRUZ.ORG AND READ EXACTLY
WHAT IT SAID.
IN THOSE 38 WORDS, IT SAID
ANYONE HERE ILLEGALLY IS
PERMANENTLY INELIGIBLE FOR
LEADERSHIP.
DIDN'T SAY A WORD --
>> THE BILL YOU'RE AMENDING
ALLOWED --
>> MEGYN, THE BILL WAS 1,000
PAGES.
I INTRODUCED A SERIOUS OF
AMENDMENTS EACH DESIGNED TO FIX
PROBLEMS IN THE BILL.
THE FACT THAT EACH AMENDMENT
DIDN'T FIX EVERY PROBLEM DIDN'T
MEAN THAT I SUPPORTED THE REST
OF THE BILL AND I'LL TELL YOU
WHO SUPPORTED MY AMENDMENT.
JEFF SESSIONS, THE STRONGEST
OPPONENT OF AMNESTY IN THE
UNITED STATES CONGRESS, AND HE
DID SO BECAUSE TAKING
CITIZENSHIP OFF THE TABLE WAS
IMPORTANT AND IT REVEALED THE
HYPOCRISY OF THE PROPONENTS OF
THIS BILL WHO WERE LOOKING FOR
VOTES.
LISTEN, WE CAN SOLVE
IMMIGRATION.
WE JUST HEARD AN ARGUMENT BACK
AND FORTH THAT WE CAN'T SOLVE
IMMIGRATION.
I HAVE A DETAILED IMMIGRATION
PLAN THAT IS ON MY WEBSITE,
TEDCRUZ.ORG.
IT WAS DESIGNED WITH IOWA'S OWN
CO STEVE KING AND JEFF
SESSIONS, AND WE HAVE THE TOOLS
IN FEDERAL LAW TO DO THIS NOW.
WE CAN BUILD THE FENCE.
WE CAN TRIPLE THE BORDER PATROL.
WE CAN END SANCTUARY CITIES BY
CUTTING OFF FUNDING TO THEM.
WE CAN END WELFARE FOR THOSE
HERE ILLEGALLY AND WHAT IS
MISSING IS THE POLITICAL WILL
BECAUSE TOO MANY DEMOCRATS AND,
SADLY, TOO MANY REPUBLICANS
DON'T WANT TO SOLVE THIS
PROBLEM.
IF I AM ELECTED PRESIDENT, WE
WILL SECURE THE BORDER AND WE
WILL END THE ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION.
>> SENATOR PAUL, YOU KNOW HOW
WASHINGTON WORKS.
DO YOU BUY THAT?
>> I WAS THERE AND I SAW THE
DEBATE.
I SAW TED CRUZ SAY WE'LL TAKE
CITIZENSHIP OFF THE TABLE AND
THEN THE BILL WILL PASS AND I'M
FOR THE BILL.
THE BILL WOULD INVOLVE
LEGALIZATION.
HE CAN'T HAVE IT BOTH WAYS.
WHAT IS PARTICULARLY INSULTING,
THOUGH, HE IS THE KING OF
SAYING, OH, YOU'RE FOR AMNESTY,
EVERYBODY'S FOR AMNESTY EXCEPT
FOR TED CRUZ, BUT IT'S A
FALSENESS.
AND THAT'S AN AUTHENTICITY
PROBLEM THAT EVERYBODY HE KNOWS
IS NOT AS PERFECT AS HIM BECAUSE
WE'RE ALL FOR AMNESTY.
I WAS FOR LEGALIZATION.
I THINK, FRANKLY, WE COULD HAVE
BORDER SECURITY, YOU CAN HAVE
LEGALIZATION.
SO WAS TED, BUT NOW HE SAYS IT
WASN'T SO.
THAT'S NOT TRUE.
>> TWO AHEAD, SIR.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU KNOW, JOHN ADAMS FAMOUSLY
SAID FACTS ARE ARE STUBBORN
THINGS.
THE FACTS ARE ARE VERY, VERY
SIMPLE.
WHEN THAT BATTLE WAS WAGED MY
FRIEND SENATOR RUBIO CHOSE TO
STAND WITH BARACK OBAMA AND
HARRY REID AND CHUCK SCHUMER AND
SUPPORT AMNESTY.
AND I STOOD ALONGSIDE JEFF
SESSIONS AND STEVE KING AND WE
LED THE FIGHT AGAINST AMNESTY.
AND IF YOU WANT TO KNOW WHO'S
TELLING THE TRUTH, YOU SHOULD
LOOK AND ASK PEOPLE LIKE JEFF
SESSIONS AND STEVE KING AND RUSH
LIMBAUGH AND MARK LEVIN, ALL OF
WHOM SAY AS JEFF SESSIONS SAID
RESPONDING TO THESE FALSE
ATTACKS JUST RECENTLY IN
ALABAMA, HE SAID IF IT WASN'T
FOR TED CRUZ, THE GANG OF EIGHT
RUBIO/SCHUMER BILL WOULD HAVE
PASSED BUT BECAUSE TED STOOD UP
AND HELPED LEAD THE EFFORT,
MILLIONS ROSE UP TO KILL IT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, EVEN CHUCK
SCHUMER, YOUR CO-SPONSOR OF THAT
BILL AGREES WITH TED CRUZ ON
THIS.
>> I UNDERSTAND, BUT LET ME
RESPOND.
THAT WAS MENTIONED IN THIS
ANSWER.
I'M GOING TO RESPOND THIS WAY.
THIS IS THE LIE THAT TED'S
CAMPAIGN IS BUILT ON AND RAND
TOUCHED UPON IT THAT HE'S THE
MOST CONSERVATIVE GUY AND
EVERYONE ELSE IS, YOU KNOW,
EVERYONE ELSE IS A RINO.
THE TRUTH IS, TED, THROUGHOUT
THIS CAMPAIGN YOU'VE BEEN SAYING
TO DO OR SAY ANYTHING TO GET
VOTES.
YOU WORKED FOR GEORGE BUSH'S
CAMPAIGN.
YOU HELPED DESIGN GEORGE W.
BUSH'S IMMIGRATION POLICY.
WHEN YOU GOT TO THE SENATE, YOU
DID AN INTERVIEW WITH CBS NEWS,
I WASN'T PART OF THE VIDEO, YOU
SAID ON THE ISSUE OF PEOPLE HERE
ILLEGALLY WE CAN REACH A
COMPROMISE.
IN THE COMMITTEE YOU SAID I WANT
TO BRING PEOPLE OUT OF THE
SHADOWS.
NOW YOU WANT TO TRUMP TRUMP ON
IMMIGRATION.
YOU CAN'T -- WE'RE NOT GOING TO
BEAT HILLARY CLINTON WITH
SOMEONE WHO'S WILLING TO SAY OR
DO ANYTHING TO WIN AN ELECTION.
>> GO AHEAD, SENATOR CRUZ.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU KNOW, I LIKE MARCO.
HE'S VERY CHARMING.
HE'S VERY SMOOTH.
BUT THE FACTS ARE SIMPLE.
WHEN HE RAN FOR ELECTION IN THE
STATE OF FLORIDA, HE TOLD THE
PEOPLE OF FLORIDA IF YOU ELECT
ME, I WILL LEAD THE FIGHT
AGAINST AMNESTY.
WHEN I RAN IN TEXAS, I TOLD THE
PEOPLE OF TEXAS IF YOU ELECT ME,
I WILL LEAD THE FIGHT AGAINST
AMNESTY.
WE BOTH MADE THE IDENTICAL
PROMISES.
BUT WHEN WE CAME TO WASHINGTON,
WE MADE A DIFFERENT CHOICE.
MARCO MADE THE CHOICE TO GO THE
DIRECTION OF THE MAJOR DONORS,
TO SUPPORT AMNESTY BECAUSE HE
THOUGHT IT WAS POLITICALLY
ADVANTAGEOUS.
I HONORED MY COMMITMENTS AND AS
PRESIDENT, I WILL HONOR EVERY
COMMITMENT THAT I MAKE TO THE
MEN AND WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY.
>> ALL RIGHT.
GO AHEAD, GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> I WANT TO ASK THE PEOPLE IN
THE AUDIENCE I'M STANDING HERE,
I WATCHED THE VIDEO OF SENATOR
CRUZ, I WATCHED THE VIDEO OF
SENATOR RUBIO.
I HEARD WHAT THEY SAID.
AND THIS IS WHY YOU NEED TO SEND
SOMEONE FROM OUTSIDE OF
WASHINGTON TO WASHINGTON.
I FEEL LIKE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
I FEEL LIKE I NEED -- I FEEL
LIKE I NEED A WASHINGTON ENGLISH
DICTIONARY CONVERTER, RIGHT?
I MEAN, I HEARD WHAT THEY BOTH
SAID.
I SAW IT ON VIDEO.
FACT IS THIS IS WHAT MAKES A
DIFFERENCE WHEN YOU'RE A
GOVERNOR.
YOU CAN CHANGE YOUR MIND.
TED CAN CHANGE HIS MIND.
MARCO CAN CHANGE HIS MIND.
IT'S PERFECTLY LEGAL IN THIS
COUNTRY TO CHANGE YOUR MIND.
BEN YOU'RE A GOVERNOR, YOU HAVE
TO ADMIT IT.
YOU CAN'T HIDE BEHIND
PARLIAMENTARY TRICKS.
THAT'S THE DIFFERENCE.
THAT'S THE KIND OF LEADER WE
NEED IN THE WHITE HOUSE.
STOP THE WASHINGTON BULL AND
LET'S GET THINGS DONE.
>> ALL RIGHT.
LET'S GO TO A YOUTUBE QUESTION.
LET'S GET TO A YOUTUBE QUESTION.
THIS IS A QUESTION FROM A
YOUTUBE CREATOR WITH OVER 2
MILLION SUBSCRIBERS.
WATCH.
>> I'M DULCE CANDY, A YOUTUBE
CREATOR WHO IMMIGRATED TO THE
UNITED STATES FROM MEXICO.
I'M PROUD TO SAY I SERVED IN THE
ARMED FORCES IN IRAQ, BECAME A
CITIZEN, I'M NOW AN
ENTREPRENEUR.
THERE ARE MANY IMMIGRANTS WHO
CONTRIBUTE POSITIVELY TO THE
AMERICAN ECONOMY.
SOME OF THE COMMENTS IN THE
CAMPAIGN MAKE US QUESTION OR
PLACE IN THE COUNTRY.
IF AMERICA DOES NOT SEEM LIKE A
WELCOMING PLACE FOR IMMIGRANT
ENTREPRENEURS, WILL THE AMERICAN
ECONOMY SUFFER?
>> DR. CARSON, THAT ONE'S FOR
YOU.
>> OH, GREAT.
[ LAUGHTER ]
AS I SAID BEFORE, WE ARE A LAND
OF IMMIGRANTS, BUT WE HAVE TO BE
INTELLIGENT ABOUT THE WAY THAT
WE FORM OUR IMMIGRATION POLICIES
AND THAT'S ONE OF THE REASONS
THAT I HAVE CALLED ON US TO
DECLARE WAR ON THE ISLAMIC
STATE.
BECAUSE WE NEED TO REORIENT OUR
IMMIGRATION POLICIES AND OUR
VISA POLICIES FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE
COMING INTO THIS COUNTRY BECAUSE
THERE ARE MANY PEOPLE OUT THERE
WHO WANT TO DESTROY US.
NOW, I RECOGNIZE THAT THE VAST
MAJORITY OF PEOPLE COMING IN
HERE PROBABLY ARE NOT THOSE
KINDS OF PEOPLE, BUT THAT'S NOT
GOOD ENOUGH.
IF YOU'VE GOT TEN PEOPLE COMING
TO YOUR HOUSE AND YOU KNOW ONE
OF THEM IS A TERRORIST, YOU'RE
PROBABLY GOING TO KEEP THEM ALL
OUT.
YOU KNOW, WE PROBABLY HAVE TO
FIGURE OUT A WAY TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
>> I JUST --
>> GO AHEAD.
>> THAT BEAUTIFUL YOUNG WOMAN
WHO'S AN ENTREPRENEUR WHO SERVED
IN THE MILITARY, FIRST OF ALL,
IS DESERVING OF OUR RESPECT FOR
SERVICE IN THE MILITARY AND THE
FACT THAT SHE'S AN ENTREPRENEUR.
AND WE SHOULD BE A WELCOMING
NATION.
OUR IDENTITY IS NOT BASED ON
RACE OR ETHNICITY.
IT'S BASED ON A SET OF SHARED
VALUES.
THAT'S AMERICAN CITIZENSHIP.
DULCE CANDY, PRETTY COOL NAME,
ACTUALLY, THAT IS NOW AN SBRUP
ENTREPRENEUR OVER YOUTUBE IS
PART OF THE AMERICAN SPIRIT.
WE SHOULD CELEBRATE IT AS
CONSERVATIVES.
THAT'S WHAT WE BELIEVE IN.
DEAL WITH THE THREAT OF TERROR
AND ALSO RECOGNIZE THIS COUNTRY
SHOULD BE ASPIRATIONAL ACROSS
THE BOARD.
>> I THINK THAT'S THE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
THAT'S THE FALSE CHOICE IN THIS
WHOLE DEBATE ABOUT IMMIGRATION.
OF COURSE, WE'RE GOING TO BE A
NATION OF IMMIGRANTS.
EVERY SINGLE YEAR CLOSE TO A
MILLION PEOPLE EMIGRATE TO THE
UNITED STATES LEGALLY.
THERE'S NO NATION ON EARTH THAT
COMES CLOSE TO THAT NUMBER.
ARE WE NOT A SOVEREIGN COUNTRY,
CHOOSE WHO COMES IN, WHEN THEY
COME IN AND HOW THEY COME IN?
THAT'S NOT WHAT'S HAPPENING NOW.
>> ALL RIGHT.
>> I THINK THE OTHER PROBLEM IS
WE HAVE AN IMMIGRATION SYSTEM
THAT'S OUTDATED, PRIMARILY BASED
ON WHETHER YOU HAVE FAMILY
MEMBERS LIVING HERE.
IN THE 21st CENTURY, IT HAS TO
BE A MERIT-BASED SYSTEM AND THAT
IS WHY OUR LEGAL IMMIGRATION
SYSTEM IS IN NEED OF
MODERNIZATION AND WE WILL ALWAYS
CELEBRATE LEGAL IMMIGRATION LIKE
DULCE'S GREAT STORY.
>> ALL RIGHT.
WE'RE MOVING ON.
>> GENTLEMEN, WE'RE GOING TO
TURN NOW TO WHAT WE CALL
ELECTABILITY, ISSUES YOU FACE IN
A PRIMARY OR GENERAL ELECTION.
YOU MAY NOT BE ALTOGETHER
UNHAPPY IF YOU'RE NOT INCLUDED
IN THIS ROUND.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU PRIDE YOURSELF
ON STANDING UP TO THE D.C.
CARTEL.
AS WE SEE TO A TURN DEGREE
TONIGHT, THERE'S A PRICE OF
STANDING UP TO THE D.C. CARTEL.
13 REPUBLICAN SENATORS HAVE
ENDORSED OTHER CANDIDATES, NONE
HAVE ENDORSED YOU.
YOU TWICE LAST YEAR, YOU ASKED
FOR A COLLEAGUE TO SECOND A
MOTION, A ROUTINE COURTESY ON
THE SENATE FLOOR AND NO SENATOR
WOULD DO IT.
TOP GOP OFFICIALS WORRY THAT IF
YOU'RE AT THE TOP OF THE TICKET,
SOME OFFICIALS, THAT NOT ONLY
WILL YOU LOSE THE WHITE HOUSE
BUT TANK THE TICKET ALL THE WAY
DOWN THE LINE.
QUESTION IS DOES YOUR STYLE
SOMETIMES GET IN THE WAY OF YOUR
ABILITY TO GET THINGS DONE, SIR?
>> WELL, CHRIS, YOU ARE EXACTLY
RIGHT THAT I AM NOT THE
CANDIDATE OF CAREER POLITICIANS
IN WASHINGTON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I'LL TELL YOU THE ENDORSEMENTS
I'M PROUD OF ARE THE OVER
200,000 VOLUNTEERS ACROSS THIS
COUNTRY WHO HAVE SIGNED UP TO
VOLUNTEER FOR OUR CAMPAIGN.
THE ENDORSEMENTS I AM PROUD OF
ARE LEADING CONSERVATIVES LIKE
IOWA'S OWN CONGRESSMAN STEVE
KING WHO'S THE NATIONAL
CO-CHAIRMAN OF MY CAMPAIGN.
THE ENDORSEMENTS THAT I'M PROUD
OF ARE CONSERVATIVE LEADERS LIKE
DR. JAMES DOBSON AND OVER
700,000 CONTRIBUTIONS
NATIONWIDE, PEOPLE GOING TO OUR
WEBSITE, TEDCRUZ.ORG.
THIS IS A GRASSROOTS CAMPAIGN
AND, YOU KNOW, WHEN I RAN FOR
SENATE IN TEXAS, I TOLD THE
PEOPLE OF TEXAS THAT I'M NOT
GOING THERE TO GO ALONG TO GET
ALONG.
WASHINGTON IS BROKEN AND THE
PEOPLE I HAVE BEEN ACCOUNTABLE
TO EVERY SINGLE DAY IN THE
SENATE ARE THE 27 MILLION TEXANS
WHO I REPRESENT AND I MADE A
PROMISE TO THEM THAT I MAKE TO
YOU TODAY WHICH IS IF I AM
ELECTED, EVERY SINGLE DAY I WILL
DO TWO THINGS.
TELL THE TRUTH, AND DO WHAT I
SAID I WOULD DO.
>> THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH.
POLL AFTER POLL SHOWS YOU
RUNNING AMONG THE WORST IN YOUR
PARTY AGAINST HILLARY CLINTON.
EVEN MITT ROMNEY SAID THAT A
BUSH V. CLINTON HEAD TO HEAD
WOULD BE TOO EASY FOR THE
DEMOCRATS.
YET STILL YOU AND THE SUPERPACS
SUPPORTING YOU CONTINUE TO
BLANKET THE AIRWAVES WITH
CUTTING ADS, NOT AGAINST MRS.
CLINTON BUT AGAINST YOUR FELLOW
REPUBLICANS ESPECIALLY SENATOR
RUBIO.
DO THESE ATTACKS DO MORE HARM
THAN GOOD BY TARGETING THOSE
CANDIDATES WHO APPEAR TO HAVE
THE BEST CHANCE OF DEFEATING
MRS. CLINTON?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I'VE SEEN POLLS
WHERE I'M BEATING HILLARY
CLINTON PRETTY REGULARLY.
I BELIEVE I CAN.
I HAVE A PROVEN RECORD.
CUTTING TAXES, SHRINKING THE
GOVERNMENT, REFORMING EDUCATION,
CHALLENGING THE STATUS QUO.
ELIMINATING CAREER CIVIL SERVICE
PROTECTIONS, SHRINKING THE
GOVERNMENT WORKFORCE BY 11 BUT
LEADING THE NATION IN JOB
GROWTH.
HILLARY CLINTON HAS NO RECORD OF
ACCOMPLISHMENT.
I'M CONFIDENT IF I WIN THIS
NOMINATION I WILL AGGRESSIVELY
GO AGAINST HER AND BEAT HER AS
IT RELATES TO THE SUPERPACS, I
HAVE NO CONTROL OVER THAT.
AND THIS IS BEANBAG COMPARED TO
WHAT THE CLINTON HIT MACHINE IS
GOING TO DO TO THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE.
THE SIMPLE FACT IS WE ALL HAVE
RECORD.
IT WILL ALL BE SCRUTINIZED.
IT'S GIVE AND TAKE.
IT'S CALL THE POLITICS AND
THAT'S THE WAY IT IS.
I'M RUNNING HARD AND I BELIEVE
I'LL BE THE REPUBLICAN NOMINEE
AND BE THE ONE BEST SUITED TO
BEAT HILLARY CLINTON WHO SHOULD
NOT BE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR RUBIO FIRST BEFORE I
ASK YOU A QUESTION, ANY RESPONSE
TO GOVERNOR BUSH?
>> WELL, I BELIEVE, AND I KNOW
THAT IF IOWA HELPS MAKE ME THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE, I WILL
DEFEAT HILLARY CLINTON.
HILLARY DOESN'T WANT TO RUN
AGAINST ME, BUT I CANNOT WAIT TO
RUN AGAINST HER AND CANNOT WAIT
TO EARN THE OPPORTUNITY TO DO IT
BECAUSE SHE CANNOT BE THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
SHE WANTS TO PUT BARACK OBAMA ON
THE SUPREME COURT OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
SHE SAID THAT HERE IN IOWA JUST
TWO DAYS AGO.
THAT WOULD BE A DISASTER FOR
THIS COUNTRY.
SO I HOPE AND PRAY AND CANNOT
WAIT UNTIL THIS STATE AND OTHERS
GIVE ME AN OPPORTUNITY TO SERVE
THIS PARTY AS ITS NOMINEE
BECAUSE I WILL DEFEAT HILLARY
CLINTON.
>> NOW LET'S TALK ABOUT
ELECTABILITY, SENATOR.
"TIME" MAGAZINE ONCE CALLED YOU
THE REPUBLICAN SAVIOR.
RUSH LIMBAUGH AND OTHERS SAID
YOU LIKELY WILL BE PRESIDENT
SOMEDAY.
BUT IF YOU LOOK AT THE RECENT
AVERAGE OF POLLS IN YOUR HOME
STATE OF FLORIDA, YOU'RE IN
THIRD TRAILING DONALD TRUMP BY
24 POINTS.
IF THE PEOPLE WHO KNOW YOU BEST
HAVE YOU THERE, WHY SHOULD THE
REST OF THE COUNTRY ELECT YOU?
>> WELL, LET ME BE CLEAR ABOUT
ONE THING.
THERE'S ONLY ONE SAVIOR AND IT'S
NOT ME.
IT'S JESUS CHRIST WHO CAME DOWN
TO EARTH AND DIED FOR OUR SINS
AND SO I'VE ALWAYS MADE THAT
CLEAR ABOUT THAT COVER STORY.
AS FAR AS THE POLLS ARE
CONCERNED, IOWA, ON MONDAY NIGHT
YOU'RE GOING TO GO TO A CAUCUS
SITE AND YOU'LL BE THE FIRST
AMERICANS THAT VOTE IN THIS
ELECTION.
YOU WILL BE THE FIRST AMERICANS
THAT GET TO ANSWER THE
FUNDAMENTAL QUESTION WHAT COMES
NEXT FOR THIS COUNTRY AFTER
SEVEN DISASTROUS YEARS OF BARACK
OBAMA?
LET ME TELL YOU WHAT THE ANSWER
BETTER NOT BE.
IT BETTER NOT BE BERNIE SANDERS.
BERNIE SANDERS IS A SOCIALIST.
I THINK BERNIE SANDERS IS GOOD
CANDIDATE FOR PRESIDENT OF
SWEDEN.
WE DON'T WANT TO BE SWEDEN.
WE WANT TO BE THE UNITED STATES
OF AMERICA.
AND HILLARY CLINTON, HILLARY
CLINTON IS DISQUALIFIED FROM
BEING THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF
THE UNITED STATES.
IN FACT, ONE OF HER FIRST ACTS
AS PRESIDENT MAY VERY WELL BE TO
PARDON HERSELF BECAUSE HILLARY
CLINTON, HILLARY CLINTON STORED
CLASSIFIED INFORMATION ON HER
PRIVATE SERVER AND HILLARY
CLINTON LIED TO THE FAMILIES OF
THOSE FOUR BRAVE AMERICANS WHO
LOST THEIR LIFE IN BENGHAZI, AND
ANYONE WHO LIES TO THE FAMILIES
OF AMERICANS WHO HAVE DIED IN
THE SERVICE OF THIS COUNTRY CAN
NEVER BE COMMANDER IN CHIEF OF
THE UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, TWO OF
YOUR FORMER TOP AIDES GO ON
TRIAL IN MAY FOR FRAUD AND
CONSPIRACY IN THE BRIDGE-GATE
CASE.
THE POLITICALLY MOTIVATED
CLOSURE OF LANES TO THE GEORGE
WASHINGTON BRIDGE.
ANOTHER FORMER AIDE WHO HAS
ALREADY PLEADED GUILTY AND WILL
LIKELY TESTIFY FOR THE
GOVERNMENT, AS YOU KNOW, SAYS
THAT YOU KNEW ABOUT THIS WHOLE
DEAL.
CAN THE GOP TAKE THE CHANCE OF
NOMINATING YOU WITH THIS SCANDAL
STILL OUT THERE, SIR?
>> SURE, BECAUSE THERE'S BEEN
THREE DIFFERENT INVESTIGATIONS
AND PROVEN THAT I KNEW NOTHING.
AND THE FACT IS THAT WHAT I DID
DO, WHAT I DID DO FROM THE
BEGINNING, CHRIS, AS SOON AS I
FOUND OUT ABOUT IT, I FIRED THE
PEOPLE WHO WERE RESPONSIBLE AND
THAT'S WHAT YOU EXPECT FROM A
LEADER.
AND I'LL TELL YOU SOMETHING
ELSE, I INHERITED A STATE IN NEW
JERSEY THAT WAS DOWNTRODDEN AND
BEATEN BY LIBERAL DEMOCRATIC
POLICIES, HIGH TAXATION, HIGH
REGULATION AND THIS YEAR IN
2015, NEW JERSEY HAS HAD THE
BEST YEAR OF JOB GROWTH THAT OUR
STATE HAS EVER HAD IN THE LAST
15 YEARS.
THAT'S BECAUSE WE PUT
CONSERVATIVE POLICIES IN PLACE.
AND I'LL TELL YOU ONE OTHER
THING.
YOU KNOW WHY THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY WILL WANT TO TAKE A CHANCE
ON ME?
BECAUSE THEY KNOW THAT HILLARY
CLINTON WILL NEVER BE PROSECUTED
BY THIS JUSTICE DEPARTMENT AND
THEY'RE GOING TO WANT TO PUT A
FORMER FEDERAL PROSECUTOR ON THE
STAGE TO PROSECUTE HER NEXT
SEPTEMBER AND THERE IS NO ONE ON
THIS STAGE BETTER PREPARED TO
PROSECUTE THE CASE AGAINST
HILLARY CLINTON THAN I AM.
I WILL BE READY, I WILL TAKE HER
ON AND WHEN I TAKE HER ON, I
GUARANTEE YOU ONE THING, SHE
WILL NEVER GET WITHIN TEN MILES
OF THE WHITE HOUSE.
THE DAYS FOR THE CLINTONS IN
PUBLIC HOUSING ARE OVER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> MUCH MORE TO COME INCLUDING
WHERE THE CANDIDATES STAND ON
FOREIGN POLICY AND, ONCE AGAIN,
YOU CAN GO TO GOOGLE.COM, OR
OPEN THE GOOGLE SEARCH APP AND
SEARCH "FOX NEWS DEBATE" TO VOTE
ON WHICH CANDIDATE YOU THINK IS
WINNING THE DEBATE TONIGHT.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY.
LET'S GET BACK TO THE QUESTIONS.
CHRIS?
>> GENTLEMEN, ALMOST 60% OF
REPUBLICAN CAUCUSGOERS IDENTIFY
THEMSELVES AS EVANGELICALS.
I'D LIKE TO SPEND A FEW MINUTES
EXPLORING SOCIAL ISSUES.
GOVERNOR KASICH, YOU TALK A GOOD
DEAL ABOUT YOUR FAITH.
IN FACT, YOU SAID IT PLAYED YOUR
ROLE IN A DECISION TO EXPAND
MEDICAID AND SAY WHEN YOU MEET
ST. PETER AT THE PEARLY GATES
HE'S GOING TO ASK WHAT YOU DID
FOR THE POOR, NOT WHAT YOU DID
TO KEEP GOVERNMENT SMALL.
SENATOR CRUZ IS ON THE OPPOSITE
SIDE OF THIS ISSUE IF YOU.
DOES THAT MEAN YOU'RE GETTING IN
AND HE ISN'T?
>> NO, YOU KNOW, CHRIS, HERE'S
WHAT HAPPENED WITH MEDICAID IN
MY STATE.
WE TOOK THE GROWTH OF MEDICAID
FROM OVER 10% IN MY SECOND
BUDGET TO 2.5% WITHOUT CUTTING
OFF ONE PERSON OR CUTTING ONE
BENEFIT BECAUSE WE INNOVATED THE
GOVERNMENT.
NOW MOM AND DAD CAN STAY IN
THEIR OWN HOME RATHER THAN BEING
FORCED INTO A NURSING HOME.
AND THEN WE DECIDED WE COULD
BRING $14 MILLION OF OUR MONEY,
WASHINGTON DOESN'T HAVE MONEY,
OUR MONEY TO TEND TO THE
MENTALLY ILL BECAUSE I DON'T
THINK THEY OUGHT TO LIVE IN
PRISON OR LIVE UNDER A BRIDGE,
TO TREAT THE DRUG ADDICTED SO
THEY'RE NOT IN AN IN AND OUT OF
DOOR POLICY OUT OF THE PRISONS
AND HELP THE WORKING POOR SO
THEY DON'T LIVE IN EMERGENCY
ROOMS.
HOW'S IT WORKED?
WE TREATED THE DRUG ADDICTED IN
OUR PRISONS AND RELEASED THEM
INTO THE COMMUNITY AND OUR
RECIDIVISM RATE IS LESS THAN
20%, THAT'S BASICALLY BORDERING
ON A MIRACLE BECAUSE OF OUR
GREAT PRISON DIRECTOR.
THE MENTALLY ILL, THEY'VE BEEN
STEPPED ON FOR TOO LONG IN THIS
SOCIETY AND WE'RE BEGINNING TO
TREAT THEM.
IN TERMS OF MY FAITH, LOOK, WHEN
I STUDY SCRIPTURE I KNOW PEOPLE
WHO LIVE IN THE SHADOWS NEED A
CHANCE.
I'M NOT DECIDING ANYBODY HAS TO
MAKE THESE DECISIONS THE WAY I
DO ON THE BASIS OF WHAT I DO,
.
THE TIME TO COME TO STOP
IGNORING THE MENTALLY ILL IN
THIS COUNTRY, BEGIN TO TREAT
THEM AND GET THEM ON THEIR FEET
ALONG, OF COURSE, WITH TREATING
THE DRUG ADDICTED BECAUSE WE
DON'T WANT THEM IN AND OUT OF
THE PRISONS.
GIVE PEOPLE A CHANCE.
WE TALKED ABOUT CRIMINAL JUSTICE
REFORM.
WE'VE ENACTED IT IN OUR STATE.
LOOK, THE CONSERVATIVE MESSAGE
IS ECONOMIC GROWTH, AND ALONG
WITH ECONOMIC GROWTH GOES
OPPORTUNITY FOR EVERYBODY IN
AMERICA.
EVERYBODY OUGHT TO HAVE A CHANCE
TO BE ABLE TO RISE TO THEIR
GOD-GIVEN PURPOSE.
AND THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE DONE IN
OHIO.
WE'RE RUNNING SURPLUSES.
WE'RE UP 400,000 JOBS.
GUESS WHAT, THE FORMULA IS
WORKING.
I'D SUGGEST PEOPLE TAKE A LOOK
AT IT.
THANK YOU.
>> GENTLEMEN, WE HAD A CASE
STUDY ON RELIGIOUS LIBERTY JUST
THIS LAST SUMMER.
A COUNTY CLERK IN KENTUCKY NAMED
KIM DAVIS REFUSED TO ISSUE
MARRIAGE LICENSES TO SAME-SEX
COUPLES AFTER THE SUPREME COURT
RULING SAYING THAT IT VIOLATED
HER RELIGIOUS BELIEFS.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, YOU SAID THAT
SHE MUST FOLLOW THE LAW OR BE
MOVED TO ANOTHER JOB THAT WOULD
BE IN KEEPING WITH HER
CONSCIENCE.
BUT SOME CONSERVATIVES SAY THAT
THAT VIOLATES HER RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY.
>> NO, WHAT I SAID, CHRIS, WAS
THE LAW NEEDS TO BE FOLLOWED AND
THAT SOMEONE IN THAT OFFICE HAS
TO DO THEIR JOB.
SO IF MISS DAVIS WANTED TO STEP
ASIDE AND GET RID OF HER ABILITY
TO BE ABLE TO DO THAT, THERE
SHOULD BE SOMEONE ELSE IN THAT
OFFICE WHO IT DIDN'T VIOLATE
THEIR CONSCIENCE SO THEY COULD
FOLLOW THE LAW OF THE STATE OF
KENTUCKY.
I NEVER SAID MISS DAVIS SHOULD
LOSE HER JOB OR SHE HAD TO DO
IT.
WHAT I DID SAY WAS THE PERSON
WHO CAME IN FOR THE LICENSE
NEEDED TO GET IT.
IFIFIFHERE'S SOMEONE IN THAT
ORGANIZATION AND IT TURNS OUT
THERE WAS WHO WAS WILLING TO BE
ABLE TO THAT, THAT'S WHAT WE
SHOULD DO.
BUT JUST AS IMPORTANTLY, AND I
AGREE WITH WHAT JOHN SAID, YOU
KNOW, WE ALL HAVE OUR OWN
INDIVIDUAL INTERPRETATIONS OF
OFFER FAITH.
AND HERE'S THE PROBLEM WITH
WHAT'S GOING ON AROUND THE
WORLD.
THE RADICAL ISLAMIC JIHADISTS,
WHAT THEY WANT TO DO IS IMPOSE
THEIR FAITH UPON EACH AND EVERY
ONE OF US.
EVERY ONE OF US.
THE REASON WHY THIS WAR AGAINST
THEM IS SO IMPORTANT IS THAT
VERY BASIS OF RELIGIOUS LIBERTY.
THEY WANT EVERYONE IN THIS
COUNTRY TO FOLLOW THEIR
RELIGIOUS BELIEFS THE WAY THEY
DO.
THEY DO NOT WANT US TO EXERCISE
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY.
THAT'S WHY AS COMMANDER IN
CHIEF, I WILL TAKE ON ISIS, NOT
ONLY BECAUSE IT KEEPS US SAFE,
BUT BECAUSE IT ALLOWS US TO
ABSOLUTELY CONDUCT OUR RELIGIOUS
AFFAIRS THE WAY WE FIND IN OUR
HEART AND IN OUR SOULS AS A
CATHOLIC, THAT'S WHAT I WANT TO
DO, AND NO MATTER WHAT YOUR
FAITH IS, THAT'S WHAT I WANT YOU
TO BE ABLE TO DO.
>> THANK YOU, SIR.
SENATOR RUBIO, DURING THE LAST
DEBATE, YOU SAID GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE HAD CHANGED HIS
POSITION AND HIS MIND ON GUN
CONTROL, ON COMMON CORE, AND
BACKING PRESIDENT OBAMA'S
NOMINATION OF SONIA SOTOMAYOR TO
THE SUPREME COURT.
HE SAID YOU'RE WRONG ON THE
FACTS AND CAN'T, QUOTE, SLIME
YOUR WAY TO THE WHITE HOUSE.
I ASSUME IN THE LAST TWO WEEKS
YOU'VE DONE SOME FACT CHECKING.
DO YOU WANT TO TAKE ANYTHING
BACK?
>> YEAH, I WOULD ENCOURAGE
PEOPLE TO GO ON MARCORUBIO.COM.
WE'LL PUT ALL THE FACTS UP SO
PEOPLE CAN SEE IT FOR
THEMSELVES.
YOU ASKED A FUNDAMENTAL QUESTION
ABOUT THE ROLE OF FAITH IN OUR
COUNTRY.
I THINK THIS IS AN IMPORTANT
QUESTION.
I THINK IF YOU DO NOT UNDERSTAND
OUR JUDEO-CHRISTIAN VALUES ARE
ONE OF THE REASONS AMERICA IS
SUCH A SPECIAL COUNTRY, YOU
DON'T UNDERSTAND OUR HISTORY.
YOU SEE, WHY ARE WE ONE OF THE
MOST GENEROUS PEOPLE IN THE
WORLD, NO, THE MOST GENEROUS
PEOPLE IN THE WORLD?
WHY DO AMERICANS CONTRIBUTE
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS TO CHARITY?
IT IS NOT BECAUSE OF THE TAX
WRITE-OFF.
IT'S BECAUSE IN THIS NATION, WE
ARE INFLUENCED BY
JUDEO-CHRISTIAN VALUES THAT
TEACH US TO CARE FOR THE LESS
FORTUNATE, REACH OUT TO THE
NEEDY, TO LOVE OUR NEIGHBOR.
THIS IS WHAT'S MADE OUR NATION
SO SPECIAL AND YOU SHOULD HOPE
THAT OUR NEXT PRESIDENT IS
SOMEONE THAT IS INFLUENCED BY
THEIR FAITH BECAUSE IF YOUR
FAITH CAUSES YOU TO CARE FOR THE
LESS FORTUNATE, IT IS SOMETHING
YOU WANT TO SEE IN YOUR PUBLIC
FIGURES AND WHEN I'M PRESIDENT,
I CAN TELL YOU THIS, MY FAITH
WILL NOT JUST INFLUENCE THE WAY
I'LL GOVERN AS PRESIDENT, IT
WILL INFLUENCE THE WAY I LIVE MY
LIFE BECAUSE IN THE END, MY GOAL
IS NOT SIMPLY TO LIVE ON THIS
EARTH FOR 80 YEARS BUT TO LIVE
AN ETERNITY WITH MY CREATOR.
I WILL ALWAYS ALLOW MY FAITH TO
INFLUENCE EVERYTHING I DO.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
SENATOR PAUL, IN MAY, IN MAY ON
THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL YOU, SAID YOU
DIDN'T GET INTO POLITICS TO
FIGHT ABOUT ABORTION.
YOU SAID YOU WERE MORE CONCERNED
ABOUT THE NATIONAL DEBT.
YOUR ANSWER IS TO TURN ABORTION
BACK TO THE STATES THE WAY IT
WAS BEFORE ROE V. WADE.
DOES THAT MEAN THAT IF A LIBERAL
STATE, LET'S SAY, WANTS TO MAKE
ABORTION LEGAL, THAT YOU'RE OKAY
WITH THAT, AND WHAT DO YOU SAY
TO CONSERVATIVE VOTERS WHO
BELIEVE DEEPLY THAT ABORTION IS
MURDER?
>> I THINK ABORTION IS ALWAYS
WRONG.
I'VE SUPPORTED A VARIETY OF
SOLUTIONS.
BOTH STATE AS WELL AS FEDERAL.
IN FACT, JUST LAST WEEK, I
INTRODUCED THE LIFE AT
CONCEPTION ACT WHICH WOULD SAY
THAT THE 14th AMENDMENT WOULD
DEFEND AN INDIVIDUAL EVEN IN THE
WOMB.
BUT I THINK ON THE BROADER
QUESTION OF RELIGION AND
POLITICS, YOU KNOW, I THINK
LIBERTY, ITSELF, REQUIRES A
VIRTUE, REQUIRE THE A VIRTUOUS
PEOPLE.
IN FACT, WASHINGTON SAID THAT
DEMOCRACY REQUIRES A VIRTUOUS
PEOPLE.
A THEOLOGIAN SAID LIBERTY
REQUIRES RESTRAINT BUT THE ONLY
RESTRAINT CONSISTENT WITH
LIBERTY IS SELF-RESTRAINT.
THERE'S A LOT PACKED INTO THAT
STATEMENT, BUT THE BOTTOM LINE
IS WE MUST HAVE VIRTUE, WE MUST
HAVE A RELIGIOUS BEARING AS A
NATION.
THE GOVERNMENT'S NOT ALWAYS
GOING TO SAVE US AND IT'S NOT
ALWAYS GOING TO COME FROM
GOVERNMENT.
IF WE DON'T KNOW RIGHT AND
WRONG, I THINK WE HAVE LOST OUR
WAY, I THINK WE BECOME UNMOORED
AND WITHOUT THE RELIGIOUS
FOUNDATION THAT GUIDES US ALL,
WE HAVE A GREAT RISK OF GOING
HORRIBLY IN THE WRONG DIRECTION.
>> SIR, 30 SECONDS TO ANSWER MY
SPECIFIC --
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
JUST 30 SECONDS TO ANSWER MY
SPECIFIC QUESTION.
DO YOU FAVOR THE IDEA THAT
ABORTION SHOULD BE A STATES
RIGHTS ISSUE AND IF A LIBERAL
STATE WANTS TO MAKE IT LEGAL,
THAT THAT'S THEIR CHOICE?
YES OR NO?
>> BOTH.
BOTH FEDERAL AND STATE APPROACH.
I HAVE SAID THAT WE COULD LEAVE
IT TO THE STATES BUT I'VE ALSO
INTRODUCED A FEDERAL SOLUTION AS
WELL.
SO THE FEDERAL SOLUTION WOULD BE
THE LIFE AT CONCEPTION ACT WHICH
IS AN ACT THAT WOULD FEDERALIZE
THE ISSUE.
BUT I'VE ALSO SAID FOR THE MOST
PART THESE ISSUES WOULD BE LEFT
BACK TO THE STATES.
SO THERE MIGHT BE AN OCCASION IF
WE DID OVERTURN ROE V. WADE, ROE
V. WADE NATIONALIZED THE ISSUE.
IF YOU HAD THE COURT REVERSE ROE
V. WADE, IT WOULD BECOME A STATE
ISSUE ONCE AGAIN.
I THINK IT WOULD BE BETTER THE
LESS ABORTIONS WE HAVE SO THE
MORE STATES THAT WE HAVE THAT
MADE ABORTION ILLEGAL, THE
BETTER AS FAR AS TRYING TO SAVE
AND PRESERVE LIVES.
>> THANK YOU, SIR.
GENTLEMEN --
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
LIKE TO ASK YOU A FEW QUESTIONS
ABOUT FOREIGN POLICY BROADLY.
DR. CARSON, MANY EXPERTS BELIEVE
RUSSIAN LEADER VLADIMIR PUTIN
HAS GREATER IDEAS, BIGGER
DESIGNS FOR THE REGION BEYOND
RUSSIA'S ACTIONS INSIDE UKRAINE.
FAST FORWARD TO FEBRUARY 2017,
AND IT IS PRESIDENT CARSON, AND
RUSSIAN UNUNIFORMED COMMANDOS
CROSS THE ESTONIAN BORDER AND
THEY OCCUPY A CITY IN ESTONIA.
ESTONIA, A MEMBER OF NATO,
ESSENTIALLY INVOKES ARTICLE 5,
AN ATTACK ON ONE IS AN ATTACK ON
ALL.
WHAT DO YOU DO?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, RECOGNIZE
THAT VLADIMIR PUTIN IS AN
OPPORTUNIST, AND HE'S A BULLY,
AND WE HAVE TO FACE HIM DOWN.
AND I WOULD, FIRST OF ALL, FACE
HIM DOWN IN THAT WHOLE REGION,
THE WHOLE BALTIC REGION.
I THINK WE NEED TO PUT IN SOME
ARMORED BRIGADES THERE.
WE ONLY HAVE ONE OR TWO.
WE NEED MUCH MORE THAN THAT.
WE NEED TO BE DOING MILITARY
EXERCISES IF NOT ONLY ESTONIA
BUT LATVIA AND LITHUANIA.
THEY'RE TERRIFIED BY THE SABER
RATTLING.
I THINK WE OUGHT TO PUT IN OUR
MISSILE DEFENSE SYSTEM.
I THINK WE OUGHT TO GIVE UKRAINE
OFFENSIVE WEAPONS AND I THINK WE
OUGHT TO FIGHT THEM ON THE
ECONOMIC BASIS BECAUSE PUTIN IS
A ONE-HORSE COUNTRY, OIL AND
ENERGY.
AND WE OUGHT TO FIGHT THEM ON
THAT LEVEL.
WE OUGHT TO BE HELPING IN TERMS
OF THE TECHNOLOGY FOR FRACKING
KEEPING THE PRICE LOW, QUITE
FRANKLY, BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT'S
KEEPING HIM CONTAINED.
SO, YES, I'D ABSOLUTELY WOULD GO
IN IF HE ATTACKED, I THINK
ARTICLE 5 OF NATO, WE WOULD
DEFINITELY PROTECT ALL OF OUR
ALLIES.
>> GENTLEMEN, YOU'VE ALL SAID
THAT THE IRAN NUCLEAR DEAL IS A
BAD ONE.
SENATOR RUBIO, YOU'RE AMONG THE
CANDIDATES WHO'VE SAID YOU WOULD
TEAR IT UP ON DAY ONE.
BUT AS YOU KNOW, IRAN HAS
ALREADY RECEIVED TENS OF
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS, TENS OF
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN THIS DEAL
AND HAS QUICKLY REESTABLISHED
TIES ECONOMICALLY WITH EUROPE.
THE MAJOR CONCESSIONS, IN OTHER
WORDS, ARE UP FRONT IN THIS
DEAL.
SO SHOULD YOU WIN BY THE TIME
YOU TAKE OFFICE, THE REMAINING
PARTS OF THE DEAL WOULD BE THE
CONSTRAINTS ON IRAN.
SO WHY BLOW UP THOSE CONSTRAINTS
ON DAY ONE?
LETTING IRAN OFF THE HOOK?
>> WELL, LET ME FIRST DESCRIBE
IRAN BECAUSE THEY'RE NOT JUST A
NORMAL NATION STATE.
WE HAVE NO QUARREL WITH THE
IRANIAN PEOPLE.
THE IRANIAN LEADER, SUPREME
LEADER IS A RADICAL SHIA CLERIC
WHO HAS AN APOCALYPTIC VISION OF
THE FUTURE.
HE VIEWS HIMSELF NOT SIMPLY AS
THE LEADER OF IRAN BUT THE
LEADER OF ALL MUSLIMS, ALL SHIA
MUSLIMS ON THE PLANET AND HAVE A
DESIRE NOT SIMPLY TO CONQUER THE
MIDDLE EAST AND BECOME THE
DOMINANT POWER IN THE REGION BUT
BE ABLE TO HOLD AMERICA HOSTAGE.
THAT IS WHY THEY'RE BUILDING
RIGHT NOW AND DEVELOPING
LONG-RANGE MISSILES CAPABLE OF
REACHING THE UNITED STATES AND
THAT IS WHY THEY'RE GOING TO USE
THOSE $100 BILLION TO EXPAND
THEIR CONVENTIONAL CAPABILITIES
AND ONE DAY BUY OUR BUILD A
NUCLEAR WEAPON.
WE WILL -- WHEN I AM PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, ON MY
FIRST DAY IN OFFICE WE ARE
CANCELING THE DEAL WITH IRAN AND
NATIONS WILL HAVE TO MAKE A
CHOICE.
THEY CAN DO BUSINESS WITH IRAN
OR DO BUSINESS WITH AMERICA AND
I AM VERY CONFIDENT THEY'RE
GOING TO CHOOSE AMERICA BEFORE
THEY CHOOSE THE IRANIAN ECONOMY.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, YOU'VE SAID
THAT MARCO RUBIO IS WRONG, THAT
SENATOR RUBIO IS WRONG WITH
TEARING IT UP ON DAY ONE.
>> LOOK, WE DON'T KNOW WHAT'S
GOING TO HAPPEN IN TEN MONTHS.
AND IF I WERE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES RIGHT NOW, I'D BE
LINING UP OUR ALLIES TO SAY THAT
IF ONE CROSSED "T" OR ONE DOTTED
"I" DOES NOT OCCUR THEY VIOLATE
THE AGREEMENT, WE SLAP BACK ON
SANCTIONS.
WE CAN SLAP ON SANCTIONS ALONE
ON DAY ONE, BUT IT'S NOT GOING
TO BE ANYWHERE NEAR AS
EFFECTIVE.
BUT THE PRESIDENT NEEDS TO BE
LAYING THE GROUNDWORK RIGHT NOW
FOR THE ABILITY TO SLAP THOSE
SANCTIONS BACK ON WORLDWIDE.
AND I'LL TELL YOU WHAT I'M
WORRIED ABOUT.
I'M WORRIED ABOUT MONEY.
YOU READ ABOUT ALL THE COMPANIES
NOW THAT ARE DOING BUSINESS,
ABOUT TO DO BUSINESS IN IRAN,
AND WE DON'T GET THIS SETTLED
DOWN WITH OTHER COUNTRIES IN THE
WORLD ABOUT SANCTIONS, THEN IRAN
COULD VIOLATE THAT AGREEMENT AND
WE'RE THE ONLY ONES PUTTING THE
SANCTIONS ON.
WE NEED TO MOVE AGGRESSIVELY
NOW.
BUT I WOULD SAY THIS TO YOU,
BRETT, NUMBER ONE, IF THEY
VIOLATE IT, WE NEED TO MOVE
AGAINST THEM AND NUMBER TWO, IF
WE FIND OUT THEY'RE DEVELOPING A
NUCLEAR WEAPON AND WE KNOW HOW
TO GET TO IT, WE'RE GOING TO GO
TAKE IT OUT.
THAT IS WHAT WE HAVE TO DO.
WE CANNOT LET THINGS GET FARTHER
DOWN THE ROAD LIKE WE DID WITH
NORTH KOREA.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, YOU KNOW THE
MOST POWERFUL SANCTION ARE THE
MULTILATERAL ONES.
>> THAT'S RIGHT.
>> THESE EUROPEAN COUNTRIES ARE
REESTABLISHING THESE TIES.
I KNOW, BRET.
BRET, HERE'S THE PROBLEM.
YOU TAKE A LOOK AT BELGIUM, I
TALKED TO A DIPLOMAT FROM
BELGIUM, I SAID HOW'S IT GOING?
HE SAID WE HAVE THE MILITARY IN
THE STREETS RIGHT NOW, WE NEVER
DREAMT WE'D EVER SEE IT.
I THINK THERE'S AN OPPORTUNITY
TO BRING THE WORLD TOGETHER.
THE TURKS ARE BEING THREATENED.
WE KNOW ABOUT THE FRENCH.
WE KNOW ABOUT THE BELGIANS.
WE KNOW ABOUT THE BRITS.
EVERYBODY IS UNDER FIRE AND
UNDER ATTACK.
WE HAVE TO STAND TOGETHER AS AN
ALLIANCE.
SO ACTUALLY THE OPPORTUNITY IS
THERE BECAUSE OF THE THREAT TO
ALL OF THESE COUNTRIES TO BRING
ALL OF US TOGETHER AND SAY THERE
IS SOMETHING MORE IMPORTANT THAN
MONEY, IT IS THE FUTURE OF THE
WORLD AND THE FUTURE OF OUR
CHILDREN AND GRANDCHILDREN.
THAT'S THE KIND OF LEADERSHIP
THIS COUNTRY NEEDS AND IT HAS
NOT BEEN IN EFFECT DURING THE
ADMINISTRATION OF BARACK OBAMA
AND THAT'S ONLY THE BEGINNING OF
THE FAILURES THAT THEY HAVE
COMMITTED NOT ONLY IN THE MIDDLE
EAST BUT ALL OVER THE WORLD
INCLUDING RUSSIA AND CHINA.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, LIBYA IS THE
NEWEST BASE FOR ISIS.
JUST TODAY DEFENSE SECRETARY
ASHTON CARTER SAID ISIS IS
CONSOLIDATING THEIR FOOTPRINT
THERE AND SETTING UP TRAINING
FACILITIES.
IF YOU WERE PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU
DEPLOY U.S. TROOPS TO LIBYA TO
TAKE OUT ISIS THERE?
>> BRET, LET ME TELL YOU, THIS
IS ANOTHER ONE OF THOSE PLACES
WHERE HILLARY CLINTON HAS SO
MUCH TO ANSWER FOR AND WHY SHE
IS COMPLETELY UNQUALIFIED TO BE
COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
IN A PREVIOUS DEMOCRATIC DEBATE,
THREE TIMES HILLARY CLINTON WAS
ASKED ABOUT THE FAILURE IN
LIBYA, A POLICY SHE TOOK CREDIT
FOR AND SAID WHAT IS YOUR
MEASURE OF RESPONSIBILITY, MADAM
SECRETARY, FOR THE FAILURE IN
LIBYA?
THREE TIMES SHE REFUSED TO
ANSWER THE QUESTION BECAUSE SHE
REFUSES TO BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE
FOR ANYTHING THAT GOES WRONG.
IF IT HAD GONE RIGHT, BELIEVE
ME, SHE WOULD HAVE BEEN RUNNING
AROUND TO BE ABLE TO TAKE CREDIT
FOR IT.
HERE'S WHAT I'D DO.
THIS IS ABOUT THE BIGGER BROADER
WAR AGAINST ISIS.
WE NEED TO BRING TOGETHER OUR
EUROPEAN AND SUNNI ARAB ALLIES
AND DEVELOP A STRATEGY TOGETHER
TO TAKE ON ISIS EVERY PLACE THAT
IT IS AROUND THE WORLD SO THAT
TOGETHER ALL OF US CAN TAKE ISIS
OUT, DESTROY IT, AND THEN MOVE
ON TO COME BACK TO OUR COUNTRY,
PROTECT OUR HOMELAND SECURITY
AND MAKE SURE THAT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE ARE SAFE.
AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT I
WILL DO.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
WE'RE NOT FINISHED YET.
MORE TO COME FROM THE
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE LIVE FROM
DES MOINES, IOWA.
NEXT.
AND REMEMBER, TO SEE HOW THE
CAMPAIGNS ARE RESPONDING TO THE
DEBATE IN REALTIME, GO TO
GOOGLE.COM OR OPEN YOUR GOOGLE
SEARCH APP AND SEARCH "FOX NEWS
DEBATE" AND PLEASE STAY WITH US.
>>> IOWA, RESUME THE DEBATE.
>> SENATOR PAUL?
>> YOU HAVE SAID FORMER
PRESIDENT BILL CLINTON'S HISTORY
WITH WOMEN IS FAIR GAME IN THIS
CAMPAIGN.
HOW DO YOU ANSWER THOSE WHO SAY
YOU DON'T HOLD THE SINS OF THE
HUSBAND AGAINST THE WIFE?
>> YOU KNOW, I'VE NEVER REALLY
BROUGHT THIS UP AND ASKED THE
QUESTION BUT I HAVE RESPONDED TO
THE QUESTION.
I DON'T BLAME HILLARY CLINTON AT
ALL FOR THIS.
I DON'T THINK SHE'S RESPONSIBLE
FOR HIS BEHAVIOR.
I DO THINK THE POSITION
PROMOTING WOMEN'S RIGHTS AND
FAIRNESS TO WOMEN IN THE
WORKPLACE THAT IF WHAT BILL
CLINTON DID, ANY CEO IN OUR
COUNTRY DID, WITH AN INTERN,
WITH A 22-YEAR-OLD, 21-YEAR-OLD
INTERN IN THEIR OFFICE, THEY
WOULD BE FIRED.
THEY WOULD NEVER BE HIRED AGAIN.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
FIRED, NEVER HIRED AGAIN AND
PROBABLY SHUNNED IN THEIR
COMMUNITY.
AND THE THING IS, SHE CAN'T BE A
CHAMPION OF WOMEN'S RIGHTS AT
THE SAME TIME SHE'S GOT THIS
THAT IS ALWAYS LURKING OUT
THERE, THIS TYPE OF BEHAVIOR.
SO IT IS DIFFICULT.
>> OF HER HUSBAND'S.
>> YEAH, BUT I COMBINE THIS ALSO
WITH THE MILLIONS UPON MILLIONS
OF DOLLARS THEY'VE TAKEN FROM
REGIMES IN THE MIDDLE EAST WHO
TREAT WOMEN LIKE, LIKE CATTLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE HAVE ANOTHER QUESTION FROM
ONE OF YOUTUBE'S TOP CREATORS.
HERE IT IS.
>> I'M NABELA NOOR, I'M A
MUSLIM-AMERICAN BORN AND RAISED
IN THE U.S. WHO CREATES BEAUTY
AND LIFESTYLE VIDEOS ON YOUTUBE.
IN 2015, THE NUMBER OF HATE
CRIMES AGAINST MUSLIMS IN THE
U.S. HAS TRIPLED.
ON SOCIAL MEDIA WHERE I'VE SPENT
A LOT OF TIMES I'VE SEEN MANY
ATTACKS DIRECTED TOWARD FELLOW
MUSLIMS.
THIS CULTURE OF HATRED IS ONLY
DRIVING ISIS TO RADICALIZE,
RECRUIT AND INSIGHT VIOLENCE.
AS PRESIDENT WHAT WOULD YOU DO
TO ADDRESS THIS TOXIC CLIMATE
AND PROMOTE INCREASED TOLERANCE
IN THE UNITED STATES?
>> HOW DO YOU ANSWER NABELA?
>> FIRST OF ALL, IT'S IMPORTANT
WHEN RUNNING FOR THE HIGHEST
OFFICE IN THE LAND WE RECOGNIZE
WE'RE LIVING IN DANGEROUS TIMES
AND HAVE TO BE SERIOUS ABOUT IT,
THAT OUR WORDS HAVE
CONSEQUENCES.
DONALD TRUMP, FOR EXAMPLE, I
MENTIONED HIS NAME AGAIN IF
ANYBODY WAS MISSING HIM.
MR. TRUMP BELIEVED IN REACTION
TO PEOPLE'S FEARS THAT WE SHOULD
BAN ALL MUSLIMS.
WELL, THAT CREATES AN
ENVIRONMENT THAT'S TOXIC IN OUR
OWN COUNTRY.
NABELA'S A RISING ENTREPRENEUR.
SHE WANTS TO PURSUE THE AMERICAN
DREAM.
SHE'S AN AMERICAN CITIZEN.
SHE SHOULD NOT FEEL
UNCOMFORTABLE ABOUT HER
CITIZENSHIP.
SHE'S NOT THE THREAT.
THE THREAT IS ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
WE NEED TO FOCUS OUR ENERGIES
THERE, NOT THESE BROAD-BLANKET
KIND OF STATEMENTS THAT WILL
MAKE IT HARDER FOR US TO DEAL
WITH ISIS.
WE NEED TO DEAL WITH ISIS IN THE
CALIPHATE.
WE NEED A STRATEGY TO DESTROY
ISIS THERE.
YOU CAN'T DO THAT WITHOUT THE
COOPERATION OF THE MUSLIM WORLD
BECAUSE THEY'RE AS THREATENED AS
WE ARE, SO I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT FOR US TO BE CAREFUL
ABOUT THE LANGUAGE WE USE WHICH
IS WHY I'VE BEEN CRITICAL OF
DONALD TRUMP DISPARAGING WOMEN,
DISPARAGING HISPANICS.
THAT'S NOT A SIGN OF STRENGTH.
MAKING FUN OF DISABLED PEOPLE,
WE'RE NEVER GOING TO WIN
ELECTIONS IF WE DON'T HAVE A
MORE BROADER UNIFYING MESSAGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
SENATOR CRUZ, CHANGE OF SUBJECT,
YOU'VE CALLED FOR AN END TO THE
RENEWABLE FUEL STANDARDS WHICH
MANDATE THAT REFINERIES BLEND
BIOFUELS INCLUDING ETHANOL INTO
GASOLINE.
AS YOU WELL KNOW, ETHANOL IS A
BIG INDUSTRY IN THIS STATE.
$10 BILLION A YEAR.
LAST WEEK TERRY BRANSTAD, THE
POPULAR GOVERNOR OF IOWA --
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
-- WHO IS IN THE HALL TONIGHT,
SAID THAT BANKROLLED BY BIG OIL
AND IOWA VOTERS WOULD BE MAKING
A MISTAKE SUPPORTING YOU.
WHY SHOULD THOSE VOTERS SIDE
WITH YOU OVER THE SIX-TERM
GOVERNOR OF THIS STATE, SIR?
>> WELL, CHRIS, I'M GLAD TO
DISCUSS MY VIEWS ON ETHANOL AND
ENERGY.
I THINK GOD HAS BLESSED THIS
COUNTRY WITH ENORMOUS NATURAL
RESOURCES AND WE SHOULD PURSUE
ALL OF THE ABOVE.
WE SHOULD BE DEVELOPING OIL AND
GAS AND COAL AND NUCLEAR AND
WIND AND SOLAR AND ETHANOL AND
BIOFUELS, BUT I DON'T BELIEVE
THAT WASHINGTON SHOULD BE
PICKING WINNERS AND LOSERS AND I
THINK THERE SHOULD BE NO MANDATE
AND NO SUBSIDIES WHATSOEVER.
INDEED, MY TAX PLAN I'VE
INTRODUCED, IT'S AVAILABLE ON
OUR WEBSITE, IT'S A SIMPLE FLAT
TAX FOR EVERYONE, PRODUCE
ENORMOUS ECONOMIC GROWTH AND
ELIMINATES EVERY MANDATE, EVERY
SUBSIDY SO THERE'S NO SUBSIDIES
FOR OIL AND GAS, NO SUBSIDIES
FOR ANYONE.
NOW, IT IS TRUE THERE ARE A
BUNCH OF LOBBYISTS AND A BUNCH
OF DEMOCRATS IN THIS STATE
SPENDING MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
TRYING TO CONVINCE THE PEOPLE OF
IOWA THAT I SOMEHOW OPPOSE
ETHANOL.
IT'S NOT TRUE.
I'VE INTRODUCED LEGISLATION THAT
WOULD PHASE OUT THE ETHANOL
MANDATE OVER FIVE YEARS BUT THAT
IS IN THE CONTEXT OF HAVING NO
MANDATES WHATSOEVER FOR ANYONE
AND I WOULD NOTE THERE'S A MUCH
MORE IMPORTANT GOVERNMENT
REGULATION TO ETHANOL AND THAT'S
THE EPA'S BLEND WALL THAT MAKES
IT ILLEGAL TO SELL MID-LEVEL
BLENDS OF ETHANOL AND GASOLINE.
I WILL TEAR DOWN THE EPA'S BLEND
WALL WHICH WILL ENABLE ETHANOL
TO EXPAND ITS MARKET SHARE BY UP
TO 60% ALL WITHOUT MANDATES, ALL
WITHOUT ANY GOVERNMENT MANDATES
WHATSOEVER THROUGH THE
MARKETPLACE.
I'LL NOTE FINALLY, CHRIS,
THERE'S A REASON IOWA'S
CONGRESSMAN STEVE KING THE
FIERCEST DEFENDER OF FARMERS IN
THIS STATE IS CHAIRING MY
CAMPAIGN.
HE UNDERSTANDS I'M COMMITTED TO
A FAIR AND LEVEL PLAYING FIELD
FOR EVERY ENERGY SOURCE WITHOUT
LOBBYISTS AND WITHOUT WASHINGTON
PICKING WINNERS AND LOSERS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DR. CARSON, I'D LIKE TO ASK
YOU ABOUT EXACTLY THAT ISSUE.
WHERE ARE YOU ON THE MANDATORY
ETHANOL STANDARD AND PRECISELY
THIS QUESTION, SHOULD GOVERNMENT
BE IN THE BUSINESS OF PICKING
WINNERS AND LOSERS?
OR SHOULD IT BE LEFT TO THE
MARKETPLACE?
>> WELL, AS ANYONE KNOWS WHO'S
BEEN LISTENING TO ME, I'M VERY
MUCH AGAINST THE GOVERNMENT
BEING INVOLVED IN EVERY ASPECT
OF OUR LIVES.
YOU KNOW, WE -- LAST YEAR THERE
WAS AN ADDITIONAL 81,000 PAGES
OF GOVERNMENT REGULATIONS, IF
YOU STACK THAT UP, IT WOULD BE A
THREE-STORY BUILDING.
THIS IS ABSOLUTELY ABSURD.
THEY'VE INSINUATED THEMSELVES
INTO EVERYTHING.
AS FAR AS THE RENEWABLE FUEL
STANDARD IS CONCERNED, CERTAIN
PROMISES WERE MADE, CERTAIN
GOVERNMENT CONTRACTS WERE ISSUED
WHICH EXTEND ALL THE WAY INTO
THE YEAR 2022.
AND I BELIEVE THAT IT'S PROBABLY
UNFAIR TO WITHDRAW THE RUG
BECAUSE PEOPLE HAVE INVESTED
MONEY, PEOPLE HAVE INVESTED A
LOT OF ENERGY INTO THAT.
BUT, YOU KNOW, WE ARE BLESSED
WITH TREMENDOUS ENERGY IN THIS
NATION AND NEED TO BE TALKING
ABOUT NEW SOURCES OF ENERGY.
70% OF OUR POPULATION LIVES
BICOASTLY.
WHAT ABOUT HYDROELECTRIC POWER?
WE CAN DEVELOP THAT.
YOU KNOW, WE HAVE SO MUCH
NATURAL GAS NOW AND CAN LIQUIFY
IT, TRANSFER IT ACROSS THE SEAS.
WE CAN MAKE EUROPE DEPENDENT ON
US INSTEAD OF PUTIN, PUT HIM
BACK IN HIS LITTLE BOX WHERE HE
BELONGS. DOING AND TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF THE TREMENDOUS
OPPORTUNITIES IN ENERGY GOD HAS
GIVEN US AND NOT GET INVOLVED IN
THESE LITTLE PETTY ARGUMENTS.
WE CAN GET A LOT OF THEM OUT IF
WE GET THE GOVERNMENT OUT OF OUR
LIVES.
>> COMING UP, CLOSING STATEMENTS
FROM OUR CANDIDATES AS OUR
DEBATE CONTINUES, LIVE, P
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY.
AND NOW, IT IS TIME FORECLOSING
STATEMENTS.
THE CANDIDATES EACH GET 30
SECONDS AND WE BEGIN WITH
KENTUCKY SENATOR, RAND PAUL.
>> THANKS FOR HAVING ME.
IT'S GREAT TO BE BACK.
I'M AN EYE SURGEON FROM
KENTUCKY, I MISS DOING EYE
SURGERY, DID A LITTLE BIT OF
SURGERY OVER CHRISTMAS LAST
YEAR, GOT TO BE ON THE FLOOR OF
THE SENATE AND IT'S BEEN AMAZING
TO ME.
THE THING THAT IS MOST IMPORTANT
TO ME AND CAUSED ME TO RUN FOR
OFFICE IS I'M WORRIED ABOUT THE
COUNTRY AND HOW MUCH DEBT WE'RE
ADDING AND I'M THE ONE TRUE
FISCAL CONSERVATIVE THAT WILL
LOOK AT ALL SPENDING.
THAT IS THE ONLY WAY WE'LL EVER
BALANCE OUR BUDGET, THANK YOU.
>> IOWA GOVERNOR, KASICH.
>> ONE OF OUR NATIONAL SECURITY
ISSUES IS THAT WE LOOK AT EACH
OTHER AND SAY WHY CAN'T WE SOLVE
PROBLEMS?
WE CAN.
WE CAN IN FACT CREATE JOBS AND
PROVIDE JOB SECURITY.
WE CAN CREATE A SITUATION WHERE
WAGES BEGIN TO RISE.
WE CAN CREATE A SITUATION FOR
OUR CHILDREN TO BE ABLE TO GET A
DECENT JOB TO PAY DOWN DEBT AND
RESUME OUR ROLE IN THE WORLD.
ALL OF US HAVE TO COME TOGETHER
WITH AN ABILITY FOR US TO SET
THE TUNE AS CONSERVATIVES.
TO INVITE OTHER PEOPLE IN TO BE
PART OF THAT ORCHESTRA.
I'M AN OPTIMIST AND WE CAN DO IT
AGAIN, TOGETHER TO STRENGTHEN
THIS COUNTRY.
WORK TOGETHER.
THANK YOU.
>> NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR, CHRIS
CHRISTIE.
>> ON SEPTEMBER 11TH, MY WIFE
WAS TWO BLOCKS IF THE WORLD
TRADE CENTER.
WHEN THE BUILDINGS CAME DOWN,
SHE WAS TRAPPED AND I DIDN'T
HEAR FROM HER.
WE HAVE THREE CHILDREN AND I HAD
TO CONFRONT THE POSSIBILITY OF
BEING A SINGLE PARENT.
TERRORISM IN THIS COUNTRY SCARES
EVERYONE.
THE FACT IS THAT WE NEED A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF THAT FEELS IN
HERE THE POSSIBILITY OF LOSS.
I'VE FACED IT, PROSECUTED
TERRORISTS, MAY HAVE HAD THE
DECISIONS THAT NEED TO BE MADE
TO PROTECT US AND AS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, NO ONE
WILL KEEP THIS COUNTRY SAFE THAN
I WILL.
>> FLORIDA GOVERNOR JEB BUSH.
>> I HAVE A PROVEN RECORD AS
GOVERNOR OF THE STATE OF FLORIDA
AS A CONSERVATIVE LEADER AND
DETAILED PLANS TO FIX THE MESS
IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
AS PRESIDENT I WILL RESTORE AND
REBUILD OUR MILITARY, RESTORE
ALLIANCES AND KEEP US SAFE.
AS OUR PARTY NOMINEE, I WILL
DEFEAT HILLARY CLINTON.
I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT MONDAY
NIGHT AND MAKE YOU PROUD AS OUR
PARTY'S NOMINEE.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> DR. BEN CARSON.
>> I WANT TO THANK THE PEOPLE OF
IOWA FOR BEING SO WELCOMING TO
ME.  PLEASE THINK OF OUR
FOUNDING FATHERS AS YOU LISTEN.
WE THE PEOPLE OF THE UNITED
STATES... IN ORDER TO FORM A
MORE PERFECT UNION, ESTABLISH
JUSTICE, ENSURE DOMESTIC
TRANQUILITY, PROVIDE FOR THE
COMMON DEFENSE, PROMOTE THE
GENERAL WELFARE AND SECURE THE
BENEFITS OF LIBERTY TO OURSELVES
DO ORDAIN AND ESTABLISH THIS
CONSTITUTION OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
FOLKS, IT'S NOT TOO LATE.
ENOUGH SAID.
>> SENATOR MARCO RUBIO.
>> THE BIBLE COMMANDS US TO LET
OUR LIGHT SHINE ON THE WORLD.
OVER 200 YEARS, AMERICA'S LIGHT
HAS BEEN SHINING ON THE WORLD
AND THE WORLD HAS NEVER BEEN THE
SAME AGAIN.
NOW, THE WORLD IS DIMMING A
LITTLE BECAUSE OF BARACK OBAMA.
THAT IS WHY WHAT WILL HAPPEN IN
IOWA IS SOUTHERN.
I'M ASKING FOR YOUR VOTE.
I WILL UNITE THIS PARTY AND
DEFEAT HILLARY CLINTON AND WHEN
I'M PRESIDENT, AMERICA'S LIGHT
WILL SHINE AGAIN, AND THE 21
CENTURY WILL BE A NEW AMERICAN
CENTURY.
>> TEXAS SENATOR, TED CRUZ.
>> 93 HOURS.
THE MEDIA NOISE WILL SOON ARE
OVER AND IT'S NOW FOR THE MEN
AND WOMEN OF IOWA TO DECIDE.
OUR COUNTRY IS IN CRISIS.
WE'RE WORRIED THE FUTURE OF OUR
CHILDREN AND HAVE BEEN BURNED,
OVER AND OVER AGAIN.
THE CENTRAL QUESTION IN THIS
RACE IS TRUST.
WHO DO YOU KNOW WILL KILL THE
TERRORISTS, DEFEND THE
CONSTITUTION AND REPEAL
OBAMACARE?
WHO DO YOU KNOW WILL SECURE
AMNESTY AND DEFEND THE BORDERS?
DEFEND RELIGIOUS LIBERTY?
AND I WILL BE HONORED IF YOU AND
YOUR FAMILY WILL COME, CAUCUS
FOR US ON MONDAY NIGHT.
>> GENTLEMEN, THANK YOU ALL SO
MUCH FOR BEING HERE TONIGHT.
WE APPRECIATE IT GREATLY.
THAT DOES IT FOR THE REPUBLICAN
DEBATE.
BUT THE KELLY FILE STARTS IN
JUST A MOMENT AND GUESS WHO IS
GOING TO BE THERE?
SENATOR TED CRUZ.
>> AFTER THE TALK, THE VOTING
HAPPENS IN JUST FOUR DAYS.
THE FIRST AMERICANS TO VOTE, THE
IOWA CAUCUSES ARE MONDAY AND FOX
NEWS WILL HAVE COMPLETE
COVERAGE.
>> WE HAVE YOU COVERED FROM IOWA
TO THE CONVENTIONS AND TO THE
GENERAL ELECTION.
THANKS AGAIN FOR JOINING US.
FOR ALL OF US HERE IN DES
MOINES, HAVE A GREAT
EVENING.