>> GOOD EVENING.
AND WELCOME TO THE FABULOUS
FOX THEATER IN DOWNTOWN
DETROIT.
THE SITE OF THE 11TH
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE OF THE 20 16
CAMPAIGN.
I'M MEGYN KELLY, ALONG WITH
MY CO-MODERATORS BRET BAIER
AND CHRIS WALLACE.
>> 59 REPUBLICAN DELEGATES
ARE AT STAKE HERE IN THE
STATE OF MICHIGAN DURING
NEXT TUESDAY'S REPUBLICAN
PRIMARY.
THE BIGGEST PRIZE OUT OF
FOUR STATES HOLDING CONTESTS
THAT DAY.
FOR TONIGHT'S DEBATE WE ARE
PARTNERING WITH FACEBOOK.
THE CONVERSATION ABOUT THIS
ELECTION HAS BEEN INTENSE,
AS THE CROWD IS HERE.
[CHANTING]
>> JANUARY 1st, 53 MILLION
PEOPLE IN THE U.S. HAD BEEN
TALKING ABOUT THE ELECTION
ON FACEBOOK.
>> TONIGHT, THERE ARE JUST
FOUR CANDIDATES ON THE
STAGE.
THEIR POSITION HAS BEEN
DETERMINED BY THEIR STANDING
IN AN AVERAGE OF THE FIVE
MOST RECENT NATIONAL POLLS
AS RECOGNIZED BY FOX NEWS
AND CONDUCTED AND RELEASED
BY MARCH 1st.
HERE THEY ARE.
BUSINESSMAN DONALD TRUMP.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> TEXAS SENATOR TED CRUZ.
>> FLORIDA SENATOR MARCO
RUBIO.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> AND OHIO GOVERNOR JOHN
KASICH.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> TONIGHT'S RULES ARE
SIMPLE.
UPMg TO 60 SECONDS FOR EACH
ANSWER.
30 SECONDS FOR EACH
FOLLOW-UP RESPONSE.
AND IF A CANDIDATE GOES OVER
THE ALLOTTED TIME, YOU WILL
HEAR THIS.
[BELL]
>> SO PLEASANT.
>> WE HAVE A BIG CROWD HERE.
AND WHILE WE EXPECT THE
AUDIENCE TO BE ENTHUSIASTIC
AND RESPONSIVE AT TIMES.
AND THEY HAVE ALREADY BEEN.
WE ALSO EXPECT THEM TO IT BE
RESPECTFUL AND WE WANT THE
CANDIDATES TO GET THEIR FULL
TIME SO SOMEWHERE BETWEEN A
LIBRARY AND A RED WING'S
GAME.
AM I RIGHT?
[CHEERS]
>> LET'S GET STARTED.
>> MR. TRUMP, AS YOU MAY
HAVE HEARD, THE 2012
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE FOR
PRESIDENT MITT ROMNEY HAD
SOME THINGS TO SAY ABOUT YOU
TODAY.
[CROWD BOOS]
HE SAID YOUR DOMESTIC POLICY
WILL LEAD TO RECESSION.
HE SAID YOUR FOREIGN POLICY
WILL MAKE US LESS SAFE, AND
THEN HE LISTED WHAT HE SAID
ARE YOUR PERSONAL QUALITIES,
QUOTING NOW ROMNEY ON TRUMP,
QUOTE:  THE BULLYING, THE
GREED, THE SHOWINGÑO OFF, THE
IS I SAGE MISOGYNY, THE 3RD
GRADE TACTICS.
HE CHALLENGED YOU TO ANSWER
WITH SUBSTANCE, NOT INSULTS.
HOW DO YOU ANSWER MITT
ROMNEY, SIR?
>> WELL, LOOK, HE WAS A
FAILED CANDIDATE.
HE SHOULD HAVE BEATEN
PRESIDENT OBAMA VERY EASY.
HE FAILED MISERABLY, AND IT
WAS AN EMBARRASSMENT TO
EVERYBODY, INCLUDING THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY.
HE WENT AWAY -- IT LOOKED
LIKE HE WENT AWAY ON
VACATION THE LAST MONTH.
SO I DON'T TAKE THAT.
AND I GUESS OBVIOUSLY HE
WANTS TO BE RELEVANT.
HE WANTS TO BE BACK IN THE
GAME.
AS FAR AS DOMESTIC POLICY
AND TRADE, WHICH IS KILLING
OUR COUNTRY, HE SAID FREE
TRADE.
AND I BELIEVE IN FREE TRADE,
ALSO.
IF YOU LOOK AT CHINA AND
LOOK AT JAPAN AND MEXICO,
BOTH AT THE BORDER BY THE
WAY WHERE THEY ARE KILLING
US, BOTH AT THE BORDER AND
WITH TRADE, AND EVERY OTHER
COUNTRY WE DO BUSINESS WITH
WE ARE GETTING ABSOLUTELY
CRUSHED ON TRADE.
AND HE SAID FREE TRADE, I
SAY FREE TRADE, GREAT, BUT
NOT WHEN THEY ARE BEATING US
SOCc BADLY.
WITH CHINA WE ARE GOING TO
LOSE $505 BILLION IN TERMS
OF TRADES.
YOU JUST CAN'T DO IT.
MEXICO, $58 BILLION.
JAPAN, PROBABLY ABOUT --
THEY DON'T KNOW IT YET ABOUT
$109 BILLION.
EVERY COUNTRY WE LOSE MONEY
WITH.
AS FAR AS I'M CONCERNED, WE
HAVE GOT TO REDUCE, WE HAVE
TO REDO OUR TRADE DEALS
100 PERCENT.
I HAVE THE GREATEST PEOPLE
IN THE WORLD LINED UP TO DO
IT.
[BELL]
>> WE WILL WILL GREAT TRADE
DEALS.
>> MR. TRUMP, ROMNEY ALSO
TALKED ABOUT YOUR POSITION
ON RACE AND THE CONTROVERSY
OVER YOUR FAILURE TO
DENOUNCE DAVID DUKE ON
SUNDAY.
YOU HAVE REPEATEDLY
DISAVOWED HIM SINCE THEN.
BUT I WOULD LIKE TO GO
DEEPER THAN THAT WHAT ARE
YOUR VIEWS ON THE KU KLUX
KLAN AND WHITE SUPREMACIST?
>> I TOTALLY DISAVOW THE KU
KLUX KLAN.
I TOTALLY DISAVOW DAVID
DUKE.
I HAVE BEEN DOING IT NOW FOR
TWO WEEKS.
YOU ARE PROBABLY ABOUT THE
18TH PERSON THAT'S ASKED ME
THE QUESTION.
IT WAS VERY CLEAR.
THAT QUESTION WAS ALSO
TALKED ABOUT IN THE FORM OF
GROUPS.
I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW WHICH
GROUPS ARE YOU TALKING
ABOUT?
YOU HAVE TO TELLru ME WHICH
GROUPS.
ULTIMATELY HE GOT TO THE KU
KLUX KLAN WHICH OBVIOUSLY
I'M GOING TO DISAVOW.
BY THE WAY IF YOU LOOK AT
TWITTER ACCOUNT ALMOST
IMMEDIATELY AFTER THE
PROGRAM THEY WERE DISAVOWED
AGAIN.
IT'S AMAZING WHEN I DO
SOMETHING ON TWITTER
EVERYBODY PICKS IT UP, GOES
ALL OVER THE PLACE.
WHEN I DID THIS ONE, NOBODY
EVER PICKS IT UP.
TAKE LOOK AT MY TWITTER
ACCOUNT.
>> THANK YOU, SIR.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THREE
WEEKS AGO YOU SAID, QU7 L
I DON'T DO THE PERSONAL
ATTACKS.
PRIMARILY BECAUSE IT'S NOT
WHO I AM.
BECAUSE I THINK IT'S BENEATH
THE OFFICE THAT I'M SEEKING
BUT ALSO BECAUSE I DON'T
WANT TO EMBARRASS MY KIDS.
BUT IN THE PAST WEEK YOU'VE
MOCKED MR. TRUMP'S TAN.
YOU'VE MADE FUN OF HIS
SPELLING.
YOU CALLED HIM A CON ARTIST.
YOU SUGGESTED HE WET HIMSELF
BACK STAGE AT THE LAST
DEBATE ALONG WITH OTHER
VULGAR JOLTS AND;p JABS SO
WHAT HAPPENS?
>> LET ME SAY SOMETHING THIS
CAMPAIGN FOR THE LAST YEAR
DONALD TRUMP HAS MOCKED
EVERYBODY WITH PERSONAL
ATTACKS.
HE HAS DONE SO TO PEOPLE
SITTING ON THE STAGE TODAY.
HE HAS DONE SO WITH PEOPLE
DISABLED.
HE HAS DONE IT WITH EVERY
CANDIDATE IN THIS RACE.
IF THERE HAS BEEN ANY
CANDIDATE DESERVED TO BE
ATTACKED THAT WAY IT'S
DONALD TRUMP FOR THE WAY HE
HAS TREATED PEOPLE IN THE
CAMPAIGN.
WITH THAT SAID, I WOULD MUCH
PREFER TO HAVE A POLICY
DEBATE.
I HOPE THAT'S WHAT WE WILL
HAVE HERE TONIGHT.
LET'S HAVE A POLICY DEBATE.
>> WE WILL.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT DONALD
TRUMP'S TRAGEDY AND MY
STRATEGY AND JOHN KASICH'S
STRATEGY WHEN IT COMES TO
ISIS AND HEALTHCARE AND THE
IMPORTANT ISSUES FACING THIS
COUNTRY.
LET'S BE HONEST ABOUT THESE
THIS TOO.
THE MEDIA HAS GIVEN PERSONAL
ATTACKS DONALD TRUMP HAS
MADE INCREDIBLE AMOUNT OF
COVERAGE.
LET'S START TALKING ABOUT
THE ISSUES THAT MATTER TO
THIS COUNTRY.
I'M WILLING TO DO THIS RIGHT
HERE RIGHT HERE TONIGHT.
MR. TRUMP, YOUR RESPONSE?
>> WELL, I ALSO HAPPEN TO
CALL HIM A LIGHT WEIGHT,
OKAY.
AND I HAVE SAID THAT.
SO I WOULD LIKE TO TAKE THAT
BACK.
HE IS REALLY NOT THAT MUCH
OF A LIGHT WEIGHT.
AND AS FAR AS -- AND I HAVE
TOÃSAY THIS, I HAVE TO SAY
THIS.
HE HIT MY HANDS.
NOBODY HAS EVER HIT MY
HANDS.
I HAVE NEVER HEARD OF THIS.
LOOK AT THOSE HANDS.
ARE THEY SMALL HANDS?
[ LAUGHTER ]
AND HE REFERRED TO MY HANDS
IF THEY ARE SMALL, SOMETHING
ELSE MUST BE SMALL.
I GUARANTEE YOU THERE IS NO
PROBLEM.
I GUARANTEE YOU.
>> OKAY.
MOVING ON.
>> OKAY, SENATOR CRUZ, YOU
SAY THAT YOU ARE THE TRUE
CONSERVATIVE IN THIS RACE.
BUT 15 STATES HAVE VOTED
NOW, AND YOU HAVE WON ONLY
FOUR OF THEM.
YOU HAVE LOST REPEATEDLY
WITH WHAT IS SUPPOSED TO BE
YOUR CORE VOTER GROUPS
INCLUDING EVANGELICALS AND
CONSERVATIVES.
HASN'T YOUR BRAND OF
CONSERVATISM BEEN REJECTED
BY AN ELECTORATE THAT
APPEARS TO BE MORE TAKEN
WITH MR. TRUMP'S POPULIST
MESSAGE?
>> WELL, MEGYN, YOU KNOW AT
THE END OF THE DAY FOR THE
FOLKS AT HOME, THIS IS NOT
ABOUT THE INSULTS BACK AND
FORTH BETWEEN THE
CANDIDATES.
ATTACKS WE CAN THROW AT EACH
OTHER.
THIS IS THE PEOPLE AT HOME
WHO ARE STRUGGLING.
THROUGH SEVEN YEARS OF
BARACK OBAMA, THIS IS THE
SINGLE MOMS WHO ARE WORKING
TWO AND THREE JOBS, 28, 29
HOURS A WEEK BECAUSE THEIR
HOURS HAVE BEEN FORCIBLY
REDUCED BECAUSE OF
OBAMACARE.
THIS IS THE TRUCK DRIVERS
MECHANICS WITH CALLUSES ON
THEIR HANDS WHO HAVE SEEN
THEIR WAGES NOT GROW YEAR
AFTER YEAR AFTER YEAR WHILE
THE COST OF LIVING GOES UP.
THIS IS ALL THE YOUNG PEOPLE
COMING OUT OF SCHOOL WITH
STUDENT LOANS UP TO THEIR
EYEBALLS THAT AREN'T ABLE TO
FIND A JOB.
AND I DON'T THINK THE PEOPLE
OF AMERICA ARE INTERESTED IN
A BUNCH OF BICKERING SCHOOL
CHILDREN.
THEY ARE INTERESTED IN
SOLUTIONS, NOT SLOGANS.
IT'S EASY TO SAY MAKE THINGS
BETTER, MAKE THINGS GREAT.
YOU CAN EVEN PRINT IT AND
PUT IT ON A BASEBALL CAP.
THE QUESTION IS DO YOU
UNDERSTAND THE PRINCIPLES
THAT MADE AMERICA GREAT IN
THE FIRST PLACE?
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL REPEAL
EVERY WORD OF OBAMACARE.
I WILL PULL BACK THE
REGULATORS THAT ARE KILLING
SMALL BUSINESSES.
AND WE WILL PASS A SIMPLE
FLAT TAX AND ABOLISH THE
IRS.
AND THAT'S GOING TO DO,
MEGYN.
[BELL]
>> SMALL BUSINESSES ARE
GOING TO EXPLODE.
WE WILL SEE MILLIONS OF HIGH
PAYING JOBS.
WE WILL SEE WAGES GOING UP.
WE WILL SEE OPPORTUNITY.
THAT'S WHERE OUR FOCUS NEEDS
TO BE.
THAT'S WHERE MY FOCUS IS.
AND THAT IS WHY OUR CAMPAIGN
IS THE ONLY CAMPAIGN THAT
OVER AND OVER AGAIN HAS
BEATEN DONALD TRUMP TO DATE,
AND IT'S WHY WE ARE THE ONE
CAMPAIGN THAT GOING FORWARD
CAN AND BEAT DONALD TRUMP IN
THIS ELECTION.
>> GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP.
>> I HAVE HEARD TED SAY THAT
OVER AND OVER AGAIN ON
TELEVISION, THAT HE IS THE
ONLY ONE THAT CAN BEAT ME.
JUST, FOR THE RECORD, I HAVE
WON 10.
HE HAS WON 3 OR 4.
LAST WEEK, IN FACT, ON
TUESDAY, I WAS A HALF A
MILLION VOTES HIGHER THAN
HIM.
I WAS A MILLION VOTES HIGHER
THAN MARCO.
1 MILLION VOTES.
THAT'S A LOT OF VOTES.
AND WAS BY FAR IN FIRST
PLACE.
SO I KEEP HEARING THAT HE IS
THE ONLY ONE THAT CAN BEAT
ME BUT HE IS GETTING BEATEN
VERY, VERY BADLY.
SO WHERE DOESVúú-b THIS COME
FROM?
WHERE DOES IT COME FROM?
>> GO AHEAD, SENATOR RUBIO.
>> I WOULDKW SAY A COUPLE OF
THINGS.
THERE IS NO DOUBT THAT
DONALD HAS DONE WELL IN
THESE ELECTIONS.
THERE IS NO DOUBT ABOUT
THAT.
THE NUMBERS ARE THERE.
HERE IS WHAT THE NUMBERS
ALSO SAY, TWO THIRDS OF THE
PEOPLE WHO CAST A VOTE IN A
REPUBLICAN PRIMARY OR CAUCUS
HAVE VOLTED AGAINST YOU.
THEY DO NOT WANTED YOU TO BE
OUR NOMINEE.
THE REASON WHY IS BECAUSE WE
ARE NOT GOING TO TURN OVER
THE CONSERVATIVE MOVEMENT OR
THE PARTY OF LINCOLN OR
REAGAN, FOR EXAMPLE, TO
SOMEONE WHOSE POSITIONS ARE
NOT CONSERVATIVE.
TO SOMEONE WHO LAST WEEK
DEFENDED PLANNED PARENTHOOD
FOR 30 SECONDS ON A DEBATE
STAGE.
TO SOMEONE, FLAMPLE, WHO HAS
NO IDEAS ON FOREIGN --
SOMEONE WHO THINKS THE
NUCLEAR TRIAD IS A ROCK BAND
FROM THE 1980S.
TIME AND TIME ON ISSUE AFTER
ISSUE HAS NOT PROVEN THAT HE
HAS THE PRINCIPLES THAT
OUTLINE WHAT THE
CONSERVATIVE MOVEMENT HAS
BEEN ABOUT AND AS TED SAID
THE THINGS THAT MADE AMERICA
GREAT.
AMERICA IS GREAT BECAUSE OF
THE CONSERVATIVE PRINCIPLES
OF LIMITED GOVERNMENT AND
FREE ENTERPRISE AND STRONG
NATIONAL DEFENSE AND OUR
NOMINEE NEEDS TO BE SOMEONE
THAT DISANDZ BY THOSE
THINGS.
DONALDS THAT NOT
DEMONSTRATED THAT.
>> GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP AND
THEN WE HAVE TO GO TO
GOVERNOR KASICH.
>> VERY NICE WORDS BUT
HAPPENS TO BE WRONG.
CNN JUST CAME OUT WITH A
POLL> TWO DAYS AGO, A
NATIONAL POLL, EXCUSE ME, A
NATIONAL POLL, A NATIONAL
POLL WHERE HE IS AT 15%.
HE IS AT 14%, AND I'M AT
49%.
SO WHEN HE SAYS 75%, THAT
WOULD MEAN THAT 80% OF THE
PEOPLE DON'T DIG YOU AND I'M
BACK DOWN TO 15%.
>> OF ALL THE PEOPLE ON THE
STAGE HE PERFORMS WORSE THAN
HILLARY CLINTON.
>> WRONG, I BEAT HILLARY
CLINTON IN MANY POLLS.
I BEAT HILLARY CLINTON IN
MANY POLLS.
>> IF YOU ARE OUR NOMINEE.
>> HOLD ON, SENATOR.
>> KEEP ON TALKING.
>> I BEAT HILLARY CLINTON.
>> HOLD ON, HOLD ON.
>> I HOPE YOU CAN.
>> IF THE AUDIENCE CANNOT
UNDERSTAND WHEN YOU ARE
TALKING OVER EACH OTHER.
FINISH YOUR POINT,
MR. TRUMP.
>> I BEAT HILLARY CLINTON IN
MANYa÷ POLLS.
THE Q POLL JUST CAME OUT, I
BEAT HILLARY CLINTON IN A
RECENT FOX POLL.
I BEAT HILLARY CLINTON IN
"U.S.A. TODAY."
I BEAT HER TODAY IN A POLL
IN OHIO.
I BEAT -- I'M THE ONLY ONE
THAT BEATS HILLARY CLINTON.
I -- AND I HAVE NOT STARTED
ON HILLARY YET.
BELIEVE ME, I WILL START
SOON.
I HAVEN'T EVEN STARTED.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, TODAY
YOU ADMITTED THAT YOU HAVE A
NARROW PATH TO THE
NOMINATION THROUGH A
CONTESTED CONVENTION.
TODAY ALSO MITT ROMNEY
PROPOSED THAT REPUBLICANS
SHOULD VOTE FOR SENATOR
RUBIO IN FLORIDA.
SHE SHOULD VOTE FOR YOU IN
OHIO.
THEY SHOULD VOTE FOR SENATOR
CRUZ IN STATES THAT HE CAN
BEAT MR. TRUMP TO PREVENT
MR. TRUMP FROM-W GETTING THE
NOMINATION.
SO, DO YOU BUY ROMNEY'S
BLUEPRINT AND CAN YOU SAY
TONIGHT TO YOUR FLORIDA
SUPPORTERS THAT THEY SHOULD
VOTE FOR SENATOR RUBIO TO
GET A CONTESTED CONVENTION?
>> YOU KNOW, THIS IS SO MUCH
ABOUT PROCESS.
IT FRANKLY IS BORING TO ME.
I WOULD LIKE IT CLEAR THOUGH
SINCE WE ARE TALKING ABOUT
POLLS, I BEAT HILLARY
CLINTON BY MORE THAN
ANYBODY, BY 11 POINTS.
THE REASON IT HAPPENS IN --
>> IN ONE POLL.
IN ONE POLL.
>> THE REASON IT HAPPENS
BECAUSE DEMOCRATS TELL ME
ALL THE TIME, CAN I GET THE
CROSSOVER VOTES.
YOU SEE, BECAUSE THROUGHOUT
THIS CAMPAIGN, I HAVE TALKED
ABOUT ISSUES.
I HAVE NEVER TRIED TO GO AND
GET INTO THESE KIND OF
SCRUMS THAT WE ARE SEEING
HERE ON STAGE AND PEOPLE SAY
WHEREVER I GO.
YOU SEEM TO BE THE ADULT ON
THE STAGE.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> IN TERMS OF, YOU KNOW,
MITT ROMNEY IS HE A GREAT
GUY, BUT HE DOESN'T
DETERMINE MY STRATEGY.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
BECAUSE I WORKED HARD TO FIX
THIS COUNTRY WHEN I WAS IN
WASHINGTON AS THE CHAIRMAN
OF THE BUDGET COMMITTEE
WHERE WE HAD SOME OF THE
MOST SIGNIFICANT JOB GROWTH
AFTER WE BALANCED THE
BUDGET.
WE HAD WAGES GOING UP.
IT WAS VERY SUCCESSFUL IN
OHIO.
OUR WAGES GROW FASTER THAN
THE NATIONAL AVERAGE.
WE'RE UP OVER 400,000 JOBS.
WE PAID DOWN BACK IN THE OLD
DAYS THEY PAID DOWN A HALF A
TRILLION DOLLARS OF THE
NATIONAL DEBT.
IT'S A FORMULA THAT WORKS.
AND I BELIEVE THAT FORMULA
WILL WORK WHEN I RETURN TO
WASHINGTON AS THE PRESIDENT.
AND, BY THE WAY, I WON'T
NEED ON-THE-JOB TRAINING
BECAUSE I KNOW) HOW TO DO ALL
OF THIS.
AND WITHIN THE FIRST 100
DAYS I WILL HAVE A PLAN THAT
WILL PASS THE CONGRESS.
[BELL]
>> BECAUSE IT IS REASONABLE
AND I CAN BRING BOTH SIDES
TOGETHER.
>> GOVERNOR, YOU SAY THIS IS
ALL ABOUT PROCESS, BUT FOR
VOTERS, THEY NEED TO SEE A
PATH TO GET TO THE
NOMINATION IF THEY'RE GOING
TO SUPPORT YOU.
ON SUPER TUESDAY, YOU
FINISHED IN SINGLE DIGITS IN
NINE OUT OF 11 STATES.
SO YOU CONCEDE THAT YOUR
PATH IS THROUGH A CONTESTED
CONVENTION.
>> BRET, I THINK WE ARE ALL
ALREADY THERE.
THE SIMPLE FACT IS YOU ALL
WROTE ME OFF.
YOU WROTE ME OFF BEFORE I
EVEN GOT TO NEW HAMPSHIRE.
THEN WHEN I FINISHED SECOND
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE YOU WROTE
ME OFF IN THE SOUTH.
THEN YOU WROTE ME OFF IN
SUPER TUESDAY.
I SPLIT DELEGATES IN VERMONT
WITH DONALD TRUMP.
I FINISHED SECONDg.çñ IN
MASSACHUSETTS AND WE WON
DELS IN VIRGINIA.
GUESS WHAT, IT'S NOW MARCH
MADNESS AND WE ARE HEADING
UP NORTH TO THE PLACE, TO MY
TURF, OKAY?
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> LET ME JUST TELL YOU
THIS, I WILL WIN OHIO.
I'M GOING TO MOVE ALL ACROSS
THIS COUNTRY AND OVER TIME
AS PEOPLE BEGIN TO FINALLY
HEAR MY MESSAGE -- DO YOU
KNOW WHAT PEOPLE SAY TO ME,
BRET, ALL THE TIME?
WHY DON'T THEY GIVE YOU ANY
TIME ON THE DEBATE STAGE?
WHY IS THAT?
NOW ALL OF A SUDDEN I'M
STARTING TO GET IT, WHAT I
WANT PEOPLE TO KNOW IS I
KNOW HOW TO BRING PEOPLE
TOGETHER,ó÷ REPUBLICANS AND
DEMOCRATS.
I HAVE SUCCESSFULLY, BOTH AT
THE FEDERAL.
[BELL]
FEDERAL LEVEL AND STATE
LEVEL BROUGHT ECONOMIC
GROWTH, WAGE GROWTH AND
ECONOMIC SECURITY TO THIS
COUNTRY.
AND I WANT TO GO BANG AND DO
IT -- BACK AND DO IT AGAIN
AND KEEP TALKING ABOUT MY
MESSAGE OF BRINGING PEOPLE
TOGETHER AND MOTIVATING
PEOPLE IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS
TO REALIZE THEY DON'T NEED
SOMEBODY FROM WASHINGTON
GALLOPING IN THERE ARE MANY
THINGS THEY CAN DO WHERE
THE
STRENGTH IN OUR COUNTRY IS
IN OUR NEIGHBORHOODS AND OUR
FAMILIES.
I'M GOING TO KEEP DOING
THIS.
>> WE WANT TO FOCUS NOW ON
THE ECONOMY, WHICH IS ONE OF
THE TOP ISSUES ON FACEBOOK
WITH 6.6 MILLION PEOPLE
DISGUSTING IT ONLINE.
A LOT OF THAT CONVERSATION
IS HAPPENING HERE IN DETROIT
WHERE THE UNEMPLOYMENT RATE
IS 10.9%.
THAT'S MORE THAN DOUBLE THE
NATIONAL AVERAGE.
SENATOR RUBIO, YOU HAVE
TAKEN TO CALLING MR. TRUMP A
CON ARTIST WHO PORTRAYS
HIMSELF AS A HERO TO WORKING
PEOPLE WHILE HE HAS REALLY
BEEN IN YOUR WORDS STICKING
IT TO THE AMERICAN WORKERS
FOR 40 YEARS.
BUT HE HAS BUILT A BIG
EMPLOYS
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE.
QUESTION:  HOW MANY JOBS YOU
HAVE CREATED?
>> FIRST OF ALL,
GOVERNMENT -- FIRST OF ALL,
CHRIS, MY POINT IS EXACTLY
RIGHT.
HE HAS SPENT A CAREER OF
CONVINCING AMERICANS THAT HE
IS SOMETHING THAT HE IS NOT
IN EXCHANGE FOR THEIR MONEY.
NOW HE IS TRYING TO DO THE
SAME IN EXCHANGE FOR THEIR
COUNTRY.
THIS IS A FACT OF THE.
HE TALKS ABOUT GREAT
BUSINESSES HE HAS BUILT.
HE INHERITED OVER
$100 MILLION.
WITH THAT MONEY.
>> WRONG.
>> WITH THAT MONEY HE LOST.
>> MR. TRUMP, IT'S NOT YOUR
TURN, SIR.
>> HE CAN START TONIGHT BY
ANNOUNCING THAT ALL THE
DONALD TRUMP CLOTHEING WILL
NO LONGER BE MADE IN CHINA
AND MEXICO BUT BE MADE HERE
IN THE UNITED STATES.
ON THE ISSUE OF JOB
CREATION, I FIND THIS
INTERESTING.
THE PRIVATE SECTOR CREATES
JOBS.
THE JOBS OF THOSE OF US IN
PUBLIC SERVICE ARE TO PUT IN
PLACE POLICIES THAT ALLOW
THE ECONOMY TO GROW.
THAT'S THE PROBLEM WITH THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
THEY THINK GOVERNMENT IS
WHAT CREATES JOBS.
GOVERNMENT DOES NOT CREATE
JOBS.
NOW, THE WAY YOU CREATE JOBS
IS YOU MAKE AMERICA THE
EASIEST AND THE BEST PLACE
IN THE WORLD TO START A
BUSINESS OR TO EXPAND AN
EXISTING BUSINESS.
IF YOU GOL ON MY WEBSITE
MARCO RUBIO.COM YOU WILL SEE
A REAL PLAN TO FIX OUR
TANKS.
[BELL.
[TO ROLL BACK AND TAXES.
FIX OBAMACARE.
NOT JUST LINES AROUND THE
UNITED STATES.
SERIOUS PROPOSALS.
>> MR. TRUMP I WOULD LIKE TO
YOU RESPOND.
YOU HAVE 30 SECONDS TO
RESPOND.
AS PART OF THAT COULD YOU
RESPOND TO HIS SPECIFIC
ASSERTION ABOUT TRUMP
COLLECTION SHOWS WHICH YOU
SAY SOME OF IT IS MADE IN
MEXICO.
>> THIS LITTLE GUY HAS LIED
SO MUCH.
>> HERE WE GO.
>> ABOUT MY RECORD.
HE HAS LIED SO MUCH ABOUT MY
RECORD.
[CROWD BOOING]
>> SENATOR RUBIO, WHY DON'T
YOU LET HIM FINISH.
>> I WILL TELL YOU THIS.
FIRST OF ALL, I GOT A CALL
FROM MY SISTER AND BROTHER
TONIGHT, WE SAID WE HAD NO
IDEA DAD GAVE YOU
$200 BILLION.
BELIEVE ME I STARTED OFF
WITH $1 MILLION.
I BUILT A COMPANY WORTH MORE
THAN $10 BILLION.
I SAY IT NOT IN A BRAGGING
WAY BUT THAT'S THE KIND OF
THINKING WE NEED.
VERY LOW DEBT, TREMENDOUS
CASH FLOW.
MY FINANCIALS ARE ALL --
THEY ARE ALL IN THERE WITH
THE FEDERAL ELECTIONS.
YOU HAVE SEEN THEM.
EVERYBODY HAS SEEN THEM.
I SAY IT ONLY BECAUSE THAT'S
THE KIND OFñS THINKING THIS
COUNTRY NEEDS WITH
$19 TRILLION IN DEBIT.
BELIEVE ME.
SPECIFIC LITTLE AND QUICKLY
ON THE QUESTION, WILL YOU
HOW SOON WILL YOU MOVE YOUR
CLOTHING COLLECTION, THE
CLOTHES THAT ARE MADE IN
CHINA AND MEXICO?
>> THEY DEVALUE THEIR
CURRENCIES -- I WILL DO
THAT.
AND BY THE WAY I HAVE BEEN
DOING IT MORE AND MORE.
THEY DEVALUE THEIR
CURRENCIES PARTICULARLY
CHINA.
MEXICO IS DOING A BIG NUMBER
NOW ALSO.
JAPAN IS UNBELIEVABLE WHAT
THEY'RE DOING.
THEY DEVALUE THEIR
CURRENCIES AND THEY MAKE IT
IMPOSSIBLE FOR CLOTHING
MAKERS IN THIS COUNTRY TO DO
CLOTHING IN THIS COUNTRY.
AND IF YOU LOOK AT WHAT'S
HAPPENED ON SEVENTH AVENUE
AND YOU LOOK AT WHAT'S
HAPPENED IN NEW YORK WITH
THE GARMENT INDUSTRY.
SO MUCH OF THE CLOTHING
COMES OUT FROM VIETNAM,
CHINA AND OTHER PLACES.
IT'S ALL BECAUSE OF
DEVALUATION.
BY THE WAY, THE
TRANSPACIFIC, IF YOU LOOK AT
THE TPP, A TOTAL DISASTER,
WHICH, BY THE WAY, MARCO IS
IN FAVOR OF, THEY NEED -- IT
IS A DISASTER FOR OUR
COUNTRY.
[BELL]
>> IT'S TRYING TO BE
APPROVED BY VARIOUS PEOPLE,
INCLUDING PRESIDENT OBAMA.
AND I WILL TELL YOU
SOMETHING.
THE BIGGEST PROBLEM WITH
THAT IS THEY DON'T TAKE INTO
CONCURRENCE THE DEVALUATION.
>> THANK YOU, MR. TRUMP.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> AND THEY ARE KILLING.
>> WAIT, SENATOR RUBIO.
>> THE ANSWER IS HE IS NOT
GOING TO DO IT.
AND YOU KNOW WHY?
BECAUSE THERE ARE PLENTY OF
CLOTHINGMAKERS IN AMERICA.
IF YOU GO ON MY WEBSITE
MARCO RUBIO.COM, EVERYTHING
WE HAVE ON THERE IS MADE IN
AMERICA.
THE REASON HE MAKES IT IN
CHINA OR MEXICO IS BECAUSE
HE CAN MAKE MORE MONEY ON
IT.
THAT'S WHY HE IS DOING IT
THE SECOND POINT, YOU SEE
WHAT HAPPENS AGAIN IF WHEN
YOU CHALLENGE HIM ON A
POLICY ISSUE.
YOU ASK HIM ABOUT THE
ECONOMY AND THE FIRST THING
HE DOES IS LAUNCH AN ATTACK
ABOUT SOME LITTLE GUY THING.
BECAUSE HE DOESN'T HAVE
ANSWER.
>> NO, NO.
I HAVE GOOD ANSWER.
>> AND HE WANTS TO BE THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
>> I KNOW WHAT'S HAPPENING
ON THE ECONOMY.
YOU DON'T KNOW A THING.
>> A ANSWER THE ECONOMY
QUESTION.
>> YOU HAVEN'T EMPLOYED IN
YOUR LIFE ONE PERSON.
I HAVE EMPLOYED TENS OF
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE.
YOU HAVEN'T EMPLOYED ONE
PEOPLE.
>> EVER HEARD OF TRUMP STEAK
OR TRUMP VODKA.
>> TAKE A LOOK AT TRUMP
STEAKS.
>> TRUMP STEAKS ISva GONE.
HAVE YOU RUINED THESE
COMPANIES.
>> MITT ROMNEY COMES UP WITH
THINGS TOTALLY FALSE.
NOW THE FUNNY THING IS HE
DIDN'T TALK ABOUT THE
HUNDREDS OF REALLY
SUCCESSFUL JOBS.
THE BUILDINGS ALL OVER THE
WORLD THAT HAVE MADE A FOR
DID YOU
FORTUNE.
HE DOESN'T TALK ABOUT THAT.
>> I HAVE A POLICY QUESTION
FOR YOU, SIR.
>> LET'S SEE IF HE ANSWERS
IT.
>> I WILL.
DON'T WORRY ABOUT IT, MARCO.
DON'T WORRY ABOUT IT.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> DON'T WORRY ABOUT IT
LITTLE MARCO, I WILL.
>> LET'S HEAR BIG DONALD.
>> DON'T WORRY ABOUT IT,
LITTLE MARCO.
>> GENTLEMEN.
>> YOU OUGHT.
>> GENTLEMEN, YOU HAVE GOT
TO DO BETTER THAN THIS.
>> THIS GUY HAS A NUMBERm@#V @@
ONE.
[CROWD BOOING]
>> NUMBER ONE ABSENTEE
RECORD IN THE UNITED STATES
SENATE.
HE WILL DOESN'T SHOW UP TO
VOTE.
>> PROPOSED TAX CUT CAN.
>> THAT'S WHY THE PEOPLE IN
FLORIDA DO NOT LIKE HIM.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOUR PROPOSED
TAX CUT WOULD ADD
$10 TRILLION TO THE NATION'S
DEBT OVER 10 YEARS.
EVEN IF THE ECONOMY GROWS
THE WAY THAT YOU SAY IT
WILL.
MAKE UP FOR A GOOD DEAL OF
THAT, YOU SAY, BY CUTTING
WASTE, FRAUD, AND ABUSE.
>> CORRECT.
>> LIKE WHAT, HAND PLEASE BE
SPECIFIC.
>> DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION.
WE'RE CUTTING COMMON CORE.
WE'RE GETTING RID OF COMMON
CORE.
WE'RE BRINGING EDUCATION
LOCALLY.
DEPARTMENT OF ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION.
WE ARE GOING TO GET RID ARE
OF IT IN ALMOST EVERY FORM.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE LITTLE
TIDBITS LEFT BUT WE'RE GOING
TO TAKE A TREMENDOUS AMOUNT
OUT.
WE HAVE VARIOUS OTHER
THINGS.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE IRS.
IF YOU LOOK AT EVERY SINGLE
AGENCY, WE CAN CUT IT DOWN
AND I MEAN REALLY CUT IT
DOWN AND SAVE.
THE WASTE, FRAUD, AND ABUSE
IS MASSIVE.
LARRY CUDLOW.
GREAT GUY, EVERYBODY
RESPECTS HIM.
SAYS MY PLAN FOR TAXES AND
TAX CUTTING IS THE BEST BY
FAR OF EVERYBODY.
>> BUT MR. TRUMP, MR. TRUMP,
YOUR NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP.
PLEASE PUT UP FULL SCREEN
NUMBER FOUR.
THE EDUCATION DEPARTMENT,
YOU TALK ABOUTVn÷ CUTTING.
THE TOTAL BUDGET FOR THE
EDUCATION DEPARTMENT IS
$78 BILLION.
AND THAT INCLUDES PELL
GRANTS FOR LOW INCOME
STUDENTS AND AID TO STATES
FOR SPECIALr EDUCATION.
I ASSUME YOU WOULDN'T CUT
THOSE THINGS.
THE ENTIRE BUDGET FOR THE
E.P.A., THE ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION AGENCY,
$8 BILLION.
>> OKAY.
>> THE DEFICIT THIS YEAR IS
$544 BILLION.
THAT'S MORE THAN A HALF
TRILLION DOLLARS.
YOUR NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP,
SIR.
>> LET ME EXPLAIN SOMETHING.
BECAUSE OF THE FACT THAT THE
PHARMACEUTICAL COMPANIES,
PHARMACEUTICAL COMPANIES ARE
NOT MANDATE TO DO BID
PROPERLY, THEY HAVE HUNDREDS
OF BILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN
WASTE.
WE DON'T BID PROPERLY.
WE DON'T HAVE PROPER BIDDING
PROCEDURES.
THE REASON WE DON'T IS
BECAUSE THEY TAKE CARE OF
ALL OF THE SENATORS, ALL OF
THE CONGRESSMAN, AND THEY
DON'T BID.
THEY DON'T OUT TO BID.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> EXCUSE ME.
YOU ARE TALKING ABOUT
HUNDREDS OF BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS.
>> NO YOU ARE NOT.
>> IF WE WENT OUT TO THE
PROPER BID.
>> OF COURSE YOU ARE.
>> LET'S PUT UP FULL SCREEN
NUMBER 2.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
YOU SAY THAT MEDICARE COULD
SAVE $300 BILLION A YEAR
NEGOTIATING LOWER DRUG
PRICES.
BUT MEDICARE TOTAL ONLY
SPENDS $78 BILLION A YEAR ON
DRUGS.
SIR, THAT'S THE FACTS.
YOU ARE TALKING ABOUT SAVING
MORE MONEY ON MEDICARE --
>> -- I'M SAYING SAVING
THROUGH NEGOTIATION
THROUGHOUT THE ECONOMY YOU
WILL SAVE $300 MILLION.
>> THAT DOESN'T CUT THE
FEDERAL DEFICIT.
>> OF COURSE IT IS.
WE ARE GOING TO BUY THINGS
FOR LESS MONEY.
OF COURSE IT IS.
>> THAT'S MORE MONEY THAT --
THE ONLY DRUGS WE PAY FOR
FOR IS THROUGH MEDICARE.
>> I'M NOT ONLY TALKING
ABOUT DRUGS I'M TALKING
ABOUT OTHER THINGS.
WE WILL SAVE $300 BILLION A
YEAR IF WE PROPERLY
NEGOTIATE.
WE DON'T DO THAT WE DON'T
WE DON'T NEGOTIAo[M% ANYTHING.
>> CAN I?
>> NO.
I PROMISE I WILL GET TO YOU
IN A MOMENT, SIR.
SENATOR CRUZ, ONE OF
CENTERPIECES OF YOUR
CAMPAIGN, YOU MENTIONED IT
TONIGHT, IS THAT YOU WILL
ABOLISH THE IRS.
QUESTION NOW, WHO WILL
hP &C@
ARE STILL CALLING FOR?
WHO WILL OVERSEE TO MAKE
SURE THAT PEOPLE PAY THE
TAXES THAT THEY RIGHTFULLY
OWE AND
THE VARIOUS TAX DEDUCTIONS
AND TAX CREDITS THAT YOU
STILL WANT?
>> SO MY SIMPLE FLAT TAX I
HAVE ROLLED OUT IN PRECISE
DETAIL HOW IT WILL WHERE
EVERY AMERICAN CAN FILL OUT
TAXES ON
IF YOU WANT TO ACTUALLY SEE
THE POSTCARD, SEE ALL THE
DETAILS YOU CAN FIND THEM ON
OUR WEBSITE IT'S TED
CRUZ.ORG.
WHEN HE WE GET RID OF ALL
THE CORPORATE WELFARE, ALL
THE SUBSIDIES, ALL THE
CARVEOUTS IN THE IRS CODE,
IT DRAMATICALLY SIMPLIFIES
IT.
UNDER OBAMA, THE IRS HAS
BECOME SO CORRUPT AND SO
POLITICIZED WE NEED TO
ABOLISH IT ALL TOGETHER.
NOW, AT THE END OF THAT
THERE WILL STILL BE AN
OFFICE IN THE TREASURY
DEPARTMENT TO RECEIVE THE
POSTCARDS BUT IT WILL BE
DRAMATICALLY SIMPLER.
LET ME GO BACK TO THIS
EXCHANGE THAT WAS GOING ON
INEZ?rK BETWEEN ALL OF THE
INSULTS, LET ME POINT OUT
THE SPECIFICITY THAT WAS
LACKING.
IT'S VERY EASY TO SAY LET'S
CUT WASTE, FRAUD, AND ABUSE.
I HAVE ROLLED OUT A DETAILED
PLAN TO CUT $500 BILLION IN
FEDERAL SPENDING, SPECIFYING
EXACTLY WHAT I WOULD CUT.
IT'S EASY TO SAY IT BUT ONE
OF THE GREAT DISCONNECTS TO
ALL THE PEOPLE, ALL OF THEgD
VOTERS, I UNDERSTAND THE
FOLKS WHO ARE SUPPORTING
DONALD RIGHT NOW, YOU ARE
ANGRY.
YOU ARE ANGRY AT WASHINGTON
AND HE USES ANGRY RHETORIC.
[ LAUGHTER ]
BUT FOR 40 YEARS, DONALD HAS
BEEN PART OF THE CORRUPTION
IN WASHINGTON THAT YOU ARE
ANGRY ABOUT.
AND YOU ARE NOT GOING TO
STOP THE CORRUPTION IN
WASHINGTON BY SUPPORTING
SOMEONE WHO HAS SUPPORTED
LIBERAL DEMOCRATS FOR FOUR
DECADES FROM JIMMY CARTER TO
JOHN KERRY TO HILLARY
CLINTON.
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO STOP THE
CORRUPTION.
[BELL]
>> AND CRONYISM BY
SUPPORTING SOMEONE WHO HAS
USED GOVERNMENT POWER FOR
PRIVATE GAIN.
INSTEAD, WE NEED A PRESIDENT
WHO STANDS WITH THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, I
PROMISE I WILL GET TO YOU,
YOU DO GET 30 SECONDS TO
RESPOND, MR. TRUMP.
>> ALL OF A SUDDEN ISIBLE I
HEAR FOR FOUR YEARS THAT I
HAVE BEEN INVOLVED IN
WASHINGTON.
I HAVE BEEN SUPPORTING
PEOPLE FOR MANY YEARS.
AND THESE PEOPLE HATE BEEN
POLITICIANS AND THEY HAVE
BEEN ON BOTH SIDES,
DEMOCRATS,M÷ REPUBLICANS,
LIBERALS, CONSERVATIVES.
I HAVE SUPPORTED EVERYBODY.
BECAUSE, UNTIL RECENTLY, I
WASN'T A POLITICIAN, AND I
HOPE MAYBE YOU DON'T ALL
CONSIDER ME A POLITICIAN
RIGHT NOW.
I HATE THE TERM POLITICIAN.
BUT I HAVE BEEN SUPPORTING
POLITICIANS.
A RECENT ARTICLE SOMEWHERE
SAID DONALD TRUMP IS A WORLD
CLASS BUSINESSMAN WHO GOES
OUT AND HE DOES GET ALONG
WITH EVERYBODY.
I'VE SUPPORTED DEMOCRATS,
AND I'VE SUPPORTED
REPUBLICANS.
[BELL]
>> AND AS A BUSINESSMAN I
OWE THAT TO MY COMPANY, MY
FAMILY, TO MY WORKERS, TO
EVERYBODY TO GET ALONG.
PART OF THE PROBLEM WE HAVE
IN áHINGTON, CHRIS, IT'S
TOTAL GRIDLOCK.
NOBODY GETS ALONG.
WE NEED PEOPLE TO GET ALONG.
WE NEED TO BE ABLE TO GET
THINGS DONE.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH,
DEMOCRATS, AS YOU KNOW, WILL
MAKE INCOME INEQUALITY A BIG
ISSUE IN THE GENERAL
ELECTION.
YOU SUPPORT RAISING THE
MINIMUM RAISE, ALTHOUGH YOU
SAY NOT TO THE $15 AN HOUR
THAT DEMOCRATS ARE TALKING
ABOUT.
MR. TRUMP OPPOSES ANY
INCREASE BECAUSE HE SAYS IT
WILL PRICE AMERICAN WORKERS
OUT OF THE WORLD MARKET.
IS HE WRONG ABOUT THAT?
NO INCREASE IN THE MINIMUM
WAGE?
>> WAIT A MINUTE, FIRST OF
ALL, I DIDN'T SAY I WAS FOR
AN INCREASE IN THE FEDERAL
MINIMUM WAGE.
I SAID IN WE<Ñ INIT MODESTLY
EVERY SINGLE YEAR.
>> YOU DID TALK ABOUT STATES
DOING IT.
>> IF STATES WANT TO DO IT
IT, THEY OUGHT TO SIT DOWN
WITH BUSINESS PEOPLE AND THE
LAWMAKERS AND FIGURE OUT
WHAT WILL WORK.
HOLD ON A SECOND HERE WITH
EVERYTHING ELSE.
I'M THE ONLY PERSON ON THIS
STAGE WHO ACTUALLY WAS THE
CHIEF ARCHITECT OF BALANCING
THE FEDERAL BUDGET.
IT'S NOT A THEORY FOR ME.
IT'S NOT SOME -- YOU HAVE TO
KNOW HOW TO PUT EVERYTHING
TOGETHER.
AND YOU KNOW I SPENT 10
YEARS OF MY LIFE TO GET
THERE, AND I DID NOT DO THAT
BECAUSE I'M WORSHIPING AT
SOME BALANCED BUDGET SHRINE.
THE REASON I DID IT IS WHEN
YOU HAVE COMMON SENSE
REGULATIONS, LOWER TAXES ON
INDIVIDUALS AND BUSINESSES,
AND YOU HAVE A FISCAL PLAN
THAT MAKES SENSE, THE JOB
CREATORS WILL EXPAND
EMPLOYMENT.
AND WHAT HAPPENEDWá÷
WHEN I WAS THERE, THE JOBS
WERE EXPLODING.
BILL CLINTON HAS TRIED TO
TAKE CREDIT FOR IT.
WHEN I WENT TO OHIO, WE ARE
UP 400,000 JOBS.
IT'S THE SAME FORMULA.
BUT IT ISN'T EASY.
I FOUGHT THE ENTIRE
WASHINGTON ESTABLISHMENT AND
WON BECAUSE WHEN YOU BALANCE
THE BUDGET, YOU MUST EFFECT
EVERY SINGLE THING.
EVERYTHING IN THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT SPECIFICALLY.
YOU CANNOT GET THERE WITH
THEORIES OR BROAD STATEMENTS
AND YOU HAVE TO BE WILLING
TO TAKE THE HEAT.
IN FACT, I FOUGHT A
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENT WHO I
THOUGHT WAS NOT OFFERING
CONSTRUCTIVE PROPOSALS TO
z
[BELL]
>> SO, WHEN WE TALK ABOUT
ALL OF THIS, THERE IS ONE
PERSON ON THIS STAGE AND ONE
PERSON WHO HAS BEEN A
CANDIDATE FOR PRESIDENT IN
EITHER PARTY THAT RESTORED
ECONOMIC STRENGTH, GROWTH, A
BALANCED BUDGET, PAID DOWN
DEBT, CUT TAXES, THE THINGS
THAT PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY
WANT.
NO THEORIES.
REALITY.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> ALL RIGHT, LET'S TALK
IMMIGRATION FOR A LITTLE
BIT.
SENATOR CRUZ, LET'S START
WITH YOU.
YOU HAVE REPEATEDLY TOUTED
HOW YOU HAVE STOOD SHOULD
TO SHOULDER WITH SENATOR
JEFF SESSIONS TO FIGHT
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION AND
AMNESTY.
BUT SENATOR SESSIONS JUST
ENDORSED DONALD TRUMP.
IF VOTERS WANT JEFF
SESSIONS' STYLE IMMIGRATION
POLICIES, ISN'T THEIR CHOICE
RATHER CLEAR?
>> YES, THEIR CHOICE IS VERY
CLEAR.
IF YOU LOOK TO THE ACTUAL
MENTIONED A MOMENT AGO THAT
HE WAS JUST DOING BUSINESS
WHEN HE WAS WRITING CHECKS
TO LIBERAL DEMOCRATS.
BUT THAT'S NOT, IN FACT, THE
CHECKS HE WAS WRITING.
WE CAN ALL UNDERSTAND IF YOU
WRITE A CHECK TO A CITY
COMMISSION BECAUSE YOU ARE
LOOKING FOR A ZONING WAIVER
ON BUILDING A BUILDING.
THAT MAY BE CORRUPT BUT YOU
COULD UNDERSTAND REAL ESTATE
DEVELOPERS DOING THAT THAT'S
NOT WHAT DONALD TRUMP DID.
DONALD TRUMP SUPPORTED JIMMY
CARTER OVER RONALD REAGAN.
DONALD SUPPORTED JOHN KERRY
OVER GEORGE BUSH.
IF YOU DON'T LIKE OBAMACARE,
DONALD TRUMP FUNDED HARRY
REID AND NANCY PELOSI TAKING
OVER CONGRESS TO PASS
OBAMACARE.
ON IMMIGRATION, IF YOU DON'T
LIKE AMNESTY, IF YOU DON'T
LIKE THE GANG OF 8, DONALD
TRUMP FUNDED FIVE OF THE
EIGHT MEMBERS OF THE GANG OF
EIGHT.
$50,000.
AND LET'S TALK ABOUT THIS
ELECTION.
THE CHOICE REPUBLICAN
PRIMARY VOTERS ARE MAKING IS
WHO IS BEST PREPARED TO
STAND UP TO HILLARY CLINTON
AND BEAT HILLARY CLINTON,
DONALD TRUMP HAS WRITTEN
CHECKS TO HILLARY CLINTON
NOT ONCE, NOT TWICE, NOT
THREE TIMES, 10 TIMES AND
FOUR OF THOSE CHECKS WERE
NOT TO HER SENATE CAMPAIGN,
IT WASN'T THAT SHE WAS THE
NEW YORK SENATOR AND IT WAS
THE COST.
[BELL]
OF DOING BUSINESS, IT WAS TO
HER PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN.
DONALD TRUMP IN 2008 WROTE
FOUR CHECKS TO ELECT HILLARY
CLINTON AS PRESIDENT, SO I
WOULD LIKE TO ASK DONALD WHY
DID YOU WRITE CHECKS TO
HILLARY CLINTON TO BE
PRESIDENT IN 2008?
IT WASN'T FOR BUSINESS, AND
HOW YOU CAN STAND ON A
DEBATE STAGE NOW WITH HER
AND SAY YOU DON'T THINK SHE
SHOULD BE PRESIDENT?
>> ACTUALLY, IT WAS FOR
BUSINESS.
IT WAS.
I PRIDE MYSELF INCLUDING
OUTSIDE OF THE UNITED
STATES.
I'M DOING ALMOST 120 DEALS
OUTSIDE OF THE UNITED
STATES.
WHICH I HOPE TO BE ABLE TO
STOP VERY SOON AND LET MY
CHILDREN HANDLE IT WE ARE
DOING MANY DEALS OUTSIDE OF
THE UNITED STATES.
I SUPPORT POLITICIANS.
IN 2008 I SUPPORTED HILLARY
CLINTON.
I SUPPORTED MANY OTHER
PEOPLE, BY THE WAY.
THAT WAS BECAUSE OF THE FACT
THAT I'M IN BUSINESS.
DID I SUPPORT VERY HEAVILY
RONALD REAGAN.
I ALSO SUPPORTED GEORGE
BUSH, BY THE WAY.
>> ALL RIGHT, MR. TRUMP.
>> WHAT WOULD YOU SAY ON
THIS DEBATE STAGE WHEN YOU
WROTE HER Ao CHECK IN 2008,
WROTE HER FOUR CHECK IN
2008.
>> LET ME TELL YOU
SOMETHING, TED, THE LAST
PERSON THAT HILLARY HILLARY CLIN
WANTS TO FACE IS TRUMP.
>> WITH ALL DUE RESPECT WE
HAVE QUESTIONS.
>> THAT, I CAN TELL YOU.
>> NO, NO, NO.
HOLD ON.
WE CAN DO MORE OF THIS
LATER.
MR. TRUMP, HI.
>> HELLO NICE TO BE WITH YOU
MEGYN.
>> GREATTó
>> YOU ARE LOOKING WELL.
>> AND SO ARE YOU.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> BACK IN JANUARY, YOU GAVE
AN OFF-THE-RECORD INTERVIEW
TO THE "NEW YORK TIMES."
IT WAS APPARENTLY AUDIO
TAPED.
NOW RECENT REPORT IN BUZZ
FEED CITING SOURCES AT THE
"TIMES" REPORTS IN THAT
INTERVIEW YOU
IT COMES TO IMMIGRATION
POLICY SPECIFICALLY WITH
TROPIC YOUR PROM MILLS TO
DEPORT THE 11 MILLION PEOPLE
THAT ARE NOW LIVING HERE
ILLEGALLY.
YOU MAY HAVE SUGGESTED THAT
YOU MAY HAVE EXPRESSED SOME
FLEXIBILITY WHEN IT COMES TO
THE SIZE OF THE WALL THAT
YOU WANT TO BUILD.
BUT DID YOU TELL THEM,
SPECIFICALLY, THAT YOU ARE
FLEXIBLE WHEN IT COMES TO
YOUR DEPORTATION PLAN?
>> I DON'T KNOWAr EXACTLY
WHAT -- WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT
OFF-THE-RECORD.
FIRST OF ALL, BUZZ FEED,
THEY WERE THE ONES THAT SAID
UNDER NO CIRCUMSTANCES WILL
I RUN FOR PRESIDENT.
AND WERE THEY WRONG.
A LOT OF PEOPLE SAID THAT.
THEN, DID I HAVE A MEETING
WITH THE EDITORIAL BOARD OF
THE "NEW YORK TIMES," A VERY
NICE MEETING.
MANY OF THOSE THINGS WERE
OFF THE RECORD.
I THINK AT THEIR SUGGESTION
AND MY SUGGESTION.
AND I THINK BEING OFF THE
RECORD IS A VERY IMPORTANT
THING.
I THINK IT'S A VERY, VERY
POWERFUL THING.
I WILL SAY THIS.
THESE THREE GENTLEMEN HAVE
GONE OFF THE RECORD MANY
TIMES WITH REPORTERS AND I
THINK THEY WANT TO HONOR IT
AND I WOULD ALWAYS HONOR
THAT.
I WILL SAY THOUGH, IN TERMS
OF IMMIGRATION AND ALMOST
ANYTHING ELSE, THERE ALWAYS
HAS TO BE SOME, YOU KNOW,
TUG AND PULL AND DEAL.
YOU KNOW, WHEN I WATCH TED
STAND ON THE SENATE FLOOR, I
HAD GREAT RESPECT FOR WHAT
HE DID.
HE STOOD THERE FOR A DAY AND
A HALF OR SOMETHING.
IN THE MEANTIME, WHAT CAME
OF IT?
NOTHING.
YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO HAVE
SOME F SOME
NEGOTIATION.
NOW, SOMETIMES YOU ASK FOR
MORE THAN YOU WANT AND YOU
NEGOTIATE DOWN TO THE POINT.
I MAY HAVE DISCUSSED
SOMETHING LIKE THAT WITH THE
"NEW YORK TIMES," BUT÷
WOULD NEVER RELEASE
OFF-THE-RECORD
CONVERSATIONS.
I DON'T THINK IT'S FAIR,
FRANKLY, TO DO THAT TO
ANYBODY.
>> NOW FLEXIBLE ARE YOU ON
THIS ISSUE?
>> NOT VERY FLEXIBLE.
NO, NOT VERY FLEXIBLE.
I GIVE THE EXAMPLE, I'M
GOING TO BUILD A WALL.
I'M THE ONE THAT WANTS THE
WALL.
I'M THE ONE THAT CAN BUILD
THE WALL.
IT'S GOING TO GET BUILT.
BY THE WAY, MEXICO IS GOING
TO PAY FOR THE WALL.
CAN I TELL YOU THAT MEXICO
IS GOING TO PAY FOR THE
WALL.
BUT, AND I USED AN EXAMPLE.
AND THIS ISN'T NECESSARILY
WHAT WAS SAID BUT WHATEVER
WAS SAID, THE WALL IS
50 FEET HIGH.
IS IT GOING TO BE 45 FEET?
THAT COULD VERY WELL BE.
HE WANTS IT TO BE HIGHER.
THERE IS ALWAYS GIVE AND
TAKE.
THERE IS ALWAYS NEGOTIATION.
AND THE BEST NEGATIVE YARTD
THAT KNOWS WHAT HE IS DOING
WILL MAKE A GREAT DEAL.
BUT WE NEED GIVE AND TAKE INy
GOVERNMENT.
IF YOU DON'T HAVE GIVE AND
TAKE,.
[BELL]
>> YOU ARE NEVER GOING TO
AGREE ON ANYTHING.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU NOT
ONLY SUPPORTED THE FAILED
IMMIGRATION REFORM EFFORT
THROUGH THE GANG OF EIGHT,
BUT YOU ARE STILL ON RECORD
AS FAVORING AN EVENTUAL PATH
TO CITIZENSHIP FOR THOSE WHO
ARE HERE ILLEGALLY AND IN
ADDITION YOU FAVORED INSTATE
TELEVISION FOR FLORIDA
ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS.
HAVE YOU BEEN HITTING
MR. TRUMP HARD ON THIS
FLEXIBILITY DISCUSSION WITH
THE "NEW YORK TIMES."
BUT HIS SUPPORTERS MIGHT SAY
AT LEAST HIS OPENING STANCE
WAS TOUGH.
>> FIRST OF ALL, LET ME SAY
ON THE ISSUE OF THE
OFF-THE-RECORD, THAT'S NOT
UP TO THE "NEW YORK TIMES."
THAT'S UP TO YOU, DONALD.
IF TONIGHT YOU TELL THE "NEW
YORK TIMES" TO RELEASE THE
AUDIO, THEY WILL DO IT AND
WE CAN EXACTLY SEE WHAT YOUR
TRUE VIEWS ARE ON
IMMIGRATION.
BECAUSE IT IS A MAJOR ISSUE.
IN YOUR CAMPAIGN THAT YOU
HAVE MADE A CENTER ISSUE.
NOW, AS FAR AS MY RECORD ON
IT IS CONCERNED, I
ABSOLUTELY WANT TO SOLVE
THIS ISSUE.
I DID THE BEST WE COULD IN
THE SENATE THAT WAS
CONTROLLED BY LIBERAL
DEMOCRATS AND HARRY REID IN
THE HOPES THAT THE HOUSE,
MADE UP OF CONSERVATIVES
WOULD TAKE IT UP AND MAKE IT
EVEN STRONGER.
I SAID THAT REPEATEDLY AT
THE TIME.
I'M NOT JUST SAYING THAT
NOW.
I SAID IT THROUGHOUT THAT
PROCESS.
WE DO NEED TO DO WITH THIS
ISSUE.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT IT WILL
NOT BE DEALT WITH THE WAY IT
WAS DONE IN THE SENATE.
IT WILL BE DONE FIRST AND
FOREMOST BY BRINGING ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION UNDER CONTROL
AND PROVING IT TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE AND ONLY
AFTER THAT IS DONE CAN
ANYTHING ELSE HAPPEN.
AND IT WILL BE SOMETHING THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE SUPPORT.
WE'LL SEE WHAT THEY ARE
WILLING TO SUPPORT.
IT'S NOT GOING TO BE AN
EXECUTIVE ORDER AND WE'RE
NOT GOING TO RAM IT COUNSEL
THEIR THROAT.
>> THERE TRUMP, WE WILL LET
RESPOND, WILL YOU RELEASE
THE TAPES?
WILL YOU AUTHORIZE OF THE
"NEW YORK TIMES" TO RELEASE
THE TAPES.
>> I UNDERSTAND MARCO HE IS
TALKING ABOUT A LITTLE GIVE
AND TAKE AND NEGOTIATION.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
THAT'S OKAY.
THAT'S NOT THE WORST THING
IN THE WORLD.
THERE IS NOTHING WRONG WITH
THAT I HAPPEN TO BE MUCH
STRONGER ON ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION.
SHERIFF JOE ARPAIO ENDORSES
ME.
BELIEVE ME IF HE ENDORSES ME
I AM THE STRONGEST FROM
ARIZONA.
I THOUGHT WHAT HE SAID IS
OKAY.
WE MAY DIFFER ON THE DEGREE.
WHAT HE SAID TO ME IS OKAY.
>> WILL YOU RELEASE THE
TAPES?
>> NO.
I WOULD NOT DO THAT I DON'T
THINK -- I HAVE TOO MUCH
RESPECT -- IF I DEAL WITH
YOU OFF THE RECORD.
IF I DEAL WITH BRET OR CHRIS
OFF THE RECORD, I HAVE TOO
MUCH RESPECT FOR THAT
PROCESS TO SAY JUST RELEASE
EVERYTHING.
I WOULD NOT DO THAT.
>> OKAY.
STAND BY.
WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE THIS
RIGHT AFTER THE BREAK.
WE HAVE
>> COMING UP, MORE WITH
MEGYN ON IMMIGRATION AND
QUESTIONS ON OTHER ISSUES
INCLUDING THE WAR ON TERROR.
THE FOX NEWS REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE LIVE
FROM DETROIT CONTINUES AFTER
A QUICK BREAK.
¶
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY,
TO THE FOX NEWS REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE LIVE
FROM THE FOX THEATER HERE IN
DETROIT.
LET'S GET BACK NOW TO THE
QUESTIONS.
MR. TRUMP, YOUR CAMPAIGN
WEBSITE TO THIS DAY ARGUES
THAT MORE VISAS FOR HIGHLY
SKILLED WORKERS WOULD,
QUOTE, ACCEPT AMERICAN
WORKERS, HOWEVER AT THE CNBC
DEBATE YOU SPOKE IN FAVOR OF
THESE VISAS, WHAT IS IT.
>> I'M CHANGING.
WE NEED HIGHLY SKILLED
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY.
IF WE CAN'T DO IT, WE WILL
GET THEM IN.
AND WE DO NEED IN SILICON
VALLEY WE ABSOLUTE6OÑ HAVE TO
HAVE.
SO WE DO NEED HIGHLY
SKILLED.
ONE OF THE BIGGEST PROBLEMS
WE HAVE PEOPLE WILL GO TO
THE BEST COLLEGES, THEY WILL
GO TO HARVARD, TO STANTON,
TO WHARTON, AS SOON AS THEY
ARE FINISHED THEY GET SHOVED
OUT.
THEY WANT TO STAY IN THIS
COUNTRY.
THEY WANT TO STAY HERE
DESPERATELY.
THEY ARE NOT ABLE TO STAY
HERE.
FOR THAT PURPOSE, WE
ABSOLUTELY HAVE TO BE ABLE
TO KEEP THE BRAIN POWER IN
THIS COUNTRY.
>> YOU ARE ABANDONING THE
POSITION ON YOUR WEBSITE.
>> I'M CHANGING IT AND I'M
SOFTENING THE POSITION
BECAUSE WE HAVE TO HAVE
TALENTED PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY.
>> AND YOU ARE NOT RELEASING
THE DISCUSSION WITH THE "NEW
YORK TIMES" BEHIND CLOSED
DOORS?
>> THAT'S CORRECT.
>> WHICH WILL HAVE SOME
ASKING WHETHER ON YOUR
IMMIGRATION POLICIES YOU ARE
REALLY JUST PLAYING TO
PEOPLE'S FANTASIES WHICH IS
A TACTIC YOU PRAISED IN YOUR
BOOK "THE ART OF THE DEAL."
>> I'M NOT PLAYING TO
ANYBODY'S FANTASIES.
I'M PLAYING TO THE FACT THAT
OUR COUNTRY IS IN TROUBLE.
WE HAVE A TREMENDOUS PROBLEM
WITH CRIME.
THE BORDER IS A DISASTER.
IT'S LIKE A PIECE OF SWISS
CHEESE, AND WE'RE GOING TO
STOP IT.
WE'RE GOING TO IT BE
STOPPING PEOPLE FROM COMING
INTO OUR COUNTRY ILLEGALLY.
WE'RE GOING TO STOP IT.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> SENATOR CRUZ, NOT LONG
AGO YOU PROPOSED
QUINTUPLETTING.
AFTER RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
YOUhy REVERSED YOURSELF CITING
THE PROGRAM HAD BEEN ABUSED.
THE ABUSE HAD BEEN AROUND
BEFORE YOUR 180.
IT WAS SO BAD A GROUP OF
SENATORS CALLED FOR
INVESTIGATION AND YOU
DECLINED TO JOIN THEM.
ISN'T IT A GOOD THING THAT
THE AMERICAN PUBLIC DIDN'T
TRUST TED ON THAT ONE?
>> THE ABUSE OF THE H 1 B
PROGRAM HAS BEEN RAMPANT AND
IN THE FACE OF THAT H 1 B
ABUSE I HAVE PROPOSED AND
PROMISED AS PRESIDENT THAT I
WILL IMPOSE 180 DAY
MORATORIUM ON THE H 1 B
PROGRAM TO IMPLEMENT A
COMPREHENSIVE INVESTIGATION
AND AUDIT BECAUSE YOU HAVE
GOT U.S. COMPANIES THAT ARE
FIRING AMERICAN WORKERS,
BRINGING IN FOREIGN WORKERS,
AND FORCING THEM TO TRAIN
THEIR REPLACEMENTS.
AND I WOULD NOTE THAT IS NOT
DISSIMILAR TO WHAT WE
DISCOVERED AT THE LAST
DEBATE CONCERNING THE HOTEL
THAT DONALD OWNS DOWN IN
FLORIDA.
DOWN IN FLORIDA THAT HOTEL
HAS BROUGHT IN HUNDREDS OF
FOREIGN WORKERS.
AND AFTERWARDS IT WAS REALLY
STRIKING.
I WATCHED A CNN INTERVIEW
DONALD DID WHERE HE
EXPLAINED HE SAID WELL, THE
PROBABLE IS YOU CAN'T FIND
AMERICANS WHO ARE QUALIFIED
©[!= WANT TO WORK AS
WAITERS OR WAITRESSES.
LET ME ASK THE PEOPLE HERE,
HOW MANY PEOPLE HERE HAVE
WORKED AS A WAITER OR
WAITRESS?
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
MILLIONS ACROSS THIS
COUNTRY.
THAT IS AN ASTONISHING
STATEMENT.
MARCO'S DAD STARTED AS
BARTENDER.
MY DAD STARTED WASHING
DISHES AND, YET, DO YOU KNOW
HOW MANY AMERICANS WANTED
THOSE JOBS?
[BELL.
IN.
[.
>> ROUGHLY 300 APPLIED.
DONALD HIRED 17.
THAT'S WHY THIS "NEW YORK
TIMES" TAPE IS SO TROUBLING
BECAUSE WHAT'S BEEN REPORTS
IS THAT DONALD TOLD THE
EDITORIAL BOARD OF THE "NEW
YORK TIMES" WHAT I'M SAYING
ON IMENTD CONGRATULATION I
DON'T BELIEVE.
I'M NOT GOING TO BUILD A
WALL.
I'M NOT GOING TO DEPORT
PEOPLE.
THIS IS ALL JUST RHETORIC
FOR THE VOTERS.
NOW, IF HE DIDN'T SAY THAT
HE HAS AN EASY SOLUTION,
SIMPLY RELEASE THE TAPE.
BUT FOR EVERYONE AT HOME WHO
IS MAD AT POLITICIANS WHO
LIED TO US, DONALD'S RECORD
RIGHT NOW, AS HE IS STANDING
HERE.
>> OKAY.
>> HIS RECORDS RIGHT NOW IS
ONE OF REPEATEDLY HIRING
ILLEGAL ALIENS.
>> YOUR TIME IS UP, SIR.
GO A)Xáy MR. TRUMP.
>> FIRST OF ALL A.
I HAVE HAD TENS OF THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE WORKING FOR ME.
MOST OF WHICH ALMOST 97, 98%
OF THE PEOPLE I'M PROUD OF.
YOU HAVE THIS CLUB
MAR-A-LAGO CLUB HAS A VERY
SHORT SEASON.
IT'S CALLED THE SEASON.
AND IT GOES FROM NOVEMBER
TILL MARCH.
IT'S A FEW MONTHS, FIVE
MONTHS AT THE MOST.
PEOPLE DON'T WANT A
SHORT-TERM JOB.
THEY DON'T WANT.
SO WE WILL BRING PEOPLE IN
AND WE WILL SEND THE PEOPLE
OUT.
ALL DONE LEGALLY, ALL DONE
WITH THE PROCESS APPROVED BY
GOVERNMENT, 100 PERCENT
APPROVED.
WEAVE BRING PEOPLE IN, WE
BRING THEM OUT.
WHEN WE CAN, WE HIRE PEOPLE
FROM PALM BEACH OR WEST PALM
BEACH.
WE BRING PEOPLE IN, WE BRING
THEM OUT.
WE WANT TO HIRE AS MANY
AMERICANS AS WE CAN BUT THEY
DON'T WANT PART-TIME, VERY
SHORT PART-TIME JOBS.
>> UNDERSTOOD.
THANK YOU.
>> THAT'S NOT ACCURATE.
I'M SORRY, MEGYN, THAT'S NOT
ACCURATE THERE WERE AT LEAST
300 AMERICANS APPLIED LAST
YEAR NONE OF THEM WERE7,B2x
HIRED.
>> WRONG,, WRONG.
>> THEY WERE NOT)%I9
>> WRONG.
>> THIS IS WHY HE HIRES THEM
H 2 B.
WHEN YOU BRING THEM IN
SOMEONE FROM ABROAD ON VISAS
THEY CAN'T GO WORK FOR
ANYBODY ELSE.
THEY EITHER WORK FOR YOU OR
GO BACK HOME.
YOU BASICALLY HAVE THEM
CAPTIVE.
DON'T HAVE TO WORRY ABOUT
COMPETING HIGHER WAGES WITH
ANOTHER HOTEL DOWN THE
STREET.
THAT'S WHY YOU BRING WORKERS
FROM ABROAD.
YOU ARGUE YOU ARE HERE TO
FIGHT ON BEHALF OF THE
AMERICAN WORKER, WHEN YOU
HAVE CHANCES TO HELP THE
AMERICAN WORKERS YOU ARE
MAKING YOUR CLOTHES OVERSEAS
AND HIRING YOUR WORKERS FROM
OVERSEAS.
>> GO AHEAD, SIR.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> THE OTHER HOTELS DURING
THE SEASON THEY DO THE SAME
THING.
THEY TAKE IN A LOT OF PEOPLE
BECAUSE YOU CAN'T GET THEM.
CAN'T GET A LOT OF PEOPLE.
LONG-TERM EMPLOYEES WE DON'T
DO THAT BUT SHORT-TERM
EMPLOYEES WE HAVE NO CHOICE
TO DO IT AND OTHER HOTELS IN
THAT VERY, VERY HOT AREA IT
IS A VERY HOT AREA.
IT'S VERY, VERY HARD TO GET
PEOPLE.
OTHER HOTELS DO THE EXACT
SAME THING.
JUST SO YOU UNDERSTAND, JUST
AGAIN, THIS IS A LEGAL
PROCESS.
THIS IS A PROCEDURE.
IT'S PART OF THE LAW.
[BELL]
>> I TAKE ADVANTAGE OF THAT
THERE IS NOTHING WRONG WITH
IT.
WE HAVE NO CHOICE.
>> DONALD, YOU CAN RESOLVE
THIS ISSUE VERY QUICKLY BY
SIMPLY RELEASING THE "NEW
YORK TIMES" TAPE.
BECAUSE,6o LISTEN, MAYBE IT'S
RIGHT --
>> -- THIS WASN'T ON THE
SUBJECT.
>> MISLEADING THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
>> THIS WAS NOT ON THE
SUBJECT.
>> IF YOU DIDN'T TELL THEM
THAT THE TAPES WILL PROVE
YOU ARE INNOCENT.
IF, IN FACT, YOU WENT TO
MANHATTAN AND SAID I'M LYING
TO THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, THEN
THE VOTERS HAVE A RIGHT TO
KNOW.
>> NO, NO.
YOU ARE THE LYING GUY UP
HERE.
YOU ARE THE ONE.
>> RELEASE THE TAPES.
>> YOU ARE THE ONE.
WHAT ARE YOU HIDING IN THE
TAPES?
>> EXCUSE ME, I HAVE GIVEN
MY ANSWER, LYING TED.
>> LET'S LEAVE IT AT THAT.
WE HAVE MORE TO GET TO.
>> GENTLEMEN, THE NEXT TOPIC
TO DISCUSS IS TERRORISM.
SENATOR RUBIO, ISIS IS A BIG
TOPIC OF CONVERSATION ON
FACEBOOK.
WE HAVE A MAP THAT SHOWS THE
CONSERVATION ABOUT ISIS
AROUND THE COUNTRY.
YOU PROPOSE SENDING A LARGER
NUMBER OF AMERICAN GROUND
TROOPS TO HELP DEFEAT ISIS
IN SYRIA AND IRAQ.
BUT MILITARY COMMANDERS SAY
THE BIGGEST ISIS THREAT IN
EUROPE IN PARTICULAR NOW IS
COMING FROM LIBYA, NOT
SYRIA.
SO JUST TO BE CLEAR, IF YOU
ARE FOR PUTTING>) MORE U.S.
GROUND TROOPS IN IRAQ AND
SYRIA, ARE YOU ALSO READY TO
SEND U.S. GROUND TROOPS ON
THE GROUND IN LIBYA?
>> BRIT, WHAT I HAVE ARGUED
FROM THE VERY BEGINNING IS
IN ORDER TO DEFEAT ISIS YOU
MUST DENY THEM OPERATING
SPACES.
THIS IS HOW ISIS OR ANY
GROUP CAN GROW.
IT'S HOW AL QAEDA WAS ABLE
TO CARRY OUT 9/11 AL GAVE
THEM OPERATING SPACE IN
AFGHANISTAN.
I HAVE BEEN WARNING ABOUT
THE LIBYAN PRESENCE FOR THE
BETTER PART OF TWO YEARS.
SO THEY NEED TO BE TARGETED
WHEREVER THEY HAVE AN
OPERATING SPACE.
THEY DO NEED TO BE DEFEATED
ON THE GROUND BY A GROUND
FORCE MADE UP PRIMARILY OF
SUNNI ARABS THEMSELVES.
THIS IS A RADICAL SUNNI
MOVEMENT.
THEY CAN ONLY BE DEFEATED IF
THEY'RE DRIVEN OUT AND
TERRITORY HELD BY SUNNI
ARABS IT.
IT WILL REQUIRE A SPECIFIC
SNUB OF SPECIAL AMERICAN
OPERATORS INCREASE IN AIR
STRIKES.
AND THAT WILL INCLUDE, IF
NECESSARY, OPERATING SPACES
IN LIBYA WHICH, IN FACT,
THEY ARE USING TO PROJECT
INTO THE SINAI AGAINST EGYPT
AND ULTIMATELY INTO EUROPE
AS WELL.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, COULD
YOU PUT GROUND TROOPS IN
LIBYA?
>> FIRST OF ALL, TO BE
CLEAR, NOT ONLY DID I
FOR 18 YEARS ON THE DEFENSE
COMMITTEE, MORE THAN ANYBODY
ON THIS STAGE, BUT,
SECONDLY, I WAS CALLED INTO
THE PENTAGON AFTER 9/11 TO
HELP SECRETARY RUMSFELD WITH
SOME OF HIS DIFFICULTIES.
I WILL SAY, LOOK, LET ME
TELL YOU WHAT HAPPENED WITH
LIBYAENED A I POINTED OUT IN
THE LAST DEBATE, HILLARY
CLINTON WORKED AGGRESSIVELY
TO DEPOSE MOM MUAMMAR
QADDAFI.
HE WAS WORKING WITH US, HE
WAS COOPERATING WITH US HE
DENUCLEARIZED.
THEY PUSHED HIM OUT AND NOW
WE HAVEv-A FERTILE GROUND FOR
ISIS.
FEW CITIES ON THE COAST.
MOST OF LIBYA IS DESERT.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS WE
ABSOLUTELY HAVE TO BE AND
NOT JUST WITH SPECIAL
FORCES, I MEAN, THAT'S NOT
GOING TO WORK.
COME ON, YOU HAVE GOT TO GO
BACK TO THE INVASION WHEN WE
PUSHED SADDAM HUSSEIN OUT OF
KUWAIT.
WE HAVE TO BE THERE ON THE
GROUND IN SIGNIFICANT
NUMBERS.
WE DO HAVE TO INCLUDE OUR
MUSLIM-ARAB FRIENDS TO WORK
WITH US ON THAT.
AND WE HAVE TO BE IN THE
AIR.
IT SHOULD BE A BROAD
COALITION MADE UP OF THE
KINDS OF PEOPLE THAT WERE
INVOLVED WHEN WE DEFEATED IS
SADDAM.
YOU HAVE TO BE ON THE AIR
AND ON THE GROUND IRAQ.
SOME POINT WE HAVE TO DEAL
WITH LIBYA.
I'M VERY CONCERNED WITH ISIS
GETTING THEIR HANDS ON THE
OIL FIELDS AND LIBYA BEING
ABLE TO FUND THEIR
OPERATION.
[BELL]
>> THE FACT IS COOL, CALM,
DELIBERATE, EFFECTIVE, TAKE
CARE OF THE JOB AND THEN
COME HOME.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO
WITH OUR MILITARY FOREIGN
POLICY.
[CHEERS AND APPLAUSE]
>> MR. TRUMP, JUST YESTERDAY
ALMOST 100 FOREIGN POLICY POLIC
EXPERTS SIGNED ON TO AN OPEN
LETTER REFUSING TO SUPPORT YOU,
SAYING YOU'RE EMBRACING
EXPANSIVE USE OF TORTURE AS
INEXCUSABLE.
GENERAL MICHAEL HAYDEN, NSA
DIRECTOR, OTHER EXPERTS HAVE
SAID WHEN YOU ASKED THE U.S.
MILITARY TO CARRY OUT SOME OF
YOUR CAMPAIGN PROMISES,
SPECIFICALLY TARGETING
TERRORISTS' FAMILIES AND ALSO
THE USE OF INTERROGATION METHODS
MORE EXTREME THAN WATERBOARDING,
THE MILITARY WILL REFUSE BECAUSE
THEY'VE BEEN TRAINED TO TURN
DOWN AND REFUSE ILLEGAL ORDERS.
SO WHAT WOULD YOU DO, AS
COMMANDER IN CHIEF, IF THE U.S.
MILITARY REFUSED TO CARRY OUT
THOSE ORDERS?
>> THEY WON'T REFUSE.
THEY'RE NOT GOING TO REFUSE ME.
BELIEVE ME.
THEY'RE ILLEGAL.
YOU LOOK AT THE MIDDLE EAST.
THEY'RE CHOPPING OFF HEADS.
THEY'RE CHOPPING OFF THE HEADS
OF CHRISTIANS AND ANYBODY ELSE
THAT HAPPENS TO BE IN THE WAY.
THEY'RE DROWNING PEOPLE IN STEEL
CAGES AND NOW WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT WATERBOARDING.
THIS REALLY STARTED WITH TED, A
QUESTION WAS ASKED OF TED
LAST -- TWO DEBATES AGO ABOUT
WATERBOARDING.
AND TED WAS, YOU KNOW, HAVING A
HARD TIME WITH THAT QUESTION, TO
BE TOTALLY HONEST WITH YOU.
THEY THEN CAME TO ME, WHAT DO
YOU THINK OF WATERBOARDING?
I SAID IT'S FINE.
IF WE WANT TO GO STRONGER, I'D
GO STRONGER, TOO.
FRANKLY, THAT'S THE WAY I FEEL.
CAN YOU IMAGINE THESE PEOPLE,
THESE ANIMALS OVER IN THE MIDDLE
EAST, THAT CHOP OFF HEADS
SITTING AROUND TALKING AND
SEEING THAT WE'RE HAVING A HARD
PROBLEM WITH WATERBOARDING?
WE SHOULD GO FOR WATERBOARDING
AND TOUGHER THAN WATERBOARDING.
>> TARGETING TERRORIST FAMILIES?
>> AND -- AND -- I'M A LEADER,
I'VE ALWAYS BEEN A LEADER.
I'VE NEVER HAD ANY PROBLEM
LEADING PEOPLE.
IF I SAY DO IT, THEY'RE GOING TO
DO IT.
THAT'S WHAT LEADERSHIP IS ALL
ABOUT.
>> EVEN TARGETING TERRORIST
FAMILIES?
>> WELL, LOOK, WHEN A FAMILY
FLIES INTO THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER, A MAN FLIES INTO THE
WORLD TRADE CENTER AND HIS
FAMILY GETS SENT BACK TO WHERE
THEY WERE GOING, AND I THINK  K
WENT, BY THE WAY, IT WASN'T
IRAQ, BUT THEY WENT BACK TO A
CERTAIN TERRITORY, THEY KNEW
WHAT WAS HAPPENING.
THE WIFE KNEW EXACTLY WHAT WAS
HAPPENING.
THEY LEFT TWO DAYS EARLY WITH
RESPECT TO THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER AND THEY WENT BACK TO
WHERE THEY WENT AND THEY WATCHED
THEIR HUSBAND ON TELEVISION
FLYING INTO THE WORLD TRADE
CENTER, FLYING INTO THE
PENTAGON, AND PROBABLY TRYING TO
FLY INTO THE WHITE HOUSE, EXCEPT
WE HAD SOME VERY, VERY BRAVE
SOULS ON THAT THIRD PLANE.
ALL RIGHT?
>> SENATOR CRUZ --
>> I HAVE NO PROBLEM WITH IT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> BRET, I THINK THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE UNDERSTAND THAT YELLING
AND CURSING AT PEOPLE DOESN'T
MAKE YOU A TOUGH GUY.
WE NEED A COMMANDER IN CHIEF
THAT, NUMBER ONE, WILL REBUILD
THE MILITARY JUST LIKE RONALD
REAGAN DID IN 1981 COMING OUT OF
THE WEAK JIMMY CARTER
ADMINISTRATION.
HE PASSED TAX REFORM AND
REGULATORY REFORM.
THE ECONOMY TOOK OFF.
IT GENERATED MILLIONS IN
HIGH-PAYING JOBS, TRILLIONS IN
NEW REVENUE.
HE REBUILT THE MILITARY.
BANKRUPTED THE SOVIET UNION.
AND WON THE COLD WAR.
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL DO THE
EXACT SAME THING WITH RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
WE WILL REBUILD THIS MILITARY SO
THAT IT REMAINS THE MIGHTIEST
FIGHTING FORCE ON THE FACE OF
THE PLANET.
AND THEN WHEN I AM COMMANDER IN
CHIEF, EVERY MILITANT ON THE
FACE OF THE EARTH WILL
UNDERSTAND THAT IF THEY GO AND
JOIN ISIS, IF THEY WAGE JIHAD
AGAINST THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA, THEY ARE SIGNING THEIR
DEATH WARRANT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, IN 2013, YOU
SAID YOU WERE OPEN -- YOU WERE
OPEN TO THE POSSIBILITY THAT
EDWARD SNOWDEN HAD PERFORMED A
CONSIDERABLE PUBLIC SERVICE.
YOU SAID BACK THEN.
IN REVEALING CERTAIN ASPECTS OF
THE NSA PROCEDURES.
MANY OF YOUR COLLEAGUES IN THE
SENATE INCLUDING SENATOR RUBIO
CALLED HIM A TRAITOR.
IT TOOK YOU UNTIL JANUARY OF
THIS YEAR TO CALL HIM A TRAITOR
AND SAY HE SHOULD BE TRIED FOR
TREASON.
WHY THE CHANGE OF HEART?
AND WHY DID IT TAKE YOU SO LONG?
>> WELL, BRET, AS SOMEONE WHO
SPENT MUCH OF HIS LIFE IN LAW
ENFORCEMENT, I BELIEVE YOU
SHOULD START WITH THE FACTS AND
EVIDENCE FIRST BEFORE ENDING UP
WITH THE VERDICT.
WHEN THE NEWS FIRST BROKE OF THE
UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT
ENGAGING IN MASSIVE SURVEILLANCE
ON AMERICAN CITIZENS, THAT WAS A
VERY TROUBLING DEVELOPMENT AND
IT'S WHY THE UNITED STATES
CONGRESS ACTED TO CORRECT IT.
NOW, AT THE SAME TIME, I SAID IN
THAT INITIAL STATEMENT THAT IF
THE EVIDENCE INDICATED THAT
EDWARD SNOWDEN VIOLATED THE LAW,
HE SHOULD BE PROSECUTED FOR
VIOLATING THE LAW AND, INDEED,
SINCE THEN THE EVIDENCE IS CLEAR
THAT NOT ONLY DOES SNOWDEN
VIOLATE THE LAW, BUT IT APPEARS
HE COMMITTED TREASON, TREASON IS
DEFINED UNDER THE CONSTITUTION
AS GIVING AID AND COMFORT TO THE
ENEMIES OF AMERICA AND WHAT
SNOWDEN DID MADE IT EASIER FOR
TERRORISTS TO AVOID DETECTION
AND SNOWDEN'S COMMENTS
AFTERWARDS AND HIS BEHAVIOR
AFTERWARDS, HE FLED TO RUSSIA,
FLED TO CHINA.
HIS CONDUCT AFTERWARDS INDICATES
HE WAS NOT A WHISTLEBLOWER BUT
INSTEAD HE WAS UNDERMINING THE
ABILITY TO DEFEND THIS COUNTRY.
BUT WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO
ISN'T RASH, WHO DOESN'T JUST POP
OFF AT -- WAITS TO SEE WHAT THE
FACTS ARE AND ACTS TO DEFEND
THIS COUNTRY.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU REPEATEDLY
DEFLECTED CALLS FOR SPECIFIC
NATIONAL SECURITY OR DEFENSE
POLICY PLANS WITH THE CLAIM THAT
YOU'LL ASK THE BEST PEOPLE WHEN
YOU BECOME PRESIDENT, AND TAKE
THEIR ADVICE.
SO WHO ARE THE BEST PEOPLE?
CAN YOU REVEAL TWO OR THREE
NAMES THAT YOU TRUST FOR
NATIONAL SECURITY?
>> I THINK RICHARD HAAS IS
EXCELLENT.
I HAVE A LOT OF RESPECT FOR HIM.
I THINK GENERAL KAINE IS
EXCELLENT.
I LIKE COLONEL JACOBS VERY MUCH.
I SEE HIM.
I KNOW HIM.
I HAVE MANY PEOPLE I THINK ARE
REALLY EXCELLENT BUT IN THE END
IT'S GOING TO BE MY DECISION.
WHEN YOU JUST ASKED THE QUESTION
ABOUT SNOWDEN, I WILL TELL YOU
RIGHT FROM THE BEGINNING, I SAID
HE WAS A SPY AND WE SHOULD GET
HIM BACK.
AND IF RUSSIA RESPECTED OUR
COUNTRY, THEY WOULD HAVE SENT
HIM BACK IMMEDIATELY, BUT HE WAS
A SPY.
IT DIDN'T TAKE ME A LONG TIME TO
FIGURE THAT ONE OUT.
BELIEVE ME.
BUT I WOULD GET THE BEST PEOPLE,
PEOPLE THAT I'D BE COMFORTABLE
WITH AND WE WILL DO THE RIGHT
THING.
>> BRET, IT'S VERY INTERESTING
TO NOTE, I THINK IT'S FOR THE
GOOD OF THE RECORD HERE THAT
THEY TOOK A SURVEY OF FOREIGN
POLICY MAGAZINES, 700 FOREIGN
POLICY EXPERTS, WHO WOULD BE THE
BEST PERSON TO CONDUCT FOREIGN
POLICY OF ALL THE CANDIDATES IN
THE RACE?
I RECEIVED 55% OF THE VOTE.
JEB BUSH RECEIVED 30% OF THE
VOTE.
AND EVERYBODY ELSE NONE OF THEM
MADE DOUBLE DIGITS.
AND THAT'S BECAUSE YOU HAVE TO
HAVE THE EXPERIENCE.
YOU KNOW, WE HEAR ABOUT RONALD
REAGAN REBUILDING THE MILITARY.
I WAS THERE WHEN RONALD REAGAN
REBUILT THE MILITARY.
I WORKED WITH HIM.
I WAS THERE WHEN RONALD REAGAN
REBUILT THE ECONOMY.
I WAS THERE.
I WORKED WITH HIM.
I KNEW RONALD REAGAN.
AND I'LL LEAVE IT RIGHT THERE
WITH WHAT COMES AFTER THAT.
YOU CAN FIGURE THAT ONE OUT.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, THANK YOU.
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE MORE
QUESTIONS FROM THE CANDIDATES
RIGHT AFTER THIS BREAK AND
DURING THE COMMERCIAL BREAK,
JOIN US FOR A FACEBOOK LIVE ON
THE FOX NEWS FACEBOOK PAGE AND
TELL US WHAT YOU THINK ABOUT
TONIGHT'S DEBATE IN COMMENT
SECTION.
BACK IN A MOMENT.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE HISTORIC
FOX THEATER IN DOWNTOWN DETROIT.
AND THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE.
LET'S GET RIGHT BACK TO THE
QUESTIONS.
>> MR. TRUMP, ONE OF THE THINGS
PEOPLE LOVE ABOUT YOU IS THEY
BELIEVE YOU TELL IT LIKE IT IS.
TIME AND TIME AGAIN IN THIS
CAMPAIGN, YOU'VE ACTUALLY TOLD
THE VOTERS ONE THING ONLY TO
REVERSE YOURSELF WITHIN WEEKS OR
EVEN SOMETIMES DAYS.
WE'VE TEED UP JUST THREE
EXAMPLES IN A VIDEOTAPE SIMILAR
TO THOSE WE USED WITH SENATOR
RUBIO AND SENATOR CRUZ IN THE
LAST DEBATE.
THE FIRST IS ON WHETHER THE WAR
IN AFGHANISTAN WAS A MISTAKE.
WATCH.
>> WHAT ABOUT AFGHANISTAN, DO
YOU BELIEVE THAT AMERICAN BOOTS
SHOULD STAY ON THE GROUND IN
AFGHANISTAN TO STABILIZE THE
SITUATION?
>> WE MADE A TERRIBLE MISTAKE
GETTING INVOLVED THERE IN THE
FIRST PLACE.
THAT THING WILL COLLAPSE ABOUT
TWO SECONDS AFTER THEY LEAVE.
JUST AS I SAID THAT IRAQ WAS
GOING TO COLLAPSE AFTER WE
LEAVE.
>> ABOUT AFGHANISTAN, YOU SAID
WE MADE A TERRIBLE MISTAKE
GETTING INVOLVED THERE IN THE
FIRST PLACE.
>> WE MADE A MISTAKE GOING INTO
IRAQ.
I'VE NEVER SAID WE MADE A
MISTAKE --
>> OUR QUESTION WAS ABOUT
AFGHANISTAN.
>> I NEVER SAID THAT.
OKAY.
WOULDN'T MATTER.
I NEVER SAID IT.
>> NEXT, ON WHETHER WE SHOULD
ACCEPT --
>> SHOULD I RESPOND TO THAT
FIRST?
>> TWO MORE THEN YOU'LL HAVE THE
FLOOR.
NEXT ON WHETHER WE SHOULD
ACCEPT --
>> YOU'LL BE HERE A LONG TIME.
>> ON WHETHER WE SHOULD ACCEPT
THE SYRIAN REFUGEES.
>> DO YOU OBJECT TO MIGRANTS WHO
ARE GETTING OUT OF THE MIDDLE
EAST AND NORTH AFRICA?
DO YOU OBJECT TO THEM COMING TO
THE USA?
>> I HATE THE CONCEPT OF IT BUT
ON A HUMANITARIAN BASIS WITH
WHAT'S HAPPENING, YOU HAVE TO.
IT'S LIVING IN HELL IN SYRIA, NO
QUESTION ABOUT IT, THEY'RE
LIVING IN HELL.
>> ARE YOU SAYING ABSOLUTELY
PEOPLE FROM SYRIA, THE MIDDLE
EAST, SHOULD WE ALLOW ANY OF
THEM INTO THIS COUNTRY?
>> LOOK, FROM A HUMANITARIAN
STANDPOINT, I'D LOVE TO HELP BUT
WE HAVE OUR OWN PROBLEMS.
WE HAVE SO MANY PROBLEMS THAT WE
HAVE TO SOLVE.
>> MOST RECENTLY, ON WHETHER
PRESIDENT GEORGE W. BUSH LIED TO
GET US INTO THE IRAQ WAR.
>> THEY LIED.
THEY SAID THERE WERE WEAPONS OF
MASS DESTRUCTION, THERE WERE
NONE, AND THEY KNEW THERE WERE
NONE.
I DON'T KNOW IF HE LIED OR NOT,
HE COULD HAVE LIED.
MAYBE HE DID.
MAYBE HE DIDN'T.
I GUESS YOU'D HAVE TO ASK HIM.
>> AND THERE ARE MANY OTHER
EXAMPLES.
HOW IS ANY OF THIS TELLING IT
LIKE IT IS?
>> ON AFGHANISTAN, I DID MEAN
IRAQ.
I THINK YOU HAVE TO STAY IN
AFGHANISTAN FOR A WHILE BECAUSE
OF THE FACT YOU'RE RIGHT NEXT TO
PAKISTAN WHICH HAS NUCLEAR
WEAPONS AND WE HAVE TO PROTECT
THAT.
NUCLEAR WEAPONS CHANGE THE GAME.
AND I WAS ALWAYS AGAINST GOING
INTO IRAQ.
IN FACT, BELIEVE ME, I WAS
ALWAYS AGAINST IT.
THERE WAS SOME CASES WHERE I
SORT OF -- IN ONE INTERVIEW WITH
A GREAT FRIEND OF MINE, AND
YOURS, HOWARD STERN, SAID
THAT -- SAID THAT -- I SAID VERY
MEEKLY, LONG BEFORE WE WENT IN,
I SAID VERY MEEKLY, WELL, MAYBE,
MAYBE, I DON'T KNOW.
BY THE TIME IT GOT TO THAT
POINT, I WAS ALWAYS AGAINST
IRAQ, BUT AFGHANISTAN, I FELT.
IN THAT ONE IF YOU NOTICE, I
CORRECTED IT THE SECOND DAY.
OKAY?
SECOND QUESTION?
>> THERE ARE SEVERAL EXAMPLES --
>> NO, NO.
>> -- AFGHANISTAN BEING A
MISTAKE.
WITHIN ONE DAY YOU REVERSED
YOURSELF ON SYRIAN REFUGEES.
>> LET ME EXPLAIN THAT.
YOU'RE RIGHT.
LET ME EXPLAIN.
FIRST TIME THE QUESTION HAD BEEN
PUT TO ME, IT WAS VERY EARLY ON.
THE MIGRATION HAD JUST STARTED.
AND I HAD HEARD THAT THE NUMBER
WAS A VERY, VERY SMALL NUMBER.
BY THE SECOND DAY, TWO OR THREE
DAYS LATER, I HEARD THE NUMBER
WAS GOING TO BE THOUSANDS AND
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE.
YOU KNOW, WHEN THEY ORIGINALLY
HEARD ABOUT IT, THEY WERE
TALKING ABOUT BRINGING VERY,
VERY SMALL NUMBERS IN AND I SAID
BEGRUDGINGLY, I GUESS MAYBE
THAT'S OKAY.
IT WAS NOT LIKE, LET'S BRING
THEM IN.
I THINK WE SHOULD BUILD A SAFE
ZONE.
WHAT WE SHOULD BE DOING IS
BUILDING SAFE ZONES SO THEY CAN
STAY IN THEIR OWN COUNTRY AND
NOT GO ALL OVER AND AT LEAST
THIS WAY WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE
THE PROBLEM.
THAT'S WHAT WE HAVE TO DO.
BECAUSE I FULLY UNDERSTAND WHAT
YOU'RE ASKING, WHEN I FIRST
HEARD THE QUESTION, FIRST TIME
THE QUESTION WAS ASKED TO ME,
FIRST TIME I REALLY HAD KNOWN
ABOUT THE QUESTION, THE
MIGRATION HAD JUST STARTED.
I WAS VERY MUCH, LIKE, OKAY, BY
THE TIME I WENT BACK AND STUDIED
IT AND THEY WERE TALKING ABOUT
BRINGING THOUSANDS AND
THOUSANDS, I CHANGED MY TUNE.
AND I DON'T THINK THERE'S
ANYTHING WRONG WITH THAT.
>> BUT THE POINT I'M GOING FOR
IS YOU CHANGE YOUR TUNE ON SO
MANY THINGS, AND THAT HAS SOME
PEOPLE SAYING, WHAT IS HIS CORE?
>> MEGYN, I HAVE A VERY STRONG
CORE.
I HAVE A VERY STRONG CORE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT I'VE NEVER SEEN A SUCCESSFUL
PERSON WHO WASN'T FLEXIBLE, WHO
DIDN'T HAVE A CERTAIN DEGREE OF
FLEXIBILITY.
YOU HAVE TO HAVE A CERTAIN
DEGREE OF FLEXIBILITY.
YOU CAN'T, FOR INSTANCE, LET'S
SAY ON THE SECOND QUESTION, YOU
CAN'T SAY, IT'S OKAY, AND THEN
YOU FIND OUT IT'S NOT OKAY AND
YOU DON'T WANT TO DO ANYTHING.
YOU HAVE TO BE FLEXIBLE BECAUSE
YOU LEARN.
BEFORE I KNEW THE QUESTION WAS
ASKED BY BILL, AND THE NEXT DAY,
OR A COUPLE OF DAYS LATER THE
QUESTION WAS ASKED BY, YOU
KNOW -- I WAS ASKED BY A NUMBER
OF PEOPLE, ACTUALLY.
I WAS ASKED BY SEAN, BUT I WAS
ASKED BY A NUMBER OF PEOPLE.
BUT BY THAT TIME, THE NUMBER HAD
INCREASED SIGNIFICANTLY.
>> SEAN WAS THE NEXT DAY AFTER
BILL.
>> THE NEXT DAY.
I HAD LEARNED.
NOBODY EVER ASKED ME THE
QUESTION.
THIS WAS BRAND NEW.
I REALLY MEAN IT, YOU HAVE TO
SHOW A DEGREE OF FLEXIBILITY.
IF YOU'RE GOING TO BE ONE WAY
AND IT'S WRONG, THE REST OF YOUR
LIFE YOU HAVE TO GO IN THE WRONG
DIRECTION BECAUSE YOU DON'T WANT
TO CHANGE?
>> MEGYN, I --
>> GO AHEAD, GOVERNOR.
>> I DID 200 MEETINGS IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
I DON'T KNOW HOW MANY IN
MICHIGAN NOW.
IN THESE TOWN HALLS, PEOPLE COME
IN AND THEY'RE VERY EMOTIONAL
MEETINGS.
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY REALLY WANT
TO KNOW?
IF SOMEBODY TELLS THEM
SOMETHING, CAN THEY BELIEVE IT?
AND THE REASON WHY PEOPLE ARE SO
UPSET IN THIS COUNTRY IS BECAUSE
POLITICIANS ALL THE TIME TELL
THEM WHAT THEY WANT TO HEAR AND
THEY GO TO WASHINGTON, OR THEY
GO TO THE STATE CAPITAL,
WHEREVER, AND THEY DON'T DELIVER
ON THOSE PROMISES.
YOU KNOW, WHEN I RAN FOR
GOVERNOR OF OHIO, I SAID NOT
ONLY WOULD WE BALANCE THE
BUDGET, BUT WE WOULD CUT TAXES.
PEOPLE SAID, IT CAN'T BE DONE.
I WOULDN'T HAVE SAID IT IF I
DIDN'T BELIEVE IT.
WE CUT TAXES IN OHIO MORE THAN
ANY GOVERNOR IN THE COUNTRY, $5
BILLION WORTH OF TAX CUTS.
WE'RE NOW RUNNING A SURPLUS IN
OHIO.
YOU SEE, WHAT'S GETTING IN THE
HEARTS AND SOULS OF PEOPLE IS
THEY WANT CHANGE AND THEY KEEP
PUTTING OUTSIDERS IN TO BRING
ABOUT THE CHANGE THEN THE CHANGE
DOESN'T COME, THEN THEY PUT MORE
OUTSIDERS IN BECAUSE WE'RE
PUTTING PEOPLE IN THAT DON'T
UNDERSTAND COMPROMISE, THEY
DON'T UNDERSTAND POLICY, AND
PEOPLE ARE GETTING MORE AND MORE
FRUSTRATED WITH THE SYSTEM WHICH
IS WHY WE MUST PICK SOMEBODY
THAT HAS A RECORD OF
ACHIEVEMENT.
NOT JUST TALK.
>> OKAY.
>> NOT JUST TALK.
BUT A RECORD OF ACHIEVEMENT.
THAT'S HOW WE'LL RESTORE
FLEXIBILITY.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> THERE'S A DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
FLEXIBILITY AND TELLING PEOPLE
WHATEVER YOU THINK YOU NEED TO
SAY TO GET THEM TO DO WHAT YOU
WANT THEM TO DO.
>> THAT'S RIGHT.
>> THAT'S WHAT DONALD HAS DONE
THROUGHOUT HIS CAREER.
THAT'S WHY TRUMP UNIVERSITY IS
SO RELEVANT HERE.
I SAW THIS VIDEO LAST WEEK.
HE'S SITTING IN FRONT OF A
CAMERA SAYING WE'RE GOING TO
HIRE THE BEST PEOPLE, I'M GOING
TO HAND PICK THEM AND THEY'RE
GOING TO BE HAND PICKED
INSTRUCTORS, THE BEST
INSTRUCTORS IN THE WORLD.
ONE OF THEM, BY THE WAY, A
MANAGER AT A BUFFALO WILD WINGS.
THAT'S WHO THEY HIRE TO DO THIS.
PEOPLE BORROWED MONEY AND SIGNED
UP FOR THIS FAKE UNIVERSITY.
THESE PEOPLE OWE ALL OF THIS
MONEY NOW AND GOT NOTHING IN
RETURN FOR IT.
YOU WERE WILLING TO SAY WHATEVER
YOU HAD TO SAY TO GET THEM TO
GIVE YOU THEIR MONEY.
>> WE'LL FIND OUT -- BY THE WAY,
JUST SO YOU UNDERSTAND -- THIS
IS A CASE THAT COULD HAVE
SETTLED VERY EASILY BUT I DON'T
SETTLE CASES VERY EASILY WHEN
I'M RIGHT.
98% APPROVAL RATING, AN "A" FROM
THE BETTER BUSINESS BUREAU,
98% --
>> THAT'S FALSE.
>> WE HAVE AN "A" FROM THE
BETTER BUSINESS BUREAU.
PEOPLE LIKE IT.
WE HAVE MANY, MANY PEOPLE THAT
WILL BE WITNESSES, AGAIN, I
DON'T SETTLE CASES.
I DON'T DO IT.
THAT'S WHY I DON'T GET SUED VERY
OFTEN BECAUSE I DON'T SETTLE
UNLIKE A LOT OF OTHER PEOPLE.
WE HAVE A SITUATION WHERE WE
WILL WIN IN COURT.
MANY OF THE PEOPLE THAT ARE
WITNESSES DID TREMENDOUSLY WELL
AND MADE A LOT OF MONEY BY
TAKING --
>> GO AHEAD.
>> YOU'RE GOING TO SEE.
>> IT'S A "D" MINUS.
>> NO, NO, BEFORE THEY HAD THE
INFORMATION --
>> HOLD ON.
>> MARCORUBIO.COM --
>> SENATOR RUBIO, STAND BY.
LET HIM FINISH HIS POINT.
>> IT IS RIGHT NOW AN "A."
ONCE THEY HAD THE INFORMATION,
IT GOT SWITCHED.
THE ONLY REASON IT WAS A "D" WAS
BECAUSE WE DIDN'T CARE, WE
DIDN'T GIVE THEM THE
INFORMATION.
WHEN THEY GOT THE INFORMATION,
IT BECAME AN "A."
>> WITH RESPECT -- WAIT, WITH
RESPECT WE WENT BACK AND LOOKED
AT THIS.
>> YES.
>> THE RATING FROM THE BETTER
BUSINESS BUREAU WAS A "D" MINUS,
THE LAST PUBLICLY AVAILABLE
RATING.
IN 2010.
IT WAS THE RESULT OF A NUMBER OF
COMPLAINTS.
>> IT WAS ELEVATED TO AN "A."
>> THAT'S NEVER BEEN PUBLICLY
RELEASED.
>> I CAN GIVE IT TO YOU.
I WILL GIVE IT TO YOU.
>> LET'S BRING THE VIEWERS UP TO
SPEED.
>> IT WAS ELEVATED TO AN "A."
>> LET ME SET THE RECORD THEN
YOU GUYS CAN HAVE AT IT.
TRUMP UNIVERSITY, A BUSINESS
THAT YOU STARTED, AND IT WAS
MARKETED TO MANY PEOPLE AND NOW
THERE IS A CLASS ACTION OF OVER
5,000 PLAINTIFFS AGAINST YOU,
MR. TRUMP.
>> RIGHT.
>> IT INVOLVES VETERANS, IT
INVOLVES TEACHERS AND IT
INVOLVES SO-CALLED MIDDLE GUY,
WORKING CLASS, LOWER WORKING
CLASS, MIDDLE CLASS WHO SAY THEY
WERE FLEECED, WHO SAY IT WAS A
SCAM.
THE CLASSES ARE CERTIFIED AND IN
THAT CASE, YOU COUNTERSUED THE
LEAD PLAINTIFF.
ALLEGING YOU WERE BEING DEFAMED.
THAT CASE WAS THROWN OUT --
>> THE LEAD PLAINTIFF IS NOW
GETTING OUT OF THE CASE BECAUSE
IT'S SO BAD FOR HER.
>> BUT WHAT HAPPENED WAS --
>> EXCUSE ME.
THE LEAD PLAINTIFF SIGNED A
LETTER SAYING HOW GREAT IT WAS
AND IS ON TAPE SAYING HOW GREAT
IT WAS.
>> OKAY.
STAND BY.
WHAT HAPPENED IN THAT CASE WAS
YOU COUNTERSUED HER.
THE COURT THREW OUT YOUR
COUNTERSUIT, MADE YOU PAY LEGAL
FEES OF HERS.
YOU MADE THE SAME ARGUMENT ABOUT
98% OF THE PEOPLE BEING HAPPY
WITH TRUMP UNIVERSITY AND THAT
WOMAN IN PARTICULAR SIGNING A
SURVEY SAYING SHE LIKED IT WHILE
SOMEONE WAS STANDING OVER HER
SHOULDER.
>> SHE'S TRYING TO GET OUT OF
THE CASE.
>> STAND BY.
THIS IS WHAT THE COURT OF
APPEALS FOUND.
THEY SAID THAT THE PLAINTIFFS
AGAINST YOU ARE LIKE THE MADOFF
VICTIMS.
>> GIVE ME A BREAK.
>> WHAT THE COURT OF APPEALS
SAID.
>> GIVE ME A BREAK.
>> THEY FOUND VICTIMS OF CON
ARTISTS SING THE PRAISES OF
THEIR VICTIMIZERS UNTIL THEY
REALIZE THEY HAVE BEEN FLEECED.
>> LET'S SEE WHAT HAPPENS IN
COURT.
THIS IS A CIVIL CASE.
VERY EASY TO SETTLE.
COULD SETTLE IT NOW.
VERY EASY TO HAVE SETTLED.
LET'S SEE WHAT HAPPENS AT THE
END OF A COUPLE YEARS WHEN THIS
CASE IS OVER, OKAY?
>> IT'S BEEN GOING FOR FIVE
YEARS.
>> BEEN GOING FOR A LONG TIME.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> I SPOKE TO ONE OF THE VICTIMS
YESTERDAY.
>> ONE.
>> THERE'S SEVERAL.
OBVIOUSLY THERE ARE SO MANY, I
CAN'T TALK TO THEM EVERY DAY.
I SPOKE TO ONE OF THEM.
HAY TOLD ME EXACTLY WHAT
HAPPENED.
THEY SIGNED UP FOR THIS COURSE,
THEY BELIEVE MR. TRUMP WAS THIS
FANTASTIC BUSINESSMAN, DONALD IS
GOING TO TEACH THEM THE TRICKS
OF THE TRADE.
THEY SIGNED UP.
PAID $15,000.
ASKED FOR ADDITIONAL MONEY FOR
THE COURSE.
IF THEY WANTED THE REAL SECRETS
OF SUCCESS, THEY HAD TO PAY MORE
MONEY SO THEY DID.
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY GOT IN THE
COURSES?
STUFF YOU CAN PULL OFF ZILLOW.
WHEN THEY REALIZED WHAT A SCAM
IT WAS, THEY ASKED FOR THEIR
MONEY BACK AND REFUSED TO GIVE
THEIR MONEY BACK.
>> I GAVE MANY PEOPLE THEIR
MONEY BACK.
>> WHY DIDN'T YOU GIVE THE MONEY
BACK TO EVERYBODY --
>> OKAY, SENATOR RUBIO, LET HIM
ANSWER.
LET HIM ANSWER.
GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP.
>> WE WILL SEE WHO'S RIGHT AT
THE END OF A FEW YEARS.
ALMOST ALL OF THE PEOPLE, MANY,
MANY PEOPLE SIGNED WHAT'S CALLED
THE REPORT AT THE END, DID YOU
LIKE THE COURSE, HOW DID YOU
LIKE IT?
ALMOST ALL OF THEM SAID IT WAS
TERRIFIC, OKAY?
WITH LETTERS, WITH THIS.
SOME OF THEM ARE ON TAPE SAYING
IT WAS TERRIFIC.
LET'S SEE WHAT HAPPENS AT THE
END OF THREE YEARS.
>> WITH RESPECT, MR. TRUMP, 1/3
OF THE PLAINTIFFS IN THAT CASE
DEMANDED REFUNDS.
IT'S NOT THE CASE THAT 98% --
>> I GAVE REFUNDS TO PEOPLE
BECAUSE IF THEY ASKED FOR
REFUNDS IN A CERTAIN PERIOD OF
TIME, WE GAVE REFUNDS TO PEOPLE.
>> OKAY.
>> LET'S SEE WHAT HAPPENS AT THE
END OF THREE YEARS.
>> MEGYN --
>> LET'S SEE WHO'S RIGHT.
>> STILL PENDING LITIGATION.
GO AHEAD, SENATOR.
>> IT'S CALLED PENDING
LITIGATION.
>> SENATOR RUBIO THEN SENATOR
CRUZ.
>> HE'S TRYING TO DO TO THE
AMERICAN VOTER WHAT HE DID FOR
THE PEOPLE THAT SIGNED UP FOR
THIS COURSE.
HE'S MAKING PROMISES HE HAS NO
INTENTION OF KEEPING AND IT
WON'T JUST BE $36,000 THAT THEY
LOSE, IT'S OUR COUNTRY THAT'S AT
STAKE HERE.
THE FUTURE OF THE UNITED STATES
AND THE MOST IMPORTANT ELECTION
IN A GENERATION AND HE'S TRYING
TO CON PEOPLE INTO GIVING THEM
THEIR VOTE JUST LIKE HE CONNED
THESE PEOPLE INTO GIVING HIM
THEIR MONEY.
>> LET ME TELL YOU THE REAL CON
ARTIST.
EXCUSE ME.
THE REAL CON ARTIST IS SENATOR
MARCO RUBIO WHO WAS ELECTED IN
FLORIDA AND WHO HAS THE WORST
VOTING RECORD IN THE UNITED
STATES SENATE.
HE DOESN'T GO TO VOTE.
HE'S ABSENT.
HE DOESN'T GO.
NOW, THE PEOPLE OF FLORIDA CAN'T
STAND HIM.
HE COULDN'T GET ELECTED
DOGCATCHER.
THE PEOPLE OF FLORIDA -- THE
PEOPLE OF FLORIDA, AND BY THE
WAY, I KNOW HE'S GOING TO SPEND
$25 MILLION ON ADS.
WITHOUT THAT HE WOULDN'T HAVE A
CHANCE.
HE'S 20 POINTS SOUTH.
THE PEOPLE IN FLORIDA WOULDN'T
ELECT HIM DOGCATCHER.
COULDN'T GET ANY -- HE'S RIGHT
NOW 21 POINTS DOWN TO ME.
AND, YOU KNOW --
>> OKAY.
>> AGAIN, THERE WILL BE A LOT OF
ADVERTISING.
IT'S THE ONLY THING THAT MIGHT
SAVE HIM.
I DOUBT IT.
>> I'M COMING TO YOU NEXT.
GO AHEAD.
>> HE SCAMMED THE PEOPLE OF
FLORIDA.
HE DOESN'T VOTE.
HE DOESN'T --
>> LET HIM RESPOND.
>> DOESN'T VOTE IN THE U.S.
SENATE --
>> THERE'S NO RESPONSE --
>> HE SCAMMED PEOPLE.
HE DEFRAUDED THE PEOPLE OF
FLORIDA.
>> WITH RESPECT YOU MADE THAT
POINT.
GO AHEAD.
>> THERE'S NO -- AS YOU CAN SEE
IN HIS ANSWER, IT'S ALWAYS THE
SAME THING.
>> YOU DEFRAUDED THE PEOPLE --
>> HE'S DEFRAUDING PEOPLE OUT OF
THINGS.
NOT JUST, BY THE WAY, ON THE
ISSUE OF TRUMP UNIVERSITY.
HE HAD ANOTHER DEVELOPMENT IN
MEXICO THAT HE HAD NOTHING TO DO
WITH EXCEPT HIS NAME ON THE
BUILDING.
PEOPLE PUT MONEY INTO THAT.
THEY LOST THEIR MONEY.
>> LICENSING.
>> YEAH, LICENSING.
YOU TOLD THEM YOU OWNED THE
BUILDING.
GAVE HIM THEIR MONEY.
TIME AND AGAIN --
>> STAND BY.
I'LL COME BACK TO YOU.
SENATOR CRUZ WANTS TO WEIGH IN.
GO AHEAD.
>> MEGYN, LET ME ASK THE VOTERS
AT HOME, IS THIS THE DEBATE YOU
WANT PLAYING OUT IN THE GENERAL
ELECTION?
THE STAKES IN THIS ELECTION ARE
TOO HIGH.
FOR SEVEN YEARS, MILLIONS OF
AMERICAN, WE'VE BEEN STRUGGLING,
WAGES HAVE BEEN STAGNATING,
PEOPLE ARE HURTING.
OUR CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS ARE
UNDER ASSAULT.
AND IF WE NOMINATE DONALD, WE'RE
GOING TO SPEND THE SPRING, THE
FALL, AND THE SUMMER WITH THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE FACING A
FRAUD TRIAL.
>> OH, STOP IT.
>> WITH HILLARY CLINTON SAYING
WHY DID YOU GIVE MY CAMPAIGN AND
MY FOUNDATION $100,000?
>> IT'S A MINOR --
>> WITH HILLARY CLINTON POINTING
OUT HE SUPPORTED HER FOUR TIMES
IN HER PRESIDENTIAL RACE.
>> IT'S A MINOR CIVIL CASE.
>> DONALD, LEARN NOT TO
INTERRUPT.
IT'S NOT COMPLICATED.
COUNT TO TEN, DONALD.
COUNT TO TEN.
>> GIVE ME A BREAK.
>> COUNT TO TEN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THE STAKES ARE TOO HIGH AND IF
YOU ARE ONE OF THE 65% TO 70% OF
REPUBLICANS WHO RECOGNIZE THAT
NOMINATING DONALD WOULD BE A
DISASTER, THEN I ASK YOU TO COME
JOIN US.
IF YOU'RE SUPPORTING OTHER
CANDIDATES, COME JOIN US.
WE WELCOME YOU TO OUR TEAM
BECAUSE WE'VE DEMONSTRATED NOT
ONCE, NOT TWICE, NOT THREE
TIMES, BUT FIVE SEPARATE TIMES
WE HAVE BEAT DONALD AND IF YOU
DON'T WANT HIM TO BE THE
NOMINEE, THEN I ASK YOU TO STAND
WITH US AS A BROAD COALITION OF
PEOPLE WHO BELIEVE IN THE
CONSTITUTION, BELIEVE IN
FREEDOM, AND WANT TO TURN THIS
COUNTRY AROUND.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP.
>> I DON'T BELIEVE THESE
POLITICIANS.
ALL TALK, NO ACTION.
I'M STANDING HERE LISTENING
TO -- I'M HEARING HIM SAY ABOUT
A PERCENTAGE.
CNN, HE GETS 15, THAT MEANS 85%
BASED ON WHAT YOU'RE SAYING OF
THE PEOPLE DON'T DIG YOU, NUMBER
ONE, NUMBER ONE.
IS THAT A CORRECT STATEMENT?
HOW DO YOU -- ARE YOU AT 15% IN
THE NEW CNN POLL?
DO YOU BELIEVE IN CNN?
I MEAN, I KNOW WE'RE AT FOX.
BUT CNN --
>> I'LL RESPOND.
>> CNN SPENT A LOT OF MONEY ON A
POLL, JUST CAME OUT.
I'M AT 49%.
HE'S AT 15%.
TELLS ME ABOUT 65% OF THE
PEOPLE, IT'S NOT 65% OF THE
PEOPLE.
IF YOU GO BY THAT, 85% OF THE
THEN HE GOES, WE HAVE FIVE.
EXCUSE ME, I WON TEN.
I WON TEN STATES.
IF YOU LISTEN TO HIM, IT'S LIKE,
EVERYBODY KNOWS THAT ON SUPER
TUESDAY, TRUMP WAS THE WINNER.
THERE WASN'T ONE PERSON THAT
DIDN'T SAY THAT.
EVEN THE TWO PEOPLE ON YOUR LEFT
AND RIGHT SAID WE DID A GREAT
JOB.
SO HOW DOES HE TAKE -- HOW DOES
HE TAKE FIVE AND SAY IT'S BETTER
THAN TEN?
I AM BY FAR THE LEADER.
IF YOU LISTEN TO A POLITICIAN,
HE'LL TRY TO CONVINCE YOU
OTHERWISE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, GO.
>> DONALD LIVES BY THE POLLS
EVERY DAY.
HE TWEETS --
>> NO, I DON'T.
>> HE'S TOLD US TO LOOK TO THE
CNN POLL.
THAT'S A VERY GOOD POLL TO LOOK
TO BECAUSE THAT CNN POLL SHOWED
THAT HEAD-TO-HEAD DONALD TRUMP
LOSES TO HILLARY CLINTON BY
EIGHT POINTS.
HE DOESN'T JUST LOSE CLOSE, HE
LOSES BY EIGHT POINTS.
THAT SAME POLL HE TOLD YOU TO
LOOK AT SHOWS ME BEATING HILLARY
CLINTON.
WE CANNOT MESS THIS UP --
>> BY THE WAY, THE LAST FOUR
POLLS IN A ROW, WHEN YOU
NOMINATE A CANDIDATE WHO
LITERALLY HAS BEEN ON EVERY SIDE
OF EVERY ISSUE AND IN THE COURSE
OF THIS DEBATE MAY BE ON TWO
OTHER SIDES BEFORE WE'RE DONE,
THAT'S NOT HOW YOU WIN AND THE
STAKES ARE TOO HIGH.
>> ALL RIGHT.
I'M GOING TO LET MR. -- LET ME
JUST -- I'M GOING TO LET YOU
RESPOND TO THAT, MR. TRUMP THEN
GO TO YOU, GOVERNOR.
YOU'RE UP NEXT.
>> -- ME BEATING HILLARY CLINTON
AND VERY, VERY EASILY.
>> ALL RIGHT.
DO YOU WANT TO WEIGH IN?
>> LOOK, HONESTLY, WHEN I SEE
PEOPLE AT THESE MEETINGS, THESE
TOWN HALLS, WHERE WE TAKE
MASSIVE QUESTIONS AND I GET TO
SPEND TIME WITH THEM.
LAST NIGHT THERE WAS A WOMAN
THAT CAME TO TELL ME ABOUT THE
LOSS OF HER 15-YEAR-OLD SON WHO
TOOK HIS OWN LIFE.
SEE, THERE'S PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY, TED'S RIGHT, THEIR
WAGES HAVEN'T GONE UP FOR SO
LONG, THEY SEE THE RICH GET
RICHER, THEY BELIEVE, AND
THEY'RE NOT MOVING.
THEY PUT THEIR MONEY IN THE BANK
AND THEY GOT NO INTEREST ON
THEIR MONEY.
THEY RECEIVE NONE.
AND THEIR SONS OR DAUGHTERS OR
LIVING IN THE BASEMENT BECAUSE
THEY CAN'T GET A GOOD JOB AFTER
THEIR RANG UP SO MUCH COLLEGE
DEBT.
WHAT PEOPLE ARE HUNGRY FOR IS
WHO CAN FIX THIS?
PEOPLE WANT TO KNOW WHO -- WHAT
CAN YOU DO TO SOLVE THE PROBLEMS
IN WASHINGTON?
TO MAKE SURE THAT WE HAVE
STRONGER JOB GROWTH AND BETTER
WAGES?
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT ELSE THEY'RE
YEARNING FOR?
THEY WANT TO BELIEVE THAT THEY
HAVE THE POWER TO FIX THINGS
WHERE THEY LIVE, AND THEY WANT
THE POWER BACK.
SO THEY CAN BEGIN TO DO THINGS
IN THEIR COMMUNITY.
LISTEN, THIS HAS BEEN GOING ON
FOR A LONG TIME HERE.
AND I APPRECIATE THE DISCUSSION
BACK AND FORTH.
BUT THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE
OUT THERE YEARNING FOR SOMEBODY
WHO'S GOING TO BRING AMERICA
BACK, BOTH AT THE LEADERSHIP
LEVEL AND IN THE NEIGHBORHOOD
WHERE WE CAN BEGIN TO REIGNITE
THE SPIRIT OF THE UNITED STATES
OF AMERICA.
AND LET'S STOP FIGHTING.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
GENTLEMEN, THANK YOU.
>> MUCH MORE TO COME LIVE FROM
THE FOX THEATER INCLUDING WHERE
THE CANDIDATES STAND ON THE
SOCIAL ISSUES FACING THE
COUNTRY.
THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE CONTINUES IN A MOMENT.
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY, TO
THE FOX NEWS REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
WE WANT TO GET RIGHT BACK TO THE
QUESTIONS.
>> WE ARE HERE IN DETROIT.
THE TOP ISSUES IN MICHIGAN
ACCORDING TO FACEBOOK ARE
DISPLAYED IN A WORD CLOUD.
YOU'RE TAKING A LOOK AT.
THE SECOND BIGGEST ISSUE IS
CLEAN WATER.
THAT, OF COURSE, IS DIRECTLY
TIED WITH THE SITUATION IN
FLINT.
SENATOR RUBIO, BERNIE SANDERS
AND HILLARY CLINTON HAVE BOTH
BEEN TO FLINT.
THEY ARE BOTH RUNNING ADS IN
THIS STATE FOCUSING ON THAT.
FOCUSING ON SUPPORTING FLINT AND
FIXING THE PROBLEMS.
SHOWING IMAGES OF PEOPLE IN
FLINT, THANKFUL THAT THEY'RE
THERE.
WITHOUT GETTING INTO THE
POLITICAL BLAME GAME HERE, WHERE
ARE THE NATIONAL REPUBLICANS'
PLANS ON INFRASTRUCTURE AND
SOLVING PROBLEMS LIKE THIS?
IF YOU TALK TO PEOPLE IN THIS
STATE, THEY ARE REALLY CONCERNED
ABOUT FLINT ON BOTH SIDES OF THE
AISLE.
SO WHY HAVEN'T GOP CANDIDATES
DONE MORE OR TALKED MORE ABOUT
THIS?
>> WELL, I KNOW I'VE TALKED
ABOUT IT AND OTHERS IN OUR
CAMPAIGN HAVE TALKED ABOUT IT
AND OTHER CANDIDATES HAVE TALKED
ABOUT IT AS WELL.
WHAT HAPPENED IN FLINT WAS A
TERRIBLE THING.
IT WAS SYSTEMIC BREAKDOWN AT
EVERY LEVEL OF GOVERNMENT, BOTH
THE FEDERAL AND PARTIALLY --
BOTH THE STATE AND PARTIALLY AT
THE FEDERAL LEVEL AS WELL.
AND BY THE WAY, THE POLITICIZING
OF IT I THINK IS UNFAIR BECAUSE
I DON'T THINK SOMEONE WOKE UP
ONE MORNING AND SAID LET'S
FIGURE OUT HOW TO POISON THE
WATER SYSTEM TO HURT SOMEONE.
ACCOUNTABILITY IS IMPORTANT.
I GIVE THE GOVERNOR CREDIT.
HE TOOK RESPONSIBILITY FOR WHAT
HAPPENED AND HE'S TALKED ABOUT
PEOPLE BEING HELD ACCOUNTABLE
AND THE NEED FOR CHANGE, WITH
GOVERNOR SNYDER.
THE WAY DEMOCRATS HAVE TRIED TO
TURN THIS INTO A PARTISAN ISSUE
THAT SOMEHOW REPUBLICANS WOKE UP
IN THE MORNING AND DECIDED, OH,
IT'S A GOOD IDEA TO POISON SOME
KIDS WITH LEAD.
IT'S ABSURD.
IT'S OUTRAGEOUS.
ALL OF US ARE OUTRAGE BY WHAT
HAPPENED AND WE SHOULD WORK
TOGETHER TO SOLVE IT AND THERE
IS A PROPER ROLE FOR THE
GOVERNMENT TO PLAY AT THE
FEDERAL LEVEL IN HELPING LOCAL
COMMUNITIES TO RESPOND TO A
CATASTROPHE OF THIS KIND NOT
JUST TO DEAL WITH THE PEOPLE
THAT HAVE BEEN IMPACTED BY IT
BUT TO ENSURE SOMETHING LIKE
THIS NEVER HAPPENS AGAIN.
>> THANKS, SENATOR.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, THE CITY OF
DETROIT HAS LONG SUFFERED WITH
URBAN BLITHE, BROKEN STREET
LIGHTS, DILAPIDATED AND VACANT
HOUSES AND SO ON.
IN 2013, DETROIT ACTUALLY
DECLARED BANKRUPTCY WHICH
HELPED, BUT THE SCHOOLS HERE
REMAIN A BIG PROBLEM.
THEY'RE $3.5 BILLION IN DEBT AND
ARE SOME OF THE MOST TROUBLED
AND POORLY TESTING IN THE
COUNTRY.
THE KIDS TOO OFTEN GO TO
CLASSROOMS THAT ARE UNSAFE,
FALLING APART, INFESTED WITH
RODENTS AND INSECTS.
EXPERTS SAY THE SCHOOLS COULD GO
BANKRUPT BY NEXT MONTH.
QUESTION TO YOU.
IF THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT BAILED
OUT THE AUTO INDUSTRY HERE IN
DETROIT, SHOULD IT ALSO BAIL OUT
THE DETROIT SCHOOLS?
>> WELL, LOOK, FIRST OF ALL, I
THINK THE MAYOR NOW IS
CONTROLLING THE SCHOOLS.
THIS IS NOT MUCH DIFFERENT THAN
WHAT HAPPENED IN CLEVELAND,
OHIO, WHERE THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
DEMOCRAT MAYOR, THE UNION AND
BUSINESS LEADERS CAME TO SEE ME
AND SAID WOULD YOU HELP US TO
PASS LEGISLATION TO REALLY
CREATE A CEO ENVIRONMENT SO WE
CAN TAKE CONTROL OF THE SCHOOLS?
WE EVEN INVESTED IN A BUYOUT
PLAN WHERE WE BOUGHT OUT THE
TEACHERS WHO HAD BEEN THERE A
LONG TIME BECAUSE THERE WERE SO
MANY YOUNG TEACHERS WHO HAD BEEN
LAID OFF WHO WERE SO
ENTHUSIASTIC TO GET BACK IN THE
SCHOOLS, IT WORKED BEAUTIFULLY.
CLEVELAND'S COMING BACK.
THE CLEVELAND SCHOOLS ARE COMING
BACK BECAUSE OF A MAJOR
OVERHAUL.
IT'S THE SAME THING THAT HAS TO
HAPPEN IN ALL OF OUR URBAN
SCHOOLS.
AND, FRANKLY, LOOK, IF I WERE
PRESIDENT, I'D TAKE 104 FEDERAL
PROGRAMS, BUNDLE THEM INTO 4
BUCKETS AND SEND IT TO THE
STATES BECAUSE FIXING SCHOOLS
RESTS AT THE STATE AND THE LOCAL
LEVEL AND PARTICULARLY AT THE
SCHOOL BOARD LEVEL.
NOW, I ALSO BELIEVE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
I ALSO BELIEVE THAT YOU NEED TO
INTRODUCE VOCATIONAL EDUCATION
IN THOSE SCHOOLS.
YOU NEED MENTORING IN THOSE
SCHOOLS.
AND YOU NEED TO HAVE A SITUATION
WHERE PEOPLE CAN HAVE AN
ALTERNATIVE FORUM TO GET A
DEGREE AND YOU NEED SCHOOL
CHOICE.
BOTH VOUCHERS AND CHARTER
SCHOOLS.
ALL OF THOSE THINGS CAN COME
TOGETHER TO HELP, MEGYN.
HERE'S THE BOTTOM LINE.
I'LL GO QUICKLY.
WE AS ADULTS HAVE TO FIGHT IN
OUR NEIGHBORHOODS, IN OUR
COMMUNITIES, FOR OUR CHILDREN'S
EDUCATION.
PUT THE POLITICS ASIDE AND
EVERYONE IN THIS ROOM CAN PLAY A
ROLE IN LIFTING THEIR SCHOOLS
AND LIFTING THE STUDENTS IN
THOSE SCHOOLS BECAUSE TOO MUCH
POLITICS GETS IN THE MIDDLE OF
IT AND WHERE WE FOCUS AS ADULTS,
PUT CHILDREN FIRST, WE SEE
TREMENDOUS RESULTS.
AND THE PEOPLE OF THIS TOWN ARE
GOING TO RISE AND THEY NEED TO
BE INVOLVED.
THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> FOR HALF A CENTURY, AS YOU
ALL KNOW, DETROIT WAS THE SYMBOL
OF AMERICA'S INDUSTRIAL MIGHT.
300,000 MANUFACTURING JOBS IN
THIS CITY.
AT LAST COUNT, THERE ARE NOW
FEWER THAN 30,000 MANUFACTURING
JOBS HERE AND THE UNEMPLOYMENT
RATE IN THIS CITY IS 11%.
TWICE THE NATIONAL AVERAGE.
SENATOR CRUZ, I KNOW THAT YOU
HAVE GENERAL PLANS FOR TAX
REFORM, BUT WHAT SPECIFICALLY
WOULD YOU DO TO BRING
MANUFACTURING JOBS BACK TO
AMERICA AND TRAIN RESIDENTS OF
CITIES LIKE DETROIT TO DO THOSE
JOBS?
>> WELL, CHRIS, THANK YOU FOR
THAT QUESTION.
LET ME START BY OBSERVING THAT
DETROIT IS A GREAT CITY WITH A
MAGNIFICENT LEGACY THAT HAS BEEN
UTTERLY DECIMATED BY 60 YEARS OF
FAILED LEFT-WING POLICY.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
HENRY FORD REVOLUTIONIZED
AUTOMOBILE MANUFACTURING AND
BROUGHT AUTOMOBILES TO THE
MIDDLE CLASS.
DURING WORLD WAR II, DETROIT
PROVIDED, FUNDED THE ARSENALS OF
DEMOCRACY TO HELP US WIN WORLD
WAR II.
IN THE 1960s, DETROIT WAS THE
SILICON VALLEY OF AMERICA.
IT HAD A POPULATION OF 2 MILLION
PEOPLE.
HAD THE HIGHEST PER CAPITA
INCOME IN THE COUNTRY.
AND THEN FOR 50 YEARS, LEFT-WING
DEMOCRATS HAVE PURSUED
DESTRUCTIVE TAX POLICIES, WEAK
CRIME POLICIES AND HAVE DRIVEN
THE CITIZENS OUT.
THIS CITY NOW HAS JUST 700,000
CITIZENS.
THERE ARE VACANT HOMES, ONE
AFTER THE OTHER AFTER THE OTHER.
CRIME HAS BEEN RAMPANT.
AND IT IS AN OUTRAGE.
LET ME SAY TO FOLKS IN THE
MEDIA, THAT IS A STORY THAT THE
TELLING OVER
AND OVER AGAIN, THE DESTRUCTION
OF LEFT-WING POLICY AND THE
MILLIONS WHO HAVE HURT BECAUSE
OF IT.
>> I WAS GOING TO SAY, I'LL GIVE
YOU 30 SECONDS TO TRY TO ANSWER
MY QUESTION.
WHAT SPECIFICALLY WOULD YOU DO
TO BRING MANUFACTURING JOBS BACK
TO DETROIT AND TO TRAIN THE
RESIDENTS HERE TO DO THOSE JOBS?
>> THE WAY YOU BRING
MANUFACTURING BACK TO AMERICA,
NUMBER ONE, YOU LIFT THE
REGULATIONS.
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL REPEAL
OBAMACARE, THE BIGGEST JOB
KILLER IN AMERICA.
I WILL PULL BACK THE FEDERAL
REGULATORS, THE EPA AND ALL THE
REGULATORS THAT ARE KILLING
SMALL BUSINESSES AND
MANUFACTURING.
AND MY TAX PLAN, WHICH IS A
VERY, VERY DETAILED PLAN ON THE
WEBSITE, TEDCRUZ.ORG, IS WHAT'S
CALLED BORDER ADJUSTABLE.
WE GET RID OF ALL THE TAXES.
WE GET RID OF THE CORPORATE
INCOME TAX AND THE DEATH TASK
AND THE OBAMACARE TAXES AND
PAYROLL TAX AND REPLACE IT WITH
A 16% BUSINESS FLAT TAX THAT IS
BORDER ADJUSTABLE WHICH MEANS
ALL EXPORTS ARE ENTIRELY TAX
FREE AND ALL IMPORTS PAY THE 16%
BUSINESS FLAT TAX.
THAT'S A 32% DIFFERENTIAL.
WHAT THAT WILL DO, CHRIS, IS
BRING MILLIONS OF MANUFACTURING
JOBS BACK TO THIS COUNTRY, BRING
THE STEEL INDUSTRY BACK TO THIS
COUNTRY, CREATE AN ENVIRONMENT
WHERE WE COMPETE ON A FAIR AND
LEVEL PLAYING FIELD, AMERICAN
INGENUITY CAN BEAT ANYONE, BUT
RIGHT NOW THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
ISN'T GIVING US A LEVEL PLAYING
FIELD.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
GENTLEMEN, THE NEXT SERIES OF
QUESTIONS WILL BE ON SOCIAL
ISSUES.
GOVERNOR KASICH, THE LAST
DEBATE, YOU WERE ASKED A
QUESTION ABOUT RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY, A HYPOTHETICAL
SITUATION WHERE A SAME SEX
COUPLE APPROACHES A CUPCAKE
MAKER TO DO THEIR WEDDING.
HERE'S WHAT YOU SAID.
>> BUSINESS OF SELLING THINGS,
IF YOU'RE NOT GOING TO SELL TO
SOMEBODY YOU DON'T AGREE WITH,
TODAY I'M NOT GOING TO SELL TO
SOMEBODY WHO'S GAY, TOMORROW
MAYBE I WON'T SELL TO SOMEBODY
WHO'S DIVORCED.
>> GOVERNOR, SOME FAITH LEADERS
GOT NERVOUS ABOUT THAT ANSWER.
DO GAY MARRIAGE DISSENTERS HAVE
RIGHTS?
>> WELL, LOOK, FIRST OF ALL, I
TRY TO BE A MAN OF FAITH EVERY
DAY AS BEST AS I CAN, AND I TRY
TO FOCUS IN MY FAITH ON THE DOS
AND I THINK THE DON'TS WILL TAKE
CARE OF THEMSELVES ONCE I GET
THE DOS RIGHT, HUMILITY, LOVING
MY ENEMY, CARING FOR MY
NEIGHBOR.
SECONDLY, LOOK, YOU'RE IN THE
COMMERCE BUSINESS, YOU WANT TO
SELL SOMEBODY A CUPCAKE, GREAT.
OKAY?
NOW IF THEY ASK YOU TO
PARTICIPATE IN SOMETHING YOU
REALLY DON'T LIKE, THAT'S A
WHOLE OTHER ISSUE.
OKAY?
ANOTHER ISSUE.
HERE'S WHAT I'D LIKE TO SEE
HAPPEN.
THE SUPREME COURT RULED, I DON'T
AGREE WITH THE RULING.
I'M OF FAVOR OF MARRIAGE
BETWEEN, TRADITIONAL MARRIAGE, A
MAN AND A WOMAN.
WHO I HOPE IS GOING TO HAPPEN
AFTER THE SUPREME COURT RULING
IS THINGS SETTLE DOWN.
IF YOU GO TO A PHOTOGRAPHER TO
TAKE PICTURES AT YOUR WEDDING,
SAY I'D RATHER NOT DO IT, FIND
ANOTHER PHOTOGRAPHER, DON'T SUE
THEM IN COURT.
YOU KNOW WHAT, THE PROBLEM IS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- IN OUR COUNTRY, IN OUR
COUNTRY, WE NEED TO LEARN TO
RESPECT EACH OTHER AND BE A
LITTLE BIT MORE TOLERANT FOR ONE
ANOTHER, AND AT THE END OF THE
DAY, DON'T GO TO COURT.
CAN'T WE HAVE COMMON SENSE IN
AMERICA?
THAT'S THE WAY IT USED TO BE.
AND THERE WAS A BOOK WRITTEN
CALLED "THE DEATH OF COMMON
SENSE."
WE NEED TO BRING IT BACK, BUT AT
THE END OF THE DAY, IF SOMEBODY
IS BEING PRESSURED TO
PARTICIPATE IN SOMETHING THAT IS
AGAINST THEIR DEEPLY-HELD
RELIGIOUS BELIEFS, THEN WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO THINK ABOUT
DEALING WITH THE LAW.
YOU KNOW WHAT, I'D RATHER PEOPLE
FIGURE THIS OUT WITHOUT HAVING
TO PUT ANOTHER LAW IN THE BOOKS
AND HAVE MORE ARGUMENTS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
WHY DON'T WE COME TOGETHER AS A
COUNTRY, RESPECT ONE ANOTHER,
LOVE ONE ANOTHER AND LIFT THIS
COUNTRY?
I THINK THAT'S WHAT PEOPLE WANT.
SO --
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
THANKS FOR ASKING.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, THE U.S.
SUPREME COURT OBVIOUSLY DECLARED
SAME-SEX MARRIAGE LEGAL IN ALL
50 STATES, A DECISION YOU HAVE
CRITICIZED.
GIVEN THE CURRENT STATUS OF THE
LAW, DO YOU BELIEVE A GAY COUPLE
SHOULD BE ABLE TO ADOPT?
>> WELL, LISTEN, ADOPTION IS
DECIDED AT THE STATE LEVEL AND I
AM A BELIEVER IN THE TENTH
AMENDMENT IN THE CONSTITUTION, I
WOULD LEAVE THE QUESTION OF
MARRIAGE TO THE STATES, I WOULD
LEAVE THE QUESTION OF ADOPTION
TO THE STATES.
THAT'S THE WAY IT'S BEEN FOR TWO
CENTURIES OF OUR NATION'S
HISTORY UNTIL FIVE UNELECTED
JUDGES IN AN ILLEGITIMATE AND
WRONG DECISION DECIDED TO SEIZE
THE AUTHORITY OVER MARRIAGE AND
WRONGFULLY TEAR DOWN THE
MARRIAGE LAWS OF ALL 50 STATES.
NOW, CONNECTED TO THIS IS THE
QUESTION OF RELIGIOUS LIBERTY.
AT THE LAST DEBATE, ONE OF MY
COLLEAGUES ON THIS STAGE SAID ON
THE QUESTION OF RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY AND SUPREME COURT
NOMINEES THAT HE'D BE WILLING TO
COMPROMISE AND NEGOTIATE.
I CAN TELL YOU, FOR ME, THERE
ARE AREAS THAT WE SHOULD
COMPROMISE ON.
MARGINAL TAX RATES.
WE CAN REACH A MIDDLE GROUND ON.
WHEN IT COMES TO CORE PRINCIPLES
AND CONVICTIONS, WHEN IT COMES
TO THE CONSTITUTION AND BILL OF
RIGHT, I CAN TELL THE MEN AND
WOMEN AT HOME I WILL NEVER
COMPROMISE AWAY YOUR RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND FOR ME, BRET, RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY HAS BEEN A LIFELONG
PASSION.
I'VE SPENT TWO DECADES DEFENDING
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY INCLUDING
DEFENDING THE TEN COMMANDMENTS
BEFORE THE U.S. SUPREME COURT
AND WINNING.
DEFENDING THE PLEDGE OF
ALLEGIANCE BEFORE THE SUPREME
COURT AND WINNING.
AND DEFENDING THE MOJAVE DESERT
VETERANS MEMORIAL, A LONE WHITE
LATIN CROSS THAT WAS ERECTED TO
HONOR THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO GAVE
THEIR LIVES IN WORLD WAR I.
I REPRESENTED 3 MILLION VETERANS
DEFENDING THAT MEMORIAL AND WON
5-4.
>> THANK YOU.
SENATOR CRUZ DEFINITELY AVOIDED
SAYING YOUR NAME, MR. TRUMP, BUT
I THINK HE WAS REFERRING TO YOU
AND YOUR RELIGIOUS LIBERTY
ANSWER.
WOULD YOU LIKE TO RESPOND?
>> I HAVE NOTHING TO SAY.
I MEAN, GENERALLY SPEAKING I
AGREE WITH WHAT HE SAID.
I WOULD HAVE CERTAINLY HAVE
RATHER LEFT IT TO THE STATES.
I WAS ALWAYS IN -- I WAS VERY
SURPRISED WHEN THEY CAME UP WITH
THAT DECISION.
I WOULD HAVE CERTAINLY -- I
WOULD HAVE PREFERRED HAD IT BEEN
LEFT TO THE STATES AND I THINK
MOST PEOPLE WOULD HAVE PREFERRED
THAT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THE LATE
SUPREME COURT JUSTICE ANTONIN
SCALIA, A CONSERVATIVE ICON
OBVIOUSLY, POINTED OUT IN THE
UNITED STATES VERSUS HELL RERKS
THAT LIKE MOST RIGHTS THE SECOND
AMENDMENT RIGHT IS NOT
UNLIMITED.
FIRST AMENDMENT DOESN'T ALLOW
YOU TO GO INTO A THEATER AND
YELL FIRE.
DO YOU AGREE WITH JUSTICE
SCALIA, WHAT LIMITS WOULD YOU'D
DRAW AROUND THE SECOND
AMENDMENT?
>> AS FEW AS POSSIBLE.
THE SECOND AMENDMENT AS I SAID
BEFORE IS NOT A SUGGESTION.
IT'S THE CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT OF
EVERY AMERICAN TO PROTECT
THEMSELVES AND THEIR FAMILIES.
IT IS A RIGHT THAT -- IT IS THE
SECOND AMENDMENT FOR A REASON.
IT IS RIGHT AFTER THE DEFENSE OF
THE FREEDOM OF SPEECH FOR A
REASON.
CLEARLY THE FOUNDERS OF OUR
NATION UNDERSTOOD AND THE
FRAMERS OF THE CONSTITUTION
UNDERSTOOD THAT YOU CANNOT HAVE
LIFE AND YOU CANNOT HAVE LIBERTY
AND CANNOT PURSUE HAPPINESS IF
YOU ARE NOT SAFE.
AND THE SECOND AMENDMENT WHEN
PEOPLE TALK ABOUT GUN LAWS, WHAT
THEY NEED TO REALIZE IS
CRIMINALS DON'T FOLLOW GUN LAWS.
THEY'RE CRIMINALS.
BY DEFINITION, THEY IGNORE THE
LAW.
BUT THE GUN RIGHTS OF AMERICANS,
IF YOU ARE TALKING TO A
LAW-ABIDING CITIZEN AND A GUN
OWNER LIKE MYSELF, IF YOU PASS A
LAW, I WILL KNOLL WHATEVER THE
LAW IS.
A CRIMINAL WILL NOT DO IT.
THEY WILL CONTINUE TO PURSUE
THESE GUNS ON THE BLACK MARKET
WHERE THEY THEN GO OUT AND
COMMIT CRIMES AND STEAL GUNS
FROM EACH OTHER.
GUN LAWS ARE NOT EFFECTIVE.
THEY SIMPLY DO NOT PROVIDE FOR
SAFETY BUT THEY DO, HOWEVER,
ENSURE THAT LAW-ABIDING PEOPLE
DON'T HAVE ACCESS TO WEAPONS TO
PROTECT THEMSELVES AND GUNS TO
PROTECT THEMSELVES, BUT
CRIMINALS ALWAYS WILL BE WELL
ARMED.
THEY DON'T CARE ABOUT THE LAW.
THEY DON'T FOLLOW THE LAW.
WE WILL PROTECT THE SECOND
AMENDMENT WHEN I'M PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU WERE ONCE A
SUPPORTER OF A WEAPONS BAN, SO
DO YOU THINK THERE SHOULD BE ANY
RESTRICTIONS ON THE SECOND
AMENDMENT?
>> NO, I'M A BIG DEFENDER OF THE
SECOND AMENDMENT.
IF YOU LOOK AT WHAT'S HAPPENED,
WHETHER IT'S IN CALIFORNIA WHERE
YOU HAD THE 14 PEOPLE KILLED,
WHETHER IT'S IN PARIS, WHICH BY
THE WAY HAS THE TOUGHEST GUN
LAWS IN THE WORLD AND 130 PEOPLE
KILLED.
MANY, MANY PEOPLE IN THE
HOSPITAL.
GRAVELY INJURED.
THEY WILL BE DYING.
MANY PEOPLE WILL BE DYING IN
ADDITION.
IF WE HAD GUNS OR IF THEY HAD
GUNS ON THE OTHER SIDE OF THE
ROOM WITH THE BULLETS GOING IN
THE OPPOSITE DIRECTION, YOU
WOULD NOT HAVE HAD 130 PEOPLE
KILLED.
THAT I CAN TELL YOU RIGHT NOW.
SO I'M A VERY, VERY BIG
SUPPORTER OF THE SECOND
AMENDMENT.
>> BUT IN 2000, YOU WROTE IN
YOUR BOOK, I GENERALLY OPPOSE
GUN CONTROL BUT I SUPPORT THE
BAN ON ASSAULT WEAPONS.
>> I DON'T SUPPORT IT ANYMORE.
I DO NOT SUPPORT THE BAN ON
ASSAULT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
ANY LIMITS TO THE SECOND
AMENDMENT?
>> WELL, LISTEN.
UNLIKE DONALD, I WOULD NOT
SUPPORT BANNING FIREARMS.
IN THAT INSTANCE, BILL CLINTON
BANNED MANY OF THE MOST POPULAR
FIREARMS IN AMERICA.
BY THE WAY, THE STUDY SHOWED
THAT BAN DID NOTHING TO REDUCE
VIOLENT CRIME BUT TOOK AWAY THE
SECOND AMENDMENT RIGHTS OF
LAW-ABIDING CITIZENS.
LET ME POINT OUT, IT IS EASY FOR
POLITICAL CANDIDATES TO HAVE
RHETORIC AND SAY I SUPPORT THE
SECOND AMENDMENT.
YOU CANNOT SAY THAT AND AT THE
SAME TIME SAY WHAT DONALD JUST
SAID WHICH IS THAT ON THE
QUESTION OF SUPREME COURT
NOMINEES HE WANTS TO COMPROMISE
AND REACH A MIDDLE GROUND WITH
HARRY REID AND CHUCK SCHUMER.
THAT'S WHAT HE SAID IN THE LAST
DEBATE.
>> I DID NOT SAY THAT.
>> HARRY REID AND CHUCK SCHUMER
SIGN OFF ON --
>> I DID NOT SAY THAT.
>> HARRY REID AND CHUCK SCHUMER
ARE BOTH DEMOCRATS MR. TRUMP HAS
WRITTEN CHECKS TO REPEATEDLY.
ANY JUSTICE THAT THOSE TWO SIGN
OFF ON IS GOING TO BE A LEFT
WING JUDICIAL ACTIVIST WHO WILL
UNDERMINE RELIGIOUS LIBERTY AND
WE'RE ONE VOTE AWAY FROM THE
HELLER DECISION BEING OVERTURNED
WHICH WOULD EFFECTIVELY ERASE
THE SECOND OF AMENDMENT FROM THE
BILL OF RIGHTS.
IF YOU CARE ABOUT THE SECOND
AMENDMENT, YOU NEED TO ASK WHO
ON THIS STAGE DO YOU KNOW WILL
APPOINT PRINCIPLED
CONSTITUTIONALISTS TO THE COURT
AND NOT CUT A DEAL WITH YOUR
SECOND AMENDMENT RIGHTS?
>> MR. TRUMP, SO WE'RE LISTENING
TO THE ALL TALK, NO ACTION
POLITICIAN AND HE WAS THE
PRIMARY SUPPORTER OF JOHN
ROBERTS WHO GAVE US --
>> FLAT-OUT WRONG.
>> NO, IT'S NOT.
YOU TAKE A LOOK.
HE WAS THE PRIMARY SUPPORTER.
HE PUSHED JOHN ROBERTS AND
PUSHED HIM AND PUSHED HIM AND
BUSH ULTIMATELY APPOINTED HIM.
HE GOT APPOINTED.
AND WHEN IT CAME HIS TIME TO
RAISE HIS HAND AND KILL
OBAMACARE, NOT ONCE, BUT TWICE,
HE LET US DOWN AND HE DID THE
WRONG THING.
THIS IS THE MAN THAT WAS THE
PRIMARY SUPPORTER AND YOU CAN
READ LAW JOURNAL, READ WHATEVER
YOU WANT TO READ, I'VE READ
PLENTY OF IT.
THERE WAS NO STRONGER SUPPORTER
OF JOHN ROBERTS THAN HIM.
AND IT WAS A VERY, VERY BIG
MISTAKE.
>> QUICKLY, SENATOR CRUZ.
>> YOU KNOW, DONALD HAS A
TENUOUS RELATIONSHIP WITH THE
TRUTH.
I WROTE ONE OP-PED SUPPORTING
PRESIDENT BUSH'S NOMINATION
AFTER HE MADE IT.
I WOULD NOT HAVE MADE THAT
NOMINATION.
LET ME POINT OUT --
>> THAT IS NOT WHAT YOU SAID --
>> DONALD, PLEASE, I KNOW IT'S
HARD NOT TO INTERRUPT.
TRY.
>> IT'S NOT WHAT YOU SAID IN THE
OP-PED.
>> BREATHE, BREATHE, BREATHE.
>> I AM, TED.
>> YOU CAN DO IT.
YOU CAN BREATHE.
I KNOW IT'S HARD.
BUT JUST --
>> WHEN THEY'RE DONE WITH THE
YOGA, CAN I ANSWER A QUESTION?
>> YOU CANNOT --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I REALLY HOPE WE DON'T SEE
YOGA ON THIS STAGE.
>> HE'S VERY FLEXIBLE, SO YOU
NEVER KNOW.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> BUT YOU CANNOT, IN FACT, CARE
ABOUT CONSERVATIVE SUPREME COURT
JUSTICES AND SUPPORT JIMMY
CARTER FOR PRESIDENT.
YOU CANNOT CARE ABOUT
CONSERVATIVE SUPREME COURT
JUSTICES AND SUPPORT JOHN KERRY
FOR PRESIDENT AS DONALD DID.
YOU CANNOT CARE ABOUT
CONSERVATIVE SUPREME COURT
JUSTICES AND SUPPORT HARRY REID
FOR SENATE MAJORITY LEADER AND
YOU CANNOT CARE ABOUT
CONSERVATIVE SUPREME COURT
JUSTICES AND WRITE FOUR CHECKS
TO HILLARY CLINTON FOR HER TO BE
PRESIDENT IF YOU CARE AT ALL
ABOUT THE SECOND AMENDMENT OR
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY OR ANYTHING
ELSE.
>> GENTLEMEN, WE'RE GOING TO
MOVE ON.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT MORE
POLICY QUESTIONS COMING UP.
>> AND COMING UP, THE CANDIDATES
TACKLE FOREIGN POLICY.
FIRST, DURING THE COMMERCIAL
BREAK, JOIN US FOR FACEBOOK LIVE
ON THE FOX NEWS FACEBOOK PAGE
AND TELL US WHAT YOU THINK ABOUT
TONIGHT'S DEBATE IN THE COMMENT
SECTION.
STAY WITH US.
MORE TO COME.
>>> WELCOME BACK, EVERYBODY.
WE'RE GOING IT GET RIGHT BACK TO
THE QUESTIONS.
>> AND GENTLEMEN, WE'RE GOING TO
FOCUS FOR A BIT ON FOREIGN
POLICY.
SENATOR RUBIO, YOU LIKE TO TAKE
A SHOT AT MR. TRUMP ON THE
CAMPAIGN TRAIL SAYING
NEGOTIATING A HOTEL DEAL IN A
FOREIGN COUNTRY IS NOT FOREIGN
POLICY.
THE OTHER DAY YOU EVEN COMPARED
HIM TO KIM JONG-UN THE NORTH
KOREAN LEADER AS LUNATICS TRYING
TO GET AHOLD OF NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
PLEASE TELL MR. TRUMP WHY HE'S
UNPREPARED TO BE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF.
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL I THINK AS
WE'VE SEEN THROUGHOUT THIS
CAMPAIGN, DONALD HAS NOT SHOWN
SERIOUSNESS ABOUT THE ISSUES OF
FOREIGN POLICIES.
HE SIMPLY HASN'T.
WHETHER IT WAS THE STRUCTURE OF
OUR MILITARY, TODAY HE WAS ASKED
THE QUESTION ABOUT THE ISSUE OF
COMMANDERS NOT FOLLOWING HIS
LEAD ON KILLING THE FAMILY OF
TERRORISTS.
AND HIS ANSWER BASICALLY WAS IF
I TELL THEM TO DO IT, THEY'RE
GOING TO DO IT.
THAT'S JUST NOT TRUE.
FOREIGN POLICY IS NOT ONLY
CONSEQUENTIAL, I THINK MUCH OF
OUR FUTURE NOW DEPENDS ON IT.
YOU KNOW, I SEE A LOT OF YOUNG
PEOPLE AT MY EVENTS AROUND THE
COUNTRY.
I FEEL GREAT WHEN THEY COME.
I ALWAYS THEM THEM THAT DESPITE
THE HARDSHIPS OF THE MOMENT, I
HONESTLY BELIEVE THAT TODAY'S
MILLENNIALS HAVE A CHANCE TO BE
THE GREATEST GENERATION WE'VE
HAD IN 100 YEARS.
I REALLY DO.
BECAUSE THE WORLD TODAY HAS
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
THAT CAN AFFORD TO BE THEIR
CLIENTS, THEIR CUSTOMERS, THEIR
PARTNERS, PEOPLE THEY
COLLABORATE WITH.
THAT WON'T HAPPEN IF THE WORLD
IS DANGEROUS AND IT'S UNSTABLE.
THAT WILL REQUIRE STRONG
AMERICAN LEADERSHIP.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES IS GOING TO HAVE EIGHT
YEARS OF A MESS OF A FOREIGN
POLICY TO CLEAN UP.
THAT'S WHY IT CAN'T BE HILLARY
CLINTON AND QUITE FRANKLY WHY IT
CAN'T BE SOMEONE WHO SIMPLY HAS
NOT SHOWN THE INTELLECTUAL
CURIOSITY OR INTEREST IN
LEARNING ABOUT THESE VERY
COMPLICATED ISSUES AND DONALD
SIMPLY HASN'T.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOUR RESPONSE.
>> WELL, LET ME JUST SAY THIS.
I'VE GOTTEN TO KNOW MARCO OVER A
PERIOD OF TIME, BELIEVE ME, HE
IS NOT A LEADER.
BELIEVE ME.
>> THAT DOESN'T ANSWER THE
QUESTION.
>> HE DIDN'T INTERRUPT YOU.
>> HE'S NOT A LEADER.
AND FRANKLY, WHEN I SAY THEY'LL
DO AS I TELL THEM, THEY'LL DO AS
I TELL THEM.
AND THAT'S VERY -- IT'S VERY
SIMPLE.
IT'S VERY SIMPLE.
WE ARE IN A VERY DANGEROUS
PLACE.
WE HAVE A DEPLETED MILITARY.
TOTALLY DEPLETED.
WE HAVE, BY THE WAY, OUR VETS
ARE TREATED HORRIBLY.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE CARE OF OUR
VETS.
WE'RE GOING TO START TAKING CARE
OF OUR VETS PROPERLY LIKE WE
SHOULD.
WE'RE GOING TO BUILD UP OUR
MILITARY AND GET THE EQUIPMENT
WE WANT, NOT THE EQUIPMENT
THAT'S SOLD TO US BY SOMEBODY
THAT GAVE HIM AND HIM AND NOT
THE GOVERNOR CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS.
OKAY?
WE'RE GOING TO GET THE EQUIPMENT
THAT THE GENERALS AND THE
SOLDIERS WANT.
I WILL PROVE TO BE A GREAT
LEADER.
AND, YOU KNOW, IT'S VERY
INTERESTING, WE TALK ABOUT THE
POLLS, EVERY SINGLE POLL WHEN IT
COMES TO ISIS AND THE MILITARY
AND THE BORDER SAY BY FAR TRUMP
IS THE BEST.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOUR TIME IS UP.
>> YEAH, I JUST WANT TO, A
COUPLE POINTS.
ONCE AGAIN, HE WAS PRESSED ON A
POLICY ISSUE TO SHOW HIS
UNDERSTANDING OF THE FOREIGN
POLICY AND HIS REACTION WAS TO
ATTACK SOMEBODY ELSE WITH A
NAME.
HERE'S THE BOTTOM LINE.
I'M GOING TO REPEAT IT AGAIN.
THE WORLD TODAY IS AS
COMPLICATED AND COMPLEX AS IT'S
BEEN CERTAINLY IN THE LIFETIME
OF ANYBODY HERE TODAY.
YOU INDEED DO HAVE A LUNATIC IN
NORTH KOREA WITH NUCLEAR
WEAPONS, INDEED HAVE THE CHINESE
GOVERNMENT TAKING OVER THE MOST
IMPORTANT SHIPPING LANE IN THE
WORLD AND VLADIMIR PUTIN WHO YOU
EXPRESSED ADMIRATION FOR.
>> WRONG, WRONG, WRONG.
YOU SAID IT.
HE SAID VERY GOOD THINGS ABOUT
ME AND I --
>> I'M GOING TO FINISH MY
STATEMENT HERE.
AND HE'S ALSO SHOWING
INSTABILITY IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
YOU HAVE IRAN IS GOING TO GET
$100 BILLION OF SANCTIONS
RELIEF.
YOU HAVE RADICAL JIHADISTS
SPREADING ALL OVER THE WORLD.
THIS IS A TIME FOR SERIOUSNESS
ON THESE ISSUES.
YOU HAVE YET TO ANSWER A SINGLE
SERIOUS QUESTION ABOUT ANY OF
THIS.
WILL YOU GIVE US A DETAILED
ANSWER ABOUT FOREIGN POLICY ANY
TIME YOU'RE ASKED ON IT?
>> LET ME JUST TELL YOU, FIRST
OF ALL, I'VE BEEN HEARING THIS
MAN SO LONG TALKING ABOUT PUTIN.
PUTIN SAID ABOUT ME, I DIDN'T
SAY ABOUT PUTIN, PUTIN SAID VERY
NICE THINGS ABOUT ME.
AND I SAY VERY NICELY, WOULDN'T
IT BE NICE IF ACTUALLY WE COULD
GET ALONG WITH RUSSIA?
WE COULD GET ALONG WITH FOREIGN
COUNTRIES?
INSTEAD OF SPENDING TRILLIONS
AND TRILLIONS OF DOLLARS.
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT FLINT,
MICHIGAN.
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT PLACES, WE
NEED TO REBUILD THE
INFRASTRUCTURE OF OUR COUNTRY.
WOULDN'T IT BE NICE IF WE GOT
ALONG WITH THE WORLD AND MAYBE
RUSSIA COULD HELP US IN OUR
QUEST TO GET RID OF ISIS, ET
CETERA, ET CETERA?
>> GENTLEMEN, YOU BOTH HAD A
CHANCE TO TALK A COUPLE OF
TIMES.
I'D LIKE TO MOVE ON TO SENATOR
CRUZ.
SENATOR, WE HAVE SOME BREAKING
NEWS TONIGHT.
NORTH KOREA'S DICTATOR, KIM
JONG-UN HAS ORDERED THAT
COUNTRY'S NUCLEAR WEAPONS TO BE
MADE READY AT A MOMENT'S NOTICE.
>> YES.
>> THIS COMES JUST HOURS AFTER
THE U.N. SECURITY COUNCIL
ANNOUNCED, APPROVED THE TOUGHEST
SANCTIONS IN TWO DECADES AGAINST
THAT COUNTRY.
ASSUME YOU'RE PRESIDENT CRUZ
TONIGHT.
WHAT DO YOU DO?
>> WELL, YOU'RE RIGHT.
THE NEWS IS VERY DISTURBING.
KIM JONG-UN PUT THEIR NUCLEAR
WEAPONS ON READY STATE.
I'M GLAD WE'RE SENDING ANOTHER
CARRIER GROUP TO THE SOUTH CHINA
SEA.
I'M GLAD CONGRESS PASSED
SANCTIONS ON NORTH KOREA.
THIS IS ALL THE RESULT OF THE
FAILURES OF THE CLINTON
ADMINISTRATION TWO DECADES AGO
THAT NEGOTIATED A DEAL WITH
NORTH KOREA LIFTING THE
SANCTIONS, ALLOWING BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS TO FLOW IN AND THEY USED
THAT MONEY TO DEVELOP NUCLEAR
WEAPONS IN THE FIRST PLACE.
NOW WE'RE IN A MUCH HARDER
POSITION.
WHEN YOU HAVE A LUNATIC WITH
NUCLEAR WEAPONS, TO SOME EXTENT
IT CONSTRAINS YOUR OPTIONS.
WE NEED TO BE MOVING THE CARRIER
GROUP TO THE SOUTH CHINA SEAS,
WE NEED TO BE PUTTING IN PLACE
MISSILE DEFENSE SUCH AS THE
MISSILE DEFENSE SYSTEM IN SOUTH
KOREA.
WE NEED TO BE PURSUING
SPACE-BASED MISSILE DEFENSE.
ONE OF THE ADVANTAGES OF
SPACE-BASED MISSILE DEFENSE IS
IF YOU HAVE A MISSILE LAUNCH IN
NORTH KOREA, YOU HAVE A MISSILE
LAUNCH IN IRAN, A SPACE-BASED
MISSILE DEFENSE CAN TAKE OUT
ONE, TWO, OR THREE MISSILES
BEFORE IT CAN CROSS OVER AND DO
DAMAGE AND WE ALSO NEED TO BE
PUTTING PRESSURE ON CHINA
BECAUSE NORTH KOREA IS
EFFECTIVELY A CLIENT STATE OF
CHINA.
ALL OF THAT WILL HAPPEN WITH A
STRONG COMMANDER IN CHIEF
DEVOTED TO KEEPING THIS COUNTRY
SAFE.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
GOVERNOR KASICH, I WANT TO MOVE
BACK TO THE DEBATE WE HEARD
EARLIER ABOUT VLADIMIR PUTIN.
IN DECEMBER AFTER VLADIMIR PUTIN
HAD NICE THING TO SAY ABOUT
DONALD TRUMP CALLING HIM BRIGHT
AND TALENTED, YOUR CAMPAIGN RAN
A VIDEO SUGGESTING THAT TRUMP
MIGHT NAME THE RUSSIAN PRESIDENT
AS HIS RUNNING MATE.
HERE'S A CLIP.
>> I'LL HAVE TO SEE THIS.
>> IF ELECTED, TRUMP PROMISED
THE DICTATORIAL DUO WOULD,
QUOTE, MAKE
>> THAT WAS YOUR CAMPAIGN VIDEO,
SIR.
>> THAT WAS A PRETTY GOOD ONE.
>> SIR, IF I MAY ASK MY
QUESTION, I THINK YOU WERE
KIDDING BUT IT WAS YOUR VIDEO
AND THE SUGGESTION IS DO YOU
THINK DONALD TRUMP IS NAIVE
ABOUT THE THREAT THAT VLADIMIR
PUTIN REPRESENTS?
>> I'M NOT BITING.
LET ME TAKE YOU AROUND THE
WORLD, OKAY?
LET ME -- LOOK.
I'M GOING TO TAKE YOU VERY
QUICKLY.
IN RUSSIA, WE NEED TO TELL THEM
WE'RE GOING TO ARM THE
UKRAINIANS WITH WEAPONS AND IF
YOU ATTACK FINLAND AND SWEDEN,
CONSIDER IT AN ATTACK ON US.
AND HE'LL UNDERSTAND THAT.
I'LL TELL THE CHINESE YOU DON'T
OWN THE SOUTH CHINA SEA.
STOP HACKING US AND WE'RE GOING
TO BEEF UP OUR CYBER COMMAND AND
WE'RE GOING TO BE ABLE TO TAKE
OUT YOUR SYSTEMS IF YOU CONTINUE
TO DO THIS.
EGYPTIANS NOW THEY'RE ON THEIR
LAST LEGS BECAUSE OF THE ATTACKS
ON ISIS.
AND THE IF THEY HAVE SIMILAR
AIMS WE NEED TO BRING THEM
CLOSER TO US.
TURKEY A CRITICAL AVENUE TO THE
MIDDLE EAST.
WE HAVE TO BRING THEM TOWARDS
THE WEST, NOT THE EAST.
AND WE HAVE A JOINT, GOOD HUMAN
INTELLIGENCE, THAT IS CALLED A
SEMI TRIP AROUND THE WORLD.
IF YOU GAVE ME MORE TIME, I'D
FINISH THE TRIP.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
>> COMING UP, A FINAL QUESTION
AND CLOSING STATEMENTS.
AND TAKE A LOOK AT THIS.
THE VOLUME OF CONVERSATION ON
FACEBOOK SURROUNDING THE
CANDIDATES OVER THE LAST MONTH.
WHETHER GOOD OR BAD, DONALD
TRUMP CLEARLY DOMINATES THE
FIELD.
WE'LL BE BACK WITH MORE OF
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
LET'S GET BACK AT IT.
GENTLEMEN, THIS IS OUR LAST
QUESTION OF THE NIGHT.
IT HAS BEEN A LONG TIME SINCE
OUR LAST DEBATE, SEVEN MONTHS
HAVE TRANSPIRED AND AN RNC
PLEDGE THAT ALL OF YOU SIGNED
AGREEING TO SUPPORT THE PARTY'S
NOMINEE AND NOT LAUNCH AN
INDEPENDENT RUN.
TONIGHT,  CAN YOU SAY YOU CAN
SUPPORT THE NOMINEE, EVEN IF IT
IS DONALD TRUMP.
>> I WILL SUPPORT THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE.
BECAUSE THE DEMOCRATS HAVE TWO
PEOPLE LEFT IN THE RACE.
ONE OF THEM IS A SOCIALIST.
AMERICA DOESN'T WANT TO BE A
SOCIALIST COUNTRY.
IF YOU WANT TO BE, THEN MOVE TO
A SOCIALIST COUNTRY.
THE OTHER ONE IS UNDER FBI
INVESTIGATION.
AND NOT ONLY UNDER FBI
INVESTIGATION, SHE LIED TO THE
FAMILIES OF THE VICTIMS OF
BENGHAZI AND ANYONE WHO LIES TO
FAMILY VICTIMS WILL NEVER BE THE
COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> YES.
BECAUSE I GAVE MY WORD THAT I
WOULD.
AND I DO WHAT I SAID I WOULD DO.
TUESDAY WE SAW AN OVERWHELMING
VICTORY IN THE STATE OF TEXAS.
I WON TEXAS BY 17%.
I WILL SAY IT WAS A POWERFUL
AFFIRMATION THAT THE PEOPLE WHO
KNOW ME BEST AND THAT I
CAMPAIGNED TO MADE PROMISES IF
YOU ELECT ME, I'LL LEAD THE
FIGHT AGAINST AMNESTY AND WILL
FIGHT FOR THE BILL OF RIGHTS
EVERY DAY.
THAT THE PEOPLE OF TEXAS SAID
YOU HAVE KEPT YOUR WORD.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, YES OR NO,
WOULD YOU SUPPORT DONALD TRUMP
AS REPUBLICAN NOMINEE?
>> YES.
AND I THINK BEFORE IT'S SAID AND
DONE, I'LL BE THE NOMINEE.
LET ME ALSO.
BUT I'M THE LITTLE ENGINE THAT
CAN.
WE'RE TRAVELING AND WORKING AND
SPENDING TIME AWAY FROM FAMILY.
WHEN IN THE ARENA YOU ENTER A
SPECIAL CIRCLE.
YOU WANT TO RESPECT THE PEOPLE
YOU'RE IN THE ARENA WITH.
IF HE ENDS UP THE NOMINEE,
SOMETIMES, IT MAKES IT A LITTLE
BIT HARD, BUT I WILL SUPPORT
WHOEVER IS THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE FOR PRESIDENT.
>> MR. TRUMP, I'M GOING TO ASK
YOU A VERSION OF THE SAME
QUESTION, TODAY, YOU RAISED A
POSSIBILITY YOU MIGHT RUN AS AN
INDEPENDENT IF YOU FEEL YOU'RE
TREATED UNFAIRLY BY THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY.
SO I'M GOING TO PHRASE THE
QUESTION THE OTHER THREE PEOPLE
ON THIS STAGE JUST GOT.
DID YOU DEFINITELY SAY THAT YOU
WILL SUPPORT THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE FOR PRESIDENT, EVEN IF
IT'S NOT YOU.
>> EVEN IF IT'S NOT ME?
LET ME JUST START OFF BY SAYING
THAT I'M VERY, VERY PROUD OF
MILLIONS AND MILLIONS PEOPLE
THAT HAVE COME TO THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY OVER THE LAST LITTLE
WHILE.
THEY HAVE COME TO THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY AND BY THE WAY, THE
DEMOCRATS ARE LOSING PEOPLE.
THIS IS A TREND TAKING PLACE,
IT'S THE BIGGEST THING HAPPENING
IN POLITICS AND I'M VERY PROUD
TO BE PART OF THEM.
I'M GOING TO GIVE THEM CREDIT,
TOO.
THOUGH THEY DON'T DESERVE IT,
BUT THE ANSWER IS, YES, I WILL.
>> YES, YOU WILL SUPPORT THE
NOMINEE OF THE PARTY?
>> YES.
I WILL.
>> CANDIDATES, IT'S NOW TIME FOR
YOUR CLOSING STATEMENTS.
GOVERNOR KASICH, WE'LL START
WITH YOU.
>> PROBABLY, LADIES AND
GENTLEMEN, I LOVE BEING HERE IN
MICHIGAN AND I WANT TO SAY TO
ALL OF YOU HERE THAT I HAVE A
RECORD OF BEING ABLE TO SOLVE
SOME OF THE BIGGEST PROBLEMS,
NOT JUST TALK AND NOT THEORY.
I DID IT IN WASHINGTON BY
HELPING PEOPLE GET INTO A
HEALTHIER ECONOMIC SITUATION AND
I'VE DONE IT IN OHIO.
WE'VE MADE PROGRESS IN OHIO WE
DID NOT LEAVE ANYONE BEHIND AND
WE HAVE RAISED OUR MINORITY
COMMUNITIES.
AND AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES I WILL GO BACK TO
WASHINGTON AND TAKE FORMULAS I
HAVE USED AND I WILL FIX THE
PROBLEMS IN WASHINGTON AND
YOU'LL WORK WITH ME AS I SEND
YOU POWER TO FIX YOUR
COMMUNITIES, YOUR NEIGHBORHOODS,
YOUR STATE AND TOGETHER, WE'LL
RESTORE THE SPIRIT OF AMERICA.
I KNOW YOU WANT THAT.
THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, 30 SECONDS,
CLOSING STATEMENT.
>> I KNOW THIS HAS BEEN AN
UNUSUAL ELECTION CYCLE AS IT
CONTINUES AND THERE ARE A LOT OF
PROBLEMS IN AMERICA AND PEOPLE
ARE HURTING.
BUT THIS IS NOT JUST CONFRONTING
OUR PROBLEMS BUT ALSO EMBRACING
OUR OPPORTUNITIES, I BELIEVE THE
21 CENTURY HOLDS THE POTENTIAL
TO BE THE GREATEST ERA IN THE
HISTORY OF THE UNITED STATES IF
WE ACT NOW.
IF WE DO, IF DO WHAT NEEDS TO BE
DONE, WE CAN LEAVE OUR CHILDREN
THE FREEST AND MOST PROSPEROUS
AMERICAN THAT'S EVER LIVED IN
THE AMAZING STORY OF AMERICA.
I ASK EVERYONE TO VOTE FOR ME
AND JOIN OUR EFFORT AT
MARCORUBIO.COM.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> I WANT TO TALK TO EVERY
SOLDIER, SAILOR, AIRMEN AND
MARINE, EVERY MOM, DAD, SISTER,
BROTHER, AND SON AND DAUGHTER OF
SOMEONE FIGHTING FOR THE
COUNTRY.
FOR SEVEN YEARS, YOU HAD A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF THAT SENDS
YOU INTO COMBAT WITH RULES OF
ENGAGEMENT THAT TIE YOUR HANDS
BEHIND YOUR BACK, IT IS WRONG,
AND IMMORAL AND IN JANUARY, 2017
IT WILL END.
I WANT TO TALK TO POLICE
OFFICERS AND FIREFIGHTERS AND
FIRST RESPONDER WHO'S HAVE BEEN
LEFT BEHIND WITH THIS PRESIDENT.
STARTING IN JANUARY, 2017, I
WILL HAVE YOUR BACK.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOUR CLOSING
STATEMENT.
>> THANK YOU.
I AM GOING TO BRING JOBS BACK TO
THE UNITED STATES.
LIKE NOBODY ELSE CAN.
WE'RE GOING TO FIX OUR VERY
DEPLETED MILITARY, WE'RE GOING
TO TAKE CARE OF OUR VETS.
WE'RE GOING TO STRENGTHEN OUR
BORDERS AND YOU'RE GOING TO BE
VERY, VERY PROUD OF THIS COUNTRY
IN JUST A FEW YEARS IF I AM
ELECTED PRESIDENT, THANK YOU.
>> AND THAT WILL DO IT FOR THE
11TH REPUBLICAN PRIMARY DEBATE
OF THE 2016 PRESIDENTIAL RACE
BUT THE NIGHT IS NOT OVER YET.
>> NOT BY A LONG SHOT.
A SPECIAL EDITION OF "THE
O'REILLY FACTOR" IS NEXT.
AND FOX NEWS HAS THE ELECTION
COVERED.
>> AND THANK YOU TO DETROIT AND
THE CROWD HERE, THANK YOU,
AGAIN, FOR JOINING US.
HAVE A GREAT EVENING.