>> THE ECONOMY THAT IS WEAK --
>> THE ENTIRE POLITICAL SYSTEM
IS TO BLAME.
>> THROW THEM OUT OF OFFICE.
>> HOW STUPID ARE THEY?
>> COLORADO, THE INSPIRATION FOR
AMERICA THE BEAUTIFUL IS NOW A
BATTLEGROUND STATE IN THE RACE
FOR THE WHITE HOUSE.
WE'RE IN THE MIDDLE OF A
CONTENTIOUS CAMPAIGN UNLIKE ANY
WE'VE SEEN BEFORE.
FRUSTRATED VOTERS, LIVING IN A
NATION MANY BELIEVE IS IN NEED
OF ECONOMIC REPAIR.
WHO WILL BEST TACKLE THE
TOUGHEST ISSUES FACING OUR
COUNTRY'S FINANCIAL FUTURE?
THE GLOBAL ECONOMY IS SHRINKING.
THE U.S. DEBT IS GROWING.
THE AMERICAN MIDDLE CLASS
FALTERING.
TONIGHT, WE'RE IN COLORADO, A
STATE REPRESENTING CHANGE.
BLAZING NEW TRAILS.
LEADING THE WAY FOR A NEW AND
CONTROVERSIAL INDUSTRY.
THE BEST TEAM IN BUSINESS IS
HERE TO TEST THE CANDIDATES IN
THE FIRST DEBATE DEDICATED TO
YOUR MONEY, YOUR VOTE.
LIVE, FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF
COLORADO IN BOULDER.
THE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE.
>> GOOD EVENING, I'M CARL
QUINTANILLA, WITH MY COLLEAGUE,
BECKY QUICK.
RULES OF THE ROAD, CANDIDATES
GET 30 SECONDS TO ANSWER THE
QUESTION, 60 SECONDS TO ANSWER A
FORMAL QUESTION, 60 SECONDS FOR
FOLLOW-UPS AND REBUTTALS, USE
THE HASH TAG, CNBC GOP DEBATE,
OR GO TO CNBC.COM/VOTE TO TELL
US WHERE YOU STAND THROUGHOUT
THE NIGHT.
LET'S INTRODUCE THE CANDIDATES,
ON STAGE FROM LEFT TO RIGHT,
GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH.
GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE.
GOVERNOR JEB BUSH.
SENATOR MARCO RUBIO.
MR. DONALD TRUMP.
DR. BEN CARSON.
MRS. CARLY FIORINA.
SENATOR TED CRUZ.
GOVERNOR CHRIS CHRISTIE.
AND SENATOR RAND PAUL.
A LOT TO GET TO TONIGHT.
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
THIS FIRST IS AN OPEN QUESTION.
THE SERIES OF DEBATES IS
ESSENTIALLY A JOB INTERVIEW WITH
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
AND IN ANY JOB INTERVIEW YOU
KNOW THIS.
YOU GET ASKED WHAT IS YOUR
BIGGEST WEAKNESS.
SO IN 30 SECONDS, WITHOUT
TELLING US THAT YOU TRIED TOO
HARD OR THAT YOU'RE A
PERFECTIONIST, WHAT IS YOUR
BIGGEST WEAKNESS AND WHAT ARE
YOU DOING TO ADDRESS IT?
WE'LL GO LEFT TO RIGHT, GOVERNOR
JOHN KASICH, 30 SECONDS.
>> GOOD QUESTION, BUT I WANT TO
TELL YOU MY GREAT CONCERN IS
WE'RE ON THE VERGE OF PERHAPS
PICKING SOMEONE WHO CANNOT DO
THIS JOB.
I'VE WATCHED TO SEE PEOPLE SAY
WE SHOULD DISMANTLE MEDICAID AND
MEDICARE AND LEAVE THE SENIOR
CITIZENS OUT IN THE COLD.
I'VE HEARD OF THEM TALKING ABOUT
DEPORTING PEOPLE OUT OF THIS
COUNTRY, SPLITTING FAMILIES.
I'VE HEARD OF TAX SCHEMES THAT
DON'T ADD UP THAT PUT OUR KIDS
IN DEEPER TROUBLE THAN THEY ARE
TODAY.
WE NEED SOMEBODYWE NEED SOMEBOD
>> FRANKLY I DID IT IN
WASHINGTON, OHIO, AND I'LL DO IT
AGAIN IN WASHINGTON IF I'M
PRESIDENT TO GET THIS COUNTRY
MOVING AGAIN.
>> GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE.
>> WELL, JOHN, I DON'T REALLY
HAVE ANY WEAKNESSES THAT I CAN
THINK OF.
BUT MY WIFE IS DOWN IN THE FRONT
AND IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO TALK TO
HER SHE CAN GIVE YOU MORE THAN
YOU WILL EVER BE ABLE TO TAKE
CARE OF.
IF I HAVE A WEAKNESS IT'S I TRY
TO LIVE BY THE RULES.
I TRY TO LIVE BY THE RULES NO
MATTER WHAT THEY ARE, AS A KID I
WAS BROUGHT UP THAT WAY.
I TELL YOU THE WEAKNESSES IN
THIS COUNTRY THERE ARE A LOT OF
PEOPLE WHO ARE SICK AND TIRED
BECAUSE WASHINGTON DOES NOT PLAY
BY THE SAME RULES THAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE TO PLAY BY.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR, GOVERNOR
BUSH.
>> YOU KNOW, I AM BY MY NATURE
IMPATIENT.
AND THIS IS NOT AN ENDEAVOR THAT
REWARDS THAT.
YOU HAVE TO BE PATIENT AND STICK
WITH IT AND ALL THAT.
BUT ALSO I CAN'T FAKE ANGER.
I BELIEVE THIS IS STILL THE MOST
EXTRAORDINARY COUNTRY ON THE
FACE OF THE EARTH.
AND IT TROUBLES ME THAT PEOPLE
ARE REWARDED FOR TEARING DOWN
OUR COUNTRY.
IT'S NEVER BEEN THAT WAY IN
AMERICAN POLITICS BEFORE.
I CAN'T DO IT.
I JUST DON'T BELIEVE THIS
COUNTRY'S DAYS ARE GOING TO BE
DEEPLY GOING DOWN.
I THINK WE'RE ON THE VERGE OF
THE GREATEST TIMES.
I WANT TO FIX THINGS THAT LET
PEOPLE RISE UP.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> THANK YOU FOR THAT QUESTION,
I BEGIN BY SAYING I'M NOT SURE
IT'S A WEAKNESS, BUT I DO
BELIEVE I SHARE A SENSE OF
OPTIMISM FOR TODAY'S COUNTRY,
THERE IS A SENSE IN THIS COUNTRY
THAT OUR BEST DAYS ARE BEHIND
US.
THAT DOESN'T HAVE TO BE TRUE.
OUR GREATEST DAYS LIE AHEAD IF
WE'RE WILLING TO DO WHAT IT
TAKES NOW.
THE 21st CENTURY WILL BE THE
GREATEST, GREATER THAN ANY OTHER
IN THIS GREAT NATION.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> I THINK MAYBE MY GREATEST
WEAKNESS IS THAT I TRUST PEOPLE
TOO MUCH.
I'M TOO TRUSTING.
AND WHEN THEY LET ME DOWN, IF
THEY LET ME DOWN I NEVER
FORGIVE.
I FIND IT VERY, VERY HARD TO
FORGIVE PEOPLE THAT DECEIVED ME.
SO I DON'T KNOW IF YOU WOULD
CALL THAT A WEAKNESS, BUT MY
WIFE SAID LET UP.
>> DR. CARSON?
>> PROBABLY IN TERMS OF APPLYING
FOR THE JOB OF PRESIDENT, THE
WEAKNESS WOULD BE NOT REALLY
SEEING MYSELF IN THAT POSITION
UNTIL HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE BEGAN TO TELL ME THAT I
NEEDED TO DO IT.
I DO HOWEVER, BELIEVE IN
REAGAN'S 11th COMMANDMENT AND
WILL NOT BE ENGAGING IN AWFUL
THINGS ABOUT MY COLLEAGUES HERE.
IN THIS ELECTION, BECAUSE WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT AMERICA FOR THE
PEOPLE VERSUS AMERICA FOR THE
GOVERNMENT.
>> MRS. FIORINA.
>> GEE, AFTER THE LAST DEBATE I
WAS TOLD I DIDN'T SMILE ENOUGH.
BUT I ALSO THINK THAT THESE ARE
VERY SERIOUS TIMES.
75% OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE THINK
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS
CORRUPT.
I AGREE WITH THEM.
AND THIS BIG, POWERFUL CORRUPT
BUREAUCRACY WORKS NOW ONLY FOR
THE BIG, THE POWERFUL, THE
WEALTHY AND THE WELL-CONNECTED.
MEANWHILE, WAGES ARE SLOWED FOR
40 YEARS, WE NEED A LEADER WHO
WILL HELP US TAKE OUR GOVERNMENT
BACK.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> I'M TOO AGREEABLE, EASYGOING.
YOU KNOW, I THINK MY BIGGEST
WEAKNESS IS EXACTLY THE
OPPOSITE.
I'M A FIGHTER.
I AM PASSIONATE ABOUT WHAT I
BELIEVE AND HAVE BEEN PASSIONATE
MY WHOLE LIFE ABOUT THE
CONSTITUTION.
FOR SIX AND A HALF YEARS, WE
HAVE A BIG PARTY, IF YOU WANT
SOMEBODY TO GRAB A BEER WITH I
MAY NOT BE THAT GUY.
BUT IF YOU WANT SOMEONE TO DRIVE
YOU HOME -- I WILL GET THE JOB
DONE.
AND I WILL GET YOU HOME.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> I DON'T SEE A LOT OF WEAKNESS
ON THE STAGE QUITE FRANKLY.
WHAT I SEE IS THE WEAKNESS, THE
THREE PEOPLE LEFT ON THE
DEMOCRATIC STAGE.
I SEE A SOCIALIST, AN
ISOLATIONIST, AND A PESSIMIST.
AND I CAN'T TELL YOU WHICH ONE
IS WHICH.
THE SOCIALIST TELLS YOU THEY
WILL GIVE YOU EVERYTHING FOR
FREE, THE ISOLATIONIST IS ONE
WHO FOLLOWS THE FOREIGN POLICY
THAT HAS FEWER, THE PESSIMIST IS
HILLARY CLINTON.
THEY WON'T GET WITHIN TEN MILES
OF THE WHITE HOUSE, TAKE IT TO
THE BANK.
>> SENATOR PAUL?
>> YOU KNOW, I LEFT MY MEDICAL
PRACTICE AND RAN FOR OFFICE
BECAUSE I WAS CONCERNED ABOUT AN
$18 TRILLION DEBT.
WE BORROW A MILLION DOLLARS A
MINUTE.
NOW IN CONSERVATIVE WASHINGTON,
THEY PUT FORWARD A BILL THAT
WILL EXPLODE THE DEFICIT.
IT ALLOWS PRESIDENT OBAMA TO
BORROW UNLIMITED AMOUNTS OF
MONEY.
I WILL STAND FIRM AND SPEND
EVERY OUNCE OF ENERGY TO STOP
IT.
I WILL BEGIN TOMORROW TO
FILIBUSTER IT.
AND I WILL ASK EVERY AMERICAN TO
CALL CONGRESS TOMORROW AND SAY
ENOUGH IS ENOUGH, NO MORE DEBT.
>> THANK YOU TO ALL THE
CANDIDATES, JOHN?
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU HAVE DONE VERY
WELL IN THIS CAMPAIGN SO FAR BY
PROMISING TO BUILD ANOTHER WALL
AND MAKE ANOTHER COUNTRY PAY FOR
IT.
SEND 11 MILLION PEOPLE OUT OF
THE COUNTRY.
CUT TAXES $10 TRILLION WITHOUT
INCREASING THE DEFICIT AND MAKE
AMERICANS BETTER OFF BECAUSE
YOUR GREATNESS WILL REPLACE THE
STUPIDITY AND INCOMPETENCE OF
OTHERS, LET'S BE HONEST.
IS THIS A COMIC BOOK VERSION OF
THE PRESIDENT?
>> NO, IT'S NOT A COMIC BOOK
VERSION.
AND BY THE WAY I DON'T LIKE THE
WAY YOU PHRASED THE QUESTION.
WE'RE BRINGING MONEY BACK IN,
CORPORATE INVERSIONS.
WE HAVE $2.5 TRILLION OUTSIDE OF
THE UNITED STATES, AS FAR AS THE
WALL IS CONCERNED.
WE'LL BUILD THE WALL, CREATE A
BORDER.
WELL, LET PEOPLE IN, THEY WILL
COME IN LEGALLY.
IT IS SOMETHING THAT CAN BE
DONE.
AND I GET QUESTIONED ABOUT IT.
THEY BUILT THE GREAT WALL OF
CHINA, THAT IS 13,000 MILES.
HERE WE ACTUALLY NEED A THOUSAND
BECAUSE WE HAVE NATURAL
BARRIERS.
WE NEED A WALL.
WE'LL HAVE A BIG FAT BEAUTIFUL
DOOR RIGHT IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
WALL.
WE'LL HAVE PEOPLE COME IN
LEGALLY.
AND MEXICO WILL PAY FOR THE WALL
-- I LOVE THE MEXICAN PEOPLE.
I RESPECT THE MEXICAN LEADERS
BUT THE LEADERS ARE MUCH
SHARPER, SMARTER AND MORE
CUNNING THAN OUR LEADERS.
AND JUST TO FINISH, PEOPLE SAY
OH, HOW WILL YOU MAKE MEXICO TO
PAY?
A POLITICIAN CANNOT GET THEM TO
PAY.
I CAN.
WE LOSE, WE HAVE A TRADE
IMBALANCE --
>> EXCUSE ME --
>> $50 BILLION --
>> WE'RE AT THE 60 SECONDS.
>> THE WORLD IS PEANUTS BY
COMPARISON.
>> I HAVE TO ASK YOU, YOU TALKED
ABOUT YOUR TAX PLAN.
YOU SAY IT WOULD NOT INCREASE
THE DEFICIT BECAUSE YOU CUT
TAXES $10 TRILLION --
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE OFF --
>> THE ECONOMY WOULD TAKE OFF
LIKE A ROCKET SHIP.
I TALKED TO ECONOMIC ADVISERS
WHO HAVE SERVED PRESIDENTS OF
BOTH PARTIES.
THEY SAY YOU HAVE A CHANCE OF
CUTTING TAXES THAT MUCH WITHOUT
INCREASING A DEFICIT AS YOU
WOULD OF FLYING AWAY FROM THAT
PODIUM BY FLAPPING YOUR ARMS --
>> THEN YOU HAVE TO GET RID OF
LARRY KUDLOW, WHO IS A GREAT
GUY, WHO SAYS I LOVE TRUMP'S TAX
PLAN.
>> AND THE TAX --
>> THIS IS ALL OF OUR PLANS --
HIS CREATES EVEN WITH THE
DYNAMIC EFFECT --
>> JOHN -- WE'LL GET BACK TO HIM
IN JUST A MINUTE.
WE'LL CONTINUE WITH THIS.
I WANT TO TALK TAXES --
>> COMING BACK TO YOU IN A
MINUTE.
BECKY.
>> DR. CARSON, LET'S TALK ABOUT
TAXES.
YOU HAVE A FLAT TAX PLAN, 10%
FLAT TAXES, AND THIS IS
SOMETHING VERY APPEALING TO A
LOT OF VOTERS.
BUT I'VE HAD A REALLY TOUGH TIME
TRYING TO MAKE THE MATH WORK ON
IT.
IF YOU TOOK A 10% TAX, WE'LL
COME IN WITH $1.5 TRILLION, LESS
THAN HALF OF WHAT WE BRING IN
RIGHT NOW.
AND BY THE WAY IT WILL LEAVE US
IN A $2 TRILLION HOLE.
WHAT ANALYSIS SAID THIS WILL
WORK?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I DIDN'T SAY
THE RATE WILL --
>> I UNDERSTAND, BUT IF YOU LOOK
AT THE NUMBERS.
>> THE RATE WILL BE MUCH CLOSER
TO 15%.
>> 15% STILL LEAVES YOU WITH A
$1.1 TRILLION HOLE.
>> YOU ALSO HAVE TO GET RID OF
THE DEDUCTIONS AND LOOPHOLES.
YOU HAVE TO STRATEGICALLY CUT IN
SEVERAL PLACES.
REMEMBER, WE HAVE 645 FEDERAL
AGENCIES AND SUB-AGENCIES.
ANYBODY WHO TELLS ME THAT WE
NEED EVERY PENNY IN EVERY ONE OF
THOSE IS IN A FANTASY WORLD.
SO ALSO WE CAN STIMULATE THE
ECONOMY.
THAT IS GOING TO BE THE REAL
GROWTH ENGINE.
STIMULATING THE ECONOMY --
BECAUSE ITS HEAD IS DOWN WITH SO
MANY REGULATIONS.
>> YOU WOULD HAVE TO CUT
GOVERNMENT ABOUT 40% TO WORK --
>> THAT IS NOT TRUE.
WHEN WE PUT ALL THE TAXES DOWN
YOU WILL BE ABLE TO SEE THAT
IT'S NOT TRUE, IT WORKS OUT VERY
WELL.
>> DR. CARSON, THANK YOU.
>> HOLD IT, I'M COMING TO YOU
RIGHT NOW.
>> WELL, I WANT TO COMMENT ON
THIS.
>> A FANTASY THAT I TALKED ABOUT
IN THE BEGINNING.
>> I'M ABOUT TO ASK YOU ABOUT
THIS.
THAT IS, YOU HAD SOME VERY
STRONG WORDS TO SAY YESTERDAY
ABOUT WHAT IS HAPPENING IN YOUR
PARTY AND WHAT YOU'RE HEARING
FROM THE TWO GENTLEMEN WE'VE
JUST HEARD FROM.
WOULD YOU REPEAT IT?
>> I'M THE ONLY PERSON ON THIS
STAGE THAT WAS ACTUALLY INVOLVED
IN THE CHIEF ARCHITECT OF
BALANCING THE BUDGET.
THESE PLANS WOULD PUT US
TRILLIONS IN DEBT.
I ACTUALLY HAVE A PLAN.
I'M THE ONLY ONE ON THIS STAGE
THAT HAS A PLAN THAT WOULD
CREATE JOBS, CUT TAXES, BALANCE
THE BUDGET AND CAN GET IT DONE
BECAUSE I'M REALISTIC.
YOU JUST DON'T MAKE PROMISES
LIKE THIS.
WHY DON'T WE JUST PUT A CHICKEN
IN EVERY POT, COMING UP WITH
THESE FANTASY TAX SCHEMES.
JUST CLEANING UP.
WHERE DO YOU CLEAN IT UP?
YOU HAVE TO DEAL WITH
ENTITLEMENTS, BE IN A POSITION
TO CONTROL DISCRETIONARY
SPENDING.
YOU HAVE TO BE CREATIVE AND
IMAGINATIVE.
LET ME BE CLEAR, I WENT INTO
OHIO WHERE WE'RE UP 347,000
JOBS.
WHEN I WAS IN WASHINGTON I
FOUGHT TO GET THE BUDGET
BALANCED.
I WAS THE ARCHITECT.
IT WAS THE FIRST TIME WE DID IT
SINCE MAN WALKED ON THE MOON.
WE CUT TAXES AND WE HAD A $5
TRILLION PROJECTED SURPLUS.
WHEN I LEFT THAT WAS HARD WORK.
FISCAL
CITIZENS WITH THAT.
IT'S NOT RESPONSIBLE.
>> YOU SAID YESTERDAY THAT YOU
WERE HEARING PROPOSALS THAT WERE
JUST CRAZY FROM YOUR COLLEAGUES.
WHO WERE YOU TALKING ABOUT?
>> WELL, RIGHT HERE THEY'RE
TALKING ABOUT WE'LL JUST HAVE A
10% TITHE AND THAT IS HOW WE'LL
FUND THE GOVERNMENT.
WE'LL JUST FIX EVERYTHING WITH
WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE.
OH THAT WE'RE JUST GOING TO BE
GREAT, AND WE'LL SHIP TEN
MILLION PEOPLE OUT OF THIS
COUNTRY, LEAVING THEIR CHILDREN
HERE IN THIS COUNTRY AND
DIVIDING FAMILIES.
FOLKS, WE GOT TO WAKE UP.
WE CANNOT ELECT SOMEBODY THAT
DOESN'T KNOW HOW TO DO THE JOB.
YOU HAVE TO PICK SOMEBODY WHO
HAS EXPERIENCE, SOMEBODY THAT
HAS THE KNOW-HOW, THE
DISCIPLINE, AND I SPENT MY
ENTIRE LIFETIME BALANCING
FEDERAL BUDGETS, FLOWING JOBS,
SAME IN OHIO, I WILL GO BACK
WITHIN 100 DAYS, IT WILL PASS
AND WE'LL BE STRONG AGAIN.
>> FIRST OF ALL, JOHN GOT LUCKY
WITH A THING CALLED FRACKING,
OKAY?
HE HIT OIL, HE GOT LUCKY WITH
FRACKING, THAT IS WHY OHIO IS
DOING REALLY WELL.
THAT IS IMPORTANT FOR YOU TO
KNOW.
NUMBER TWO, THIS WAS THE MAN WHO
WAS A MANAGING GENERAL PARTNER
AT LEHMAN BROTHERS, AND ALMOST
TOOK US DONE WITH IT TOO.
THE LEHMAN BROTHERS, THEY
MANAGED IT ALL.
THIRDLY, HE WAS SUCH A NICE GUY.
HIS POLL NUMBERS TANKED.
THAT IS WHY HE IS ON THE END.
HE GOT NASTY, SO YOU KNOW WHAT?
YOU CAN HAVE HIM.
>> LET ME RESPOND.
FIRST OF ALL, OHIO DOES HAVE AN
ENERGY INDUSTRY, BUT WE'RE
DIVERSIFIED.
WE'RE ONE OF THE FASTEST GROWING
STATES IN THE COUNTRY.
WE CAME BACK FROM THE DEAD.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT?
IT WORKS VERY, VERY WELL.
SECONDLY WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT ME
BEING ON THE BOARD OF LEHMAN
BROTHERS.
I WAS A BANKER AND TRAVELED
AROUND THE COUNTRY AND LEARNED
HOW PEOPLE MADE JOBS.
WE OUGHT TO HAVE POLITICIANS WHO
NOT ONLY HAVE GOVERNMENT
EXPERIENCE BUT KNOW HOW THE
STATE WORKS.
GUESS WHAT IN 2011, I HAVE --
>> AN AGREEMENT --
>> HE TRIED TO PAY --
>> FOUR YEARS LATER.
IT'S A JOKE.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> DR. CARSON, LET ME GET 30
SECONDS WITH DR. CARSON.
>> LET ME JUST SAY -- IF YOU'RE
TALKING ABOUT AN $18 TRILLION
ECONOMY YOU TALK ABOUT A 15% TAX
ON YOUR GROSS DOMESTIC PRODUCT.
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT $2.7
TRILLION.
WE HAVE A BUDGET CLOSER TO $3.5
BUT IF YOU ALSO APPLY THAT SAME
15% TO SEVERAL OTHER THINGS
INCLUDING CORPORATE TAXES, AND
INCLUDING THE CAPITAL GAINS
TAXES YOU MAKE THAT AMOUNT UP
PRETTY QUICKLY.
SO THAT IS NOT BY ANY STRETCH A
PIE IN THE SKY.
>> IF YOU WANT A 10% FLAT TAX
WHERE THE NUMBERS ADD UP I
ROLLED OUT MY TAX PLAN TODAY YOU
CAN FIND IT ON LINE AT
TEDCRUZ.ORG.
IT IS A SIMPLE FLAT TAX WHERE
FOR INDIVIDUALS A FAMILY OF FOUR
PAYS NOTHING ON THE FIRST
$36,000.
AFTER THAT YOU PAY 10% OF THE
FLAT TAX GOING UP.
THE BILLIONAIRE AND THE WORKING
MAN, NO HEDGE FUND MANAGER PAYS
LESS THAN HIS SECRETARY.
ON TOP OF THAT, THERE IS A
BUSINESS FLAT TAX OF 16%.
NOW THAT APPLIES UNIVERSALLY TO
GIANT CORPORATIONS THAT WITH
LOBBYISTS RIGHT NOW ARE NOT
PAYING TAXES.
AND WITH SMALL BUSINESS, YOU
WANT TO KNOW THE NUMBERS, THIS
SHOWS THE PLAN WILL ALLOW THE
ECONOMY TO GENERATE $4.9 -- 4.9
MILLION JOBS AND TO GENERATE 14%
GROWTH.
THOSE ARE THE HARD NUMBERS AND
EVERY SINGLE INCOME -- THEY
DOUBLE DIGIT INCREASE AFTER TAX
INCOME.
GROWTH IS THE ANSWER.
AS AS REAGAN DEMONSTRATED.
IF WE CUT TAXES --
>> GENTLEMEN, I'M SORRY --
>> WE'RE GOING TO TRY TO MOVE
ON.
>> LET ME JUST SAY ON TAXES HOW
LONG HAVE WE BEEN TALKING ABOUT
TAX REFORM IN WASHINGTON, D.C.?
WE HAVE BEEN TALKING ABOUT IT
FOR DECADES.
WE NOW HAVE A 73,000-PAGE TAX
CODE.
THERE HAVE BEEN MORE THAN 4,000
CHANGES TO THE TAX PLAN SINCE
2001 ALONE.
THERE ARE ROWS OF GREAT IDEAS,
GREAT CONSERVATIVE IDEAS FROM
WONDERFUL THINK TANKS ABOUT HOW
TO REFORM THE TAX CODE.
THE PROBLEM IS WE HAVE NEVER GET
IT DONE.
WE HAVE TALKED ABOUT TAX REFORM
IN EVERY SINGLE ELECTION FOR
DECADES.
IT NEVER HAPPENS.
AND THE POLITICIANS ALWAYS SAY
IT IS SO COMPLEX NOBODY BUT A
POLITICIAN CAN FIGURE IT OUT.
THE BIG PROBLEM IS WE NEED A
LEADER IN WASHINGTON WHO
UNDERSTANDS HOW TO GET SOMETHING
DONE.
NOT TO TALK ABOUT IT.
NOT TO PROPOSE IT.
TO GET IT DONE.
>> YOU WANT TO PUSH 70,000 PAGES
TO THREE?
YOU KNOW WHY THREE?
BECAUSE ONLY IF IT'S ABOUT THREE
PAGES ARE YOU LEVELING THE
PLAYING FIELD BETWEEN THE BIG,
THE POWERFUL, THE WEALTHY AND
THE WELL-CONNECTED WHO CAN HIRE
THE ARMIES OF LAWYERS AND
ACCOUNTANTS AND YES LOBBYISTS TO
HELP THEM NAVIGATE THEIR WAY
THROUGH 73,000 PAGES.
THREE PAGES IS ABOUT THE
MAXIMUM, BUT A SINGLE BUSINESS
OWNER OR FARMER OR JUST A COUPLE
CAN UNDERSTAND WITHOUT HIRING
SOMEBODY, ALMOST 63% OF PEOPLE
NOW NEED TO HIRE AN EXPERT TO
UNDERSTAND THEIR TAXES SO YES,
YOU'RE GOING TO HEAR A LOT OF
TALK ABOUT TAX REFORM.
>> TO MOVE ON --
>> WE'LL COME AROUND TO THAT.
I PROMISE, THIS ONE FOR SENATOR
RUBIO.
YOU HAVE BEEN A YOUNG MAN IN A
HURRY EVER SINCE YOU WON YOUR
FIRST ELECTION FOR YOUR 20s.
YOU HAVE HAD A BIG
ACCOMPLISHMENT IN THE SENATE, AN
IMMIGRATION BILL PROVIDING A
PATH TO CITIZENSHIP THAT
CONSERVATIVES IN YOUR PARTY HATE
AND EVEN YOU DON'T SUPPORT
ANYMORE.
NOW YOU'RE SKIPPING MORE VOTES
THAN ANY SENATOR TO RUN FOR
PRESIDENT.
WHY NOT SLOW DOWN, GET A FEW
MORE THINGS DONE FIRST AND AT
LEAST FINISH WHAT YOU START?
>> THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT THE
REPUBLICAN ESTABLISHMENT SAYS,
TOO, WAIT IN LINE.
WAIT FOR WHAT?
THIS COUNTRY IS RUNNING OUT OF
TIME.
WATCHING THIS BROADCAST TONIGHT
AND MILLIONS OF PEOPLE ARE
LIVING PAYCHECK TO PAYCHECK.
THEY'RE WORKING AS HARD AS
EVERYTHING HAS, EVERYTHING COSTS
MORE.
THEY HAVE NOT HAD A RAISE IN
DECADES.
YOU HAVE SMALL BUSINESSES
STRUGGLING, MORE BUSINESSES
CLOSING THAN STARTED.
A WORLD OUT OF CONTROL, A
PRESIDENT WEAKENING OUR MILITARY
AND MAKING THE FOREIGN POLICY
UNSTABLE AND OUR ADVERSEARIES
CONTINUE TO GROW STRONGER, THE
TIME TO ACT IS NOW, THE TIME TO
TURN THE PAGE IS NOW.
IF WE DON'T ASK NOW, WE'LL BE
THE FIRST GENERATION THAT LEAVES
OUR CHILDREN WORSE OFF THAN
OURSELVES.
>> WHEN SOME SAY RUBIO SHOULD
RESIGN, WHEN THEY SAY PEOPLE OF
FLORIDA SENT YOU TO WASHINGTON
TO DO YOUR JOB, WHEN THEY SAY
YOU ACT LIKE YOU HATE YOUR JOB,
DO YOU?
>> I READ THE EDITORIAL WITH
GREAT AMUSEMENT --
>> DO YOU HATE YOUR JOB?
>> BACK IN 2004, ONE OF MY
PREDECESSORS BY THE NAME OF BOB
GRANT RAN FOR PRESIDENT.
I DON'T RECALL THEM CALLING FOR
HIS RESIGNATION.
LATER THAT YEAR, JOHN KERRY
MISSED 40 TO 70% OF THE VOTES.
IN 2008, BARACK OBAMA MISSED 60
OR 70% OF HIS VOTES AND THE SAME
NEWSPAPER ENDORSED HIM AGAIN.
THIS IS ANOTHER EXAMPLE OF THE
DOUBLE STANDARD THAT EXISTS IN
THIS COUNTRY, BETWEEN THE
MAINSTREAM MEDIA AND THE
CONSERVATIVES.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
>> I'M A CONSTITUENT OF THE
SENATOR AND I HELPED HIM AND I
EXPECTED HE WOULD DO CONSTITUENT
SERVICE WHICH MEANS HE SHOWS UP
TO WORK.
HE GOT ENDORSED BY THE SUN
SENTINEL, HE IS THE MOST GIFTED
POLITICIAN.
WHEN YOU SIGNED UP FOR THIS,
THIS IS A SIX-YEAR TERM.
YOU SHOULD BE SHOWING UP TO
TERM.
LITERALLY, THE SENATE, IS IT A
FRENCH WORK WEEK?
YOU GET THREE DAYS TO SHOW UP.
JUST RESIGN AND LET SOMEBODY
ELSE TAKE THE JOB.
THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE WHO
ARE LIVING PAYCHECK TO PAYCHECK
IN FLORIDA.
>> WELL, THAT IS INTERESTING
OVER THE LAST FEW WEEKS, I
LISTENED TO JEB, HE SAID YOU'RE
MODELLING YOUR CAMPAIGN AFTER
JOHN MCCAIN, AND WILL LAUNCH A
SERIOUS COMEBACK LIKE HE DID BY
FIGHTING HARD IN PLACES LIKE NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
YOU KNOW HOW MANY VOTES JOHN
MCCAIN MISSED -- JEB, LET ME
TELL YOU, I DON'T REMEMBER YOU
EVER COMPLAINING ABOUT JOHN
MCCAIN'S VOTE RECORD.
THE ONLY REASON YOU'RE DOING IT
NOW IS BECAUSE WE'RE RUNNING FOR
THE SAME POSITION.
SOMEONE CONVINCED YOU ATTACKING
ME IS GOING TO HELP YOU.
I CAN'T CAMPAIGN ABOUT THE
FUTURE OF AMERICA OR ATTACKING
ANYONE ELSE ON THIS STAGE.
I WILL CONTINUE TO HAVE
TREMENDOUS ADMIRATION FOR
GOVERNOR BUSH, I'M NOT RUNNING
AGAINST ANYONE ON THE STAGE.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
THERE IS NO WAY WE CAN ELECT
HILLARY CLINTON TO CONTINUE THE
POLICIES --
>> I --
>> JOHN HARWOOD -- THERE IS A
BIGGER ISSUE --
>> QUESTIONS FOR GOVERNOR BUSH.
>> GOVERNOR, THE FACT THAT
YOU'RE AT THE FIFTH LECTERN
TONIGHT SHOWS HOW FAR YOUR STOCK
HAS FALLEN, DESPITE THE AMOUNTS
THE DONORS HAVE MADE.
YOU INITIALLY SAID YOU HAD
BETTER THINGS TO DO THAN SIT
AROUND AND BE DEMONIZED --
>> I SAID I DON'T BELIEVE I
WOULD BE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES AND HAVE THE SAME
DYSFUNCTION.
DON'T VOTE IF YOU WANT TO SAME
GRID LOCK.
IF YOU WANT SOMEBODY THAT HAS A
PROVEN LEADERSHIP, ELECT ME SO I
CAN FIGHT FOR THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE AND CHANGE THE CULTURE IN
WASHINGTON, D.C.
>> IT'S A QUESTION ABOUT WHY
YOU'RE HAVING DIFFICULTY.
I WANT TO ASK YOU IN THIS
CONTEXT.
BEN BERNANKE WHO WAS APPOINTED
FED CHAIRMAN SAID HE NO LONGER
CONSIDERS HIMSELF A REPUBLICAN
BECAUSE THE REPUBLICAN PARTY HAS
GIVEN INTO NO-NOTHINGISM.
IS THAT WHY YOU'RE HAVING A
DIFFICULT TIME IN THIS RACE?
>> LOOK, THE GREAT MAJORITY OF
THE REPUBLICANS BELIEVE IN A
HOPEFUL FUTURE AND DON'T BELIEVE
IN BUILDING WALLS AND A
PESSIMISTIC FUTURE.
THE RATES WERE LOWER THAN 1977.
SIX MILLION MORE PEOPLE LIVING
IN POVERTY THAN THE DAY THAT
BARACK OBAMA GOT ELECTED
PRESIDENT.
THE LEFT JUST WANTS MORE OF THE
SAME.
WE HAVE TO OFFER A COMPELLING
ARGUMENT THAT IS BASED ON HOPE
AND OPTIMISM.
AND GROUNDED IN SERIOUS POLICY.
THAT YOU CAN GO GET.
JEB BUSH FOR 2016 --
>> WE'LL GET TO EVERYONE.
MS. FIORINA, I WOULD LIKE TO ASK
YOU A QUESTION.
YOU'RE RUNNING FOR QUESTION
BECAUSE OF YOUR PERFORMANCE AS
CEO OF HEWLETT-PACKARD.
SOMEBODY WHO INVESTED IN YOUR
COMPANY HAD LOST HALF OF THE
DOLLAR IN THE MONEY THEY
INVESTED.
ANYBODY FOLLOWING THE MARKET
KNOWS THAT YOUR STOCK WAS A MUCH
WORSE PERFORMER IF YOU LOOKED AT
YOUR COMPETITORS AND THE OVERALL
MARKET.
I JUST WONDER, IN TERMS OF ALL
THAT, YOUR BOARD FIRED YOU.
I JUST WONDER WHY YOU THINK WE
SHOULD HIRE YOU NOW.
>> YOU KNOW, THE NASDAQ DROPPED
80%, 80% AND IT TOOK 15 YEARS
FOR THE NASDAQ TO RECOVER.
I WAS RECRUITED TO HP TO SAVE A
COMPANY.
IT WAS A COMPANY THAT HAD GROWN
INTO A BLOATED INEPT BUREAUCRACY
THAT COST TOO MUCH AND DELIVERED
TOO LITTLE TO CUSTOMERS AND
SHAREHOLDERS.
IT HAD MISSED BEFORE I HAD
ARRIVED EXPECTATIONS FOR NINE
QUARTERS IN A ROW.
AS AN OUTSIDER, I TACKLED HP'S
PROBLEMS HEAD-ON, CUT THE
BUREAUCRACY DOWN TO SIZE.
RE-INTRODUCED ACCOUNTABILITY.
FOCUSED ON SERVICE AND
INNOVATION ON LEADING IN EVERY
PRODUCT AND SEGMENT.
AND YES, IT WAS A DIFFICULT
TIME.
HOWEVER, WE SAVED 80,000 JOBS
AND WENT ON TO GROW 106,000
JOBS, AND SCORED COMPANIES
LITERALLY LIKE GATE WAY THAT
TOOK ALL THEIR JOBS WITH THEM.
THE TRUTH IS I HAD TO MAKE TOUGH
CALLS DURING TOUGH TIMES.
YES, I WAS FIRED OVER A
DISAGREEMENT IN THE BOARD ROOM.
THERE ARE POLITICS IN THE BOARD
ROOM AS WELL, YET THE MAN WHO
READ MY FIRING, TOM PERKINS, AN
ICON IN THE SILICON VALLEY, SAID
YOU KNOW WHAT?
SHE WAS RIGHT, WE WERE WRONG,
THE LEADERSHIP SHE BROUGHT TO HB
IS EXACTLY THE LEADERSHIP WE
NEED IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
>> IT IS INTERESTING YOU BRING
HIM UP.
HE SAID A LOT OF QUESTIONABLE
THINGS, LAST YEAR IN AN
INTERVIEW HE SAID HE THINKS
WEALTHY PEOPLE SHOULD GET MORE
VOTES THAN POOR PEOPLE.
HE SAID IF YOU PAY A MILLION
DOLLARS IN TAXES YOU SHOULD GET
A MILLION VOTES?
>> THIS IS ONE OF THE REASONS
WHY TOM PERKINS AND I HAD HAD
DISAGREEMENTS IN THE BOARD ROOM,
BECKY.
NEVERTHELESS, ONE OF THE THINGS
THAT I THINK PEOPLE DON'T ALWAYS
UNDERSTAND IS HOW ACCOUNTABLE A
CEO ACTUALLY IS.
SO YOU KNOW, I HAD TO REPORT
RESULTS EVERY 90 DAYS IN
EXCRUCIATING DETAIL.
I HAD TO ANSWER EVERY SINGLE
QUESTION ABOUT EVERY SINGLE
RESULT AND EVERY SINGLE
PROJECTION IN PUBLIC UNTIL THERE
WERE NO MORE QUESTIONS.
AND IF I MISREPRESENTED THOSE
RESULTS OR THOSE PROJECTIONS IN
ANY WAY I WAS HELD CRIMINALLY
LIABLE.
IMAGINE, IMAGINE IF A POLITICIAN
WERE HELD TO THAT STANDARD OF
ACCOUNTS.
I WILL RUN ON MY RECORD ALL DAY
LONG.
AND I BELIEVE PEOPLE NEED A
LEADER WHO IS PREPARED TO MAKE
TOUGH CALLS IN TOUGH TIMES AND
STAND UP AND BE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE.
>> THANK YOU, MRS. FIORINA,
WE'RE OUT OF TIME.
>> AND CONGRESSIONAL DEMOCRATS
AND REPUBLICANS ARE ABOUT TO
STRIKE A COMPROMISE THAT WOULD
RAISE THE DEBT LIMIT, DURING THE
FEAR THAT A WASHINGTON CRISIS IS
ON THE WAY.
DOES YOUR OPPOSITION TO IT SHOW
YOU'RE NOT THE KIND OF
PROBLEM-SOLVER THAT AMERICAN
VOTERS WANT?
>> LET ME SAY SOMETHING AT THE
OUTSET.
THE QUESTIONS ASKED IN THIS
DEBATE ILLUSTRATE WHY THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE DON'T TRUST THE
MEDIA.
THIS IS NOT A CAGE MATCH.
DONALD TRUMP, ARE YOU A COMIC
BOOK VILLAIN?
MARCO RUBIO, WHY DON'T YOU
RESIGN?
JEB BUSH, WHY HAVE YOUR NUMBERS
FALLEN?
HOW ABOUT TALKING ABOUT THE
SUBSTANTIVE ISSUES --
>> DO WE GET CREDIT --
>> AND CARL, I'M NOT FINISHED
YET.
THE CONTRAST WITH THE DEMOCRATIC
DEBATE, WHERE EVERY THOUGHT AND
QUESTION FROM THE MEDIA WAS,
WHICH OF YOU IS MORE HANDSOME
AND WHY?
>> LET ME SAY, YOU HAVE 30
SECONDS LEFT TO ANSWER SHOULD
YOU CHOOSE TO DO SO.
>> LET ME BE CLEAR.
THE MEN AND WOMEN ON THIS STAGE
HAVE MORE IDEAS, MORE
EXPERIENCE, MORE COMMON SENSE,
THAN EVER PARTICIPANT IN THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE.
THAT DEBATE REFLECTED A DEBATE
BETWEEN THE BOLSHEVIKS AND THE
MENCHAVICKS.
NOBODY BELIEVES THAT THE
MODERATORS HAVE ANY INTENTION OF
VOTING IN A REPUBLICAN PRIMER.
THE QUESTIONS BEING ASKED
SHOULDN'T BE TRYING TO GET
PEOPLE TO TEAR INTO EACH OTHER,
IT SHOULD BE WHAT ARE YOUR
SUBSTANTIVE --
>> I ASKED YOU ABOUT THE DEBT
LIMIT AND GOT NO ANSWER.
>> I'M HAPPY TO ANSWER -- LET ME
TELL YOU -- LET ME TELL YOU --
>> WE'RE MOVING ON.
>> SENATOR PAUL, I HAVE A
QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> YOU DON'T ACTUALLY WANT TO
HEAR THE ANSWER, JOHN?
YOU JUST WANT --
>> YOU USED YOUR TIME ON
SOMETHING IS.
>> YOU'RE NOT INTERESTED IN AN
ANSWER.
>> JOHN.
>> SENATOR PAUL, THE BUDGET DEAL
CRAFTED BY SPEAKER JOHN BOEHNER
AND PASSED BY THE HOUSE TODAY
MAKES CUTS IN ENTITLEMENT
PROGRAMS, MEDICARE AND SOCIAL
SECURITY DISABILITY WHICH ARE
THE VERY PROGRAMS CONSERVATIVES
SAY NEED CUTTING TO SHRINK
GOVERNMENT AND SOLVE OUR
COUNTRY'S LONG-TERM BUDGET
DEFICIT.
DO YOU OPPOSE THAT BUDGET DEAL
BECAUSE IT DOESN'T CUT THESE
PROGRAMS ENOUGH?
>> NO, I OPPOSE IT BECAUSE
YOU'RE TAKING MONEY FROM THE
ENTITLEMENTS AND THEN SPENDING
IT IMMEDIATELY ON OTHER ITEMS.
THAT IS WHAT THEY'RE DOING.
THEY'RE TAKING MONEY FROM SOCIAL
SECURITY AND THEY'RE GOING TO
SPEND IT ON THE MILITARY.
AND THEY'RE GOING TO SPEND IT ON
DOMESTIC SPENDING.
HERE IS THE THING, WHEN YOU LOOK
AT RAIING THE DEBT LIMIT IT
SHOULD BE LEVERAGE TO TRY TO
REFORM THE GOVERNMENT.
IN 2011, THE SEQUESTER WAS
PASSED TO SLOW DOWN GOVERNMENT.
INSTEAD, THE WASHINGTON
ESTABLISHMENT RAISED BOTH.
WE RAISED THE MILITARY SPENDING,
TOOK THE ENTITLEMENTS AND RAISED
DOMESTIC SPENDING AND THE
DEFICIT WILL EXPLODE UNDER THIS.
THIS IS THE UNHOLY ALLIANCE THAT
PEOPLE NEED TO KNOW ABOUT
BETWEEN RIGHT AND LEFT.
RIGHT AND LEFT ARE SPENDING US
INTO OBLIVION, WE SHOULD USE THE
DEBT CEILING AS PRECISELY
DESIGNED TO FORCE UPON THEM
BUDGETARY REFORM.
>> SENATOR, IF WHAT YOU JUST
SAID IS TRUE, WHY DID SPEAKER
JOHN BOEHNER CRAFT THIS DEAL,
AND WHY ABOUT PAUL RYAN WHO HAD
A STRONG RECORD FOR FISCAL
DISCIPLINE, VOTE FOR IT?
>> WELL, THAT IS THE QUESTION,
WILL THERE BE MUCH CHANGE IN THE
WHITE HOUSE WITH NEW LEADERSHIP?
I DON'T THINK THERE WILL BE MUCH
CHANGE.
PEOPLE IN WASHINGTON THINK THEY
WERE SENT THERE TO BE ADULTS AND
GOVERN AND DO ALL THIS.
YOU KNOW WHAT I'M WORRIED ABOUT?
NOT KEEPING THE GOVERNMENT OPEN,
I'M WORRIED ABOUT BANKRUPTING
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
WE'RE BORROWING A MILLION
DOLLARS A MINUTE.
THAT IS IMPORTANT AND WHAT WE
HAVE TO CONTRAST, KEEPING THE
GOVERNMENT OPEN, AND --
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, I WOULD
LIKE TO COME TO YOU.
ACTUALLY I HAVE A QUESTION FOR
YOU.
IN YOUR "TELL IT LIKE IT IS"
CAMPAIGN YOU SAID TOUGH THINGS,
WE NEED TO RAISE THE RETIREMENT
FOR SOCIAL SECURITY AND NEED TO
CUT BENEFITS FOR PEOPLE WHO MAKE
OVER $80,000 AND ELIMINATE THE
ENTITLEMENTS FOR PEOPLE MAKING
OVER $200,000.
GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE AND
OTHERS SAY THEY THINK YOU'RE
TRYING TO ROB PEOPLE OF BENEFITS
THAT THEY HAVE EARNED.
WHEN IS IT ACCEPTABLE TO BREAK A
SOCIAL CONTRACT?
>> I WISH YOU WOULD HAVE ASKED
THE QUESTION YEARS AGO WHEN THEY
BROKE IT.
LET ME BE HONEST WITH THE PEOPLE
AT HOME.
THE GOVERNMENT HAS LIED TO YOU
AND STOLEN FROM YOU.
THEY TOLD YOU THAT YOUR SOCIAL
SECURITY MONEY IS IN A TRUST
FUND.
ALL THAT IS IN A TRUST FUND IS A
PILE OF IOUs THAT THEY BORROWED
FROM YEARS AGO.
71% OF FEDERAL SPENDING TODAY IS
ON ENTITLEMENTS AND DEBT
SERVICE.
THAT IS WITH ZERO PERCENT
INTEREST RATES.
I'M THE ONLY PERSON WHO PUT OUT
A DETAILED PLAN TO DEAL WITH
ENTITLEMENTS AND WE'LL SAVE A
TRILLION DOLLARS OVER THE NEXT
TEN YEARS.
THIS IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
ME AND HILLARY CLINTON.
WHAT HILLARY CLINTON IS GOING TO
SAY AND HAS SAID BEFORE SHE
WANTS TO RAISE SOCIAL SECURITY
TAXES.
LET ME ASK YOU A QUESTION,
EVERYBODY.
IF SOMEBODY OWNS A LANDSCAPING
BUSINESS AND SOMEBODY HAS
ALREADY STOLEN MONEY FROM YOU,
ARE YOU GOING TO GIVE THEM MORE?
OR ARE YOU GOING TO SAY I'M
GOING TO DEAL WITH PEOPLE DOING
WELL WITH BENEFITS ON THE BACK
END.
WE NEED TO GET REALISTIC.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, FORGET
ABOUT ANYBODY ELSE.
THEY HAVE ALREADY BEEN LIED TO
AND STOLEN FROM.
>> WE PROMISE WE'LL GET TO
EVERYBODY.
GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE, I'LL
GIVE YOU 60 SECONDS ON THIS.
I WOULD REALLY APPRECIATE THAT.
YES WE'VE STOLEN AND LIED TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE ABOUT SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE.
YOU KNOW WHAT WE'RE NOT TELLING
THEM?
IT'S THEIR MONEY.
THIS IS NOT THE GOVERNMENT'S
MONEY.
THIS IS NOT ENTITLEMENT OR
WELFARE.
THIS IS MONEY THAT PEOPLE HAVE
CONFISCATED OUT OF THEIR
PAYCHECKS.
EVERY TIME THEY GOT MONEY THE
GOVERNMENT WENT IN AND TOOK
MONEY BEFORE THEY EVER SAW IT.
NOW TODAY CONGRESS DECIDED TO
TAKE ANOTHER $150 BILLION AWAY
FROM SOCIAL SECURITY SO THEY CAN
BORROW MORE MONEY.
THAT MAYBES NO SENSE TO ANYBODY.
THEY SAY WE'LL FIX THIS ONE DAY,
NO THEY'RE NOT.
IT'S LIKE A 400-POUND MAN SAYING
I'M GOING TO GO ON A DIET BUT
I'M GOING TO EAT A SIX-POUNDS
BAG OF KRISPY KREMES BEFORE I
DO.
LET'S QUIT BLAMING THE PEOPLE ON
SOCIAL SECURITY.
LET'S QUIT MAKING IT A PROBLEM
FOR THEM.
IT'S LIKE THEY'RE GETTING MUGGED
AND THEY'RE NOT SAYING WELL,
WE'LL MUG YOU SOME MORE YOU
OUGHT TO BE ABLE TO JUST GET
OVER IT.
GET USED TO IT.
NO, SIR.
WE NEED TO HONOR -- THIS IS THE
ONLY TIME I'VE HAD A CHANCE.
LET ME FINISH.
THIS IS A MATTER NOT OF MATH,
THIS IS A MATTER OF MORALITY.
IF THIS COUNTRY DOESN'T KEEP ITS
PROMISE TO SENIORS, THEN WHAT
PROMISE CAN THIS COUNTRY HOPE TO
BE TRUSTED TO KEEP?
AND THE FACT IS, NONE OF IT.
>> BY THE WAY, THE ONLY WAY --
THE ONLY WAY WE'RE GOING TO BE
MORAL.
THE ONLY WAY WE'RE GOING TO KEEP
OUR PROMISES TO SENIOR, TREAT
THEM LIKE ADULTS AND TELL THEM
THE TRUTH.
IT IS NOT THEIR MONEY ANYMORE,
MIKE, THEY STOLE IT.
LET'S NOT TRY TO GIVE THEM
PROMISES WE'LL BREAK.
>> WE'RE CURRENTLY NOT HAVING A
BEER --
>> BUT I'LL BUY YOU TEQUILA, OR
EVEN FAMOUS BROWNIES --
>> DO I GET TO RESPOND?
RESPOND ON THE DEBT LIMIT OR IN
ANSWER TO THE GOVERNOR,
WHICHEVER YOU CHOOSE.
>> WELL, SURE, THE DEAL IN
WASHINGTON IS AN EXAMPLE OF WHY
WASHINGTON IS BROKEN.
REPUBLICAN LEADERSHIP JOINED
WITH EVERY SINGLE DEMOCRAT TO
ADD $80 TRILLION TO OUR DEBT TO
DO NOTHING TO FIX THE PROBLEMS.
WE'RE GETTING INTO A GOOD
SUBSTANTIVE CHANGE.
BOTH CHRIS AND MIKE ARE RIGHT.
GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE IS
EXACTLY RIGHT.
WE NEED TO HONOR THE PROMISES
MADE TO OUR SENIORS.
FOR YOUNGER WORKERS, I'M 44
YEARS OLD.
IT'S HARD TO FIND SOMEBODY IN MY
GENERATION THAT THINKS SOCIAL
SECURITY WILL BE THERE FOR US.
WE CAN SAVE AND PRESERVE AND
STRENGTHEN SOCIAL SECURITY BY
MAKING NO CHANGES FOR SENIORS
BUT FOR YOUNGER WORKERS
GRADUALLY INCREASING THE
RETIREMENT AGE, CHANGING THE
RATE OF GROWTH SO THAT IT
MATCHES INFLATION AND CRITICALLY
ALLOWING YOUNGER WORKERS TO KEEP
A PORTION OF OUR TAX PAYMENTS IN
A PERSONAL ACCOUNT WE OWN AND WE
CONTROL AND CAN PASS ONTO OUR
KIDS.
>> 30 SECONDS, MR. HUCKABEE.
>> JOHN, WHEN I HEAR PEOPLE
TALKING ABOUT MEANS TESTING JUST
REMEMBER WHAT THAT MEANS.
IF WE MEANS TEST SOCIAL SECURITY
IT MEANS THAT THE GOVERNMENT
DECIDES WHETHER OR NOT I DESERVE
IT.
BUT A PERSON LIVES IN A
SEVEN-ROOM HOUSE DOES THE
GOVERNMENT GET TO SAY YOU DON'T
NEED SEVEN ROOMS, WE'RE GOING TO
TAKE TWO OF THEM AWAY.
FOLKS, THE GOVERNMENT HAS NO
BUSINESS STEALING FROM PEOPLE
PAYING THIS.
PEOPLE PAID THEIR MONEY, THEY
EXPECT TO HAVE IT.
THEY ARE DOING TO PEOPLE ON
SOCIAL SECURITY WHAT THEY HAVE
DONE TO OTHERS.
>> WE'LL TAKE A BREAK, THE
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE FOR THE
REPUBLICANS.
WE ARE LIVE IN BOULDER,
COLORADO, RIGHT HERE ON CNBC.
FOLKS, WE'LL GET RIGHT BACK INTO
THIS.
MR. TRUMP, LET'S TALK A LITTLE
BIT ABOUT BANKRUPTCIES.
YOUR ATLANTIC CITY CASINOS FILED
FOR BANKRUPTCY FOUR TIMES, IN
FACT, THEY WERE SAID TO BE
SERIAL FILERS.
YOU SAID YOU DID GREAT IN
ATLANTIC, BUT SOME OF THE
INDIVIDUALS, THE BONDHOLDERS AND
OTHERS DIDN'T FARE SO WELL.
BANKRUPTCY IS A BROKEN PROMISE.
WHY SHOULD THE VOTERS BELIEVE
THE PROMISES THAT YOU'RE TELLING
THEM NOW?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, VERY BIG
BUSINESSMEN, I COULD NAME THEM
HERE, I'M NOT GOING TO DO THIS
FOR A LOT OF REASONS.
BUT ALMOST ALL OF THEM, THEY
USED THE CHAPTER LLAWS, THE
BANKRUPTCY LAWS FOR THEIR OWN
BENEFIT.
BEFORE THAT, I WAS A VERY
SUCCESSFUL DEVELOPER AND
BUSINESSMAN.
ATLANTIC CITY HAS GONE BAD, AND
CHRIS WILL KNOW ABOUT THAT.
I AM NOT BLAMING HIM, BUT HE
WILL KNOW ABOUT THAT.
CEASARS', THE ROLL'S ROYCE, IN
BANKRUPTCY.
I USED IT TO MY ADVANTAGE FOR MY
FAMILY, I NEVER FILED
BANKRUPTCY.
BUT MANY, MANY PEOPLE DID.
WHAT HAPPENED WITH ATLANTIC CITY
IS VERY, VERY DISGRACEFUL.
HUNDREDS OF COMPANIES I HAVE
OPENED.
I HAVE USED IT THREE OR FOUR
TIMES.
CAME OUT GREAT.
BUT I GUESS I'M SUPPOSED TO COME
OUT GREAT.
THAT IS WHAT I COULD DO FOR THE
COUNTRY, WE OWE 19 TRILLION --
BOY AM I GOOD.
ATLANTIC CITY, HUNDREDS OF
COMPANIES THAT I HAVE OPENED
HAVE DOWN GREAT.
I BUILT A NET WORTH OF OVER $10
BILLION, AND I AM GLAD I DID IT.
I USED THE LAWS OF THE COUNTRY
TO MY BENEFIT, I'M SORRY.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
>> IN RECENT WEEKS, ANOTHER
PHARMACEUTICAL COMPANY HAS BEEN
ACCUSED OF PROFITEERING, FOR
DRAMATICALLY RAISING THE PROFITS
OF LIFE-SAVING DRUGS.
YOU HAVE SPENT A LIFETIME IN
MEDICINE.
HAVE THESE COMPANIES GONE TOO
FAR?
SHOULD THE GOVERNMENT BE
INVOLVED IN CONTROLLING SOME OF
THESE PRICE INCREASES?
>> WELL, THERE IS NO QUESTION
THAT SOME PEOPLE GO OVERBOARD
WHEN IT COMES TO TRYING TO MAKE
PROFITS AND THEY DON'T TAKE INTO
CONSIDERATION THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
WHAT WE HAVE TO START THINKING
ABOUT AS LEADERS, PARTICULARLY
IN GOVERNMENT, IS WHAT CAN WE DO
FOR THE AVERAGE AMERICAN?
AND YOU THINK ABOUT THE REASONS
THAT WE'RE HAVING SUCH
DIFFICULTY RIGHT NOW WITH OUR
JOB MARKET.
WELL, THE AVERAGE SMALL
MANUFACTURER, WHATEVER THEY'RE
MANUFACTURING, DRUGS OR
ANYTHING, IF THEY HAVE LESS THAN
50 EMPLOYEES THE AVERAGE COST IN
TERMS OF REGULATIONS IS $34,000
PER EMPLOYEE.
MAKES IT A WHOLE LOT EASIER FOR
THEM TO WANT TO GO SOMEWHERE
ELSE.
SO WHAT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
START DOING INSTEAD OF YOU KNOW
PICKING ON THIS GROUP OR THIS
GROUP IS WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
HAVE A MAJOR REDUCTION IN THE
REGULATORY INFLUENCE THAT IS
GOING ON.
THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT SUPPOSED
TO BE IN EVERY PART OF OUR LIVES
AND THAT IS WHAT IS CAUSING THE
PROBLEM.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON,
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> THERE IS A LOT OF RHETORIC
THAT SOME OF THE PEOPLE SHOULD
HAVE GONE TO JAIL FOR THE
FINANCIAL CRISIS.
BUT GENERAL MOTORS PAID MORE
THAN A BILLION DOLLARS IN FINES
AND SETTLEMENTS FOR ITS IGNITION
SWITCH DEFECT.
124 PEOPLE DIED AS A RESULT OF
THESE FAULTY SWITCHES.
NO ONE WENT TO JAIL.
AS A FORMER PROSECUTOR DO YOU
BELIEVE THE PEOPLE RESPONSIBLE
FOR THE SWITCH AND THE COVER-UP
BELONG BEHIND BARS?
>> YOU BET THEY DO.
AND IF I WERE THE PROSECUTOR
THAT IS EXACTLY WHERE THEY WOULD
BE.
THE FACT IS THAT THIS JUSTICE
DEPARTMENT UNDER THIS PRESIDENT
HAS BEEN A POLITICAL JUSTICE
DEPARTMENT, A JUSTICE DEPARTMENT
THAT DECIDES THEY WANT TO PICK
WHO THE WINNERS AND LOSERS ARE.
THEY LIKE GENERAL MOTORS, THEY
GIVE THEM A PASS.
THEY DON'T LIKE SOMEBODY LIKE
GENERAL PETRAEUS, THEY HAVE HIM
RESIGN IN DISGRACE.
JIM, YOU KNOW FULL WELL IN THE
SEVEN YEARS I WAS U.S. ATTORNEY
WE WENT AFTER PHARMACEUTICAL
COMPANIES AND AFTER PHARMACIES
THAT RIPPED OFF SHAREHOLDERS AND
WE WENT AFTER COMPANIES DOING
THINGS AGAINST THE LAW.
TO EXPAND ON DR. CARSON'S
ANSWER, WE HAVE ENOUGH LAWS.
WE DON'T NEED HILLARY CLINTON'S
PRICE CONTROLS FOR AGAIN, DOES
ANYBODY OUT THERE THINK THAT
GIVING WASHINGTON THE
OPPORTUNITY TO RUN THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY IS A
GOOD IDEA?
GIVEN HOW WELL THEY HAVE RUN THE
GOVERNMENT.
WHAT WE DO THOUGH, IF THERE IS
SOMEBODY THAT IS PRICE GOUGING,
I WILL MAKE AN ATTORNEY GENERAL
WHO WILL ENFORCE THE LAW AND
MAKE JUSTICE MORE THAN JUST A
WORD.
IT WILL BE A WAY OF LIFE.
>> THANK YOU, GREAT CHRISTIE.
>> SENATOR BUSH, IN A DEBATE
LIKE THIS FOUR YEARS AGO EVERY
REPUBLICAN RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
PLEDGED TO OPPOSE A BUDGET DEAL
CONTAINING ANY TAX INCREASE EVEN
IF IT HAD SPENDING CUTS TEN
TIMES AS LARGE.
YOU SAID YOU WOULD TAKE THAT
DEAL, STILL FEEL THAT WAY?
>> WELL, THE DEAL WAS DONE,
BARACK OBAMA GOT THE MASSIVE
INCREASES, AND THERE WAS MORE
SPENDING, MORE TAX INCREASING.
MORE REGULATION, AND NOW WE HAVE
TO ACCEPT 2%, THE NEW NORMAL FOR
ECONOMIC GROWTH.
THE NET RESULT IS THE MIDDLE
CLASS HAVE $2300 LESS IN THEIR
POCKETS THAN THE DAY THAT BARACK
OBAMA GOT ELECTED PRESIDENT.
AND NOW THEY SAY HILLARY CLINTON
PROPOSING A THIRD TERM OF
ECONOMIC POLICY FOR OUR COUNTRY.
WE NEED TO REVERSE THAT.
AND MY RECORD WAS ONE OF CUTTING
TAXES EACH AND EVERY YEAR.
YOU DON'T HAVE TO GUESS ABOUT IT
BECAUSE I ACTUALLY HAVE A
RECORD.
$19 BILLION OF TAX CUTS.
1.3 MILLION JOBS CREATED.
WE WERE ONE OF TWO STATES --
>> BUT TO THE POINT THAT YOU
MADE TO CONGRESS, IF YOU WERE
PRESIDENT AND YOU WERE OFFERED A
BIPARTISAN DEAL THAT HAD ONE
DOLLAR OF TAX INCREASES PER TEN
DOLLARS -- WOULD YOU TAKE IT?
>> YOU FIND ME A DEMOCRAT THAT
WILL CUT SPENDING TEN DOLLARS?
HECK, I'M A REPUBLICAN IN
CONGRESS THAT WOULD CUT SPENDING
IN TEN DOLLARS.
>> YOU DON'T WANT THEM TO FIT
YOU IN --
>> THE DEAL IS GONE, YOU FIND A
DEMOCRAT THAT IS FOR CUTTING
SPENDING TEN DOLLARS, I'LL GIVE
THEM A WARM KISS.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> MRS. FIORINA, IN 2010, WHILE
RUNNING FOR SENATE IN CALIFORNIA
YOU CALLED AN INTERNET SALES TAX
A BAD IDEA.
TRADITIONAL BRICK AND MORTAR
STORES OBVIOUSLY DISAGREED.
NOW THAT THE INTERNET SHOPPING
PLAYING FIELD HAS MATURED WHAT
WOULD BE A FAIR PLAN TO EVEN
THAT PLAYING FIELD?
>> YOU KNOW I WANT TO GO BACK
FOR A MOMENT TO WHAT WE JUST
TALKED ABOUT.
CRONY CAPITALISM IS ALIVE AND
WELL IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
WHAT IS CRONY CAPITALISM?
THAT IS WHAT HAPPENS WHEN
GOVERNMENT GETS SO BIG AND
POWERFUL THAT ONLY THE BIG AND
POWERFUL CAN HANDLE IT.
BUT WHY ARE THE PHARMACEUTICAL
COMPANIES CONSOLIDATING?
WHY ARE THEIR FIVE BIGGER WALL
STREET BANKS NOW, MORE THAN WHAT
WE USED TO HAVE.
WHEN THE GOVERNMENT GETS BIG AND
POWERFUL, THE GOVERNMENT FEELS
LIKE THEY NEED TO GET BIGGER AND
EVEN MORE POWERFUL TO DEAL WITH
ALL THAT CHAOS.
THIS IS HOW SOCIALISM STARTS.
GOVERNMENT CAUSES A PROBLEM, AND
THEN GOVERNMENT STEPS IN TO
SOLVE THE PROBLEM.
THIS IS WHY FUNDAMENTALLY WE
HAVE TO TAKE OUR GOVERNMENT
BACK.
THE STUDENT LOAN PROBLEM HAS
BEEN CREATED BY GOVERNMENT.
GOVERNMENT TRYING TO LEVEL THE
PLAYING FIELD BETWEEN INTERNET
AND BRICK AND MORTAR CREATES A
PROBLEM.
THE FCC JUMPING IN NOW SAYING
WE'RE GOING TO PUT 400 PAGES OF
REGULATION OVER THE INTERNET IS
GOING TO CREATE MASSIVE
PROBLEMS, BUT GUESS WHO PUSHED
FOR THAT REGULATION?
THE BIG INTERNET COMPANIES.
THIS IS WHAT IS GOING ON, BIG
AND POWERFUL.
USE BIG AND POWERFUL GOVERNMENT
TO THEIR ADVANTAGE.
IT'S WHY YOU SEE WALGREENS
BUYING RITE-AID.
WHY YOU SEE THE PHARMACEUTICALS
GETTING TOGETHER AND WHY YOU SEE
THE HEALTH INSURANCE COMPANIES
THE BANKS CONSOLIDATING.
MEANWHILE, SMALL BUSINESSES ARE
GETTING CRUSHED.
COMMUNITY-BASED BUSINESSES AND
FARMS ARE GOING OUT OF BUSINESS.
BIG GOVERNMENT SAVERS, THE
POWERFUL AND WEALTHY CRUSHES THE
OTHERS, IT'S WHY WE HAVE TO
BECOME MORE SIMPLE AND LEVEL THE
PLAYING FIELD BETWEEN BIG AND
POWERFUL AND SMALL AND
POWERLESS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU YOURSELF
HAVE SAID THAT YOU HAD ISSUES, A
LACK OF BOOKKEEPING SKILLS.
YOU ACCIDENTALLY INTER-MINGLED
YOUR MONEY.
IN TERMS OF ALL OF THAT, IT
RAISES THE QUESTION WHETHER YOU
HAVE THE MATURITY AND WISDOM TO
WORK WITH THE OFFICE?
>> I'M GOING TO TELL YOU THE
TRUTH.
I DIDN'T INHERIT ANY MONEY.
MY DAD WAS A BARTENDER, MY
MOTHER WAS A MAID.
THEY DIDN'T SAVE ENOUGH MONEY
FOR US TO GO TO SCHOOL.
I HAD TO WORK MY WAY THROUGH.
I TRIED TO EXPLAIN TO MY WIFE
WHY SOMEBODY NAMED SALLY MAY WAS
TAKING MONEY OUT OF OUR BANK KKT
ACCOUNTS.
WE OWN A HOME FOUR BLOCKS AWAY
FROM THE PLACE I GREW UP IN.
MY FOUR CHILDREN RECEIVED A GOOD
CHRISTIAN EDUCATION AND I'VE
BEEN ABLE TO SAVE FOR THEM TO GO
TO COLLEGE SO THEY NEVER HAVE TO
HAVE THE LOANS THAT I DID.
I'M NOT WORRIED ABOUT MY
FINANCES, I'M WORRIED ABOUT THE
FINANCES OF EVERYDAY AMERICANS
WHO STRUGGLE IN THE ECONOMY THAT
IS NOT MAKING GOOD JOBS.
THAT IS WHAT THIS DEBATE NEEDS
TO BE ABOUT.
THIS DEBATE NEEDS TO BE ABOUT
THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO ARE
STRUGGLING TO PROVIDE FOR THEIR
FAMILIES, THE BETTER FUTURE THAT
WE'VE ALWAYS SAID WHAT THIS
COUNTRY IS ABOUT.
>> I HAD A LOT OF STUDENT LOANS
WHEN I GOT OUT OF SCHOOL.
YOU HAVE HAD A WINDFALL.
>> I USED THE MONEY FROM MY BOOK
TO PAY OFF MY LOANS.
IT'S AVAILABLE IN PAPERBACK.
>> AND LIQUIDATED THAT
RETIREMENT ACCOUNT AFTER THAT
FACT.
IT COST YOU ABOUT $24,000.
>> AS I SAID WE'RE RAISING A
FAMILY IN THE 21st CENTURY.
ONE OF THE REASONS WHY MY TAX
PLAN IS A PRO-FAMILY TAX PLAN.
I DIDN'T READ ABOUT THIS IN A
BOOK.
I KNOW FOR A FACT HOW DIFFICULT
IT IS TO RAISE CHILDREN AND HOW
EXPENSIVE IT IS FOR WORKING
FAMILIES.
I MAKE A LOT MORE THAN THE
AVERAGE AMERICAN.
IMAGINE HOW IT IS FOR PEOPLE
MAKING 40, 50, $60,000 A YEAR
TRYING TO PROVIDE FOR THEIR
FAMILIES.
WE CAN'T AFFORD ANOTHER FOUR
YEARS OF THAT.
WHICH IS WHAT WE WILL GET IF WE
ELECT A BIG GOVERNMENT LIBERAL
LIKE HILLARY CLINTON TO THE
WHITE HOUSE.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH, YOU
TALKED ABOUT PROVIDING THE
EXPORT MEASURE, YOU CALL IT
CORPORATE WELFARE.
ONE OF THE LARGEST NEWSPAPERS IN
YOUR STATE READ AN EDITORIAL
SAYING IF THAT IS CORPORATE
WELFARE, WHAT DOES JOHN KASICH
CALL THE MILLIONS DOLED OUT TO
ATTRACT JOBS BY HIS DEVELOPMENT
DEVELOPMENT JOBS IN OHIO.
>> FIRST OF ALL WHEN WE TALK
ABOUT THE IMPORT, EXPORT BANK,
IT'S TIME TO CLEAN UP WELFARE,
IF WE'RE GOING TO REFORM WELFARE
FOR POOR PEOPLE WE OUGHT TO
REFORM IT FOR RICH PEOPLE.
SECONDLY, WE WENT TO A GAIN OF
47,000 JOBS TO THE POSITIVE.
OUR WAGES ARE GOING FASTER THAN
THE NATIONAL AVERAGE.
I CUT TAXES MORE THAN ANY
SITTING GOVERNOR IN THE STATE,
$5 BILLION, INCLUDING NO TAXES
ON SMALL BUSINESS AND KILLING
THE DEATH TAX.
I WANT TO GO BACK TO WHAT WE
TALKED ABOUT EARLIER, THIS
BUDGET DEAL IN WASHINGTON.
THIS IS THE SAME OLD STUFF SINCE
I LEFT.
YOU SPEND THE MONEY TODAY AND
THEN YOU HOPE YOU'RE GOING TO
SAVE MONEY TOMORROW.
I DON'T KNOW IF PEOPLE
UNDERSTAND BUT I SPENT A
LIFETIME WITH MY COLLEAGUES
GETTING US TO A FEDERAL BALANCED
BUDGET.
WE ACTUALLY DID IT.
AND I HAVE A ROAD MAP AND A PLAN
RIGHT NOW TO GET US THE BALANCE.
REFORMING ENTITLEMENTS, CUTTING
TAXES.
IF YOU REALLY WANT TO GET TO A
BALANCED BUDGET, YOU NEED TO
GROW YOUR ECONOMY AND CUT TAXES.
OUR INCENTIVES ARE TIGHT AND AT
THE END OF THE DAY WE MAKE SURE
THAT WE GAIN MORE FROM THE
CREATION OF JOBS THAN WHAT WE
LOSE.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
OHIO, ONE OF THE BEST GROWING
PLACES IN THE COUNTRY, I NOT
ONLY DID IT IN WASHINGTON, I DID
IT IN OHIO AND I'LL GO BACK TO
WASHINGTON AND THERE WILL BE NO
MORE SILLY DEALS, BEING WE'LL
HAVE A CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT
TO RETIRE THE MEMBERS TO DO
THEIR JOB.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, WORKING WOMEN
IN THIS COUNTRY STILL EARN JUST
77% OF WHAT MEN EARN.
YOU SAY YOU ARE SYMPATHETIC TO
OUR CAUSE.
ALSO YOU SAID THE DEMOCRATS
MOVED TO TRY AND CHANGE THIS,
THE POLITICAL SHOW VOTES.
I JUST WONDER WHAT YOU WOULD DO
AS PRESIDENT TO TRY TO TURN THIS
CAUSE?
>> WE HAVE TO TURN THE ECONOMY
AROUND.
THE DEMOCRATS' ANSWER IS MORE
GOVERNMENT CONTROL OVER WAGES
AND MORE EMPOWERING TRIAL
LAWYERS TO FILE LAWSUITS.
WHEN YOU LOOK AT WOMEN WORKING,
MY SISTER WAS A SINGLE MOM, BOTH
OF MY AUNTS WHO WERE A SINGLE
MOM.
MY MOM WAS A SINGLE MOM WHEN MY
FATHER LEFT US WHEN I WAS 3
YEARS OLD.
NOW, THANK GOD, MY FATHER WAS
INVITED TO A BIBLE STUDY AND
BECAME BORN AGAIN AND HE CAME
BACK TO MY MOM AND ME AND WE
WERE RAISED TOGETHER.
BUT THE STRUGGLE OF SINGLE MOMS
IS EXTRAORDINARY.
AND YOU KNOW, WHEN YOU SEE
HILLARY CLINTON AND BERNIE
SANDERS AND ALL THE DEMOCRATS
TALKING ABOUT WANTING TO ADDRESS
THE PLIGHT OF WORKING WOMEN, NOT
A ONE OF THEM MENTIONED THE FACT
THAT UNDER BARACK OBAMA 3.7
MILLION WOMEN HAVE ENTERED
POVERTY.
NOT A ONE OF THEM MENTIONED THE
FACT THAT UNDER BARACK OBAMA AND
THE BIG GOVERNMENT
MEDIAN WAGE TO WOMEN HAS DROPPED
$733.
THE THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS,
BIG GOVERNMENT BENEFITS THE
WEALTHY, THE LOBBYISTS, IT
BENEFITS THE GIANT CORPORATIONS
AND THE PEOPLE GETTING HAMMERED
ARE SMALL BUSINESSES.
THAT IS WHO I'M FIGHTING FOR.
THE PEOPLE THAT WASHINGTON
LEAVES BEHIND.
>> THANKS.
BECKY, IT IS THE HEIGHT OF
HYPOCRISY FOR MRS. CLINTON TO
TALK ABOUT BEING THE FIRST WOMAN
PRESIDENT WHEN EVERY SINGLE
POLICY SHE ESPOUSES, AND EVERY
SINGLE POLICY OF PRESIDENT OBAMA
HAS BEEN HUGELY BAD FOR WOMEN.
92%, 92% OF THE JOBS LOST DURING
BARACK OBAMA'S FIRST TERM
BELONGED TO WOMEN.
SENATOR CRUZ IS PRECISELY RIGHT.
THREE MILLION WOMEN HAVE FALLEN
INTO POVERTY UNDER THIS
ADMINISTRATION.
THE NUMBER OF WOMEN LIVING IN
EXTREME POVERTY IS THE HIGHEST
LEVEL ON RECORD.
I AM A CONSERVATIVE.
BECAUSE I KNOW OUR VALUES OUR
PRINCIPLES AND OUR POLICIES WILL
TRY TO LIFT EVERYONE UP.
MEN AND WOMEN.
>> THANK YOU, MRS. FIORINA.
>> DR. CARSON, WE KNOW YOU AS A
PHYSICIAN BUT WE WANTED TO ASK
YOU ABOUT YOUR INVOLVEMENT ON
CORPORATE BOARDS INCLUDING
COSTCO'S.
LAST YEAR, THE MARKET STUDY
CALLED THE BRAND THE NUMBER ONE
GAY-FRIENDLY BRAND IN AMERICA,
PARTLY BECAUSE OF ITS DOMESTIC
PARTNER BENEFITS.
WHY WOULD YOU CHOOSE TO RUN A
COMPANY THAT SEEMS TO HAVE A
COUNTER VIEW ON MATTERS?
>> I BELIEVE THAT OUR
CONSTITUTION PROTECTS EVERYBODY,
REGARDLESS OF THEIR SEXUAL OR
ORIENTATION, THERE IS NO REASON
WHY YOU CAN'T BE PERFECTLY FAIR
TO THE GAY COMMUNITY.
THEY SHOULD NOT AUTOMATICALLY
ASSUME BECAUSE YOU BELIEVE THAT
MARRIAGE IS BETWEEN ONE MAN AND
ONE WOMAN THAT YOU ARE A
HOMOPHOBE.
THIS IS A MYTH THAT THE LEFT
PERPETRATES ON OUR SOCIETY.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, WE
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE NOT EACH
OTHER'S ENEMY.
IT IS PEOPLE WHO ARE TRYING TO
DIVIDE US THAT ARE THE ENEMY.
WE NEED TO MAKE THAT CLEAR TO
EVERYBODY.
>> THIS IS A COMPANY THAT IS A
MAKER OF NUTRITIONAL
SUPPLEMENTS, WITH WHICH YOU HAD
A TEN-YEAR RELATIONSHIP.
THEY OFFERED CLAIMS THEY COULD
CURE AUTISM, CANCER, AND PAID
MILLIONS TO SETTLE A LAWSUIT IN
TEXAS.
YET YOUR INVOLVEMENT CONTINUED.
WHY?
>> WELL, THAT IS EASY TO ANSWER,
I DIDN'T HAVE AN INVOLVEMENT
WITH THEM.
THAT IS TOTAL PROPAGANDA.
THIS IS WHAT HAPPENS IN OUR
SOCIETY.
TOTAL PROPAGANDA, I DID A COUPLE
OF SPEECHES FOR THEM AND OTHER
PEOPLE.
THEY WERE PAID SPEECHES.
IT IS ABSOLUTELY ABSURD TO SAY I
HAD ANY KIND OF RELATIONSHIP
WITH THEM.
DO I TAKE THE PRODUCT?
YES, I THINK IT'S A GOOD
PRODUCT.
>> TO BE FAIR YOU WERE ON THE
HOME PAGE OF THEIR WEBSITE WITH
THE LOGO OVER YOUR SHOULDER.
>> IF SOMEBODY PUT ME ON THEIR
HOME PAGE THEY DID IT WITHOUT MY
PERMISSION.
>> DOES THAT NOT SPEAK TO YOUR
VETTING PROCESS OR PROCESS IN
ANY WAY --
>> NO, IT SPEAKS TO THE FACT I
DON'T KNOW --
>> THEY KNOW.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
ON CNBC, LIVE FROM BOULDER,
COLORADO, AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
COLORADO.
SENATOR MIKE HUCKABEE -- I MEAN,
EXCUSE ME, SENATOR RUBIO.
WIRED MAGAZINE RECENTLY CARRIED
THE HEADLINE, MARCO RUBIO WANTS
TO BE THE TECH INDUSTRY'S
SAVIOR.
IT TALKED ABOUT H 1-B, DESIGNED
FOR SKILLS THAT SILICON VALLEY
WANTS.
ONE SOURCE SAYS IT USES THIS TO
CUT WAGES
>> I AM THE ONLY PERSON IN
EITHER CAMPAIGN THAT -- I AM
PUTTING UP 100% OF MY OWN MONEY.
AND RIGHT NOW --
>> YOU BETTER GET RID OF THEM.
THEY ARE CAUSING A LOT OF
DECISIONS TO BE MADE BY SOME
VERY GOOD PEOPLE, AND I'M NOT
BLAMING THESE FOLKS, SOME VERY
GOOD PEOPLE ARE MAKING BAD
DECISIONS RIGHT NOW.
IF ANYTHING COMES OUT OF THESE
NASTY AND RIDICULOUS QUESTIONS,
YOU BETTER GET RID OF THE SUPER
PACs, BECAUSE THEY'RE CAUSING A
BIG PROBLEM NOT ONLY WITH THE
DISHONESTY BUT ALSO WITH THE BIG
LOBBYISTS AND SPECIAL INTERESTS.
>> YOU KNOW, MR. TRUMP --
>> JUST A FOLLOW UP --
>> YOU TALKED A LITTLE BIT ABOUT
MARCO RUBIO.
I THINK YOU CALLED HIM MARK
ZUCKERBERG'S PERSONAL SENATOR
BECAUSE HE WAS IN FAVOR --
>> I NEVER SAID THIS.
>> THIS WAS A WRONG ARTICLE --
>> ANOTHER GENTLEMAN IN FLORIDA
WHO HAPPENS TO BE A VERY NICE
GUY.
>> MY APOLOGIES --
>> IF I HAVE BEEN MENTIONED, CAN
I RESPOND?
>> SOME OF THE DEMOCRATS WHO
HAVE THE ULTIMATE MEDIA --
THEY'RE CALLED THE MAINSTREAM
MEDIA.
LAST WEEK, HILLARY CLINTON
ADMITTED SHE SENT E-MAILS TO HER
FAMILY SAYING HEY, THIS ATTACK
IN BENGHAZI WAS CAUSED BY AL
QAEDA-LIKE ELEMENTS.
SHE SPENT OVER A WEEK SAYING IT
WAS BECAUSE OF A VIDEO.
THE MAINSTREAM MEDIA IS SAYING
IT WAS THE GREATEST WEEK IN
HILLARY CLINTON'S CAMPAIGN.
IT WAS THE WEEK SHE GOT EXPOSED
AS A LIAR.
BUT SHE HAS HER SUPER PAC
HELPING HER OUT.
THE AMERICAN MAINSTREAM MEDIA.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, I WOULD LIKE
TO INTRODUCE MY COLLEAGUE WITH
COMMENTS AS WELL.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, LET'S FOCUS ON
OUR CENTRAL BANK, THE FEDERAL
RESERVE.
ARGUING FOR MORE TRANSPARENCY.
WHERE DO YOU WANT TO TAKE THAT?
GET CONGRESS INVOLVED IN
MONETARY POLICY OR IS IT TIME TO
SLAP THE FED BACK OR DOWN SIZE
THEM COMPLETELY?
WHAT ARE YOUR THOUGHTS?
>> I HAVE DEEP CONCERNS ABOUT
THE FED.
THE FIRST THING I THINK WE NEED
TO DO IS AUDIT THE FED.
I AM AN ORIGINAL CO-SPONSOR OF
RAND PAUL'S AUDIT THE FED
LEGISLATION.
THE SECOND THING WE NEED TO DO
IS LOOK AT THE BIPARTISAN
COMMISSION LOOKING BACK AT
RULES-BASED MONETARY POLICY AND
THE STAR CHAMBER THAT HAS BEEN
ENGAGING IN THIS INCREDIBLE
EXPERIMENT OF QUANTITATIVE
EASING, QE-1, 2, 3, INFINITI.
THE PEOPLE ASKING QUESTIONS,
IT'S INTERESTING IF YOU LOOK AT
WALL STREET, THE FED IS DOING
GREAT.
THE TOP 1% EARN A HIGHER SHARE
OF OUR INCOME SINCE 1928.
BUT IF YOU LOOK AT WORKING MEN
AND WOMEN.
AT A SINGLE MOM BUYING
GROCERIES, SHE SEES BURGER
PRICES GOING UP NEARLY 40%.
SHE SEES HER COSTS OF
ELECTRICITY GOING UP, SHE SEES
HER HEALTH INSURANCE GOING UP
AND LOOSE MONEY IS ONE OF THE
MAJOR PROBLEMS.
WE NEED SOUND MONEY.
AND I THINK THE FED SHOULD GET
OUT OF THE BUSINESS OF TRYING TO
JUICE OUR ECONOMY AND SIMPLY BE
FOCUSED ON SOUND MONEY AND
STABILITY.
IDEALLY TIED TO GOALS.
>> SAME QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
I WOULD LIKE TO THANK TED FOR
CO-SPONSORING MY BILL.
IT IS PRECISELY OF SOMEONE WITH
THE ARROGANCE OF BEN BERNANKE
WHO NOW CALLS US KNOW-NOTHINGS,
THAT IS PRECISELY WHY WE NEED TO
REWRITE THE FED.
IT IS A HUGE PROBLEM THAT AN
ORGANIZATION AS POWERFUL AS THE
FED COMES IN LOBBYING AGAINST
THEM BEING AUDITED ON THE HILL.
I WOULD PREVENT THEM LOBBYING
US.
I THINK WE SHOULD EXAMINE HOW
THE FED HAS REALLY BEEN PART OF
THE PROBLEM.
YOU WANT TO STUDY INCOME
INEQUALITY.
LET'S BRING THE FED FORWARD AND
TALK ABOUT FED POLICY AND HOW IT
CAUSES INCOME INEQUALITY.
LET'S ALSO BRING THE FED FORWARD
AND EXPLAIN HOW THEY CAUSED THE
HOUSING CRISIS AND MAKE THEM
EXPLAIN.
THE FED HAS BEEN A GREAT PROBLEM
IN OUR SOCIETY.
YOU NEED TO FREE UP INTEREST
RATES, INTEREST RATES OF THE
PRICE OF MONEY.
WE SHOULD NOT HAVE PRICE
CONTROLS ON THE PRICE OF MONEY.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
>> DR. CARSON.
>> GOVERNMENT SUBSIDIES, YOU SAY
IT INTERFERES WITH THE FREE
MARKET.
BUT YOU SAID YOU'RE IN FAVOR OF
PUTTING OIL SUBSIDIES IN FAVOR
OF ETHANOL PROCESSING.
ISN'T THAT JUST SWAPPING ONE
SUBSIDY FOR ANOTHER?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I WAS WRONG
ABOUT TAKING THE OIL SUBSIDY.
I HAVE STUDIED THAT ISSUE IN
GREAT DETAIL.
AND WHAT I HAVE CONCLUDED, THAT
THE BEST POLICY IS TO GET RID OF
ALL GOVERNMENT SUBSIDIES AND GET
THE GOVERNMENT OUT OF OUR LIVES
AND LET PEOPLE RISE AND FALL
BASED ON HOW GOOD THEY ARE.
AND ALL OF THIS TOO BIG TO FAIL
STUFF AND PICKING AND CHOOSING
WINNERS AND LOSERS.
THIS IS A BUNCH OF CRAP AND IS
REALLY CAUSING A GREAT DEAL OF
PROBLEMS FOR OUR SOCIETY RIGHT
NOW.
IT GOES BACK TO THE WHOLE
CONCEPT OF REGULATIONS, WHICH
ARE IN EVERYTHING.
THE REASON I HATE THEM SO MUCH
IS THAT EVERY SINGLE REGULATION
COSTS IN TERMS OF GOODS AND
SERVICES.
THAT GETS PASSED ON TO THE
PEOPLE.
WHO ARE THE PEOPLE AFFECTED BY
THAT?
MIDDLE CLASS AND POOR PEOPLE.
NOT THE RICH, BUT IT HURTS THE
POOR AND MIDDLE CLASS.
AND BERNIE SANDERS WILL TELL
THEM THAT IT'S BECAUSE OF THE
RICH.
WELL, I'LL TELL YOU SOMETHING
YOU CAN TAKE EVERYTHING FROM THE
TOP 1% AND APPLY IT TO OUR
FISCAL GAP AND YOU WON'T EVEN
MAKE A DIP IN IT.
>> GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE, YOU
DISCUSSED INCOME INEQUALITY,
SAYING SOME WALL STREET
EXECUTIVES SHOULD HAVE GONE TO
JAIL OVER THE ROLES THEY PLAYED
IN THE FINANCIAL CRISIS.
APART FROM YOUR TAX PLAN, ARE
THERE SPECIFIC STEPS YOU WOULD
REQUIRE TO REDUCE THE INCOME
INEQUALITY.
>> I DON'T THINK IT'S SO MUCH
ABOUT WHEN THE GOVERNMENT ORDERS
CORPORATIONS TO DO SOMETHING,
THAT IS PART OF THE PROBLEM, THE
BLIMP INCIDENT THAT HAPPENED
TODAY, A PERFECT EXAMPLE OF
GOVERNMENT.
BASICALLY A BAG OF GAS, CUT
LOOSE DESTROYED EVERYTHING IN
ITS PATH, LEFT THOUSANDS
POWERLESS BUT THEY COULDN'T GET
RID OF IT, BECAUSE WE HAD TOO
MUCH MONEY INVESTED SO WE HAD TO
KEEP IT.
THAT IS OUR GOVERNMENT TODAY.
WE SAW IT IN THE BLIMP.
THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT WE SAW.
SO LOOK, CORPORATIONS OUGHT TO
EXERCISE SOME RESPONSIBILITY.
WHEN CEO INCOME HAS RISEN 90%
ABOVE THE AVERAGE WORKER, WHEN
THE BOTTOM 90% OF THIS COUNTRY'S
ECONOMY HAS HAD STAGNANT WAGES
FOR THE PAST 40 YEARS, SOMEBODY
IS TAKING IT IN THE TEETH.
AND IT'S NOT THE FOLKS ON WALL
STREET.
I'M NOT ANTI-WALL STREET, BUT I
DON'T BELIEVE THE GOVERNMENT
OUGHT TO WEAR A TEAM JERSEY,
PICK WINNERS AND LOSERS.
THE GOVERNMENT OUGHT TO WEAR A
STRIPED SHIRT AND LET EVERYBODY
PLAY FAIRLY.
NOW, EVERYBODY HAS GONE OVER,
DON'T CUT ME OFF TOO QUICKLY,
BECKY.
>> OKAY, HOW ABOUT A FEW MORE
SECONDS?
>> WE NEED TO FOCUS ON WHAT
FIXES THIS COUNTRY.
ONE THING WE HAVE NOT TALKED
ABOUT TONIGHT.
WHY AREN'T WE TALKING ABOUT
INSTEAD OF CUTTING BENEFITS FOR
OLD PEOPLE, CUTTING BENEFITS FOR
SICK PEOPLE, WHY DON'T WE SAW
LET'S CURE THE FOUR BIG
COST-DRIVING DISEASES, DIABETES,
HEART DISEASE, CANCER AND
ALZHEIMER'S.
IF YOU DO THAT, YOU DON'T JUST
CHANGE THE ECONOMY, YOU
TRANSFORM THE LIVES OF MILLIONS
OF HURTING AMERICANS.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
>> GOSH I WOULD LOVE FOR US TO
TALK ABOUT SOMETHING LIKE THAT.
THANK YOU.
>> APPRECIATE IT.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, THE TAX REFORM
BILL THAT RONALD REAGAN SIGNED
CUT THE PERSONAL TAX RATE TO 28%
JUST LIKE YOUR PLAN DOES.
BUT PRESIDENT REAGAN TAXED
CAPITAL GAINS AT THE SAME RATE
WHILE YOU WOULD TAX THEM AT JUST
20%.
GIVEN THE PROBLEMS WE HAVE BEEN
DISCUSSING, GROWING GAP BETWEEN
RICH AND POOR, WHY WOULD YOU TAX
LABOR AT A HIGHER RATE THAN
INCOME FROM INVESTMENTS?
>> LOOK, THE SIMPLE FACT IS THAT
MY PLAN ACTUALLY GIVES THE
MIDDLE CLASS THE GREATEST BREAK,
$2,000 PER FAMILY.
IF YOU MAKE $40,000 A YEAR, A
FAMILY OF FOUR, YOU DON'T PAY
ANY INCOME TAX AT ALL.
MAKING IT SIMPLE, FOR PERSONAL
RATES IS EXACTLY WHAT WE NEED TO
DO.
YOU THINK ABOUT THE REGULATORY
COST AND TAX COST THAT IS WHY
SMALL BUSINESSES ARE CLOSING
RATHER THAN BEEN REFORMED IN OUR
COUNTRY.
WHAT I THINK ALL OF US ARE
SAYING IS OUR MONETARY POLICY,
THE TAX POLICY, REGULATORY
POLICY NEEDS TO BE RADICALLY
CHANGED SO WE CAN SUSTAIN HIGH
INCOME GROWTH.
UNDER BARACK OBAMA AND THE
PROPOSALS OF BERNIE SANDERS AND
HILLARY CLINTON AND OTHERS THEY
TRIED IT THEIR WAY.
IT FAILED MISERABLY.
WE NEED TO TAKE A NEW APPROACH
REFORMING HOW WE TAX AND
REFORMING THE REGULATIONS IN OUR
COUNTRY BEFORE IT'S TOO LATE.
>> AND THE TAX FOUNDATION, THEY
CONCLUDED THAT YOU GIVE NEARLY
TWICE AS MUCH OF A GAIN IN
AFTER-TAX INCOME TO THE TOP 1%
AS TO PEOPLE IN THE MIDDLE OF
THE INCOME SCALE.
SINCE YOU'RE THE CHAMPION OF
AMERICANS LIVING PAYCHECK TO
PAYCHECK, DON'T YOU HAVE THAT
BACKWARD?
>> NO, IN FACT, THE LARGEST IS
FOR THE PEOPLE AT THE LOWEST
SPECTRUM.
NUMBER ONE, YOU HAVE PEOPLE IN
THIS --
>> TAX FOUNDATION, JUST TO BE
CLEAR -- AFTER TAX --
>> YOU KNOW THE STORY, YOU HAD
TO GO BACK AND CORRECT IT.
>> NO, I DIDN'T.
>> SENATOR, THE TAX FOUNDATION
SAID AFTER TAX INCOME FOR THE
TOP 1% UNDER YOUR PLAN WOULD GO
UP 27.9%.
>> WELL, YOU'RE --
>> PEOPLE IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
INCOME SPECTRUM, ABOUT 15% --
>> BECAUSE THE MATH IS, 5% OF A
MILLION IS A LOT MORE THAN 5% OF
A THOUSAND.
SO IF SOMEBODY MAKES MORE MONEY,
IT WILL BE HIGHER.
BUT THE GREATEST GAINS
PERCENTAGE-WISE FOR PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO BE AT THE LOWER END OF
OUR PLAN.
HERE IS WHY, IN ADDITION TO A
GENERAL PERSONAL EXEMPTION,
WE'RE LOWERING TAXES ON SMALL
BUSINESS.
A LOT OF TAX BUSINESSES IN
AMERICA, THIS MAN PAYS ON HIS
PERSONAL RATE, PAYING HIGHER
THAN THE BIG DRY CLEANER DOWN
THE STREET, HE IS PAYING UNDER
HIS PERSONAL RATE.
UNDER MY PLAN, THEY WILL PAY A
FLAT RATE, A DRAMATIC DECREASE
FOR PEOPLE RUNNING THEIR OWN
BUSINESS.
ONE MORE POINT, IT IS THE MOST
PRO-GROWTH PLAN I CAN IMAGINE
BECAUSE IT DOESN'T TAX
INVESTMENTS AT ALL.
YOU KNOW WHY?
THE MORE YOU TAX SOMETHING THE
LESS YOU GET.
I WANT AMERICA TO BE THE BEST --
>> JOHN, COULD I FOLLOW UP ON
THIS?
>> WE'LL COME BACK AROUND.
I WANT TO GET TO GOVERNOR JOHN
KASICH.
WHAT ARE THE RULES ON WHO GETS
TO FOLLOW UP?
>> IT WAS AT THE MODERATOR'S
DISCRETION.
>> GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH, LET'S
TALK ABOUT -- LET'S TALK ABOUT
--
>> I WOULD LIKE TO MENTION
SOMETHING ABOUT MY TAX PLAN AND
HOW IT RELATES TO MY DISCUSSION.
>> SURE, 30 SECONDS.
>> ALL RIGHT, MUCH OF THE
DISCUSSION IS CENTERED OFFER
WHETHER OR NOT THE DIFFERENT TAX
PLANS HELP OR AFFECT THE MIDDLE
CLASS.
IN FACT, IT'S THE CHIEF ARGUMENT
BY DEMOCRATS AGAINST MANY OF THE
DIFFERENT FLAT TAX PROPOSALS.
MINE IS UNIQUE IN THE SENSE THAT
MY TAX PLAN ACTUALLY GETS RID OF
THE PAYROLL TAX AS WELL.
IT SHIFTS IT TO THE BUSINESS AND
IT WOULD ALLOW MIDDLE CLASS
PEOPLE TO GET A TAX CUT.
IF YOU JUST CUT THEIR INCOME TAX
THERE IS NOT MUCH INCOME TAX TO
CUT.
MINE ACTUALLY CUTS THE PAYROLL
TAX AND I THINK IT WOULD SPREAD
THE TAX CUT ACROSS ALL
SOCIOECONOMIC STRUCTURES AND
WOULD ALLOW IT TO BE BROADLY
SUPPORTED IN AN ELECTION.
>> HIS PLAN IS A GOOD PLAN AND I
WILL NOTE THAT MY 10% PLAN ALSO
ELIMINATES THE PAYROLL TAX,
ELIMINATES THE DEATH TAX,
ELIMINATES THE BUSINESS TAX --
AND 10% FLAT RATE --
>> WE'RE GOING TO GO TO GOVERNOR
JOHN KASICH NOW.
>> PERSONAL RATE OF ANY
CANDIDATE UP HERE HAS.
IT WOULD HELP EVERY CITIZEN TO
FILL OUT THEIR TAXES ON A POST
CARD SO WE CAN ELIMINATE THE
IRS.
>> OKAY, THANK YOU, SENATOR.
GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH, LET'S TALK
ABOUT MARIJUANA.
WE'RE BROADCASTING FROM COLORADO
WHICH HAS SEEN $150 MILLION IN
NEW REVENUE FOR THEr STATE SIN
LEGALIZING LAST YEAR.
GOVERNOR HICKENLOOPER WAS NOT A
BIG FAN OF LEGALIZATION BUT HE
SAYS THE PEOPLE WHO USED TO
SMOKE IT ARE STILL SMOKING IT,
JUST PAYING STAC TAXES NOW.
>> WE'RE RUNNING A $2 BILLION
SURPLUS, WE'RE NOT HAVING A
SURPLUS RIGHT NOW.
DRUGS IS ONE OF THE GREATEST
SCOURGE IN THIS COUNTRY.
I SPENT TIME TO TRY TO REIN IN
THE PROBLEM OF OVERDOSES.
IT GOES ON AND ON, WE CAN DO A
WHOLE SHOW ON THAT.
I WANT TO GO BACK TO THIS ISSUE
OF INCOME INEQUALITY.
MY PROGRAM WOULD MOVE THE 104
PROGRAMS OF THE FEDERAL
DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION INTO
FOUR BLOCK GRANTS AND SEND THEM
BACK TO THE STATES BECAUSE
INCOME INEQUALITY IS DRIVEN BY A
LACK OF SKILLS WHEN KIDS DON'T
GET WHAT THEY NEED TO BE ABLE TO
COMPETE AND WIN IN THIS COUNTRY.
THE FACT IS IN ORDER TO GET THIS
ECONOMY MOVING AGAIN I CALL FOR
FREEZING REGULATIONS FOR A YEAR.
EXCEPT FOR THE PROBLEM OF PUBLIC
SAFETY.
I BELIEVE THAT WE NEED TO CUT
THESE TAXES DOWN.
WE NEED TO BE ON A ROAD MAP TO
BALANCING THE BUDGET AND WE NEED
TO SEND POWER, MONEY AND
INFLUENCE.
THE WELFARE DEPARTMENT, THE
EDUCATION DEPARTMENT.
JOB TRAINING, INFRASTRUCTURE,
MEDICAID, ALL OF IT OUT OF
WASHINGTON BACK TO THE STATES SO
WE CAN RUN THESE PROGRAMS FROM
WHERE WE LIVE TO THE TOP, NOT A
ONE SIZE FITS ALL MENTALITY THAT
THEY HAVE IN WASHINGTON.
AND THAT WILL GET TO THE NUB OF
OPPORTUNITY FOR OUR CHILDREN AND
AN ABILITY TO SEE WAGES RISE.
AGAIN, ONE MORE TIME IN OHIO,
OUR WAGES ARE GROWING FASTER
THAN THE NATIONAL AVERAGE.
WE'VE CUT TAXES, BALANCED
BUDGETS, CHANGED THE REGULATORY
ENVIRONMENT.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR, YOU WANT
TO FIX AMERICA?
THIS IS THE
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
UNIVERSITY OF COLORADO AND THE
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE RIGHT HERE
ON CNBC.
MR. TRUMP, I'M GOING BACK TO AN
ISSUE WE TALKED ABOUT BEFORE.
I FOUND THAT I READ BEFORE IT
WAS FROM THE DONALD J. TRUMP
WEBSITE.
AND IT SAYS THAT AGAIN, MARK
INTO THIS COUNTRY LEGALLY.
YOU KNOW WHAT, YOU CAN CALL IT
ANYTHING YOU WANT.
VISAS, WORK PERMITS, I CREATED
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF JOBS.
ACTUALLY, WITH ALL DUE RESPECT
TO SOME OF THESE PEOPLE WHO I
LIKE A LOT.
I WILL CREATE MANY MILLIONS OF
JOBS IF I'M GIVEN THE
OPPORTUNITY TO BE PRESIDENT.
AS FAR AS MARK IS CONCERNED AND
AS FAR AS THE VISAS ARE
CONCERNED, IF WE NEED PEOPLE,
THAT IS FINE.
THEY HAVE TO COME IN TO THIS
COUNTRY LEGALLY.
WE HAVE A COUNTRY OF BORDERS.
WE HAVE A COUNTRY OF LAWS.
WE HAVE TO OBEY THE LAWS.
IT'S FINE OF THEY COME IN, BUT
THEY HAVE TO COME IN LEGALLY.
>> THANK YOU, SIR.
>> THAT WAS --
>> YOU GET 30 SECONDS.
>> LOOK, IN ADDITION TO WHAT
DONALD IS SAYING, WE ALSO NEED
TO TALK ABOUT THE LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM FOR PERMANENT
RESIDENTS.
TODAY WE HAVE A LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SITUATION THAT IS
LARGELY BASED ON IF YOU HAVE
FAMILY HERE.
IN 2016 WE HAVE A VERY DIFFERENT
ECONOMY.
OUR LEGALIZATION SYSTEM HAS TO
BE BASED ON MERIT BASE.
WHAT SKILLS YOU HAVE AND WHETHER
OR NOT YOU'RE COMING HERE TO NOT
JUST LIVE IN AMERICA, BUT BE AN
AMERICAN.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU SAID YOU HAVE
A SPECIAL PERMIT TO CARRY A GUN
IN NEW YORK?
>> YES.
>> AFTER THE MASS SHOOTING IN
OREGON, YOU SAID BY THE WAY IT
WAS A GUN-FREE ZONE.
IF YOU HAD A COUPLE OF TEACHERS
WITH GUNS, YOU WOULD HAVE BEEN A
LOT BETTER OFF.
>> OR SOMEBODY WITH GUNS.
>> WOULD YOU FEEL BETTER IF YOUR
EMPLOYEES BROUGHT THEM TO WORK?
>> YES, I MIGHT FEEL MORE
COMFORTABLE.
I WOULD SAY THAT I WOULD.
AND I HAVE A PERMIT, WHICH IS
VERY UNUSUAL IN NEW YORK, A
PERMIT TO CARRY.
AND I DO CARRY ON OCCASION.
SOMETIMES A LOT.
BUT I LIKE TO BE UNPREDICTABLE.
SO --
>> AND ARE YOU CARRYING RIGHT
NOW?
>> BY THE WAY, UNLIKE OUR
COUNTRY WHERE WE'RE TOTALLY
PREDICTABLE AND THE ENEMY,
WHETHER IT'S ISIS OR ANYBODY
ELSE, THEY KNOW EXACTLY WHAT
WE'RE DOING BECAUSE WE HAVE THE
WRONG LEADERSHIP.
BUT I FEEL THAT THE GUN-FREE
ZONES AND YOU KNOW WHEN YOU SAY
THAT, THAT IS TARGET PRACTICE
FOR THE SICKOS, AND FOR THE
MENTALLY ILL.
THAT IS TARGET -- THEY LOOK
AROUND FOR GUN-FREE ZONES.
AND WE COULD GIVE YOU ANOTHER
EXAMPLE.
THE MARINES, THE ARMY, THESE
WONDERFUL SIX SOLDIERS KILLED.
TWO OF THEM WERE THE MOST HIGHLY
DECORATED.
THEY WERE NOT ALLOWED ON A
MILITARY BASE TO HAVE GUNS AND
SOMEBODY SHOT THEM AND KILLED
THEM.
I CAN TELL YOU THERE WOULDN'T
HAVE BEEN MUCH DAMAGE.
I THINK GUN-FREE ZONES ARE A
FEEDING FRENZY FOR SICKOS.
>> WOULD YOU CHANGE POLICIES?
>> I WOULD CHANGE THEM.
>> ALL RIGHT, THANK YOU.
>> JOHN?
>> GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE, YOU
WROTE ABOUT THE HUGE DIVIDE AND
VALUES BETWEEN MIDDLE AMERICA
AND THE BIG COASTAL CITIES LIKE
NEW YORK AND LOS ANGELES.
AS A POLITICIAN, YOU KNOW
PRESIDENTS NEED THE MORAL
AUTHORITY TO BRING THE ENTIRE
COUNTRY TOGETHER.
LEADING REPUBLICAN CANDIDATE
WHEN YOU LOOK AT THE AVERAGE
NATIONAL POLLS RIGHT NOW IS
DONALD TRUMP.
WHEN YOU LOOK AT HIM DO YOU SEE
SOMEBODY LIKE HIM WITH THE MORAL
AUTHORITY TO UNITED THE COUNTRY?
>> YOU KNOW -- THERE ARE A FEW
QUESTIONS I GOT, THE LAST THING
I NEED IS TO GIVE HIM MORE TIME.
I LOVE DONALD TRUMP, HE IS A
GOOD MAN.
I'M WEARING A TRUMP TIE TONIGHT.
GET OVER THAT ONE.
NOW -- MADE IN MEXICO, I DON'T
KNOW --
>> MADE IN CHINA?
>> I HAVE NO IDEA.
>> SUCH A NASTY QUESTION, BUT
THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> YOU'RE WELCOME.
>> LET ME TELL YOU, DONALD TRUMP
WOULD BE A BETTER PRESIDENT
EVERY DAY OF THE WEEK AND TWICE
ON SUNDAY RATHER THAN HILLARY
CLINTON.
I HAVE SPENT A LIFETIME IN
POLITICS FIGHTING THE CLINTON
MACHINE.
YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT WHAT
WE'RE GOING TO BE UP AGAINST
NEXT YEAR.
I'M THE ONLY GUY THIS, YOU KNOW
HOW THEY HAVE THE ONLY GUY THIS,
ONLY GUY THAT.
LET ME TELL YOU WHAT I'M THE
ONLY GUY WITH, THE ONLY GUY
CONSISTENTLY FOUGHT THE CLINTON
MACHINE EVERY ELECTION I WAS IN
OVER THE PAST 26 YEARS.
AND NOT ONLY DID I FIGHT THEM
BUT I BEAT THEM.
SOMEBODY SAYS I'M A FIGHTER.
WELL, I WANT TO KNOW DID YOU
WIN?
WELL, I DID.
NOT ONLY DID I FIGHT THEM AND
WIN I LIVED TO TELL ABOUT IT AND
STANDING ON THIS STAGE TONIGHT
AS EVIDENCE OF THAT AND I THINK
THAT OUGHT TO BE WORTH
SOMETHING.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> I WILL TELL YOU, YOU WANT TO
TALK ABOUT MORAL AUTHORITY.
LET'S TALK ABOUT SOMETHING THAT
HAPPENED THIS WEEK IN THE NEWS.
YOU KNOW, THE FBI DIRECTOR, THE
PRESIDENT'S APPOINTED FBI
DIRECTOR HAS SAID THIS WEEK THAT
BECAUSE OF A LACK OF SUPPORT FOR
POLITICIANS LIKE THE PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES THAT POLICE
OFFICERS ARE AFRAID TO GET OUT
OF THEIR CARS AND ENFORCE THE
LAW.
HE SAYS, THE PRESIDENT'S
APPOINTEE, THAT CRIME IS GOING
UP BECAUSE OF THIS.
AND WHEN THE PRESIDENT GETS UP
TO SPEAK ABOUT THIS, DOES HE
STAND FOR LAW ENFORCEMENT?
DOES HE SPEAK FOR LAW
ENFORCEMENT?
NO, HE DOESN'T, I'LL TELL YOU
WHAT.
THE NUMBER ONE JOB OF THE
PRESIDENT IS TO PROTECT THE
SAFETY AND SECURITY OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
THIS PRESIDENT HAS FAILED.
WHEN I'M IN THE OVAL OFFICE,
POLICE OFFICERS WILL KNOW THEY
HAVE THE SUPPORT OF THE POLICE
OFFICERS.
THAT IS REAL MORAL AUTHORITY WE
NEED IN THE OFFICE.
>> DON'T FORGET MY COLLEAGUE,
SHARON EPPERSON.
>> YOU WERE THE CEO OF A LARGE
CORPORATION THAT OFFERED 401(k)
TO THEIR EMPLOYEES.
MORE THAN HALF OF AMERICANS
DON'T HAVE ACCESS TO RETIREMENT
PLANS.
THAT INCLUDES THE GROWING RANKS
OF PART-TIME DRIVERS AND UBER
DRIVERS, AND BUSINESS PEOPLE.
SHOULD THE GOVERNMENT HELP TO
SET UP RETIREMENT PLANS FOR
THESE WORKERS?
>> NO, THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
SHOULD NOT PLAY A LARGER ROLE.
LOOK, EVERY TIME THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT GETS ENGAGED IN
SOMETHING IT GETS WORSE.
AND THEN THE GOVERNMENT STEPS IN
TO TRY TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM AND
WE GET A LITTLE FURTHER DOWN TO
THAT PROGRESSION THAT HILLARY
CLINTON IS TALKING ABOUT.
COMPANIES SHOULD, IF THEY WANT
TO ATTRACT THE BEST WORKERS
PROVIDE A GOOD SET OF BENEFITS.
BUT HONESTLY, IF YOU'RE A SMALL
BUSINESS OWNER TODAY YOU ARE
BEING CRUSHED.
WE HAVE 400,000 SMALL BUSINESSES
FORMING EVERY YEAR IN THE
COUNTRY.
HOW GREAT IS THAT?
THEY ARE EMPLOYING THEMSELVES
AND POTENTIALLY EMPLOYING
OTHERS.
THE BAD NEWS IS, WE HAVE 470,000
GOING OUT OF BUSINESS EVERY
YEAR.
AND WHY?
THEY CITE OBAMACARE.
>> YOU WOULDN'T AGREE TO START
401(k) BUSINESSES FOR EMPLOYEES?
>> I THINK IT'S A WONDERFUL
IDEA.
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SHOULD
NOT BE IN A LOT OF THINGS.
THERE IS NO CONSTITUTIONAL ROLE
FOR THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IN
SETTING UP RETIREMENT PLANS.
THERE IS NO CONSTITUTIONAL LAW
FOR THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO BE
SETTING MINIMUM WAGES.
THE MORE THE GOVERNMENT GETS
ENGAGED IN THE ECONOMY, THE
SLOWER THE ECONOMY BECOMES.
THE MORE THE GOVERNMENT GETS
ENGAGED IN THE ECONOMY, THE MORE
THE BIG, THE POWERFUL, THE
WEALTHY AND THE WELL-CONNECTED
ARE ADVANTAGED.
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, I WANT TO TURN MY
ATTENTION TO YOU NOW, GOVERNOR
JOHN KASICH.
MOST PEOPLE CAN'T GET A COLLEGE
DEGREE WITHOUT GOING INTO DEBT.
OVER 40 MILLION AMERICANS HAVE
STUDENT LOANS AND MANY OF THEM
CANNOT PAY THEM BACK.
THIS COUNTRY HAS OVER $100
BILLION IN STUDENT LOAN
DEFAULTS.
THAT IS BILLION, WITH A B.
WHAT WILL YOU DO TO MAKE SURE
THAT STUDENTS, THEIR FAMILIES,
TAXPAYERS, WON'T FEEL THE
ECONOMIC IMPACT OF THIS BURDEN
FOR GENERATIONS?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL IN OHIO
WE'RE CHANGING THE WHOLE SYSTEM.
UNIVERSITIES WILL NOT GET PAID
ONE DIME UNLESS THE STUDENT
GRADUATES OR COMPLETES A COURSE.
SECONDLY, YOU CAN BE IN HIGH
SCHOOL AND COMPLETE ALMOST AN
ENTIRE FIRST YEAR BEFORE YOU GO
TO COLLEGE AND GET CREDIT TO DO
THAT.
AND OF COURSE, IN ADDITION TO
THAT WE ARE WORKING NOW TO GO
AFTER THE COST DRIVERS IN OUR
UNIVERSITIES.
AND LET ME GIVE YOU AN EXAMPLE.
UNIVERSITIES TODAY HAVE SO MANY
NON-ACADEMIC ASSETS.
AT OHIO STATE THEY SOLD THE
PARKING GARAGE AND THE PARKING
LOT AND THEY GOT $500 MILLION
BECAUSE THEY SHOULD NOT BE IN
THE PARKING LOT BUSINESS.
THEY SHOULD NOT BE IN THE DINING
BUSINESS OR THE DORM BUSINESS.
AND OF COURSE, WE NEED TO TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF ON-LINE EDUCATION
TO REDUCE THESE COSTS AND BEGIN
TO DIS-INTERMEDIATE THE COST.
FOR THOSE WHO HAVE THESE BIG
HIGH COSTS I THINK WE CAN
SERIOUSLY LOOK AT AN IDEA OF
WHERE YOU CAN DO PUBLIC SERVICE.
I MEAN LEGITIMATE PUBLIC SERVICE
AND BEGIN TO PAY OFF SOME OF
THAT DEBT THROUGH THE PUBLIC
SERVICE THAT YOU DO.
AND IN THE MEANTIME, IT MAY
INSPIRE US TO CARE MORE ABOUT
OUR COUNTRY, MORE ABOUT
OURSELVES.
THIS IS A BIG MORAL ISSUE IN
AMERICA.
LIVING A LIFE BIGGER THAN
YOURSELF AND BEING A CENTER OF
HEALING AND JUSTICE AND PEOPLE
CAN LEARN IT THROUGH PUBLIC
SERVICE.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU, HIGHER
EDUCATION --
>> WE DON'T NEED THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT TO BE INVOLVED.
BECAUSE WHEN THEY DO WE CREATE A
$1.2 TRILLION DEBT.
IN FLORIDA WE HAVE THE LOWEST
IN-STATE TUITION OF ANY STATE.
BECAUSE THERE IS ACCOUNTABILITY,
AS JOHN SAID.
LET THE STATES DO THIS.
YOU WILL CREATE A MUCH BETTER
GRADUATION RATE AND WOULDN'T
GIVE THE NEXT GENERATION THE
RECOURSE ON THEIR BACK.
>> IT IS BROKEN, IT IS NOT
WORKING.
>> GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH, WE HAVE
TO MOVE ON.
>> WE CAN LET THEM -- ELIMINATE
SOME OF THEIR DEBT.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, DAILY FANTASY
SPORTS HAS BECOME A PHENOMENON
IN THIS COUNTRY.
IT WILL AWARD BILLIONS IN PRIZE
MONEY THIS YEAR.
TO PLAY YOU HAVE TO ASSESS YOUR
ODDS, WAIT FOR A SITUATION THAT
IS OUT OF YOUR CONTROL.
ISN'T THAT THE DEFINITION OF
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT --
>> I'M 7 AND 0 IN MY FANTASY
LEAGUE.
GRONKOWSKI IS STILL GOING
STRONG.
MARCO IS MY QUARTERBACK, HE WAS
18 FOR 19 LAST WEEK.
SO I'M DOING GREAT, BUT WE'RE
NOT GAMBLING.
THIS IS SOMETHING THAT NEEDS TO
BE LOOKED AT IN TERMS OF
REGULATION.
EFFECTIVELY IT IS DAY TRADING.
WHEN YOU HAVE INSIDER
INFORMATION WHICH IS APPARENTLY
THE CASE WHERE PEOPLE USE THAT
INFORMATION AND USE BIG DATA TO
TRY TO TAKE ADVANTAGE OF IT,
THERE HAS TO BE SOME REGULATION.
IF THEY CAN'T REGULATE
THEMSELVES, THEN THE NFL NEEDS
TO LOOK AT MOVING AWAY FROM
THEM.
I HAVE NO CLUE IF THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT IS THE PROPER PLACE,
MY INSTINCT IS TO SAY HELL NO,
JUST ANYTHING ABOUT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT.
>> ARE RE--
>> WE ARE TALKING ABOUT GETTING
GOVERNMENT INVOLVED IN FANTASY
FOOTBALL?
WAIT A SECOND, WE HAVE $19
TRILLION IN DEBT, PEOPLE OUT OF
WORK, ISIS AND AL QAEDA
ATTACKING US AND WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT FANTASY FOOTBALL?
CAN WE STOP?
>> HOW ABOUT?
-- LET'S GET THE GOVERNMENT TO
PROTECT OUR PEOPLE AND SUPPORT
THE AMERICAN FAMILY.
ENOUGH ON FANTASY FOOTBALL.
LET PEOPLE PLAY, WHO CARES?
>> I WANT TO GO BACK TO THE
ISSUES -- IF I MAY --
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE YOU SAID
SOMETHING THAT MANY IN YOUR
PARTY DO NOT BELIEVE, WHICH IS
THAT CLIMATE CHANGE IS
UNDENIALABLE.
>> WE DON'T DO WHAT JOHN KERRY,
AND HILLARY CLINTON AND BARACK
OBAMA WANT TO DO, WHICH THEIR
SOLUTION IS PUT MORE TAXES ON
AND THEY WILL FIX IT.
THERE IS NO EVIDENCE THEY CAN
FIX ANYTHING IN WASHINGTON, D.C.
WHAT WE SHOULD DO IS INVEST IN
ALL TYPES OF ENERGY, JOHN.
>> YOU MEAN GOVERNMENT?
>> NO, JOHN, DO YOU WANT ME TO
ANSWER OR DO YOU WANT TO ANSWER?
BECAUSE -- I GOT TO TELL YOU THE
TRUTH, EVEN IN NEW JERSEY WHAT
YOU'RE DOING IS CALLED RUDE.
SO -- WE LAID OUT A NATIONAL
ENERGY CLIMATE -- I TELL YOU,
YOU COULD WIN A BET AT A BAR
TONIGHT SINCE WE'RE TALKING
ABOUT FANTASY FOOTBALL, YOU TALK
ABOUT THE TOP THREE STATES,
CALIFORNIA, ARIZONA, THEY'RE
EASY, BUT NEW JERSEY, WE WORK
WITH THE PRIVATE SECTOR TO MAKE
SOLAR ENERGY AFFORDABLE TO
INDIVIDUALS IN OUR STATE.
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE WE DO
EVERYTHING WE CAN FOR ALL KINDS
OF ENERGY.
NATURAL GAS, ALSO WHERE IT'S
AFFORDABLE SOLAR, WIND IN IOWA
IS VERY AFFORDABLE AND IT MAKES
SENSE.
THAT IS WHERE WE DEAL WITH
GLOBAL WARMING, CLIMATE CHANGE,
NOT THROUGH GOVERNMENT
INTERVENTION, AND FOR GOD SAKES,
DON'T SEND WASHINGTON MORE
MONEY.
>> AND IN 1960s, RONALD REAGAN
WARNED THAT IT WOULD LEAD TO
SOCIALISM.
CONSIDERING THE MOUNTING COST OF
MEDICARE, DO YOU LIKE OR OPPOSE
IT EXPLOSIVE.
>> THE QUESTION IS ALWAYS, WHAT
WORKS BETTER, THE PRIVATE
MARKETPLACE OR GOVERNMENT?
AND WHAT DISTRIBUTES GOODS
BETTER?
IT ALWAYS SEEMS TO BE THAT THE
PRIVATE MARKETPLACE DOES A
BETTER JOB?
IS THERE A BETTER PLACE FOR
SOCIAL SECURITY?
YOU ACKNOWLEDGE THAT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT DOESN'T DO A VERY
GOOD JOB OF IT.
THE MAIN PROBLEM WITH MEDICARE,
THE AVERAGE PERSON PAYS INTO
TAXES OVER THEIR WHOLE LIFETIME,
ABOUT $100,000.
BUT THE AVERAGE PERSON TAKES OUT
ABOUT $350,000.
WE HAVE AN ENORMOUS MISMATCH
BECAUSE WE HAVE SMALLER AND
SMALLER FAMILIES.
WHEN PEOPLE ASK WHOSE FAULT IS
IT THAT MEDICARE AND SOCIAL
SECURITY IS OUT OF MONEY?
I SAY LOOK, IT'S NOT
REPUBLICANS' FAULT, IT'S YOUR
GRANDPARENTS' FAULT FOR HAVING
TOO MANY KIDS.
AFTER THE WAR WE HAD ALL OF
THESE KIDS, BABY BOOMERS.
WE USED TO HAVE 16 WORKERS FOR
ONE RETIREE, NOW YOU HAVE THREE
WORKERS FOR ONE RETIREE.
IT IS NOT WORKING.
I HAVE A BILL TO FIX SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE.
FOR BOTH OF THEM, YOU'RE GOING
TO HAVE TO RAISE THE AGE.
IF YOU'RE NOT WILLING TO RAISE
THE AGE YOU'RE NOT SERIOUS ABOUT
EITHER ONE OF THEM.
>> WE'LL TAKE A BREAK.
WE WANT TO SAVE TIME FOR
>>> WELCOME BACK TO BOULDER,
COLORADO, AND THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE RIGHT HERE
ON CNBC.
GOVERNOR MIKE HUCKABEE, YOU
WANTED TO RESPOND TO SOME OF THE
POINTS THAT SENATOR RAND PAUL
WAS JUST MAKING IN RESPONSE TO
MEDICARE BENEFITS.
>> 85% OF THE COST OF MEDICARE
IS CHRONIC DISEASE.
THE FACT IS IF WE DON'T ADDRESS
WHAT IS COSTING SO MUCH WE CAN'T
THROW ENOUGH MONEY AT THIS.
AND IT'S WHY I CONTINUED TO
FOCUS ON THE FACT WE NEED TO
DECLARE WAR ON THE FOUR BIG COST
DRIVERS.
BECAUSE 80% OF ALL MEDICAL COST
S IN THIS COUNTRY ARE CHRONIC
DISEASE.
UNTIL WE DEAL WITH THE HEALTH OF
AMERICANS AND DO WHAT WE DID
WITH POLIO WHEN I WAS A KID, WE
ERADICATED IT.
YOU WANT TO FIX MEDICARE?
FOCUS ON THE DISEASES THAT ARE
COSTING US THE TRILLIONS OF
DOLLARS, ALZHEIMER'S, DIABETES,
HEART DISEASE AND CANCER.
ERADICATE THOSE AND YOU FIX
MEDICARE.
AND YOU FIX AMERICA, ITS ECONOMY
AND YOU'VE MADE PEOPLE'S LIVES A
HECK OF A LOT BETTER.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> THE GOVERNOR IS RIGHT, WE
ALSO NEED TO REFORM MEDICARE AND
SOCIAL SECURITY.
WE CAN'T JUST ALLOW IT TO
CONTINUE IN ITS CURRENT PATH THE
WAY HILLARY CLINTON WANTS US TO
DO.
BECAUSE THERE WILL BE MAJOR
REDUCTIONS IN BENEFITS IF WE DO
NOTHING.
I HAVE A CONCRETE MAN TO DO JUST
THAT.
WHICH ALLOWS PEOPLE TO KEEP FHAs
THAT ENCOURAGE SAVINGS.
THAT ALLOWS FOR PEOPLE RETIRING
WITH SOCIAL SECURITY TO BE ABLE
TO GET A MINIMUM OF 125% OF THE
POVERTY LEVEL SO THAT THERE IS A
BASE LINE IN THIS GENEROUS
COUNTRY OF OURS NO ONE GOES
BELOW.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, MR. TRUMP SAYS
THAT HE IS CAPABLE OF GROWING
THE ECONOMY SO MUCH THAT SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE DON'T HAVE
TO BE TOUCHED.
DO YOU WANT TO EXPLAIN HOW THAT
IS GOING TO HAPPEN, MR. TRUMP?
>> YES, IT IS VERY SIMPLE.
WE'LL MAKE A REALLY DYNAMIC
ECONOMY FROM WHAT WE HAVE RIGHT
NOW WHICH IS NOT AT ALL DYNAMIC.
WE'LL BRING JOBS BACK FROM
CHINA, JAPAN AND MEXICO, WHEREAS
YOU PROBABLY SAW NABISCO IS
LEAVING CHICAGO WITH ONE OF
THEIR BIGGEST PLANTS AND MOVING
IT TO MEXICO.
WE'RE GOING TO BRING JOBS AND
MANUFACTURING BACK.
WE'RE GOING TO CUT COSTS AND
SAVE SOCIAL SECURITY AND WE'RE
GOING TO SAVE MEDICARE.
>> GOVERNOR, YOU JUST HEARD HIM.
>> YOU HAVE TO REFORM SOCIAL
SECURITY AND THE SIMPLE WAY TO
DO IT IS TO MAKE SURE THAT THE
RICHEST DON'T RECEIVE THE SAME
BENEFITS AS PEOPLE THAT ARE
LOWER INCOME.
AND MAKE SURE YOU ENHANCE
SAVINGS IN THE PRIVATE MARKET.
THE IDEA OF 401(k)s.
I HAVE A SMALL BUSINESS THAT I
SET UP.
IT TOOK AN ARM AND A LEG TO BE
ABLE TO SET UP 401(k).
BECAUSE OF ALL THE LAWS AND
FEDERAL MANDATES IT WAS TOO
EXPENSIVE.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE THAT SOCIAL
SECURITY --
>> THE IDEA THAT YOU CAN'T --
YOU JUST GROW YOUR WAY OUT OF
THIS.
YOU WILL HAVE TO MAKE
ADJUSTMENTS FOR BOTH MEDICARE
AND SOCIAL SECURITY.
>> GOVERNOR, IN MY STATE, WE
TOOK MEDICAID, THE HIGHEST
PROGRAM TO CONTROL.
WE TOOK IT FROM THE 10% GROWTH
RATE AND CUT IT TO 2%, WITHOUT
CUTTING A SINGLE BENEFIT.
AND SO MUCH OF WHAT WE DID TO
FORCE COMPETITION, TO USE
TECHNOLOGY, TO STAND DOWN THE
SPECIAL INTEREST GROUPS.
CAN YOU IMAGINE TAKING MEDICAID
FROM 10 TO 2.5%?
WE CAN TAKE MANY OF THOSE SAME
PROCEDURES AND APPLY IT THROUGH
MEDICARE.
WE CAN MAKE A STRONGER PROGRAM.
I AGREE WITH JEB, YOU CAN'T JUST
DO THIS BY GROWING THE ECONOMY.
YOU CAN'T GROW YOUR WAY OUT OF
DEMOGRAPHICS.
BUT WE CAN GIVE PEOPLE BETTER
HEALTH CARE AND FINALLY ON
HEALTH CARE, WHY DON'T WE START
TO GIVE INCENTIVES FOR PEOPLE TO
KEEP PEOPLE HEALTHY RATHER THAN
GIVING THE INCENTIVES TO TREAT
THEM WHEN THEY'RE SICK?
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
SENATOR PAUL, LET'S GO BACK TO
YOU.
DO THESE SOLUTIONS SOUND LIKE
THEY WORK?
>> SAY AGAIN?
>> DO THESE SOLUTIONS SOUND LIKE
THEY WORK?
>> YOU CAN'T DO NOTHING.
I HEAR FROM PEOPLE, WELL, WE'LL
DO NOTHING AND IT WILL FIX
ITSELF.
THAT IS ABSURD, AND PEOPLE ARE
MISSING THE BOAT HERE WHEN THEY
DON'T WANT TO CHANGE SOMETHING.
THE AGE WILL HAVE TO RISE, THE
ONLY WAY YOU FIX MEDICARE AND
SOCIAL SECURITY.
YOU WILL ALSO HAVE TO MEANS TEST
THE BENEFITS AND DECLARE THERE
IS NOT ENOUGH MONEY.
IT IS NOT OH, I PUT MONEY IN,
I'M GETTING IT BACK.
THERE IS NO MONEY, THERE IS A
STACK OF PAPER.
THERE IS NO MONEY IN THE SOCIAL
SECURITY ACCOUNT OR THE MEDICARE
ACCOUNT.
THERE IS ONLY A PROMISE TO PAY
BY THE NEXT GENERATION AND THE
NEXT GENERATION IS NOT BIG
ENOUGH TO PAY IT.
>> WE DID IT 200 DAYS AGO.
>> I HAVE A QUESTION FOR DR.
CARSON.
>> ON MEDICARE?
>> YES, YOU SAID YOU WOULD LIKE
TO REPLACE MEDICARE WITH A
SYSTEM OF INDIVIDUAL FAMILY
SAVINGS ACCOUNTS SO THAT
FAMILIES COULD COVER THEIR OWN
EXPENSES.
OBVIOUSLY, THAT WOULD BE A VERY
CONTROVERSIAL IDEA.
EXPLAIN HOW THAT WOULD WORK,
OBVIOUSLY.
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL THE PLAN
GIVES THE PEOPLE THE OPTION OF
OPTING OUT.
BUT I THINK THEY WOULD SEE A
VERY GOOD OPTION HERE.
YOU KNOW, THE ANNUAL MEDICARE
BUDGET IS OVER $600 BILLION.
AND THERE ARE 48 MILLION PEOPLE
INVOLVED.
40 MILLION, 65 AND OVER, AND 8
MILLION AND OTHERS.
DIVIDE THAT OUT.
THAT COMES OUT TO $12,500 FOR
EACH ONE.
NOW, I CAN TELL YOU THERE ARE A
LOT OF PRIVATE SECTOR THINGS
THAT YOU CAN DO WITH $12,500
WHICH GETS YOU A LOT MORE THAN
YOU GET FROM THIS GOVERNMENT
PROGRAM.
THAT IS REALLY THE THEME OF WHAT
I'M TALKING ABOUT.
HOW DO WE USE OUR INTELLECTUAL
ABILITIES RATHER THAN ALLOW THE
GOVERNMENT TO USE THE INTELLECT,
TO BE ABLE TO LIVE HEALTHIER AND
BETTER LIVES.
IT WAS NEVER INTENDED THAT THE
GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE IN EVERY
ASPECT OF OUR LIVES.
THIS IS A COUNTRY THAT WAS UP
FOR AND BY THE PEOPLE.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
>> BEN IS ABSOLUTELY RIGHT IN
SAYING WHAT WE DON'T NEED TO DO
IS TO SEND MORE MONEY TO
WASHINGTON, D.C. TO FIX THIS
PROBLEM.
AND THAT IS WHAT YOU WILL HEAR
FROM HILLARY CLINTON.
AND I'VE ALREADY HEARD FROM HER,
SEND MORE MONEY IN SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE TAXES,
SEND MORE MONEY FOR MEDICAID AND
THAT WILL SOLVE THE PROBLEM.
WE KNOW WE'RE LIVING LONGER.
IT'S A BLESSING THAT WE'RE
LIVING LONGER SO WE HAVE TO
INCREASE THE RETIREMENT AGE TO
REFLECT THAT BLESSING.
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE PEOPLE
UNDERSTAND THAT IF YOU HAVE DONE
EXTRAORDINARILY WELL IN THE
COUNTRY, DO YOU WANT THEM TO
TAKE MORE OF YOUR TAXES NOW AND
THINK THEY WILL GET IT BACK TO
YOU LATER OR WOULD YOU RATHER
TAKE LESS LATER ON?
>> DO YOU THINK THAT DR. CARSON
IS RIGHT THAT WE CAN REPLACE
MONEY WITH INDIVIDUAL SAVINGS
ACCOUNTS?
>> WHAT I SAID, HIS IDEAS ARE
GOOD IDEAS, NOT NECESSARILY MY
IDEAS.
I DON'T NECESSARILY AGREE WITH
THEM.
THIS IS WHAT YOU SEE IN THE
REPUBLICAN DEBATE AND YOU DIDN'T
SEE IT IN THE DEMOCRATIC DEBATE.
THEY ARE TRYING TO HELP REFORM
THE VOTER OUT THERE.
WHAT YOU SAW WAS A PARADE OF
I'LL GIVE YOU THIS FOR FREE,
I'LL GIVE YOU THAT FOR FREE, LET
ME TELL YOU EVERYBODY, WHEN THEY
SAY THEY WANT TO GIVE YOU
SOMETHING TO FREE KEEP YOUR
HANDS ON YOUR WALLET, BECAUSE
THEY'RE COMING TO YOU TO PAY FOR
IT.
I THINK WE NEED TO HAVE MORE
DISCUSSIONS AND LESS GOTCHA.
>> I WANT TO ARGUE ONE OF THE
SAME THINGS, ONE OF THE THINGS
YOU'RE WATCHING, 11 QUALIFIED
CANDIDATES.
THE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATE HAS
GOOD CANDIDATES, THE DEMOCRATICS
CAN'T EVEN COME UP WITH ONE.
THEY'RE GOING TO DEMAGOGUE WHAT
WE'RE SAYING HERE TONIGHT.
EVERYBODY TALKING ABOUT REFORM,
I KNOW I SPEAK FOR THIS.
WE'RE ALL TALKING ABOUT REFORM
FOR FUTURE GENERATIONS.
MY MOTHER IS ON MEDICARE AND
SOCIAL SECURITY.
I'M AGAINST ANYTHING THAT IS BAD
FOR MY MOTHER.
SO WE'RE TALKING ABOUT -- WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT REFORM FOR PEOPLE
LIKE ME AND PEOPLE LIKE SENATOR
CRUZ AS HE TALKED ABOUT EARLIER,
WHO ARE YEARS AWAY FROM
RETIREMENT.
IN A WAY THAT IS VERY
REASONABLE.
IT'S NOT TOO MUCH TO ASK OF OUR
GENERATION AFTER EVERYTHING THAT
OUR PARENTS AND GRANDPARENTS DID
FOR US.
>> A LOT OF PEOPLE JUMPED IN
HERE, I WOULD LIKE TO JUMP IN.
>> WE'RE RIGHT AT THE END OF OUR
TIME.
YOU ONLY -- ALL RIGHT, GO AHEAD.
>> I WOULD JUST SAY THIS, THERE
ARE A LOT OF GREAT IDEAS UP
HERE.
AND I AGREE WITH WHAT SENATOR
RUBIO SAID.
EVERY ELECTION WE TALK ABOUT
THIS.
MEDICARE AND SOCIAL SECURITY
REFORM, IT NEVER HAPPENS.
I WOULD LIKE TO START WITH A
BASIC.
LET US ACTUALLY GO TO ZERO BASE
BUDGETING SO WE KNOW WHERE THE
MONEY IS BEING SPENT.
IT'S KIND OF BASIC.
THERE IS A BILL SITTING IN THE
HOUSE THAT WOULD ACTUALLY PASS
AND HAVE US GO TO ZERO BASE
BUDGETING SO WE KNOW WHERE EVERY
DIME OF YOUR MONEY IS BEING
SPENT INSTEAD OF ONLY TALKING
ABOUT HOW MUCH MORE WE'RE GOING
TO SPEND, YEAR AFTER YEAR AFTER
YEAR.
MY POINT IS THIS, WHILE THERE
ARE LOTS OF GOOD IDEAS FOR
REFORM WE HAVE NEVER TACKLED THE
BASICS.
AND WE FINALLY NEED TO TACKLE
THE BASICS TO CUT THIS
GOVERNMENT DOWN TO SIZE AND HOLD
IT ACCOUNTABLE.
SO LET'S START BY KNOWING WHERE
YOUR MONEY IS BEING SPENT BY THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
>> WE HAVE NOW REACHED THE POINT
OF THE PROGRAM WHERE THE
CANDIDATES GET CLOSING
STATEMENTS 30 SECONDS APIECE.
TO THE LEFT, SENATOR PAUL.
>> LIBERTY THRIVES WHEN
GOVERNMENT IS SMALL.
I WANT A GOVERNMENT SO SMALL I
CAN BARELY SEE IT.
I WANT A GOVERNMENT SO SMALL
THAT THE INDIVIDUAL HAS A CHANCE
TO THRIVE AND PROSPER.
I THINK GOVERNMENT IS TOO BIG
NOW.
WHAT YOU WILL SEE IN WASHINGTON
THIS WEEK IS ESTABLISHMENT
REPUBLICANS HAVE MADE AN
AGREEMENT WITH THE PRESIDENT TO
RAISE THE DEBT CEILING IN AN
UNLIMITED FASHION.
NO LIMIT TO THE DEBT CEILING
RAISE.
THIS IS EXTRAORDINARY, IT IS
EXTRAORDINARILY WRONG.
YOU WILL SEE ME ON THE FLOOR OF
THE SENATE TOMORROW
FILIBUSTERING IT AND SAYING
ENOUGH IS ENOUGH, NO MORE DEBT
INTO GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU, ARE YOU
FED UP WITH HOW WASHINGTON
WASTES YOUR MONEY?
ARE YOU CONCERNED LIKE I AM THAT
THE DEBTS AND DEFICITS OF
WASHINGTON, D.C. ARE ENDANGERING
AMERICA'S FUTURE?
I GOT ONE MORE QUESTION FOR YOU.
ARE YOU SERIOUS ABOUT THIS
ELECTION?
BECAUSE IF YOU ARE YOU NEED TO
ELECT SOMEBODY WHO IS VERY
SERIOUS ABOUT CHANGING THIS
CULTURE.
I AM DEADLY SERIOUS ABOUT
CHANGING THIS CULTURE.
I CHANGED IT IN NEW JERSEY, AND
I'M DEADLY SERIOUS ABOUT
CHANGING IT.
I'M PREPARED, TESTED AND READY
AND I WANT TO MAKE THIS OUR
GOVERNMENT.
TO THE PEOPLE WHO SAY WE CAN'T
DO IT.
I SAY HELL NO, WE CAN DO IT
TOGETHER.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> YOU KNOW, EVERYBODY TALKING
ABOUT THE NEED TO TAKE ON
WASHINGTON, THE NATURAL NEXT
QUESTION IS WHO ACTUALLY STOOD
UP TO DEMOCRATS AND LEADERS IN
OUR OWN PARTY.
WHEN MILLIONS OF AMERICANS ROSE
UP AGAINST OBAMACARE, I WAS
PROUD TO LEAD THAT FIGHT.
WHEN MILLIONS OF AMERICANS ROSE
UP AGAINST AMNESTY, I WAS PROUD
TO LEAD THAT FIGHT.
WHEN MILLIONS OF AMERICANS ROSE
UP AGAINST PLANNED PARENTHOOD I
WAS PROUD TO LEAD THAT FIGHT.
IF PEOPLE PROMISE TO STAND UP TO
CRONYISM, FREEDOM IS PERSONAL TO
ME AND I WILL ALWAYS KEEP MY
WORD AND FIGHT FOR FREEDOM.
>> YOU KNOW, EVERY ELECTION WE
HEAR A LOT OF TALK, WE HEAR A
LOT OF GOOD PLANS.
WE HEAR ACTUALLY A LOT OF GOOD
INTENTIONS.
BUT SOMEHOW FOR DECADES NOTHING
REALLY HAS CHANGED.
WHAT WE NEED NOW IS A PROVEN
LEADER WHO HAS PRODUCED RESULTS.
THAT IS HOW YOU GO FROM
SECRETARY TO CEO.
YOU LEAD AND PRODUCE RESULTS.
I WILL CUT THIS GOVERNMENT DOWN
TO SIZE AND HOLD IT ACCOUNTABLE,
SIMPLIFY THE TAX CODE AND ROLL
BACK REGULATIONS THAT HAVE BEEN
COMING OUT OF WASHINGTON, D.C.
FOR 50 YEARS.
I MAY NOT BE YOUR DREAM
CANDIDATE JUST YET.
BUT I CAN ASSURE YOU I'M HILLARY
CLINTON'S WORST NIGHTMARE.
AND IN YOUR HEART OF HEARTS, YOU
CAN'T WAIT TO SEE A DEBATE
BETWEEN HILLARY CLINTON AND
CARLY FIORINA.
I WILL TELL YOU THIS, I WILL
BEAT HILLARY CLINTON AND WITH
YOUR PRAYERS AND SUPPORT I WILL
LEAD THE CITIZENS OF THIS GREAT
NATION.
THE RESURGENCE OF THIS GREAT
>> THANK YOU, DR. BEN CARSON.
>> I JUST WANT TO THANK ALL OF
MY COLLEAGUES FOR BEING CIVIL
AND NOT FALLING FOR THE TRAP.
AND I WANT TO THANK THE AUDIENCE
FOR BEING ATTENTIVE AND NOTICING
THE QUESTIONS AND ANSWERS.
THIS IS WHAT I'M FINDING
THROUGHOUT AMERICA, PEOPLE ARE
WAKING UP.
IT WILL BE US DETERMINING THE
DIRECTION OF OUR COUNTRY.
IT WAS MADE FOR WE THE PEOPLE.
WE ARE THE ONES WHO DECIDE WHO
WE ARE.
AND WE SHOULD NEVER GIVE AWAY
THE VALUES AND PRINCIPLES THAT
MADE OUR NATION GREAT FOR THE
SAKE OF POLITICAL CORRECTNESS.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> OUR COUNTRY DOESN'T WIN
ANYMORE.
WE HAVE USED TO WIN, WE DON'T
WIN ANYMORE.
WE LOSE ON TRADE.
WE LOSE WITH ISIS.
WE LOST WITH ONE OF THE WORST
DEALS I HAVE EVER SEEN
NEGOTIATED OF ANY KIND.
THAT IS OUR RECENT CATASTROPHE
WITH IRAN.
WE DON'T WIN.
LET ME GIVE YOU A TERRIFIC
EXAMPLE.
THESE FOLKS AT CNBC, THEY HAD IT
DOWN TO THREE AND A HALF HOURS.
I JUST READ IN "THE NEW YORK
TIMES," $350,000 FOR A
THIRD-SECOND AD.
NOBODY WANTS TO WATCH THREE AND
A HALF OR THREE HOURS.
IT WAS A BIG SACRIFICE.
WE HAVE TO HAND IT TO BEN, HE
WAS WITH ME 100%.
WE CALLED IN, WE SAID WE'RE NOT
DOING IT.
THEY LOST A LOT OF MONEY,
EVERYBODY SAID IT WOULD BE THREE
AND A HALF HOURS, INCLUDING
THEM.
AND IN ABOUT TWO MINUTES I
RE-NEGOTIATING IT DOWN TO TWO
HOURS SO WE CAN GET THE HELL OUT
OF HERE.
NOT BAD.
AND I'LL DO THAT WITH THE
COUNTRY.
WE WILL MAKE AMERICA GREAT
AGAIN, AND THANK YOU EVERYBODY.
>> JUST FOR THE RECORD, THE
DEBATE WAS ALWAYS GOING TO BE
TWO HOURS.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THAT WAS NOT
RIGHT.
YOU KNOW THAT THAT IS NOT RIGHT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO --
>> AMERICA DOESN'T OWE ME
ANYTHING.
I HAVE A DEBT TO AMERICA I WILL
NEVER REPAY.
THIS IS NOT JUST THE COUNTRY I
WAS BORN IN, THIS IS THE NATION
THAT LITERALLY CHANGED THE
HISTORY OF MY FAMILY.
MY PARENTS WERE ABLE TO GIVE ME
THE CHANCE TO DO ALL THE THINGS
THEY NEVER DID.
WE CALL IT THE AMERICA DREAM.
ALTHOUGH IT'S BUILT ON A
UNIVERSAL DREAM FOR EVERY LIFE.
THAT IS WHAT MAKES IT SPECIAL.
FOR MILLIONS OF AMERICANS IT'S
SLIPPING AWAY.
WE HAVE LEADERS AND THE
GOVERNMENT OUT OF TOUCH.
WE CAN EXPAND THE GOVERNMENT TO
REACH PEOPLE AND CHANGE LIVES
AND THAT IS WHY TONIGHT I'M
ASKING FOR YOUR VOTE.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR, GOVERNOR
BUSH.
>> AMERICA IS AT A CROSSROADCRO
THE D.C. POLITICIANS, I HAVE A
PROVEN RECORD, EIGHT YEARS AS
THE GOVERNOR OF THE STATE OF
FLORIDA.
I WILL CHANGE THE CULTURE IN
WASHINGTON JUST AS I CHANGED THE
CULTURE IN TALLAHASSEE AND WILL
DO SO IN A WAY TO BRING PEOPLE
TOGETHER.
WE NEED SOMEBODY TO UNIFY, NOT A
DIVIDER IN CHIEF.
IMAGINE A COUNTRY WHERE PEOPLE
WERE LIFTED OUT OF POVERTY AGAIN
AND A COUNTRY WHERE PEOPLE CAN
GET RISING INCOME AGAIN.
WE CAN DO THIS BECAUSE WE'RE
STILL THE MOST EXTRAORDINARY
COUNTRY ON THE FACE OF THE
EARTH.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR, GOVERNOR
MIKE HUCKABEE.
>> AND A LOT OF PEOPLE IN THE
MEDIA, THIS IS A GREAT BIG GAME
AND WE'RE THE PLAYERS.
AND WE COME OUT HERE AND DO OUR
THINGS AND SOMETIMES WE'RE HELD
UP IN CONTEMPT BY PEOPLE WHO
WRITE COLUMNS, BUT I GARLT YOU
TO EVERY PERSON ON THIS STAGE
THERE IS SOMETHING DEEP INSIDE
OF US THAT WOULD CAUSE US TO
GIVE UP OUR LIVELIHOODS AND STEP
OUT ON THIS STAGE AND FIGHT FOR
THE PEOPLE IN AMERICA.
I HAVE FIVE GRANDKIDS.
I DO NOT WANT TO WALK MY FIVE
GRANDKIDS THROUGH THE CHARRED
REMAINS OF A ONCE-GREAT COUNTRY
CALLED AMERICA AND SAY HERE YOU
GO, $20 TRILLION IN DEBT, GOOD
LUCK MAKING SOMETHING OUT OF
THIS MESS.
FOR THOSE OF US SERIOUS ENOUGH
TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT THINK LONG
AND HARD WHY WE'RE HERE AND
HOPEFULLY YOU WILL KNOW WE'RE
NOT HERE FOR OURSELVES.
WE HONEST TO GOD ARE HERE TO GET
THIS COUNTRY BACK ON TRACK.
I KNOW THIS, I CERTAINLY AM.
>> THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH.
>> I WAS ON MORNING JOE AT A
TOWN HALL AND A YOUNG STUDENT
STOOD UP AND SAID CAN I STILL BE
IDEAISTIC?
I SAID ABSOLUTELY, YOU CAN STILL
CHANGE THE WORLD.
YOU KNOW THE OLD MOTTO, IF YOU
CHANGE ONE LIFE YOU CHANGED THE
WORLD.
FOLKS, WE HAVE A PROBLEM HERE IN
WASHINGTON, BUT WE NEED TO HAVE
STRONGER FAMILIES AND WE NEED TO
KNOW WHO OUR NEIGHBORS ARE.
WE NEED TO COME TOGETHER AS A
COUNTRY BECAUSE WE HAVE TO
REALIZE THAT AMERICA IS GREAT
NOT FROM THE TOP DOWN, OH, YEAH,
WE WANT TO ELECT A GOOD
PRESIDENT.
BUT AMERICA IS GREAT FROM THE
BOTTOM UP.
AND THE BOTTOM UP IS OUR
FAMILIES, COMMUNITIES,
NEIGHBORHOODS.
WE WILL RENEW AMERICA IF WE WORK
TOGETHER AND I AM TOTALLY
CONFIDENT THAT WE WILL.
AND GOD BLESS AMERICA.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> THAT CONCLUDES TONIGHT'S
DEBATE ON BEHALF OF MY
COLLEAGUES, BECKY QUICK, JOHN
HARWOOD, SHARON EPPERSON.
WE WOULD LIKE TO THANK OUR
HOSTS, THE REPUBLICAN NATIONAL
COMMITTEE, THE CANDIDATES, AND