>>> IT'S THE BIG NIGHT FOR THE
REPUBLICANS.
FIVE CANDIDATES REMAIN AND THE
BIGGEST ROUND OF VOTING YET.
>> IN THE HEART OF TEXAS, THE
FINAL GOP DEBATE BEFORE A
PRIMARY NIGHT BLOCKBUSTER.
>> ON TO SUPER TUESDAY --
>> I NEED YOUR VOTES.
>> VOTERS IN NEARLY A DOZEN
STATES COULD TIP THE SCALES OF
THE REPUBLICAN RACE, JUST FIVE
DAYS FROM NOW.
>> IF YOU'RE NOT GOING TO VOTE
FOR ME, DO NOT VOTE.
>> TONIGHT, THE REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES IN A HARD-HITTING
CLASH OF IDEAS, APPEALING TO
VOTERS ALL ACROSS THE NATION.
>> USA!
USA!
>> DONALD TRUMP ON A WINNING
STREAK.
>> LET'S PUT THIS THING AWAY AND
LET'S MAKE AMERICA GREAT AGAIN.
>> MARCO RUBIO WITH NEW
MOMENTUM.
>> NOW THE CHILDREN OF THE
REAGAN REVOLUTION ARE READY TO
ASSUME THE MANTLE OF LEADERSHIP.
>> TED CRUZ ON HIS TEXAS HOME
TURF.
>> ONLY ONE STRONG CONSERVATIVE
IS IN A POSITION TO WIN THIS
RACE.
>> JOHN KASICH, LOOKING FORWARD.
>> THAT'S WHERE WE'RE GOING TO
GO, ALL THE WAY TO THE
NOMINATION IN CLEVELAND, OHIO.
>> BEN CARSON, FIGHTING ON.
>> WE TAKE CONTROL OF AMERICA.
I SAY NOW IS THE TIME TO DO
THAT.
>> IT'S AN EPIC BATTLE FOR THE
SOUL OF THE REPUBLICAN PARTY AND
FOR A HUGE PRIZE.
A TREASURE-TROVE OF DELEGATES
NEEDED TO WIN THE NOMINATION.
>> NOTHING EASY ABOUT RUNNING
FOR PRESIDENT.
IT'S NASTY, IT'S MEAN, IT'S
VICIOUS.
WHEN YOU WIN, IT'S BEAUTIFUL.
>> NOW, THE STAGE IS SET FOR A
SPIRITED GIVE-AND-TAKE THAT
COULD SHAKE THINGS UP ON SUPER
TUESDAY.
>> THIS IS SERIOUS.
THIS IS NOT A COLLEGE FOOTBALL
GAME.
THIS IS NOT A SPORT.
>> THE TIME FOR GAMES IS OVER.
>> DO YOU THINK THIS IS FUN?
>> ONLY FIVE REPUBLICANS ARE
STILL IN THE RACE.
AND THEY'RE READY TO DEBATE,
RIGHT NOW.
>> WE'RE LIVE HERE AT THE
UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON, AND FOR
THE TENTH REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
AN ENTHUSIASTIC CROWD IS ON HAND
HERE IN THE BEAUTIFUL OPERAHOUSE
OF THE MOORE SCHOOL OF MUSIC.
TEXAS IS THE BIGGEST PRIZE.
THAT'S TUESDAY, SUPER TUESDAY,
WHEN 11 STATES VOTE.
A DAY THAT WILL GO A LONG WAY
TOWARDS DECIDING WHO WINS THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINATION.
WE WANT TO WELCOME OUR VIEWERS
IN THE UNITED STATES AND AROUND
THE WORLD.
I'M WOLF BLITZER.
THIS DEBATE IS AIRING ON CNN,
CNN INTERNATIONAL, AND CNN IN
ESPANOL.
IT'S ALSO BEING SEEN ON
TELEMUNDO AND HEARD ON THE SALEM
RADIO NETWORK.
TELEMUNDO AND SALEM ARE OUR
PARTNERS IN THIS DEBATE, ALONG
WITH THE REPUBLICAN NATIONAL
COMMITTEE.
WE'D ALSO LIKE TO WELCOME A VERY
SPECIAL GUEST WITH US HERE
TONIGHT.
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, THE 41st
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES,
GEORGE HERBERT WALKER BUSH AND
FORMER FIRST LADY, BARBARA BUSH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> EVERYONE HERE IS LOOKING
FORWARD TO A LIVELY DEBATE.
I'LL BE YOUR MODERATOR TONIGHT.
JOINING ME IN THE QUESTIONING,
TELEMUNDO HOST, MARIA SLAIS AND
DANA BASH, AND SALEM RADIO
NETWORK'S HUGH HEWITT, WHO
WORKED IN THE REAGAN
ADMINISTRATION FOR SIX YEARS.
TONIGHT, THERE ARE FIVE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES.
AND THEY'RE READY TO JOIN US
RIGHT NOW.
PLEASE WELCOME OHIO GOVERNOR,
JOHN KASICH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SENATOR TED CRUZ OF TEXAS.
BUSINESSMAN AND REAL ESTATE
DEVELOPER, DONALD TRUMP.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SENATOR MARCO RUBIO OF FLORIDA.
AND RETIRED NEUROSURGEON, DR.
BEN CARSON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN.
WELCOME THE REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW PLEASE RISE FOR OUR NATIONAL
ANTHEM, PERFORMED BY COUNTRY
MUSIC ARTIST, DENA CARTER.
OH, SAY CAN YOU SEE
BY THE DAWN'S EARLY LIGHT
WHAT SO PROUDLY WE HAILED
AT THE TWILIGHT'S LAST
GLEAMING
WHOSE BROAD STRIPES AND BRIGHT
STARS
THROUGH THE PERILOUS FIGHT
O'ER RAMPARTS WE WATCHED
WERE SO GALLANTLY STREAMING
AND THE ROCKET'S RED GLARE
THE BOMBS BURSTING IN AIR
GAVE PROOF THROUGH THE NIGHT
THAT OUR FLAG WAS STILL
THERE
O, SAY DOES THAT STAR-SPANGLED
BANNER YET WAVE
FOR THE LAND OF THE FREE AND
THE HOME OF THE BRAVE
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, DEANA
CARTER.
A BEAUTIFUL, BEAUTIFUL NATIONAL
ANTHEM.
FINAL DEBATE BEFORE SUPER
TUESDAY BEGINS RIGHT AFTER THIS
QUICK BREAK.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON AND THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
THE CANDIDATES, THEY ARE NOW IN
PLACE.
THEIR POSITIONS WERE SELECTED
BASED ON THEIR STANDING IN THE
DELEGATE RACE, THROUGH NEVADA,
WITH THE TOP CANDIDATE IN THE
CENTER AND THE OTHERS EXTENDING
OUTWARD.
I WANT TO TELL YOU HOW TONIGHT'S
DEBATE WILL WORK.
AS MODERATOR, I WILL GUIDE THE
DISCUSSION, ASKING QUESTIONS AND
FOLLOW-UPS, AS MR. MARIA
CELESTE, DANA BASH, AND HUGH
HEWITT.
CANDIDATES, YOU'LL HAVE A MINUTE
AND 15 SECONDS TO ANSWER AND 30
SECONDS FOR FOLLOW-UPS AND
REBUTTALS.
WE HAVE TIMING LIGHTS THAT ARE
VISIBLE TO THE CANDIDATES.
THOSE LIGHTS WILL WARN YOU WHEN
YOUR TIME IS UP.
AND AS THE CANDIDATES REQUESTED,
A BELL WILL SOUND LIKE THIS.
WE KNOW YOU ALL WANT TO JUMP IN
AND DEBATE THESE CRITICALLY
IMPORTANT ISSUES, BUT PLEASE,
WAIT UNTIL YOU'RE CALLED ON.
THESE ARE THE RULES ALL OF THE
CANDIDATES HAVE AGREED TO.
IT'S TIME FOR THE CANDIDATES TO
INTRODUCE THEMSELVES RIGHT NOW.
YOU'LL EACH HAVE 30 SECONDS.
DR. CARSON, YOU'RE FIRST.
>> IF SOMEONE HAD TRIED TO
DESCRIBE TODAY'S AMERICA TO YOU
30 YEARS AGO, YOU WOULD HAVE
LISTENED IN DISBELIEF.
AMERICANS KNOW THAT OUR NATION
IS HEADING OFF THE ABYSS OF
DESTRUCTION, SECONDARY
DIVISIVENESS, FISCAL
IRRESPONSIBILITY, AND FAILURE TO
LEAD.
MARCO, DONALD, TED, JOHN, WE
WILL NOT SOLVE ANY OF THESE
PROBLEMS BY TRYING TO DESTROY
EACH OTHER.
WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS BE LOOKING
FOR SOLUTIONS TONIGHT.
IT'S NOT ABOUT US, IT'S ABOUT
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, ON THE WAY
OVER HERE, EVEN GETTING READY
EARLIER AND SITTING IN THE GREEN
ROOM AND WATCHING THE EARLY
COVERAGE, YOU KNOW, MY FATHER
CARRIED ME ON HIS BACK AND HIS
FATHER WAS A COAL MINER AND MY
MOTHER'S MOTHER WAS AN
IMMIGRANT, COULD BARELY SPEAK
ENGLISH.
AND I'M STANDING ON THIS STAGE.
IT'S PRETTY REMARKABLE.
BUT I WANT TO TELL YOU, THERE'S
A LOT OF YOUNG PEOPLE WATCHING
TONIGHT.
YOU CAN DO WHATEVER YOU WANT TO
DO IN YOUR LIFE.
AMERICA IS AN AMAZING COUNTRY,
WHERE A KID LIKE ME CAN GROW UP
TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES AND BE ON THE
STAGE TONIGHT.
SO TO ALL THE YOUNG PEOPLE THAT
ARE OUT THERE, YOUR HOPES, YOUR
DREAMS, PURSUE THEM.
SHOOT FOR THE STARS.
AMERICA'S GREAT, AND YOU CAN DO
IT.
THANK YOU, WOLF.
>> SENATOR WRUBIO?
>> THANK YOU.
THIS ELECTION, WE HAVE TO DECIDE
THE IDENTITY OF AMERICA AND THE
12st CENTURY, BUT WE HAVE TO
FIND OUT OUR IDENTITY AS A PARTY
AND A MOVEMENT.
36 YEARS AGO, RONALD REAGAN AND
GEORGE H.W. BUSH BEGAN THE
REAGAN REVOLUTION.
FOR A GENERATION, THEY DEFINED
CONSERVATISM, AS LIMITED
GOVERNMENT AND FREE ENTERPRISE
AND A STRONG NATIONAL DEFENSE.
BUT THEY ALSO APPEALED TO OUR
HOPES AND OUR DREAMS.
NOW WE HAVE TO DECIDE IF WE ARE
STILL THAT KIND OF PARTY AND
STILL THAT KIND OF MOVEMENT, OR
IF WE'RE SIMPLY GOING TO BECOME
A PARTY THAT PREYS ON PEOPLE'S
ANGERS AND FEARS.
I HOPE WE REMAIN THAT
CONSERVATIVE MOVEMENT THAT
APPEALS TO OUR HOPES AND OUR
DREAMS AND THE BELIEF THAT
AMERICA WILL ALWAYS BE BETTER IN
ITS FUTURE THAN IT'S BEEN IN ITS
HIS
HISTORY.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> WELCOME TO TEXAS.
HERE TEXAS PROVIDED MY FAMILY
WITH HOPE.
HERE, MY MOM BECAME THE FIRST IN
OUR FAMILY EVER TO GO TO
COLLEGE.
HERE, MY DAD FLED CUBA AND
WASHED DISHES, MAKING 50 CENTS
AN HOUR TO PAY HIS WAY THROUGH
THE UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS.
I GRADUATED FROM HIGH SCHOOL AT
SECOND BAPTIST NOT TOO FAR AWAY
FROM HERE.
WHEN I RAN FOR SENATE, I
PROMISED 27 MILLION TEXANS I
WOULD FIGHT FOR YOU EVER DAY AND
NOT FOR THE WASHINGTON BOSSES.
AND I'LL TELL YOU, AS I TRAVEL
THE STATE, DEMOCRATS TELL ME, I
DIDN'T VOTE FOR YOU, BUT YOU'RE
DOING WHAT YOU SAID YOU WOULD
DO, AND AS PRESIDENT, I WILL DO
THE SAME.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> THANK YOU.
MY WHOLE THEME IS MAKE AMERICA
GREAT AGAIN.
WE DON'T WIN ANYMORE AS A
COUNTRY.
WE DON'T WIN WITH TRADE.
WE DON'T WIN WITH THE MILITARY,
ISIS, WE CAN'T EVEN KNOCK OUT
ISIS, AND WE WILL, BELIEVE ME.
WE WILL.
WE DON'T WIN IN ANY CAPACITY
WITH HEALTH CARE.
WE HAVE TERRIBLE HEALTH CARE.
OBAMACARE IS GOING TO BE
REPEALED AND REPLACED.
WE JUST DON'T WIN.
YOU LOOK AT OUR BORDERS, THEY'RE
LIKE SWISS CHEESE.
EVERYBODY POURS IN.
WE'RE GOING TO MAKE A GREAT
COUNTRY AGAIN.
WE'RE GOING TO START WINNING
AGAIN.
WE'RE GOING TO WIN A LOT.
IT'S GOING TO BE A BIG
DIFFERENCE, BELIEVE ME.
IT'S GOING TO BE A BIG, BIG
DIFFERENCE.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
IT'S NOW TIME TO BEGIN
QUESTIONS.
VOTERS IN THE FIRST FOUR STATES
HAVE SPOKEN, AND MR. TRUMP HAS
EMERGED AS THE FRONT-RUNNER, BUT
IN FIVE DAYS, THE CANDIDATES
WILL FACE THEIR BIGGEST TEST
YET, SUPER TUESDAY, WHEN NEARLY
HALF OF THE DELEGATES NEEDED TO
WIN THE REPUBLICAN NOMINATION
WILL BE AWARDED AND THE BIGGEST
PRIZE OF THE NIGHT IS TEXAS.
IMMIGRATION IS A KEY ISSUE IN
THIS STATE FOR ALL VOTERS
NATIONWIDE, INCLUDING THE MANY
PEOPLE WATCHING US TONIGHT ON
TELEMUNDO.
SO THAT'S WHERE WE BEGIN.
MR. TRUMP, YOU'VE CALLED FOR A
DEPORTATION FORCE TO REMOVE THE
11 MILLION UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS FROM THE UNITED
STATES.
YOU'VE ALSO PROMISED TO LET,
WHAT YOU CALL, THE GOOD ONES
COME BACK IN.
YOUR WORDS, THE GOOD ONES, AFTER
THEY'VE BEEN DEPORTED.
SENATOR CRUZ WOULD NOT ALLOW
THEM TO COME BACK IN.
HE SAYS, THAT'S THE BIGGEST
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN THE TWO OF
YOU.
HE CALLS YOUR PLAN AMNESTY.
IS IT?
>> FIRST OF ALL, HE WAS IN
CHARGE OF AMNESTY.
HE WAS THE LEADER, AND YOU CAN
ASK MARCO, BECAUSE THEY'VE BEEN
DEBATING THIS EVERY DEBATE THAT
WE'VE HAD.
AS FAR AS COMING BACK IN, NUMBER
ONE, YOU WOULDN'T EVEN BE
TALKING AND YOU WOULDN'T HAVE
ASKED THAT AS THE FIRST QUESTION
IF IT WEREN'T FOR ME IN MY
OPENING WHEN I TALKED ABOUT
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION.
IT WOULDN'T EVEN BE A BIG
SUBJECT.
BUT WE EITHER HAVE A COUNTRY OR
WE DON'T HAVE A COUNTRY.
WE HAVE AT LEAST 11 MILLION
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY THAT CAME
IN ILLEGALLY.
THEY WILL GO OUT.
THEY WILL COME BACK, SOME WILL
COME BACK, THE BEST.
THROUGH A PROCESS.
THEY HAVE TO COME BACK LEGALLY.
THEY HAVE TO COME BACK THROUGH A
PROCESS, AND IT MAY NOT BE A
VERY QUICK PROCESS, BUT I THINK
THAT'S VERY FAIR AND VERY FINE.
THEY'RE GOING TO GET ONLINE WITH
OTHER PEOPLE.
THE BEST OF THEM WILL COME BACK,
BUT THEY'RE GOING TO COME BACK
THROUGH A PROCESS.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, WHAT'S WRONG
WITH LETTING WHAT MR. TRUMP
CALLS "THE GOOD ONES" COME BACK
TO THE UNITED STATES.
>> THE PEOPLE THAT GET FORGOTTEN
IN THIS DEBATE OVER IMMIGRATION
ARE THE HARD-WORKING MEN AND
WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY.
MILLIONS OF AMERICANS THAT ARE
LOSING THEIR JOBS, MILLIONS OF
LEGAL IMMIGRANTS THAT ARE LOSING
THEIR JOBS OR SEEING THEIR WAGES
DRIVEN DOWN.
YOU KNOW, THE PAST COUPLE OF
WEEKS, "THE WALL STREET JOURNAL"
HAD A VERY INTERESTING ARTICLE
ABOUT THE STATE OF ARIZONA.
ARIZONA PUT IN VERY TOUGH LAWS
ON ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION.
AND THE RESULT WAS, ILLEGAL
IMMIGRANTS FLED THE STATE.
AND WHAT'S HAPPENED THERE, IT
WAS A VERY INTERESTING ARTICLE.
SOME OF THE BUSINESS OWNERS
COMPLAINED THAT THE WAGES THEY
HAD TO PAY WORKERS WENT UP.
AND FROM THEIR PERSPECTIVE, THAT
WAS A BAD THING, BUT WHAT THE
STATE OF ARIZONA HAS SEEN IS THE
DOLLARS THEY'RE SPENDING ON
WELFARE, ON PRISONS, ON
EDUCATION, ALL OF THOSE HAVE
DROPPED BY HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS
OF DOLLARS, AND THE AMERICANS,
AND FOR THAT MATTER, THE LEGAL
IMMIGRANTS, WHO ARE IN ARIZONA,
ARE SEEING UNEMPLOYMENT DROP,
ARE SEEING WAGES RISE.
THAT'S WHO WE NEED TO BE
FIGHTING FOR.
LISTEN, WE HAVE ALWAYS WELCOMED
LEGAL IMMIGRANTS, BUT I THINK IT
IS A MISTAKE TO FORGIVE THOSE
WHO BREAK THE LAW, TO ALLOW THEM
TO BECOME U.S. CITIZENS, AND
THAT'S WHY I'VE LED THE FIGHT
AGAINST GRANTING CITIZENSHIP TO
THOSE HERE ILLEGALLY, AND THAT'S
WHY I WILL DO THE SAME THING AS
PRESIDENT.
>> MR. TRUMP, DO YOU WANT TO
RESPOND TO THAT?
>> WELL, I'M VERY GLAD THAT TED
MENTIONED ARIZONA, BECAUSE
PROBABLY, THE TOUGHEST MAN ON
BOARD IS SHERIFF JOE ARPAIO.
AND TWO DAYS AGO, WE TOTALLY
ENDORSED ME.
SO, THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> WELL, FIRST --
>> SENATOR CRUZ HAS CALLED YOUR
IMMIGRATION PLAN AMNESTY AND HAS
AN AD OUT THERE COMPARING IT TO
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S.
HE SAYS BOTH OF YOU SUPPORT
ALLOWING UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS
LEGAL STATUS HERE IN THE UNITED
STATES AFTER A BACKGROUND CHECK,
PAYING A FINE, AND PAYING TAXES.
ARE THOSE CLAIMS CORRECT?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, BEFORE WE
DO ANYTHING, AND I'VE,
ABUNDANTLY CLEAR ON THIS, WHEN
I'M PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, BEFORE WE DO ANYTHING ON
IMMIGRATION, WE ARE GOING TO
SECURE THE BORDER.
AND THAT'S NOT JUST THE PHYSICAL
BORDER WITH MEXICO.
IT'S VISA OVERSTAYS.
THAT'S 45% OF THE PROBLEM RIGHT
THERE.
IT ALSO HAS TO DO -- THAT'S WHY
WE NEED E-VERFY AND AN
ENTRY/EXIT TRACKING SYSTEM AND
SO FORTH.
AND UNTIL THAT HAPPENS, WE'RE TO
THE DOING ANYTHING ELSE.
AND THEN WE'LL SEE WHAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE WILLING TO
SUPPORT.
AND DONALD MENTIONED, BECAUSE HE
MENTIONED ME IN HIS ANSWER, THAT
HIS POSITION ON IMMIGRATION IS
WHAT'S DRIVEN THIS DEBATE.
THE TRUTH IS, THOUGH, A LOT OF
THESE POSITIONS THAT HE'S NOW
TAKE RG NEW TO HIM.
IN 2011, HE TALKED ABOUT THE
NEED FOR A PATHWAY TO
CITIZENSHIP.
IN 2012, DONALD CRITICIZED MITT
ROMNEY, SAYING THAT MITT LOST
HIS ELECTION BECAUSE OF
SELF-DEPORTATION.
AND EVEN TODAY, WE SAW A REPORT
IN ONE OF THE NEWSPAPERS THAT
DONALD, YOU'VE HIRED A
SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF PEOPLE
FROM OTHER COUNTRIES TO TAKE
JOBS THAT AMERICANS COULD HAVE
FILLED.
MY MOM WAS A MADE AT A HOTEL,
AND INSTEAD OF HIRING AN
AMERICAN LIKE HER, YOU HAVE
BROUGHT IN OVER A THOUSAND
PEOPLE FROM ALL OVER THE WORLD
TO FILL THOSE JOBS INSTEAD.
SO I THINK THIS IS AN IMPORTANT
ISSUE.
AND I THINK WE ARE REALIZING
THAT IT'S AN IMPORTANT ISSUE FOR
THE COUNTRY THAT'S BEEN DEBATED
FOR 30 YEARS, BUT FINALLY NEEDS
TO BE SOLVED ONCE AND FOR ALL.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> FIRST OF ALL,
SELF-DEPORTATION IS PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO LEAVE AS SOON AS THEY
SEE OTHERS GOING OUT.
IF YOU LOOK AT DWIGHT EISENHOWER
IN THE 1950s, THEY STARTED
MOVING PEOPLE OUT AND THE REST
OF THEM LEFT.
SELF-DEPORTATION, AS I REALLY
DEFINE IT, AND THAT'S THE WAY I
DEFINE IT, IS YOU'RE GOING TO
GET SOME TO GO, AND THE REST ARE
GOING TO GO OUT.
AS FAR AS THE PEOPLE I'VE HIRED
IN VARIOUS PARTS OF FLORIDA
DURING THE ABSOLUTE PRIME
SEASON, LIKE PALM BEACH AND
OTHER LOCATIONS, YOU COULD NOT
GET HELP.
IT'S THE UP SEASON.
PEOPLE DIDN'T WANT TO HAVE
PART-TIME JOBS.
THEY WERE PART-TIME JOBS, VERY
SEASONAL, 90-DAY JOBS, 120-DAY
JOBS, AND YOU COULDN'T GET.
EVERYBODY AGREES WITH ME ON
THAT.
THEY WERE PART-TIME JOBS.
YOU NEEDED THEM, OR WE JUST
MIGHT AS WELL CLOSE THE DOORS,
BECAUSE YOU COULDN'T GET HELP IN
THOSE HOT, HOT SECTIONS OF
FLORIDA.
>> THAT -- MY POINT THAT I MADE
WAS YOU HAD CRITICIZED MITT
ROMNEY FOR SELF-DEPORTATION.
YOU SAID THAT HIS STRATEGY OF
SELF-DEPORTATION IS WHY HE LOST
THE ELECTION.
AND I THINK PEOPLE IN FLORIDA
WOULD BE SURPRISED, BECAUSE, IN
FACT, THE ARTICLE THAT WAS
TODAY, THEY INTERVIEWED A NUMBER
OF PEOPLE, THAT WOULD HAVE BEEN
WILLING TO DO THOSE JOBS, IF YOU
WOULD HAVE BEEN WILLING TO HIRE
THEM TO DO IT.
>> I CRITICIZE MITT ROMNEY FOR
LOSING THE ELECTION.
HE SHOULD HAVE WON THAT
ELECTION.
HE HAD A FAILED PRESIDENT, HE
RAN A TERRIBLE CAMPAIGN, HE WAS
A TERRIBLE CANDIDATE.
THAT'S WHAT I CRITICIZE MITT
ROMNEY --
>> HE --
>> EXCUSE ME.
HE RAN ONE TERRIBLE CAMPAIGN.
THAT'S AN ELECTION THAT SHOULD
HAVE BEEN WON.
>> WELL, IN FACT, I AGREE HE
SHOULD HAVE WON AND I WISHED HE
WOULD HAVE, WAS, IN FACT, YOU
DID CRITICIZE HIM FOR USING THE
TERM "SELF-DEPORTATION."
THAT'S ON THE RECORD AND PEOPLE
CAN LOOK IT UP RIGHT NOW ONLINE.
BUT I WANT TO REITERATE, I THINK
IT'S REALLY IMPORTANT, THIS
POINT.
I THINK IT'S FINE, IT'S AN
IMPORTANT POINT YOU RAISE AND WE
DISCUSS ON IMMIGRATION.
THIS IS A BIG ISSUE FOR TEXAS
AND A HUGE ISSUE FOR THE
COUNTRY.
BUT I ALSO THINK THAT IF YOU'RE
GOING TO CLAIM THAT YOU'RE THE
ONLY ONE THAT LIFTED THIS INTO
THE CAMPAIGN, THAT YOU
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT, FOR EXAMPLE,
YOU'RE ONLY PERSON ON THIS STAGE
THAT'S EVER BEEN FIND FOR HIRING
PEOPLE TO WORK ON YOUR PROJECTS
ILLEGALLY.
YOU HIRED SOME --
>> NO, NO, I'M THE ONLY ONE AT
THIS STAGE THAT'S HIRED PEOPLE.
YOU HAVEN'T HIRED ANYBODY.
>> IN FACT, SOME OF THE
PEOPLE --
>> AND BY THE WAY -- I'VE
HIRED --
>> AND BY THE WAY --
>> I'VE HIRED TENS OF THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE OVER MY JOB.
YOU'VE HIRED NOBODY.
YOU'VE HAD NOTHING BUT PROBLEMS
WITH YOUR CREDIT CARDS, ET
CETERA.
>> LET ME -- DON'T ME --
>> SENATOR, HOLD ON.
>> YOU HAVEN'T HIRED ONE PERSON,
YOU LIAR.
>> HE HIRED WORKERS FROM POLAND.
>> THAT'S WRONG.
TOTALLY WRONG.
>> PEOPLE CAN LOOK IT UP.
I'M SURE PEOPLE ARE GOOGLING
RIGHT NOW.
POLISH WORKERS.
FINED $1 MILLION FOR HIRING
POLISH WORKERS ON ONE OF HIS
PROJECTS.
HE DID IT.
THAT HAPPENED.
>> I'VE HIRED TENS OF THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE OVER MY LIFETIME.
TENS OF THOUSANDS.
>> MANY FROM OTHER COUNTRIES
INSTEAD OF HIRING AMERICANS.
>> JUST BE QUIET.
LET ME TALK.
I'VE HIRED TENS OF THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE.
HE BRINGS UP SOMETHING FROM 30
YEARS AGO, IT WORKED OUT VERY
WELL.
EVERYBODY WAS --
>> YEAH, YOU PAID $1 MILLION --
>> BY THE WAY, THE LAWS WERE
TOTALLY DIFFERENT.
THAT WAS A WHOLE DIFFERENT
WORLD.
>> THANK YOU.
>> BUT I'VE HIRED PEOPLE.
NOBODY UP HERE HAS HIRED
ANYBODY.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU SAY YOU
WANT TO O DEPORT THE 11 MILLION
UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS, BUT YOU
NEVER WANT TO ALLOW THEM TO COME
BACK TO THE UNITED STATES.
WHAT WOULD HAPPEN TO THE
CHILDREN WHO ARE U.S.-BORN
CITIZENS WHOSE PARENT WILL BE
DEPORTED UNDER YOUR PLAN?
>> WELL, EXISTING LAW PROVIDES
THAT THOSE WHO ARE DEPORTED
CANNOT COME BACK HERE LEGALLY.
U.S. CITIZENS CAN COME BACK.
THAT'S EXISTING LAW.
BUT LET ME SAY, WOLF, I REALLY
FIND IT AMAZING THAT DONALD
BELIEVES THAT HE IS THE ONE WHO
DISCOVERED THE ISSUE OF ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION.
I CAN TELL YOU, WHEN I RAN FOR
SENATE HERE IN THE STATE OF
TEXAS, I RAN PROMISING TO LEAD
THE FIGHT AGAINST AMNESTY,
PROMISING TO FIGHT TO BUILD A
WALL, AND IN 2013, WHEN I WAS
LEADING THE FIGHT AGAINST THE
GANG OF EIGHT AMNESTY BILL,
WHERE WAS DONALD?
HE WAS FIRING DENNIS RODMAN ON
"CELEBRITY APPRENTICE."
AND INDEED, IF YOU LOOK AT THE
GANG OF EIGHT, ONE INDIVIDUAL ON
THIS STAGE BROKE HIS PROMISE TO
THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO ELECTED
HIM AND WROTE THE AMNESTY BILL.
BUT DONALD FUNDED THE GANG OF
EIGHT.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE EIGHT MEMBERS
OF THE GANG OF EIGHT, DONALD
GAVE OVER $50,000 TO THREE
DEMOCRATS AND TWO REPUBLICANS.
AND WHEN YOU'RE FUNDING OPEN
BORDER POLITICIANS, YOU
SHOULDN'T BE SURPRISED WHEN THEY
FIGHT FOR OPEN BORDERS.
AND I THINK IF YOU WANT TO KNOW
WHO ACTUALLY WILL SECURE THE
BORDERS AND FOLLOW THROUGH, YOU
OUGHT TO ASK, WHO HAS A RECORD
BEFORE THEY WERE A CANDIDATE FOR
PRESIDENT, OF FIGHTING TO SECURE
THE BORDERS AND STOP AMNESTY,
AND I'M THE ONLY ONE ON THIS
STAGE THAT HAS THAT RECORD.
AND BY THE WAY, MARCO IS EXACTLY
RIGHT, THAT A FEDERAL COURT
FOUND DONALD GUILTY OF BEING
PART OF A CONSPIRACY --
>> THANK YOU.
>> -- TO HIRE PEOPLE ILLEGALLY
AND ENTERED A $1 MILLION
JUDGMENT AGAINST HIM.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> I CAN ONLY SAY THIS.
AND I'VE SAID IT LOUD AND CLEAR
AND I'VE SAID IT FOR YEARS.
AND MANY OF THESE PEOPLE ARE
SITTING RIGHT IN THE AUDIENCE
RIGHT NOW, YOUR LOBBYISTS AND
SPECIAL INTERESTS AND YOUR
DONORS, BECAUSE THE AUDIENCE IS
PACKED WITH THEM AND THEY'RE
PACKED WITH YOU.
I'VE HAD AN AMAZING RELATIONSHIP
WITH POLITICIANS -- WITH
POLITICIANS, BOTH DEMOCRAT,
REPUBLICAN, BECAUSE I WAS A
BUSINESSMAN.
AS ONE MAGAZINE SAID, HE'S A
WORLD-CLASS BUSINESSMAN, HE WAS
FRIENDLY WITH EVERYBODY.
I GOT ALONG WITH EVERYBODY.
YOU GET ALONG WITH NOBODY.
YOU DON'T HAVE ONE REPUBLICAN --
YOU DON'T HAVE ONE REPUBLICAN
SENATOR, AND YOU WORK WITH THEM
EVERY DAY OF YOUR LIFE, ALTHOUGH
YOU SKIPPED A LOT OF TIME, THESE
ARE MINOR DETAILS.
BUT YOU DON'T HAVE ONE
REPUBLICAN SENATOR BACKING YOU,
NOT ONE.
YOU DON'T HAVE THE ENDORSEMENT
OF ONE REPUBLICAN SENATOR AND
YOU WORK WITH THESE PEOPLE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> YOU SHOULD BE ASHAMED OF
YOURSELF.
>> YOU KNOW, I ACTUALLY THINK
DONALD IS RIGHT.
HE IS PROMISING, IF HE'S
ELECTED, HE WILL GO AND CUT
DEALS IN WASHINGTON.
AND HE'S RIGHT.
HE HAS SUPPORTED --
>> GOOD DEALS.
>> BUT HE HAS GIVEN HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS TO
DEMOCRATS.
ANYONE WHO REALLY CARED ABOUT
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION WOULDN'T BE
HIRING ILLEGAL IMMIGRANTS.
ANYONE WHO REALLY CARED ABOUT
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION WOULDN'T BE
FUNDING HARRY REID AND NANCY
PELOSI, WOULDN'T BE FUNDING THE
GANG OF EIGHT.
AND, YOU KNOW, HE IS RIGHT.
WHEN YOU STAND UP TO WASHINGTON,
WHEN YOU HONOR THE PROMISE YOU
MADE TO THE MEN AND WOMEN WHO
ELECTED YOU AND SAY, ENOUGH WITH
THE CORRUPTION, ENOUGH WITH THE
CRONYISM, LET'S ACTUALLY STAND
FOR THE WORKING MEN AND WOMEN OF
THIS COUNTRY, WASHINGTON DOESN'T
LIKE IT, AND DONALD, IF YOU WANT
TO BE LIKED IN WASHINGTON,
THAT'S NOT A GOOD ATTRIBUTE FOR
A PRESIDENT.
>> THIS IS ROBIN HOOD OVER HERE.
HE TALKS ABOUT CORRUPTION ON HIS
FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE FORM, HE
DIDN'T EVEN PUT THAT HE'S
BORROWED MONEY FROM CITIBANK AND
FROM GOLDMAN SACHS, WHICH IS A
TOTAL VIOLATION.
HE DIDN'T TALK ABOUT THE FACT
THAT HE PAYS ALMOST NO INTEREST.
HE JUST LEFT IT OFF, AND NOW
HE'S GOING TO PROTECT THE PEOPLE
FROM THE BIG, BAD BANKS.
GIVE ME A BREAK.
>> WE'LL MOVE ON TO GOVERNOR
KASICH.
>> CAN I RESPOND?
>> YOU CAN RESPOND, BUT LET ME
GET GOVERNOR KASICH IN.
HE'S BEEN WAITING PATIENTLY.
GOVERNOR KASICH?
THE IDEA -- YOU'VE SAID THIS AND
I WANT TO QUOTE YOU NOW.
THE IDEA THAT WE'RE GOING TO
DEPORT ALL THESE PEOPLE IS
LUDICROUS AND EVERYBODY KNOWS
IT.
THOSE ARE YOUR WORDS.
SHOULD PEOPLE BE ALLOWED TO
BREAK THE LAW, JUST BECAUSE IT'S
NOT FEASIBLE TO STOP THEM?
>> LOOK, WE HAVE A GREAT
PRESIDENT HERE, GEORGE BUSH,
41st PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, HE WORKED WITH RONALD
REAGAN, TO PASS AN EFFORT TO TRY
TO SOLVE THIS PROBLEM.
A PATH TO LEGALIZATION.
YOU SEE, THAT WAS A TIME WHEN
THINGS WORKED.
IT WAS A TIME WHEN PRESIDENT
REAGAN AND GEORGE BUSH DECIDED
THAT WE NEED TO MAKE THE COUNTRY
WORK.
LOOK, I THINK THERE IS AN ANSWER
HERE.
THE ANSWER IS, YOU COMPLETE THE
BORDER.
YOU LET PEOPLE KNOW, ONCE IT'S
DONE, YOU DON'T HAVE A RIGHT TO
COME IN.
IF YOU COME IN, WE DON'T WANT
ANY EXCUSE, YOU'RE GOING TO GO
BACK.
BUT I FAVOR A GUEST WORKER
PROGRAM.
I THINK IT'S PRACTICAL.
AND I THINK FOR THE 11 OR 11.5
MILLION AMERICANS, THE ILLEGALS
THAT ARE HERE, IF THEY HAVE NOT
COMMITTED A CRIME SINCE THEY'VE
BEEN HERE, I'D MAKE THEM PAY A
FINE, SOME BACK TAXES, MAYBE
SOME COMMUNITY SERVICE, AND AT
THE END, I WOULD GIVE THEM A
PATH TO LEGALIZATION, BUT NOT A
PATH TO CITIZENSHIP.
I DON'T THINK WE'RE GOING TO
TEAR FAMILIES APART.
RIDE AROUND IN PEOPLE'S
NEIGHBORHOODS AND GRAB PEOPLE
OUT OF THEIR HOMES.
FIRST OF ALL, I DON'T THINK IT'S
PRACTICAL AND I DON'T THINK IT
REFLECTS AMERICA.
YOU KNOW WHAT HAPPENED?
THE PROBLEM WITH PRESIDENT
REAGAN IS WE DIDN'T GET IN THERE
AND ACTUALLY FINISH THE BORDER.
AND I THINK IT WAS PROBABLY
BUSINESS INTERESTS THAT AFFECTED
IT.
BUT AT THE END OF THE DAY, LET'S
BE PRACTICAL.
LET'S START SOLVING PROBLEMS IN
THIS COUNTRY INSTEAD OF KICKING
THEM UPSTAIRS WITH, AND WITH
PRESIDENT REAGAN AND GEORGE
BUSH, IT WAS A BIPARTISAN
COALITION TO ADDRESS THE ISSUE,
AND I THINK WE CAN AND SHOULD DO
IT AGAIN AND I WILL HAVE A PLAN
IN THE FIRST HUNDRED DAYS TO GET
IT DONE AND GET THIS ISSUE
BEHIND US.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
DR. CARSON?
YOU'VE BEEN CRITICAL OF MASS
DEPORTATION.
YOU SAID BACK IN NOVEMBER, YOU
DON'T THINK MR. TRUMP'S PLAN
NECESSARILY REPRESENTS THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY.
GIVEN HOW WELL MR. TRUMP HAS
BEEN DOING WITH THE REPUBLICAN
PRIMARY VOTERS, DO YOU STILL
BELIEVE THAT?
>> I BELIEVE IN LIBERTY AND
JUSTICE FOR ALL.
I THINK EVERYTHING THAT WE DO
SHOULD BE FAIR.
AND I'VE ALREADY DESCRIBED, YOU
KNOW, HOW WE CAN SECURE THE
BORDER.
WE NEED TO SECURE ALL THE
BORDERS, BECAUSE IT'S NOT JUST
PEOPLE COMING IN FROM SOUTH
AMERICA AND MEXICO, BUT THERE
ARE TERRORISTS WHO WANT TO
DESTROY US, WHO ARE GETTING
ACROSS OUR BORDERS FAIRLY
EASILY.
AND WE HAVE TO STOP THAT.
BUT IN TERMS OF THE PEOPLE WHO
ARE HERE ALREADY, AFTER WE STOP
THE ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION, WE NEED
TO BE REASONABLE.
AND I WOULD GIVE THEM A
SIX-MONTH PERIOD IN WHICH TO GET
REGISTERED, AS A GUEST WORKER,
ASSUMING THEY HAVE AN ACCEPTABLE
RECORD, THEY HAVE TO PAY A
BACK-TAX PENALTY, HAVE TO PAY
TAXES GOING FORWARD, BUT DON'T
HAVE TO LIVE UNDERGROUND
ANYMORE, AND I THINK THEY DO NOT
BECOME AMERICAN CITIZENS, THEY
DO NOT VOTE.
IF THEY WANT TO BECOME AN
AMERICAN CITIZEN, THEY GO
THROUGH EXACTLY THE SAME PROCESS
THAT ANYBODY ELSE GOES THROUGH.
I THINK THAT'S THE KIND OF
SITUATION THAT IS ACTUALLY FAIR
TO PEOPLE.
AND WE HAVE OTHER WAYS OF
UTILIZING OUR FACILITIES AND OUR
TALENTS, AS FOREIGN AID.
DOING THINGS IN SOUTH AMERICA
AND CENTRAL AMERICA AND MEXICO
THAT IMPROVE THE ECONOMY THERE,
SO THAT THEY DON'T FEEL THE NEED
TO COME OVER HERE.
THAT WOULD COST US A LOT LESS
THAN BORROWING MONEY FROM CHINA,
PAYING INTEREST ON IT.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
MR. TRUMP?
YOUR CAMPAIGN, AS YOU WELL
REMEMBER, BEGAN WITH THE IDEA OF
BUILDING A WALL ALONG THE
SOUTHERN BORDER, IT'S ABOUT 315
MILES SOUTHWEST OF WHERE WE ARE
RIGHT NOW.
YOU'VE SAID THE MEXICAN
GOVERNMENT WILL PAY FOR IT.
>> CORRECT.
>> THE SPOKESPERSON FOR THE
CURRENT PRESIDENT OF MEXICO
SAYS, THAT WILL NEVER HAPPEN.
THE LAST TWO PRESIDENTS OF
MEXICO SAY, THAT WILL NEVER
HAPPEN.
IN FACT, THE FORMER PRESIDENT OF
MEXICO, VICENTE FOX, HE SAID
TODAY, AND I'M QUOTING HIM, HE
SAID, I'M NOT GOING TO PAY FOR
THAT, QUOTE, EFFING WALL.
SO IF YOU DON'T GET AN ACTUAL
CHECK FROM THE MEXICAN
GOVERNMENT FOR $8 BILLION OR $10
BILLION OR $12 BILLION, WHATEVER
IT WILL COST, HOW ARE YOU GOING
TO MAKE THEM PAY FOR THE WALL?
>> I WILL AND THE WALL JUST GOT
10 FEET TALLER, BELIEVE ME.
IT JUST GOT 10 FEET TALLER.
I SAW HIM MAKE THAT -- I SAW HIM
MAKE THE STATEMENT.
I SAW HIM USE THE WORD THAT HE
USED.
I CAN ONLY TELL YOU, IF I WOULD
HAVE USED EVEN HALF OF THAT
WORD, IT WOULD HAVE BEEN
NATIONAL SCANDAL.
THIS GUY USED A FILTHY,
DISGUSTING WORD ON TELEVISION
AND HE SHOULD BE ASHAMED OF
HIMSELF AND HE SHOULD APOLOGIZE,
OKAY?
NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO, WE HAVE A TRADE
DEFICIT WITH MEXICO OF $58
BILLION A YEAR.
AND THAT DOESN'T INCLUDE ALL THE
DRUGS THAT ARE POURING ACROSS
AND DESTROYING OUR COUNTRY.
WE'RE GOING TO MAKE THEM PAY FOR
THAT WALL.
NOW, THE WALL IS $10 BILLION TO
$12 BILLION, IF I DO IT.
IF THESE GUYS DO IT, IT WILL END
UP COSTING $200 BILLION.
BUT THE WALL IS $10 BILLION TO
$12 BILLION.
YOU NEED A THOUSAND MILES.
THE GREAT WALL OF CHINA, BUILT
2,000 YEARS AGO, 2,000, IS
13,000 MILES.
WE NEED A THOUSAND, BECAUSE WE
HAVE A LOT OF NATURAL BARRIERS.
WE CAN DO IT FOR 10 TO 12, AND
THIS IS A REAL WALL.
THIS IS A WALL THAT'S A HECK OF
A LOT HIGHER THAN THE CEILING
YOU'RE LOOKING AT.
THIS IS A WALL THAT'S GOING TO
WORK.
MEXICO WILL PAY FOR IT, BECAUSE
THEY'RE NOT DOING US ANY FAVORS.
THEY COULD STOP ALL OF THIS
ILLEGAL TRADE IF THEY WANTED TO,
IMMEDIATELY.
MEXICO WILL PAY FOR THE WALL.
IT'S A SMALL PORTION OF THE KIND
OF MONEY THAT WE LOSE AND THE
DEFICITS THAT WE HAVE WITH
MEXICO.
>> IF THE --
IF THE MEXICANS DON'T PAY FOR
THE WALL, WILL YOU START A TRADE
WAR WITH MEXICO?
>> YOU KNOW, I DON'T MIND TRADE
WARS WHEN WE'RE LOSING $58
BILLION A YEAR, YOU WANT TO KNOW
THE TRUTH.
WE'RE LOSING SO MUCH.
WE'RE LOSING SO MUCH WITH MEXICO
AND CHINA, WITH CHINA, WE'RE
LOSING $500 BILLION A YEAR.
AND THEN PEOPLE SAY, OH, DON'T
WE WANT TO TRADE?
I DON'T MIND TRADING, BUT I
DON'T WANT TO LOSE $500 BILLION.
I DON'T WANT TO LOSE $58
BILLION.
MEXICO JUST TOOK CARRIER
OPERATION, MAKER OF
AIR-CONDITIONERS.
THEY JUST TOOK FORD.
THEY'RE BUILDING A $2.5 BILLION
PLANT.
THEY JUST TOOK NABISCO OUT OF
CHICAGO.
AND I ALWAYS SAY, I'M NOT HAVING
OREOS ANYMORE, WHICH IS TRUE, BY
THE WAY.
BUT THEY JUST TOOK A BIG PLANT
FROM NABISCO INTO MEXICO.
THEY'RE TAKING OUR BUSINESSES.
I DON'T MIND.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> YEAH, A COUPLE POINTS.
IF HE BUILDS THE WALL THE WAY HE
BUILT TRUMP TOWERS, HE'LL BE
USING ILLEGAL IMMIGRANT LABOR TO
DO IT.
>> SUCH A CUTE SOUND BITE.
>> IT'S NOT A SOUND BITE.
IT'S A FACT.
AGAIN, GO ONLINE AND GOOGLE IT.
DONALD TRUMP, POLISH WORKERS.
THE SECOND THING ABOUT THE TRADE
WAR, I DON'T UNDERSTAND, BECAUSE
YOUR CLOTHES AND THE TIE YOU
WEAR ARE MADE IN MEXICAN AND IN
CHINA.
YOU'LL BE STARTING A TRADE WAR
AGAINST YOUR OWN CLOTHES AND
SUITS.
>> THEY DEVALUE THEIR
CURRENCIES --
>> MAKE THEM IN AMERICA.
>> YOU DON'T KNOW A THING ABOUT
BUSINESS.
>> WELL, MAKE THEM IN AMERICA.
>> LET ME JUST TELL YOU, THEY
DEVALUE THEIR CURRENCIES, CHINA,
MEXICO, EVERYBODY, JAPAN, WITH
THE CARS.
THEY DEVALUE THEIR CURRENCIES TO
SUCH AN EXTENT THAT OUR
BUSINESSES CANNOT COMPETE WITH
THEM.
OUR WORKERS LOSE THEIR JOBS.
>> THAT'S WHY YOU MAKE THEM IN
CHINA AND RUSSIA --
>> YOU DON'T KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
IT BECAUSE YOU'RE A LOUSY
BUSINESSMAN.
>> I DON'T KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
BANKRUPTING COMPANIES.
I DON'T KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
STARTING A FAKE UNIVERSITY.
>> ONE AT A TIME.
>> A FAKE UNIVERSITY!
THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO BORROW
$36,000 TO GO TO TRUMP
UNIVERSITY AND THEY'RE SUING HIM
NOW.
$36,000 TO GO TO A UNIVERSITY --
>> AND BY THE WAY -- AND BY THE
WAY --
>> THAT'S A FAKE SCHOOL.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT THEY GOT, THEY
GOT TO TAKE A PICTURE WITH A
CARDBOARD CUTOUT OF DONALD
TRUMP.
THAT'S WHAT THEY GOT FOR
$36,000.
>> AND THEY ACTUALLY DID A VERY
GOOD JOB.
I WON MOST OF THE LAWSUIT.
>> MOST OF THE LAWSUIT.
>> I WANT TO BRING IN MY
COLLEAGUE, MARIE --
>> AM I ALLOWED TO RESPOND TO
THIS?
>> YOU'RE ALLOWED -- YOU'VE BEEN
RESPONDING.
>> I HAVEN'T.
I REALLY HAVEN'T.
>> HE'S TALKED THE THROUGH THE
WHOLE THING.
>> HERE'S A GUY WHO BUYS A HOUSE
FOR $179,000 AND SELLS TO IT A
LOBBYIST WHO'S PROBABLY HERE FOR
$380,000 AND THEN LEGISLATION IS
PASSED.
YOU TELL ME -- THIS GUY!
>> HERE'S THE GUY THAT INHERITED
$200 MILLION.
IF HE HADN'T INHERITED $200
MILLION, YOU KNOW WHERE DONALD
TRUMP WOULD BE RIGHT NOW,
SELLING WATCHES --
>> NO, NO, NO, THAT IS SO WRONG.
WE'LL WORK ON THAT.
I TOOK $1 MILLION AND I TURNED
IT INTO $10 BILLION.
I BORROWED $1 MILLION --
>> THEN RELEASE YOUR TAX RETURN.
>> I BORROWED $1 MILLION --
>> HE DOESN'T MAKE THAT MUCH
MONEY.
>> THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BRING IN MARIA CELESTE
OF TELEMUNDO.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, LAST WEEK YOU
SAID THAT ON YOUR FIRST DAY IN
OFFICE, YOU WILL GET RID OF
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S EXECUTIVE
ACTION, KNOWN AS DEFERRED ACTION
FOR CHILDHOOD ARRIVALS, DACA FOR
SHORT.
IT'S A PROGRAM THAT HAS
PROTECTED HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS
OF YOUNG PEOPLE THAT CAME HERE
WHEN THEY WERE CHILDREN, BROUGHT
TO THE U.S. BY UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS.
THIS IS THE ONLY HOME THEY KNOW.
AND THAT IS A DRAMATIC CHANGE
FROM LAST APRIL, WHEN YOU SAID
IN SPANISH, AND I'M GOING TO
QUOTE YOU --
[ SPEAKING SPANISH ]
WHICH TRANSLATES TO, DACA IS
GOING TO HAVE TO END AT SOME
POINT, BUT IT WOULDN'T BE FAIR
TO CANCEL IT IMMEDIATELY.
SO SENATOR RUBIO, WHAT CHANGED?
>> IT DIDN'T CHANGE.
>> WHY IS IT NOW FAIR TO CANCEL
IT ON DAY ONE?
>> NO, IT'S THE SAME POLICY.
IT WILL HAVE TO END AT SOME
MOMENT, AND AS I SAID, WE WILL
ELIMINATE THAT EXECUTIVE ORDER.
THE PEOPLE THAT ARE ON IT NOW
WILL NOT BE ALLOWED TO RENEW IT
AND NEW APPLICANTS WILL NOW BE
ALLOWED TO APPLY TO IT.
AND IT'S NOT BECAUSE WE'RE NOT
COMPASSIONATE TO THE PLIGHT OF
SOMEONE WHO CAME HERE WHEN THEY
WERE 2 YEARS OLD.
WE UNDERSTAND.
I KNOW PEOPLE WHO ARE PERSONALLY
IMPACTED BY THAT.
THE PROBLEM WITH THE EXECUTIVE
ORDER IS IT IS UNCONSTITUTIONAL.
THE PRESIDENT DOESN'T HAVE THE
POWER TO DO THAT.
AND HE HIMSELF ADMITTED THAT.
>> SENATOR, SENATOR --
>> I'M SORRY, BUT --
>> BUT YOU WENT FROM SAYING THAT
IT WAS DEEPLY DISRUPTIVE TO
DEPORT THEM IMMEDIATELY TO
DEPORT THEM ON DAY ONE.
>> NO, THIS IS NOT ABOUT
DEPORTATION.
EVERYBODY ALWAYS GOES
IMMEDIATELY TO THE ISSUE OF
DEPORTATION.
THIS IS ABOUT DACA.
DACA IS AN EXECUTIVE ORDER THAT
IS UNCONSTITUTIONAL.
I WILL CANCEL IT ON MY FIRST DAY
IN OFFICE.
WHICH MEANS PEOPLE WHO CURRENTLY
HOLD THOSE PERMS WILL NOT BE
ALLOWED TO RENEW THEM WHEN THEY
EXPIRE AND NEW PEOPLE WILL NOT
BE ABLE TO APPLY THEM.
I AM SYMPATHETIC TO THE PLIGHT
OF PEOPLE WHO CAME HERE WHEN
THEY WERE 2 OR 3 YEARS OLD
THROUGH NO FAULT OF THEIR OWN.
NO MATTER HOW SYMPATHETIC WE MAY
BE TO A CAUSE, WE CAN NOT
VIOLATE THE CONSTITUTION OF THE
UNITED STATES THE WAY THIS
PRESIDENT NOW DOES ON A REGULAR
BASIS.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU ACCUSED
SENATOR CRUZ IN A PREVIOUS
DEBATE OF LYING WHEN HE SAID
THAT YOU SAID ONE THING IN
SPANISH AND ANOTHER ONE IN
ENGLISH.
SO IN WHAT SENSE DID HE LIE?
>> BECAUSE IT IS NOT TRUE THAT
I'M NOT GOING TO GET RID OF
DACA.
I AM GOING TO GET RID OF DACA.
IN THE SPANISH INTERVIEW, YOU
JUST READ OUT THE TRANSCRIPT IN
SPANISH, I SAID, IT WILL HAVE TO
END.
THAT WILL BE WHEN I ELIMINATE
THE EXECUTIVE ORDER AND THE
PEOPLE WHO HAVE THOSE PERMITS
WHEN THEY EXPIRE WILL NOT BE
ABLE TO RENEW IT.
AND NEW PEOPLE WILL NOT BE
ALLOWED TO APPLY.
AND THAT IS HOW THE PROGRAM ENDS
AND HOW YOU WIND IT DOWN.
YOU ALLOW THE PEOPLE WHO ARE ON
IT, WHEN THE PROGRAM EXPIRES,
THEY CANNOT RENEW IT, AND IT
GOES AWAY.
BUT I WILL CANCEL THE EXECUTIVE
ORDER AS SOON AS I TAKE -- AS
SOON AS I STEP FOOT INTO THE
OVAL OFFICE.
>> I HAVE TO SAY, HE LIED THIS
TIME.
HE LIED.
100%.
>> YOU LIED ABOUT THE POLISH
WORKERS.
>> YEAH, YEAH, YEAH.
38 YEARS AGO.
>> OH, HE LIED 38 YEARS AGO.
I GUESS THERE'S A STATUTE OF
LIMITATION ON LIES.
>> MARIA, I WOULD NOTE YOU MADE
THE EXACT SAME POINT I MADE AT
THE LAST DEBATE AND I WOULD
AGREE SENATOR RUBIO CALLED ME A
LIAR FOR SAYING THAT.
WE'VE ALL SEEN AT HOME WHEN
POLITICIANS SAY, IT WILL HAVE TO
END SOME DAY IN THE FUTURE.
THAT IS INEVITABLY WHEN A
POLITICIAN DOESN'T PLAN TO END
IT AT ALL.
I'M REMINDED OF, THAT IS THE
SAME POSITION THAT MARCO TOOK IN
IOWA ON ETHANOL SUBSIDIES.
WHEN I CAMPAIGNED IN IOWA AND
TOOK ON THE LOBBYISTS, TOOK ON
THE CORPORATE WELFARE, AND SAID,
WE SHOULD HAVE NO ETHANOL
SUBSIDIES, MARCO'S POSITION WAS
THE SAME AS IT IS TOWARDS
ILLEGAL AMNESTY.
WELL, SOME DAY IT SHOULD END,
JUST NOT NOW.
AND FRANKLY, I THINK WE NEED A
PRESIDENT WHO KNOWS WHAT HE
BELIEVES AND IS WILLING TO SAY
IT ON DAY ONE, NOT AT THE END OF
HIS TERM WHEN IT'S SOMEBODY
ELSE'S PROBLEM.
>> THAT'S NOT AN ACCURATE
ASSESSMENT OF WHAT I SAID ABOUT
ETHANOL.
WHAT I SAID IS ETHANOL WILL
PHASE OUT.
IT IS FACING OUT NOW.
BY 2022, THAT PROGRAM EXPIRES,
BY VIRTUE OF THE EXISTING LAW
AND AT THAT POINT IT WILL GO
AWAY.
I DON'T AGREE WITH THE MANDATE
AND THE PROGRAM THAT'S IN PLACE.
BUT I THINK IT'S UNFAIR THAT
THESE PEOPLE HAVE GONE OUT AND
INVESTED ALL THIS MONEY INTO
THIS PROGRAM AND WE'RE JUST
GOING TO YANK IT AWAY FROM THEM.
AND AGAIN, YOU READ THE
STATEMENT IN SPANISH.
I SAID VERY CLEARLY ON SPANISH
TELEVISION, DACA WILL HAVE TO
END AT SOME POINT, AND AT THAT
TIME, I WAS NOT A CANDIDATE FOR
PRESIDENT.
I SAID, IT WILL END ON MY FIRST
DAY IN OFFICE AS PRESIDET, AND
THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE IT NOW WILL
NOT BE ABLE TO RENEW IT AND NEW
APPLICANTS WILL NOT BE ABLE TO
APPLY.
THAT IS THE END OF DACA.
I AM SYMPATHETIC TO THIS CAUSE.
BUT ONCE AGAIN, IT CANNOT
SUPERSEDE THE CONSTITUTION OF
THE UNITED STATES, WHICH THIS
PRESIDENT HABITUALLY AND
ROUTINELY, EVERY SINGLE DAY,
IGNORES AND VIOLATES.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU AND SENATOR
RUBIO ARE THE TWO CANDIDATES OF
HISPANIC DESCENT ON THE STAGE.
AS A MATTER OF FACT, YOU ARE THE
FIRST HISPANIC CANDIDATE EVER TO
WIN A CAUCUS OR PRIMARY.
AND YET THERE IS THE --
AND YET THERE IS THE PERCEPTION
IN THE LATINO COMMUNITY THAT
INSTEAD OF TRYING TO PROVE TO
LATINOS WHO HAS THE BEST PLAN,
THE BEST PLATFORM TO HELP THEM,
THAT YOU TWO ARE SPENDING THE
TIME ARGUING WITH EACH OTHER,
TRYING TO FIGURE OUT WHICH ONE
IS TOUGHER ON IMMIGRATION, IN
ORDER TO APPEAL TO THE MAJORITY
OF REPUBLICANS.
SO MY QUESTION TO YOU IS, ARE
YOU MISSING A HUGE OPPORTUNITY
TO EXPAND THE REPUBLICAN BASE?
>> WELL, MARIA, LISTEN.
YOU ARE RIGHT.
IT IS EXTRAORDINARY THAT OUT OF
THE FIVE PEOPLE STANDING ON THIS
STAGE, THAT TWO OF US ARE THE
CHILDREN OF CUBAN IMMIGRANTS.
IT REALLY IS AN EMBODIMENT OF
THE INCREDIBLE OPPORTUNITY AND
PROMISE THIS NATION PROVIDES.
YOU KNOW, I WOULD NOTE THAT A
LOT OF FOLKS IN THE MEDIA HAVE A
DEFINITION OF HISPANICS THAT YOU
COULD ONLY BE HISPANIC IF YOU'RE
LIBERAL.
THAT MAKES SENSE IN THE MEDIA,
BUT I'VE GOT TO TELL YOU, ONE OF
THE THINGS I WAS MOST PROUD OF,
WHEN I RAN FOR SENATE HERE IN
TEXAS, I EARNED 40% OF THE
HISPANIC VOTE HERE IN TEXAS, AT
THE SAME TIME, MITT ROMNEY WAS
GETTING CLOBBERED WITH 27% OF
THE HISPANIC VOTE NATIONWIDE.
AND THE REASON IS, AS YOU KNOW,
YOU LOOK AT THE VALUES IN THE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY, THE VALUES
IN OUR COMMUNITY ARE FAITH,
FAMILY, PATRIOTISM.
YOU KNOW, WE'VE GOT THE HIGHEST
RATE OF MILITARY ENLISTMENT
AMONG HISPANICS OF ANY
DEMOGRAPHIC IN THIS COUNTRY.
AND WHEN I CAMPAIGNED AND I
CAMPAIGNED THE SAME HERE IN
HOUSTON OR DALLAS, AS I DID DOWN
IN THE RIO GRANDE VALLEY,
DEFENDING CONSERVATIVE
PRINCIPLES, DEFENDING
JUDEO-CHRISTIAN PRINCIPLES,
TELLING MY FATHER'S STORY.
TELLING MY DAD'S STORY OF COMING
TO AMERICA WITH $100 IN HIS
UNDERWEAR, NOT SPEAKING ENGLISH,
WASHING DISHES, HAVING HOPES AND
DREAMS FOR THE AMERICAN DREAM,
AND THE TRUTH IS, THE
OBAMA/CLINTON ECONOMY HAS DONE
ENORMOUS DAMAGE TO THE HISPANIC
COMMUNITY.
IT IS NOT WORKING IN THE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY, AND I AM
FIGHTING SO THAT EVERYONE WHO IS
STRUGGLING IN THE HISPANIC
COMMUNITY AND BEYOND WILL HAVE A
FAIR AND EVEN SHAKE AND THE
AMERICAN DREAM.
>> MARIA, I WAS MENTIONED IN
THAT.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH --
>> I WAS MENTIONED.
I'LL BE BRIEF.
A COUPLE POINTS.
NUMBER ONE, I DO THINK IT'S
AMAZING THAT ON THE STAGE
TONIGHT, THERE ARE TWO DESCENDS
OF IMMIGRANTS OF CUBAN ORIGIN
AND AN AFRICAN-AMERICAN.
WE ARE THE PARTY OF DIVERSITY.
NOT THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY.
AND THE SECOND POINT I WOULD
MAKE IS THAT WE HAVE TO MOVE
PAST THIS IDEA THAT SOMEHOW THE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY ONLY CARES
ABOUT IMMIGRATION.
YES, IT'S AN IMPORTANT ISSUE,
BECAUSE WE KNOW AND LOVE PEOPLE
THAT HAVE BEEN IMPACTED BY IT.
BUT I'M GOING TO TELL YOU, THE
MOST POWERFUL SENTIMENT IN THE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY, AS IT IS IN
EVERY IMMIGRANT COMMUNITY IS THE
BURNING DESIRE TO LEAVE YOUR
CHILDREN BETTER OFF THAN
YOURSELF.
AND YOU CAN ONLY DO THAT THROUGH
FREE ENTERPRISE.
THAT'S WHAT WE STAND FOR.
NOT SOCIALISM, LIKE BERNIE
SANDERS AND INCREASINGLY HILLARY
CLI
CLINTON.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, AFTER THE
LAST PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION, THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY REALIZED THAT
IN ORDER TO WIN THE PRESIDENCY,
IT NEEDED THE SUPPORT OF
LATINOS.
GUIDELINES AS TO HOW TO
ACCOMPLISH THAT WERE SPELLED OUT
IN AN AUTOPSY REPORT THAT
CONCLUDED, AND I'M GOING TO
QUOTE IT, IF HISPANIC AMERICANS
HEAR THAT THE GOP IN THE UNITED
STATES, THEY WON'T PAY ATTENTION
TO OUR NEXT SENTENCE.
SO DO YOU THINK THAT YOUR FELLOW
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES GET IT?
>> WELL, I'M NOT GOING TO TALK
ABOUT THAT.
I'VE GOT TO TELL YOU, I WAS WITH
THIS LITTLE 12-YEAR-OLD GIRL,
WAS AT A TOWN HALL MEETING, AND
SHE SAID, YOU KNOW, I DON'T LIKE
ALL THIS YELLING AND SCREAMING
AT THE DEBATES.
MY MOTHER'S THINKING I MIGHT NOT
BE ABLE TO WATCH THE THING
ANYMORE.
I THINK WE OUGHT TO MOVE BEYOND
THAT.
ABOUT WHAT THEY THINK.
I'M GOING TO TELL YOU WHAT I
THINK.
MY POSITION ON THIS WHOLE
IMMIGRATION ISSUE HAS BEEN CLEAR
FROM THE BEGINNING.
I HAVEN'T CHANGED ANYTHING WITH
IT.
AND, LOOK, MY VIEW IS, WE NEED
ECONOMIC GROWTH.
EVERYTHING STARTS WITH ECONOMIC
GROWTH.
AND HOW DO YOU GET IT?
COMMON SENSE REGULATIONS, LOWER
TAXES FOR BOTH BUSINESS AND
INDIVIDUALS, AND, OF COURSE, A
FISCAL PLAN THAT BALANCES THE
BUDGET.
THAT GIVES YOU ECONOMIC GROWTH.
I DID IT WHEN I WAS IN
WASHINGTON, AS THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE CHAIRMAN, NEGOTIATING
ACTUALLY WITH DEMOCRATS, THAT
GAVE US SURPLUSES, ECONOMIC
GROWTH, AND THE SAME THING IN
OHIO.
BUT HERE'S THE THING THAT I
BELIEVE.
ECONOMIC GROWTH IS NOT AN END
UNTO ITSELF.
WE HAVE NO MAKE SURE THAT
EVERYBODY HAS A SENSE THAT THEY
CAN RISE.
OF COURSE, OUR FRIENDS IN THE
HISPANIC COMMUNITY, OUR FRIENDS
IN THE AFRICAN-AMERICAN
COMMUNITY, THE PROMISE OF
AMERICA IS THAT OUR SYSTEM, WHEN
WE FOLLOW THE RIGHT FORMULA, IS
GOING TO GIVE OPPORTUNITY FOR
EVERYONE.
IT'S WHAT JACK KEMP USED TO SAY.
A RISING TIDE LIFTS ALL BOATS,
NOT JUST SOME BOATS, BUT ALL
BOATS.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT?
WITH ME IN THE HISPANIC
COMMUNITY, I THINK THEY LIKE ME.
AND I APPRECIATE THAT, BECAUSE I
WANT THEM TO HAVE THE SAME
OPPORTUNITY THAT I AND MY
CHILDREN AND MY WIFE AND THE
PEOPLE WE LOVE HAVE HAD IN THIS
COUNTRY.
IT'S TIME TO SOLVE PROBLEMS.
>> DR. CARSON, CONCERNING THIS
RECOMMENDATION OF REPORT, ARE
YOU, AS A CANDIDATE, GETTING IT?
>> I DIDN'T HEAR THE FIRST PART
OF THE QUESTION?
>> THE FIRST PART OF THE
QUESTION IS, THERE WAS A REPORT
THAT RECOMMENDED THAT IN ORDER
TO APPROACH HISPANICS AND BRING
THEM TO VOTE FOR THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY, CERTAIN THINGS NEEDED TO
HAPPEN.
AND ONE OF THEM WAS THAT THEY
SHOULDN'T FEEL LIKE THEY WERE
GOING TO GET KICKED OUT OF THE
UNITED STATES, OTHERWISE THEY
WOULDN'T PAY ATTENTION TO ONE
MORE SENTENCE FROM CANDIDATES.
>> OKAY, WELL, FIRST OF ALL, LET
ME JUST MENTION THAT LAST YEAR
AT THE NATIONAL ASSOCIATION FOR
LATINO ELECTED OFFICIALS, I WAS
THE ONLY ONE OF 17 REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES TO GO THERE.
AND THE REASON THAT I DON'T FEAR
GOING TO AN ORGANIZATION LIKE
THAT IS BECAUSE THE MESSAGE THAT
I GIVE IS THE SAME MESSAGE TO
EVERY GROUP.
YOU KNOW, THIS IS AMERICA.
AND WE NEED TO HAVE POLICIES
THAT ARE, THAT GIVE LIBERTY AND
JUSTICE TO ALL PEOPLE AND THAT'S
THE WAY THAT I HAVE FASHIONED
VIRTUALLY EVERY POLICY, LOOKING
AT THAT.
AND THAT'S THE WAY THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY GENERALLY
THINKS.
WE DON'T PICK AND CHOOSE WINNERS
AND LOSERS.
WE ARE COMPASSIONATE.
BUT REAL COMPASSION IS PROVIDING
PEOPLE WITH A LADDER OF
OPPORTUNITY TO CLIMB UP FROM A
STATE OF DEPENDENTS, TO BECOME
PART OF THE FABRIC OF AMERICA.
WHEN WE BEGIN TO EMPHASIZE THAT,
I THINK WE WILL ATTRACT
EVER
EVERYBODY.
>> MR. TRUMP, IT IS COMMON
KNOWLEDGE THAT THE HISPANIC VOTE
IS VERY IMPORTANT IN THIS RACE.
YOU KEEP SAYING THAT HISPANICS
LOVE YOU.
>> TRUE.
>> AND, YES, YOU WON THE
HISPANIC VOTE IN NEVADA.
>> TRUE.
>> BUT A BRAND-NEW TELEMUNDO
POLL SAYS THAT THREE OUT OF FOUR
HISPANICS THAT VOTE NATIONWIDE
HAVE A NEGATIVE OPINION OF YOU.
THEY DON'T LIKE YOU.
WOULDN'T THAT MAKE YOU AN
UNELECTABLE --
>> NO.
>> -- CANDIDATE IN A GENERAL
ELECTION?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I DON'T BELIEVE
ANYTHING TELEMUNDO SAYS.
>> YOU USED TO SAY THAT YOU
LOVE --
>> NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO.
I CURRENTLY EMPLOYEE THOUSANDS
OF HISPANICS, AND OVER THE
YEARS, I'VE EMPLOYED TENS OF
THOUSANDS OF HISPANICS.
THEY'RE INCREDIBLE PEOPLE.
THEY KNOW, AND THE REASON I WON
IN NEVADA, NOT ONLY ONE THE BIG
ONE, BUT I ALSO WON SUBS, LIKE,
AS AN EXAMPLE, I WON WITH WOMEN.
I WON WITH EVERY SINGLE
CATEGORY.
I WON WITH MEN, I WON WITH
HIGH-INCOME, I WON WITH
LOW-INCOME, I WON WITH HISPANICS
AND I GOT 46%.
NOBODY ELSE WAS CLOSE.
BECAUSE THEY KNOW I'M GOING TO
BRING JOBS BACK FROM CHINA, FROM
JAPAN, FROM SO MANY OTHER
PLACES.
THEY GET IT.
THEY'RE INCREDIBLE PEOPLE,
THEY'RE INCREDIBLE WORKERS, THEY
GET IT.
AND I'VE WON MANY OF THE POLLS
WITH HISPANICS.
I DIDN'T MAYBE WIN THE TELEMUNDO
POLL, BUT ONE THING I'M ALSO
GOING TO GO, I'M BRINGING A LOT
OF PEOPLE IN WHO ARE DEMOCRATS,
WHO ARE INDEPENDENTS, AND YOU'RE
SEEING WITH THE POLLS.
BECAUSE IF YOU LOOK AT ANYWHERE,
LOOK AT ANY OF THE ELECTIONS.
EVERY SINGLE ELECTION, IT'S BEEN
RECORD-SETTING.
AND THE GOOD NEWS IS, FOR THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY, THE DEMOCRATS
ARE GETTING VERY POOR NUMBERS IN
TERMS OF BRINGING THEM IN.
WE'RE GETTING RECORD-SETTING
NUMBERS.
I THINK I HAVE SOMETHING TO DO
WITH THAT.
WE'RE GETTING RECORD-SETTING
NUMBERS.
AND I WON EVERY ONE -- THE THREE
OF THEM THAT I WON, I WON WITH
RECORD-SETTING NUMBERS.
NEW PEOPLE ARE COMING INTO THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY.
WE ARE BUILDING A NEW REPUBLICAN
PARTY, A LOT OF NEW PEOPLE ARE
COMING IN.
>> FOR THE RECORD, YOU HAVE
SAID, PUBLICLY, THAT YOU LOVE
TELEMUNDO IN THE PAST.
BUT IT IS NOT JUST A TELEMUNDO
POLL.
>> I LOVE THEM.
I LOVE THEM.
>> ALL RIGHT, WELL, IT'S NOT THE
ONLY POLL.
>> THEY'RE FINE.
YOU KNOW WHAT, THEY'RE FINE.
>> LET ME FINISH, PLEASE.
>> THEY'RE FINE.
>> JUST LAST NIGHT, "THE
WASHINGTON POST" SHOWED THAT 80%
OF HISPANIC VOTERS IN THEIR
POLLS HAVE A NEGATIVE VIEW OF
YOU.
AND CONCERNING THE NEVADA
VICTORY, ALLOW ME TO EXPLAIN
THAT THE POLL IN NEVADA WAS
BASED ON A TINY SAMPLE,
STATISTICALLY INSIGNIFICANT, OF
ONLY LIKE A HUNDRED --
>> OH, I SEE.
>> -- LET ME FINISH, PLEASE.
OF 100 REPUBLICANS IN THE STATE
OF NEVADA.
I AM MAKING REFERENCE TO
HISPANIC VOTERS NATIONWIDE IN A
GENERAL ELECTION.
>> I'M JUST TELLING YOU, I'M
DOING VERY WELL WITH HISPANICS.
AND BY THE WAY, I SETTLED MY
SUIT, AS YOU KNOW, WITH
UNIVISION.
IT WAS SETTLED.
WE'RE GOOD FRIENDS NOW.
IT WAS ALL SETTLED.
DONE.
VERY HAPPY.
VERY GOOD PEOPLE.
BUT I'M JUST TELLING YOU, I'M
JUST TELLING YOU THAT I WILL DO
REALLY WELL WITH HISPANICS.
I WILL DO BETTER THAN ANYBODY ON
THIS STAGE.
I HAVE RESPECT FOR THE PEOPLE ON
BUT I WILL DO VERY WELL WITH
HISPANICS.
BUT I'M TELLING YOU ALSO, I'M
BRINGING PEOPLE, DEMOCRATS OVER,
AND I'M BRINGING THE
INDEPENDENTS OVER, AND WE'RE
BUILDING A MUCH BIGGER, MUCH
STRONGER REPUBLICAN PARTY.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO TURN OUR ATTENTION NOW
TO ANOTHER CRITICALLY IMPORTANT
ISSUE FOR THE AMERICAN PEOPLE,
THE UNITED STATES SUPREME COURT.
WHERE FILLING THE VACANCY LEFT
BY THE LATE JUSTICE ANTONIN
SCALIA HAS BECOME A MAJOR
CAMPAIGN ISSUE.
I WANT TO BRING IN SALEM RADIO
NETWORK HOST HUGH HEWITT.
HUGH?
>> THANK YOU, WOLF.
TO ME, IT'S THE MOST IMPORTANT
ISSUE.
I'LL START WITH YOU, SENATOR
CRUZ.
DO YOU TRUST MR. TRUMP TO
NOMINATE CONSERVATIVE JUSTICES?
>> WELL, HUGH, I AGREE WITH YOU
THAT JUST SCALIA'S PASSING
UNDERSCORES THE ENORMOUS GRAVITY
OF THIS ELECTION.
JUSTICE SCALIA WAS SOMEONE I
KNEW PERSONALLY FOR 20 YEARS,
WAS PRIVILEGED TO BE AT HIS
FUNERAL THIS WEEKEND.
AND WITH HIS PASSING, THE COURT
IS NOW HANGING IN THE BALANCE.
WE ARE ONE LIBERAL JUSTICE AWAY
FROM A FIVE-JUSTICE RADICAL,
LEFTIST MAJORITY, THAT WOULD
UNDERMINE OUR RELIGIOUS LIBERTY,
THAT WOULD UNDERMINE THE RIGHT
TO LIFE, AND THAT WOULD
FUNDAMENTALLY ERASE THE SECOND
AMENDMENT RIGHT TO KEEP AND BEAR
ARMS FROM THE CONSTITUTION.
NOW, I THINK THE VOTERS OF
TEXAS, THE VOTERS ACROSS SUPER
TUESDAY ARE ASSESSING EVERYONE'S
STANDING ON THIS, THIS STAGE.
IN THE PAST, REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTS ALWAYS PROMISE TO
NOMINATE STRICT
CONSTITUTIONALISTS.
SO I'M CERTAIN IF YOU TOOK A
SURVEY, EVERYONE WOULD SAY THEY
WOULD DO THAT.
BUT THE REALITY IS, DEMOCRATS
BAT ABOUT A THOUSAND.
JUST ABOUT EVERYONE THEY PUT ON
THE COURT VOTES EXACTLY AS THEY
WANT.
REPUBLICANS HAVE BATTED WORSE
THAN 500.
MORE THAN HALF OF THE PEOPLE WE
PUT ON THE COURT HAVE BEEN A
DISASTER.
I'VE SPENT MY WHOLE LIFE
FIGHTING TO DEFEND THE BILL OF
RIGHTS AND THE CONSTITUTION.
AND I CAN TELL YOU THAT FOR
VOTERS THAT CARE ABOUT LIFE OR
LIBERTY OR THE SECOND AMENDMENT,
THEY'RE ASKING THE QUESTION, WHO
DO YOU KNOW, BEYOND A SHADOW OF
A DOUBT, WHO DO YOU KNOW WILL
NOMINATE PRINCIPLED
CONSTITUTIONALISTS TO THE COURT,
I GIVE YOU MY WORD, EVERY
JUSTICE I NOMINATE WILL
VIGOROUSLY DEFEND THE BILL OF
RIGHTS FOR MY CHILDREN AND FOR
YOURS.
>> MR. TRUMP, SENATOR CRUZ
MENTIONED THE ISSUE THAT KEEPS
ME UP AT NIGHT, WHICH IS
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY.
CHURCHES, CATHOLIC AND CHRISTIAN
COLLEGES, CATHOLIC ADOPTION
AGENCIES, ALL SORTS OF RELIGIOUS
INSTITUTIONS FEAR THAT HOBBY
LOBBY, IF IT'S REPEALED, IT WAS
A 5-4 DECISION, THEY'RE GOING TO
HAVE TO BEND THEIR KNEE AND
PROVIDE MORNING-AFTER PILLS.
THEY FEAR THAT IF BOB JONES IS
EXPANDED, THEY WILL LOSE THEIR
TAX EXEMPTION.
WILL YOU COMMIT TO VOTERS
TONIGHT THAT RELIGIOUS LIBERTY
WILL BE AN ABSOLUTE LITMUS TEST
FOR ANYONE YOU APPOINT, NOT JUST
TO THE SUPREME COURT, BUT TO ALL
COURTS.
>> YES, I WOULD.
AND I'VE BEEN THERE AND I'VE
BEEN THERE VERY STRONGLY.
I DO HAVE TO SAY SOMETHING, AND
THIS IS INTERESTING AND IT'S NOT
ANYBODY'S FAULT, IT'S NOT TED'S
FAULT.
JUSTICE ROBERTS WAS STRONGLY
RECOMMENDED AND PUSHED BY TED.
JUSTICE ROBERTS GAVE US
OBAMACARE.
MIGHT AS WELL BE CALLED
ROBERTS'CARE.
TWO TIMES OF THE SUPREME COURT,
JUSTICE ROBERTS APPROVED
SOMETHING THAT HE SHOULD HAVE
NEVER RAISED HIS HAND TO
APPROVE.
AND WE ENDED UP WITH OBAMACARE.
THAT IS A ROUGH THING, AND I
KNOW TED FEELS BADLY ABOUT IT,
AND I THINK HE PROBABLY STILL
RESPECTS THE JUDGE, BUT THAT
JUDGE HAS BEEN A DISASTER IN
TERMS OF EVERYTHING WE STAND
FOR.
BECAUSE THERE IS NO WAY, NO WAY
THAT HE SHOULD HAVE APPROVED
OBAMACARE.
NOW, WITH THAT BEING SAID.
THESE ARE THE THINGS THAT
HAPPEN.
BUT TED VERY, VERY STRONGLY
PUPUSH
ED JUDGE ROBERTS AND JUSTICE
ROBERTS GAVE US SOMETHING THAT
WE DON'T WANT.
>> TED CRUZ, SENATOR, THE CHIEF
JUSTICE GOT HOBBY LOBBY RIGHT,
BUT WHAT DO YOU MAKE OF MR.
CRUZ'S CRITICISM?
>> LISTEN, DONALD KNOWS THAT IT
WAS GEORGE W. BUSH THAT
NOMINATED JUSTICE ROBERTS.
YES, IT'S TRUE, I SUPPORTED THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE ONCE HE WAS
MADE.
BUT I WOULD NOT HAVE NOMINATED
ROBERTS, I WOULD HAVE NOMINATED
MY FORMER BOSS, MIKE LEWDICK.
AND IT'S INTERESTING THAT DONALD
SAYS HE WILL APPOINT JUSTICES
THAT WILL DEFEND RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY, BUT THIS IS A MAN FOR
40 YEARS HAS GIVEN MONEY TO
JIMMY CARTER, TO JOE BIDEN, TO
HILLARY CLINTON, TO CHUCK
SCHUMER, TO HARRY REID.
NOBODY WHO SUPPORTS FAR-LEFT
LIBERAL DEMOCRATS WHO ARE
FIGHTING FOR JUDICIAL ACTIVISTS
CAN POSSIBLY CARE ABOUT HAVING
PRINCIPLED CONSTITUTIONALISTS ON
THE COURT.
AND WHAT DONALD HAS TOLD US IS
HE WILL GO TO WASHINGTON AND CUT
A DEAL.
SO THAT MEANS ON SUPREME COURT,
HE'S GOING TO LOOK TO CUT A DEAL
RATHER THAN FIGHT FOR SOMEONE
WHO WON'T CUT A DEAL ON THE
CONSTITUTION, BUT WILL DEFEND IT
FAITHFULLY.
>> CAN I TRUST YOU ON RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY?
>> LET ME JUST SAY THIS.
I WATCH TED, AND I RESPECT HIM,
BUT HE GETS NOWHERE, STAND ON
THE SENATE FLOOR FOR A DAY TWOR
D
OR TWO DAYS AND TALK AND TALK
AND TALK.
I WATCHED THE OTHER SENATORS
LAUGHING AND SMILING.
AND WHEN TED WAS TOTALLY
EXHAUSTED, HE LEFT THE SENATE
FLOOR AND THEY WENT BACK TO
WORK.
WE HAVE TO HAVE SOMEBODY WHO
MAKE DEALS.
IT'S WONDERFUL TO STAND UP AND
DO THAT.
I HAVE A SISTER WHO'S A
BRILLIANT -- EXCUSE ME!
SHE'S A BRILLIANT JUDGE.
HE'S BEEN CRITICIZING MY SISTER
FOR SIGNING A CERTAIN BILL.
YOU KNOW WHO ELSE SIGNED THAT
BILL?
JUSTICE SAMUEL ALITO, A VERY
CONSERVATIVE MEMBER OF THE
SUPREME COURT, WITH MY SISTER,
SIGNED THAT BILL.
SO I THINK THAT MAYBE WE SHOULD
GET A LITTLE BIT OF AN APOLOGY
FROM TED.
WHAT DO YOU THINK?
>> LET ME -- SENATOR.
>> LET ME TELL YOU RIGHT NOW,
DONALD, I WILL NOT APOLOGIZE FOR
A MINUTE FOR DEFENDING THE
CONSTITUTION.
I WILL NOT APOLOGIZE FOR
DEFENDING THE BILL OF RIGHTS.
AND I FIND IT AMAZING THAT YOUR
ANSWER TO HUGH AND TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE IS ON RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY IS YOU CAN'T HAVE ONE OF
THE THESE CRAZIES ZEALOTS THAT
ACTUALLY BELIEVES IN IT.
YOU'VE GOT TO BE WILLING TO CUT
A DEAL.
AND YOU KNOW, THERE IS A REASON
WHY WHEN HARRY REID WAS ASKED OF
ALL THE PEOPLE ON THIS STAGE,
WHO DOES HE WANT THE MOST, WHO
DOES HE LIKE THE MOST, HARRY
REID SAID, DONALD TRUMP.
WHY?
BECAUSE DONALD HAS SUPPORTED HIM
IN THE PAST, AND HE KNOWS HE CAN
CUT A DEAL WITH HIM.
YOU KNOW WHAT, WITH DONALD, I
DON'T WANT A SUPREME COURT
JUSTICE THAT YOU CUT A DEAL WITH
HARRY REID TO UNDERMINE
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY, BECAUSE THAT
SAME JUSTICE WILL ALSO ERASE THE
SECOND AMENDMENT FROM THE BILL
OF RIGHTS.
>> WHEN YOU SAY CRAZY ZEALOT,
ARE YOU TALKING ABOUT YOU?
CRAZY ZEALOT.
GIVE ME A BREAK.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU'VE HEARD
THIS EXCHANGE ON RELIGIOUS
LIBERTY.
YOU SAID THAT RELIGIOUS LIBERTY
WILL TRUMP EVEN THE ABILITY OF
PEOPLE TO STAY AWAY FROM
SAME-SEX MARRIAGES, NOT PROVIDE
FLOWERS, NOT PROVIDE BAKED
GOODS, ET CETERA.
ARE YOU SATISFIED WITH THIS
EXCHANGE ON RELIGIOUS LIBERTY?
>> I THINK YOU ASK A VERY
IMPORTANT QUESTION.
BECAUSE THE ISSUE HERE, THE NEXT
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
HAS TO FILL THIS VACANCY.
JUSTICE SCALIA, IN THE HISTORY
OF THE REPUBLIC, THERE HAS NEVER
BEEN ANYONE BETTER THAN HIM AT
STANDING FOR THE PRINCIPLE THAT
THE CONSTITUTION IS NOT A LIVING
AND BREATHING DOCUMENT, IT IS
SUPPOSED TO BE APPLIED AS
ORIGINAORIGIN
N
ORI
ORIGINALLY MEANT.
AND THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES MUST BE SOMEONE
YOU CAN TRUST AND BELIEVE IN, SO
YOU CAN APPOINT SOMEONE JUST AS
GOOD AS SCALIA, AND THERE COULD
BE TWO OTHER VACANCIES.
YOU ASK MR. TRUMP TO RESPOND AND
SAY THAT HE WOULD, AND HE SAYS
THAT HE WOULD.
BUT IF YOU LOOK AT HIS RECORD
OVER THE LAST 25 TO 30 YEARS, ON
ISSUE AFTER ISSUE, HE HAS NOT
BEEN ON OUR SIDE.
IF HE'S CHANGED, WE'RE ALWAYS
LOOKING FOR CONVERTS INTO THE
CONSERVATIVE MOVEMENT.
THE BOTTOM LINE IS, YOU DON'T
HAVE A RECORD THERE TO LOOK AT
AND SAY, I FEEL AT PEACE, THAT
WHEN DONALD TRUMP IS PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES, HE'S GOING
TO BE FIRMLY ON OUR SIDE, ON
THESE ISSUES.
IN FACT, VERY RECENTLY, HE WAS
STILL DEFENDING PLANNED
PARENTHOOD.
HE SAYS HE'S NOT GOING TO TAKE
SIDES IN THE PALESTINIANS VERSUS
ISRAEL.
THESE ARE CONCERNING THINGS.
AND SO, YES, I HAVE A DOUBT
ABOUT WHETHER DONALD TRUMP, IF
HE BECOMES PRESIDENT, WILL
REPLACE JUSTICE SCALIA WITH
SOMEONE JUST LIKE JUSTICE
SCALIA.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> WELL, LET ME JUST SAY, LET ME
JUST SAY, FIRST OF ALL, I HAVE
GREAT RESPECT FOR JUSTICE
SCALIA.
I THOUGHT HE WAS TERRIFIC.
AND IF YOU TALK ABOUT EVOLVING,
RONALD REAGAN WAS A SOMEWHAT
LIBERAL DEMOCRAT.
RONALD REAGAN EVOLVED INTO A
SOMEWHAT STRONG CONSERVATIVE,
MORE IMPORTANTLY, HE WAS A GREAT
PRESIDENT.
A GREAT PRESIDENT.
AS FAR AS PLANNED PARENTHOOD IS
CONCERNED, I'M PRO-LIFE.
I'M TOTALLY AGAINST ABORTION
HAVING TO DO WITH PLANNED
PARENTHOOD, BUT MILLIONS AND
MILLIONS OF WOMEN, CERVICAL
CANCER, BREAST CANCER, ARE
HELPED BY PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
SO YOU CAN SAY WHATEVER YOU
WANT, BUT THEY HAVE MILLIONS OF
WOMEN GOING THROUGH PLANNED
PARENTHOOD, THAT ARE HELPED
GREATLY.
AND I WOULDN'T FUND IT.
I WOULD DEFUND IT BECAUSE OF THE
ABORTION FACTOR, WHICH THEY SAY
IS 3%.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT PERCENTAGE IT
IS.
THEY SAY IT'S 3%.
BUT I WOULD DEFUND IT, BECAUSE
I'M PRO-LIFE.
BUT MILLIONS OF WOMEN ARE HELPED
BY PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
BACK TO RELIGIOUS LIBERTY.
YOU'VE BEEN A LITTLE BIT LESS
EMPHATIC.
YOU'VE SAID SAME-SEX COUPLE
APPROACHES A CUPCAKE MAKER, SELL
THEM A CUPCAKE.
CAN WE TRUST YOU AS MUCH ON
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY AS THE REST OF
THESE PEOPLE?
>> I MEAN, OF COURSE.
AND I WAS INVOLVED IN JUST BEING
A PIONEER IN A NEW CHURCH.
RELIGIOUS INSTITUTIONS SHOULD BE
ABLE TO PRACTICE THE RELIGION
THAT THEY BELIEVE IN.
NO QUESTION AND NO DOUBT ABOUT
IT.
NOW, IN REGARD TO SAME-SEX
MARRIAGE, I DON'T FAVOR IT.
I'VE ALWAYS FAVORED TRADITIONAL
MARRIAGE, BUT, LOOK, THE COURT
HAS RULED AND I'VE MOVED ON.
AND WHAT I'VE SAID, HUGH, IS
THAT, LOOK, WHERE DOES IT END?
IF YOU'RE IN THE BUSINESS OF
SELLING THINGS, IF YOU'RE NOT
GOING TO SELL TO SOMEBODY YOU
DON'T AGREE, OKAY, TODAY I'M NOT
GOING TO SELL TO SOMEBODY WHO'S
GAY, AND TOMORROW MAYBE I WON'T
SELL TO SOMEBODY WHO'S DIVORCED.
IF YOU'RE IN THE BUSINESS OF
COMMERCE, CONDUCT COMMERCE.
THAT'S MY VIEW.
AND IF YOU DON'T AGREE WITH
THEIR LIFESTYLE, SAY A PRAYER
FOR THEM WHEN THEY LEAVE AND
HOPE THEY CHANGE THEIR BEHAVIOR.
BUT WHEN IT COMES TO THE
RELIGIOUS INSTITUTIONS, THEY ARE
IN INVIOLATE IN MY MIND, AND I
WOULD FIGHT FOR THOSE RELIGIOUS
INSTITUTIONS.
AND LOOK, I'VE APPOINTED OVER A
HUNDRED JUDGES AS GOVERNOR.
I EVEN APPOINT ADJUDGE TO THE
OHIO SUPREME COURT.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT THEY ARE?
THEY'RE CONSERVATIVES.
GO CHECK IT OUT.
THEY ARE CONSERVATIVES, THEY
DON'T MAKE THE LAW, THEY
INTERPRET THE LAW.
THAT'S ALL THEY DO.
AND THEY STICK BY THE
CONSTITUTION.
SO I WILL DO THAT.
BUT LET'S JUST NOT GET SO NARROW
HERE AS TO GOTCHA THIS OR THAT.
I THINK MY POSITION IS CLEAR.
>> DR. CARSON, LET ME WRAP IT UP
WITH YOU.
ARE THEIR POSITIONS CLEAR?
ARE THE POSITIONS YOU'VE HEARD
CLEAR ABOUT THE FIRST AMENDMENT
AND THE FIRST FREEDOM?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, LET ME
JUST ADD MY PRAISE TO JUSTICE
SCALIA.
I FIRST MET HIM WHEN WE GOT AN
HONORARY DEGREE TOGETHER A LONG
TIME AGO.
A TREMENDOUS WIT AND INTELLECT.
AS FAR AS RELIGIOUS FREEDOM IS
CONCERNED, ONE OF THE BASIC
TENANTS OF THIS NATION, AND I
BELIEVE THAT THE CONSTITUTION
PROTECTS ALL OF OUR RIGHTS.
AND IT GIVES PEOPLE WHO BELIEVE
IN SAME-SEX MARRIAGE THE SAME
RIGHTS AS EVERYBODY ELSE.
BUT WHAT WE HAVE TO REMEMBER IS
EVEN THOUGH EVERYBODY HAS THE
SAME RIGHTS, NOBODY GET EXTRA
RIGHTS.
SO NOBODY GETS TO REDEFINE
THINGS FOR EVERYBODY ELSE AND
THEN HAVE THEM HAVE TO CONFORM
TO IT.
THAT'S UNFAIR.
AND THIS IS THE RESPONSIBILITY
OF CONGRESS TO COME BACK AND
CORRECT WHAT THE SUPREME COURT
HAS DONE.
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE DIVIDED
GOVERNMENT.
AND WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
ENCOURAGE THEM TO ACT IN AN
APPROPRIATE WAY, OR WE WILL LOSE
OUR RELIGIOUS FREEDOM.
AND AS PRESIDENT, I WILL GO
THROUGH AND I WILL LOOK AT WHAT
A PERSON'S LIFE HAS BEEN.
WHAT HAVE THEY DONE IN THE PAST,
WHAT KIND OF JUDGMENTS HAVE THEY
MADE?
WHAT KIND OF ASSOCIATIONS DO
THEY HAVE?
THAT WILL TELL YOU A LOT MORE
THAN AN INTERVIEW WILL TELL YOU.
THE FRUIT SALAD OF THEIR LIFE IS
WHAT I WILL LOOK AT.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
ALL OF YOU WANT TO REPEAL AND
REPLACE OBAMACARE, SO LET'S TALK
ABOUT YOUR PLAN, SPECIFIC PLANS
TO REPLACE IT.
I WANT TO BRING IN OUR CHIEF
POLITICAL CORRESPONDENT, DANA
BASH.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU SAID
YESTERDAY, RIGHT HERE IN
HOUSTON, THAT MR. TRUMP THINKS
THAT PART OF OBAMACARE IS PRETTY
GOOD.
SO, HE SAYS HE IS GOING TO
REPEAL OBAMACARE.
ARE YOU SAYING THAT YOU'RE
WORRIED HE WON'T?
>> HE SAID HE LIKES THE
INDIVIDUAL MANDATE PORTION OF
IT.
WHICH I DON'T BELIEVE, THAT
SHOULDN'T BE PART OF IT.
THAT SHOULD NOT REMAIN THERE.
I THINK HERE'S WHAT WE NEED TO
REPLACE IT WITH.
WE NEED TO REPEAL OBAMACARE
COMPLETELY AND REPLACE IT WITH A
SYSTEM THAT PUTS AMERICANS IN
CHARGE OF THEIR HEALTH CARE
MONEY AGAIN.
IF YOUR EMPLOYER WANTS TO BUY
HEALTH INSURANCE FOR YOU, THEY
CAN CONTINUE TO DO SO SO FROM
ANY COMPANY IN AMERICA THEY WANT
TO BUY IT FROM.
OTHERWISE, YOUR EMPLOYERS CAN
PROVIDE YOU HEALTH CARE MONEY,
TAX-FREE, NOT TREATED AS INCOME,
AND YOU CAN USE THAT MONEY ONLY
FOR HEALTH CARE, BUT YOU CAN USE
IT TO FUND HEALTH CARE ANY WAY
YOU WANT, FULLY FUND A HEALTH
SAVINGS ACCOUNT, THE COMBINATION
OF A HEALTH SAVINGS ACCOUNT OR A
PRIVATE PLAN FROM ANY COUNTRY OR
ANY STATE IN THE COUNTRY.
AND IF YOU DON'T HAVE THAT, THEN
YOU WILL HAVE A REFUNDABLE TAX
CREDIT THAT WILL PROVIDE YOU
MONEY TO FUND YOUR OWN HEALTH
CARE.
AND I THINK THAT'S A MUCH BETTER
APPROACH THAN OBAMACARE.
IT'S NOT ONLY BAD FOR HEALTH
CARE, BUT BAD FOR OUR COUNTRY.
IT'S FORCING PEOPLE TO LAY
PEOPLE OFF, CUT PEOPLE'S HOURS,
MOVE PEOPLE TO PART-TIME.
IT'S A JOB-KILLING LAW AND I
WILL REPEAL IT AS PRESIDENT AND
WE WILL REPLACE IT WITH
SOMETHING SUBSTANTIALLY BETTER
FOR ALL AMERICANS.
>> MR. TRUMP, SENATOR RUBIO JUST
SAID THAT YOU SUPPORT THE
INDIVIDUAL MANDATE.
>> I JUST WANT TO SAY, I AGREE
WITH THAT 100%, EXCEPT
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS, I WOULD
ABSOLUTELY GET RID OF OBAMACARE,
WE'LL SOMETHING MUCH BETTER, BUT
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS, WHEN
I'M REFERRING TO THAT, AND I WAS
REFERRING TO THAT VERY STRONGLY
ON THE SHOW WITH ANDERSON
COOPER, I WANT TO KEY
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS.
I THINK WE NEED IT.
I THINININ IT'S A MODERN AGE, AI
THINK WE HAVE TO HAVE IT.
>> OKAY, SO LET'S TALK ABOUT
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS.
WHAT THE INSURANCE COMPANIES
SAY, IS THAT THE ONLY WAY THEY
CAN COVER PEOPLE IS TO HAVE A
MANDATE REQUIRING EVERYBODY
PURCHASE HEALTH INSURANCE.
ARE THEY WRONG?
>> I THINK THEY'RE WRONG 100%.
WHAT WE NEED -- LOOK, THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES TAKE CARE OF
THE POLITICIANS.
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES GET WHAT
THEY WANT.
WE SHOULD HAVE GOTTEN RID OF THE
LINES AROUND EACH STATE SO WE
COULD HAVE REAL COMPETITION.
WE THOUGHT THAT WAS GONE.
WE THOUGHT THOSE LINES WERE
GOING TO BE GONE AND SOMETHING
HAPPENED AT THE LAST MOMENT
WHERE OBAMACARE GOT APPROVED AND
ALL OF THAT WAS THROWN OUT THE
WINDOW.
THE REASON IS SOME OF THE PEOPLE
IN THE AUDIENCE ARE INSURANCE
PEOPLE AND INSURANCE LOBBYISTS
AND SPECIAL INTERESTS.
THEY GOT -- I'M NOT GOING TO
POINT TO THESE GENTLEMAN.
OF COURSE, THEY'RE PART OF THE
PROBLEM, OTHER THAN BEN, IN ALL
FAIRNESS, AND ACTUALLY, THE
GOVERNOR TOO.
LET'S JUST TALK ABOUT THESE TWO,
OKAY?
BECAUSE I DON'T THINK THE
GOVERNOR HAD TOO MUCH TO DO WITH
THIS.
BUT WE SHOULD HAVE GOTTEN RID OF
THE BORDERS, GOTTEN RID OF THE
LINES AROUND THE STATE SO
THERE'S GREAT COMPETITION.
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES ARE
MAKING A FORTUNE ON EVERY SINGLE
THING THEY DO.
I'M SELF-FUNDING MY CAMPAIGN.
I'M THE ONLY ONE IN EITHER PARTY
SELF-FUNDING MY CAMPAIGN.
I'M GOING TO DO WHAT'S RIGHT.
WE HAVE TO GET RID OF THE LINES
AROUND THE STATES, SO THERE'S
SERIOUS, SERIOUS COMPETITION.
AND YOU'RE GOING TO SEE --
EXCUSE ME.
THEN YOU'RE GOING TO SEE
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS AND
EVERYTHING ELSE BE PART OF IT,
BUT THE PRICE WILL BE DONE.
AND THE INSURANCE COMPANIES CAN
PAY.
RIGHT NOW, THEY'RE MAKING A
FORTUNE.
>> JUST TO BE SPECIFIC HERE,
WHAT YOU'RE SAYING IS GETTING
RID OF THE BARRIERS BETWEEN
STATES, THAT IS GOING TO SOLVE
THE PROBLEM OF PRE-EXISTING --
>> THAT'S GOING TO SOLVE A LOT
OF THE PROBLEMS.
AND THE INSURANCE COMPANIES
AREN'T GOING TO SAY THAT, THEY
WANT TO KEEP IT.
THEY'LL SAY WHATEVER THEY HAVE
TO SAY TO KEEP IT THE WAY IT IS.
I KNOW THE INSURANCE COMPANIES.
THEY'RE FRIENDS OF MINE.
THE TOP GUYS, THEY'RE FRIENDS OF
MINE.
I SHOULDN'T TELL YOU GUYS, IT'S
TERRIBLE, YOU'LL SAY I HAVE A
CONFLICT OF INTEREST.
THEY'RE FRIENDS OF MINE.
SOME OF THEM ARE IN THE
AUDIENCE.
ONE OF THEM WAS WAVING TO ME, HE
WAS LAUGHING AND SMILING.
HE'S NOT LAUGHING SO MUCH
ANYMORE.
HI.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT?
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES ARE
MAKING AN ABSOLUTE FORTUNE.
YES, THEY WILL KEEP PRE-EXISTING
CONDITIONS AND THAT WOULD BE A
GREAT THING.
GET RID OF OBAMACARE, WE'LL COME
UP WITH NEW PLANS, BUT WE SHOULD
KEEP PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS.
>> AND I MENTIONED IN HIS
RESPONSE, SO IF I MAY ABOUT THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES, YOU MAY NOT
BE AWARE OF THIS, DONALD,
BECAUSE YOU DON'T FOLLOW THIS
STUFF VERY CLOSELY, BUT HERE'S
WHAT HAPPENED.
WHEN THEY PASSED OBAMACARE, THEY
PUT A BAILOUT FUND IN OBAMACARE.
ALL OF THESE LOBBYISTS THEY KEEP
TALKING ABOUT, THEY PUT A
BAILOUT FUND IN THE LAW THAT
WOULD ALLOW TAXPAYER MONEY TO BE
USED TO BAIL OUT COMPANIES WHEN
THEY LOST MONEY.
AND WE LED THE EFFORT AND WIPED
OUT THAT BAILOUT FUND.
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES AREN'T
IN FAVOR OF ME.
THEY HATE THAT.
THEY'RE SUING TO GET THAT
BAILOUT MONEY TO BE PUT BACK IN.
THIS IS AN IMPORTANT THING.
WHAT IS YOUR PLAN, I UNDERSTAND
THE LINES AROUND THE STATE,
WHATEVER THAT MEANS.
THIS IS NOT A GAME WHERE YOU
DRAW MAPS --
>> YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT IT MEANS.
THAT IS THE PROBLEM.
>> WHAT IS YOUR PLAN?
>> THE BIGGEST PROBLEM, HE
DOESN'T KNOW.
THE BIGGEST PROBLEM HE'S GOT IS
HE DOUNT KNOW.
>> WHAT'S HIS PLAN?
>> I WATCHED HIM MELT DOWN TWO
WEEKS AGO WITH CHRIS CHRISTIE,
I'VE GOT TO TELL YOU, THE
BIGGEST PROBLEM HE'S GOT IS HE
REALLY DON'T KNOW ABOUT THE
LINES.
THE BIGGEST THING WE'VE GOT AND
THE REASON WE HAVE NO
COMPETITION IS BECAUSE WE HAVE
LINES AROUND THE STATE AND YOU
HAVE --
>> YOU ALREADY MENTIONED THAT AS
PART OF MY PLAN.
I KNOW WHAT THAT IS.
WHAT ELSE IS PART OF YOUR PLAN?
THE ONLY THING IS TO GET RID OF
THE LINES AROUND THE STATES?
WHAT ELSE IS PART OF YOUR HEALTH
CARE?
>> WHAT THE LINES AROUND THE
STATE MEANS -- AND YOU WERE
ALMOST DONE.
EXCUSE ME.
>> WHAT'S YOUR PLAN?
>> BRINGS IN COMPETITION.
WHEN YOU GET RID OF THE LINES,
IT BRINGS IN COMPETITION.
SO INSTEAD OF HAVING ONE
INSURANCE COMPANY TAKING CARE OF
NEW YORK OR TEXAS, YOU'LL HAVE
MANY.
THEY'LL COMPETE.
AND IT WILL BE A BEAUTIFUL
THING.
>> RIGHT AND WHAT -- SO THAT'S
THE ONLY PART OF THE PLAN?
JUST THE LINES.
THE INTERSTATE COMPETITION?
>> THE NICE PART ABOUT -- YOU
HAVE MANY DIFFERENT PLANS.
YOU'LL HAVE COMPETITION.
YOU'LL HAVE SO MANY DIFFERENT
PLANS.
>> NOW HE'S REPEATING HIMSELF.
>> NO, I'M NOT -- NO, NO, NO,
NO.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> NO, NO, NO.
>> I DON'T REPEAT MYSELF.
I DON'T REPEAT MYSELF.
>> YOU DON'T REPEAT YOURSELF?
>> HERE'S THE GUY WHO REPEATS
HIMSELF.
I DON'T --
>> YOU REPEAT YOURSELF EVERY
DAY.
>> TALKING ABOUT REPEATING.
I WATCHED HIM REPEAT HIMSELF
FIVE TIMES FOUR WEEKS AGO --
>> I SAW YOU REPEAT YOURSELF
FIVE TIMES FOUR SECONDS AGO.
>> I WATCHED HIM.
I WATCHED HIM MELT DOWN ON THE
STAGE LIKE I'VE NEVER SEEN
ANYBODY --
>> LET'S STAY --
>> -- SWIMMING POOL.
>> I SAID --
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT YOUR PLAN.
>> HE SAYS FIVE THINGS,
EVERYONE'S DUMB, HE'S GOING TO
MAKE AMERICA GREAT AGAIN.
WIN, WIN, WIN.
HE'S WINNING IN THE POLLS.
AND THE LINES AROUND THE STATES.
EVERY NIGHT.
SAME THING.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> I TELL THE TRUTH.
I TELL THE TRUTH.
>> YOU WILL HAVE TIME TO
RESPOND, IF YOU CAN JUST LET MR.
TRUMP RESPOND.
IF YOU CAN TALK A LITTLE BIT
MORE ABOUT YOUR PLAN.
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE MANY
DIFFERENT PLANS --
>> HE'S DONE IT AGAIN!
>> THERE'S GOING TO BE
COMPETITION.
THERE IS GOING TO BE COMPETITION
AMONG ALL OF THE STATES AND THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES.
THEY'RE GOING TO HAVE MANY, MANY
DIFFERENT PLANS
>> IS THERE ANYTHING ELSE THAT
YOU WOULD LIKE TO ADD TO THAT?
>> NO, THERE'S NOTHING TO ADD.
WHAT'S TO ADD?
WHAT IS TO ADD?
>> THANK YOU BOTH.
>> ALL RIGHT.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH.
YOU HAVE SAID IT IS, QUOTE,
UN-AMERICAN TO DENY SOMEONE
HEALTH INSURANCE IF THEY HAVE A
PRE-EXISTING CONDITION.
WOULD YOU LEAVE THE INDIVIDUAL
MANDATE IN PLACE, REQUIRING ALL
AMERICANS TO PURCHASE INSURANCE?
>> NO, I WOULDN'T.
BUT THAT DOESN'T MATTER WHEN IT
COMES TO THE ISSUE OF
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS.
YOU DON'T WANT ANY AMERICAN TO
LOSE THEIR HOUSE, EVERYTHING
THEY'VE SAVED BECAUSE THEY GET
SICK.
NOW, I THINK IT IS MORE
COMPLICATED THAN WHAT WE'VE
HEARD HERE TONIGHT.
WE'RE ACTUALLY RUNNING
SIGNIFICANT HEALTH REFORM IN MY
STATE.
I WOULD REPEAL OBAMACARE FOR A
NUMBER OF REASONS.
I WOULD TAKE SEVERAL COMBINED
RESOURCES, FREED UP WITH THE
MEDICAID PLAN, AND COVER THE
PEOPLE WHO ARE CURRENT THE
WORKING POOR, BECAUSE WE DON'T
WANT TO HAVE TENS OF MILLIONS OF
AMERICANS LOSING THEIR HEALTH
INSURANCE.
AND THEN WE'RE DRIVING TOWARDS
TOTAL TRANSPARENCY.
THE ANY OF YOU HERE EVER GET A
HOSPITAL BILL, IT'S EASIER TO
INTERPRET THE DEAD SEA SCROLLS
THAN TO UNDERSTAND YOUR HOSPITAL
BILL.
THE FACT IS, WHAT WE NEED IS
TRANSPARENCY WITH HOSPITALS AND
WITH THE PROVIDERS.
AND I'LL TELL YOU WHAT WE WILL
DO.
WE ARE ACTUALLY GOING TO MAKE
PAYMENTS TO PHYSICIANS AND TO
HOSPITALS WHO ACTUALLY DELIVER
HEALTH CARE WITH GREAT QUALITY
AT LOW PRICES.
WE ACTUALLY ARE GOING TO MAKE
THE MARKET WORK.
>> GOVERNOR, LET ME GO BACK TO
THE ORIGINAL QUESTION ABOUT THE
INDIVIDUAL MANDATE.
IN 1994, WHEN YOU WERE IN
CONGRESS, YOU PROPOSED A PLAN,
REQUIRING AN INDIVIDUAL MANDATE.
SO WHAT CHANGED?
>> WELL, DANA, THE HERITAGE
FOUNDATION HAD THIS POSITION AS
WELL.
AND WHEN I LOOK AT IT, I DON'T
THINK IT'S TENABLE.
AND WE DON'T NEED TO DO THAT.
AGAIN, I'M TELLING YOU THAT WE
ARE GOING TO -- WE HAVE A
PROPOSAL, A PLAN THAT WE'RE
ENACTING NOW, THAT SAYS, IF YOU
ARE A HOSPITAL OR A DOCTOR, AND
YOU'RE PROVIDING VERY
HIGH-QUALITY, AT LOWER PRICES,
BELOW THE MID-POINT, SOME CHARGE
HIGH, SOME CHARGE LOW.
IF YOU ARE BELOW THE
MID-POINT,MID-POINT,
WE ARE GOING TO GIVE YOU A
FINANCIAL REWARD FOR ALLOWING
YOU TO PROVIDE SERVICES THAT
RESULT IN HIGH QUALITY FOR OUR
PEOPLE AT LOWER PRICES.
THAT IS THE WAY IN WHICH WE ARE
GOING TO TAMP DOWN THE RISING
COSTS OF HEALTH CARE.
BECAUSE IF YOU THINK ABOUT YOUR
OWN DEDUCTIBLES TODAY, THEY'RE
GOING HIGHER AND HIGHER AND
HIGHER.
AND YOU KNOW WHAT, AT SOME
POINT, PEOPLE CAN'T AFFORD IT.
OUR PLAN WILL WORK.
IT USES THE MARKET.
IT USES TRANSPARENCY.
IT GETS THE PATIENT IN THE
MIDDLE.
AND GUESS WHAT, WE'RE ACTUALLY
DOING IT IN MY STATE, THE
SEVENTH LARGEST STATE IN THE
COUNTRY.
AND THIS WILL GO NATIONAL, WE
WILL GET OUR HANDS ON HEALTH
CARE WHERE YOU WILL KNOW WHAT'S
GOING ON.
WE WILL PAY FOR QUALITY, LOWER
PRICES, AND WE WILL BEGIN TO SEE
HEALTH CARE BECOME AFFORDABLE IN
AMERICA.
AND WHERE PEOPLE WILL ALSO BE
ABLE TO HAVE HEALTH INSURANCE,
EVEN IF THEY HAVE A PRE-EXISTING
CONDITION.
WE DON'T WANT TO THROW MILLIONS
OF PEOPLE OUT INTO THE COLD AND
NOT HAVE THE HEALTH INSURANCE,
DANA.
SO THAT'S REALLY WHAT WE'RE
DOING.
THIS IS NOT A THEORY.
THIS IS WHAT WE ARE ACTUALLY
DOING IN OUR STATE.
WE WILL BEGIN PAYMENTS NEXT
YEAR, BASED ON SUPPOSED THAT WE
HAVE IN OUR LIVES.
IF OUR PRIMARY CARE PHYSICIANS
KEEP US HEALTHY FOR A YEAR, WITH
REALLY HIGH QUALITY, GUESS WHAT,
THEY WILL GET A FINANCIAL
REWARD.
OUR PRIMARY CARE PHYSICIANS NEED
HELP, THEY NEED SUPPORT, WE'RE
REDUCING THEM.
THIS WILL ALLOW THEM TO GET A
REWARD FOR DOING A GREAT JOB.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU.
>> DR. CARSON.
DR. CARSON, YOU HAVE DEALT WITH
THE SICKEST OF PATIENTS.
YOU SUPPORT COVERING
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS.
HOW WOULD YOU CHANGE OBAMACARE,
BUT MAINTAIN THAT COVERAGE?
>> FIRST OF ALL, HEALTH CARE IS
NOT A RIGHT, BUT I DO BELIEVE IT
IS A RESPONSIBILITY FOR A
RESPONSIBLE SOCIETY, AND WE ARE
THAT.
WE SPEND ALMOST TWICE AS MUCH
PER CAPITA ON HEALTH CARE AS
MANY OTHER NATIONS WHO HAVE
ACTUALLY MUCH BETTER ACCESS THAN
WE DO.
I PROPOSE A SYSTEM IN WHICH WE
USE HEALTH EMPOWERMENT ACCOUNTS,
WHICH ARE LIKE A HEALTH SAVINGS
ACCOUNT, WITH NO BUREAUCRATS,
AND WE GIVE IT TO EVERYBODY FROM
BIRTH UNTIL DEATH, THEY CAN PASS
IT ON WHEN THEY DIE.
WE PAY FOR IT WITH THE SAME
DOLLARS THAT WE PAY FOR
TRADITIONAL HEALTH CARE WITH.
WE GIVE PEOPLE THE ABILITY TO
SHIFT MONEY WITHIN THEIR HEALTH
EMPOWERMENT ACCOUNT, WITHIN
THEIR FAMILY.
SO DAD'S $500 SHORT, MOM CAN
GIVE IT TO HIM, OR COUSIN OR
UNCLE, AND IT MAKES EVERY FAMILY
THEIR OWN INSURANCE CARRIER,
WITH NO MIDDLEMAN.
IT GIVES YOU ENORMOUS
FLEXIBILITY.
AND ALSO, YOU KNOW, IF UNCLE JOE
IS SMOKING LIKE A CHIMNEY,
EVERYBODY'S GOING TO HIDE HIS
CIGARETTES, BECAUSE THEY'RE ALL
INTERESTED IN WHAT'S GOING ON
THERE.
AND ALSO, YOUR CATASTROPHIC
HEALTH CARE IS GOING TO COST A
LOT LESS MONEY NOW.
BECAUSE THE ONLY THING COMING
OUT OF THAT IS CATASTROPHIC
HEALTH CARE.
SO, IT'S LIKE A HOMEOWNER'S
POLICY, WITH A LARGE DEDUCTIBLE,
VERSUS A HOMEOWNER'S POLICY
WHERE YOU WANT EVERY SCRATCH
COVERED.
ONE COSTS $1,500 A YEAR, ONE
COSTS $10,000 A YEAR.
YOU CAN BUY THE $1,500 ONE.
THAT WILL TAKE CARE OF 75% OF
THE PEOPLE.
THE PEOPLE WHO ARE INDIGENT, HOW
DO WE TAKE CARE OF THEM NOW?
MEDICAID.
WHAT'S THE MEDICAID BUDGET,
ALMOST $500 BILLION.
ALMOST 80 MILLION PEOPLE
PARTICIPATE, WHICH IS WAY TOO
MANY, AND THAT WILL GET A LOT
BETTER WHEN WE FIX THE ECONOMY,
WHICH I HOPE WE GET A CHANCE TO
TALK ABOUT.
BUT OVER $5 MILLION FOR EACH
MAN, WOMAN, AND CHILD.
AND THEY COULD HAVE A LOT MORE
FLEXIBILITY.
YOU COULD BUY A CONCIERGE
PRACTICE AND YOU COULD STILL
HAVE THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS LEFT
OVER.
>> THANK YOU.
>> LET ME JUST FINISH.
BECAUSE I DON'T GET TO TALK THAT
MUCH.
AND LET'S -- YOU HAVE THE MONEY
THAT'S LEFT OVER TO BUY YOUR
CATASTROPHIC INSURANCE.
BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY, WE GIVE
THEM A MENU, JUST LIKE WE DO ON
MEDICARE PART "C," AND THEY HAVE
THE CHOICES THAT WILL ALLOW THEM
NOT ONLY TO HAVE CATASTROPHIC
HEALTH CARE, BUT DRUG CARE, AND
EVERYTHING ELSE.
IT WILL BE SUCH A GOOD PROGRAM,
THAT NOBODY WILL WANT OBAMACARE
AFTER THAT.
AND THAT'S PROBABLY THE BEST WAY
TO DO IT, ALTHOUGH IF ANYBODY
STILL DID, I WOULD STILL DEFUND
IT.
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
LET'S TALK ABOUT THE ECONOMY.
LET'S TALK ABOUT --
>> WOLF, WOLF, WOLF.
DOES EVERYONE GET TO ADDRESS
OBAMACARE BUT ME?
>> I WANT TO MOVE ON, BUT
THERE'LL BE PLENTY OF
OPPORTUNITIES FOR YOU TO
ADDRESS --
>> IT'S KIND OF AN ISSUE I HAVE
A LONG HISTORY WITH.
>> I KNOW YOU DO.
ALL RIGHT, GO AHEAD.
>> THANKNKNKYOU, WOLF.
>> HOW DO YOU GET THAT EXTRA
TIME, CRUZ?
YOU'RE VERY GOOD AT --
>> YOU KNOW, THIS IS ANOTHER
ISSUE ON WHICH DONALD AND I HAVE
SHARP DISAGREEMENTS ON PLANNED
PARENTHOOD.
HE THINKS PLANNED PARENTHOOD IS
WONDERFUL.
I WOULD INSTRUCT THE DEPARTMENT
OF JUSTICE TO INVESTIGATE THEM
AND PROSECUTE ANY AND ALL
CRIMINAL VIOLATIONS.
ON OBAMACARE, BOTH DONALD AND I
SAY WE WANT TO END IT, BUT FOR
VERY DIFFERENT REASONS.
I WANT TO END IT BECAUSE IT'S
GONE TOO FAR, IT'S KILLED
MILLIONS OF JOBS, AND IT'S
HURTING PEOPLE'S HEALTH CARE.
DONALD WANTS TO END IT, BECAUSE
HE SAYS IT DOESN'T GO FAIRLY
NEAR ENOUGH.
AND WHAT WAS AMAZING IN THAT
EXCHANGE THAT'S MISSING IS THAT
FOR DECADES DONALD HAS BEEN
ADVOCATING SOCIALIZED MEDICINE.
WHAT HE'S SAID IS THAT THE
GOVERNMENT SHOULD PAY FOR
EVERYONE'S HEALTH CARE.
AND A COUPLE OF DEBATES AGO, HE
SAID, IF YOU DON'T SUPPORT
SOCIALIZED HEALTH CARE, YOU'RE
HEARTLESS.
SOCIAL DEMOCRATS HAVE BEEN
SAYING THAT FOR YEARS.
IF YOU'RE A SMALL BUSINESS
OWNER, DONALD TRUMP'S SOCIALIZED
MEDICINE, PUTTING THE GOVERNMENT
IN CHARGE OF YOUR HEALTH CARE
WOULD KILL MORE JOBS THAN
OBAMACARE, AND IF YOU'RE
ELDERLY, THE RESULTS OF
SOCIALIZED MEDICINE IN EVERY
COUNTRY ON EARTH WHERE IT'S BEEN
IMPLEMENTED HAS BEEN RATIONING,
HAS BEEN THE GOVERNMENT SAYING,
NO, YOU DON'T GET THAT HIP
REPLACEMENT, YOU DON'T GET THAT
KNEE REPLACEMENT, THE GOVERNMENT
IS IN CHARGE OF YOUR HEALTH
CARE.
I'LL TELL YOU THAT.
AS PRESIDENT, I WILL REPEAL
EVERY WORD OF OBAMACARE.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
MR. TRUMP?
>> I DO NOT WANT SOCIALIZED
MEDICINE, JUST SO YOU
UNDERSTAND.
HE GOES AROUND SAYING, HE WANTS
IT.
I DO NOT WANT SOCIALIZED
MEDICINE.
I DO AGREE WITH HIM, IT'S GOING
TO BE A DISASTER, OBAMACARE, FOR
THE ECONOMY.
IN 2016, IT WILL BE IMPOSSIBLE
FOR US THE TO PAY FOR IT IF YOU
LOOK AT WHAT'S GOING ON.
THAT'S WHY IT HAS TO BE
REPEALED.
FOR A LOT OF REASONS, NUMBER
ONE, IT DOESN'T WORK.
NUMBER TWO, YOU LOOK AT PREMIUMS
GOING UP, 25, 35, EVEN 45%.
AND MORE.
WE HAVE TO GET RID OF OBAMACARE.
IT IS GOING TO DESTROY OUR
ECONOMY COMPLETELY.
OUR ECONOMY IS NOT DOING WELL.
IT IS GOING TO DESTROY OUR
ECONOMY GREATLY.
AND ON THAT, I AGREE.
>> DONALD, TRUE OR FALSE, YOU'VE
SAID THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD PAY
FOR EVERYONE'S HEALTH CARE?
>> THAT'S FALSE.
>> YOU'VE NEVER SAID THAT?
>> I SAID IT WORKED IN A COUPLE
OF COUNTRIES --
>> YOU'VE NEVER STOOD ON THIS
DEBATE STAGE AND SAYS IT WORKS
GREAT IN CANADA AND SCOTLAND AND
WE SHOULD DO IT HERE.
>> NO, I DID NOT.
>> DID YOU SAY, IF YOU WANT
PEOPLE TO DIE ON THE STREET IFS
YOU DON'T SUPPORT SOCIALIZED
HEALTH CARE, YOU HAVE NO HEART.
>> CORRECT.
I WILL NOT LET PEOPLE DIE ON THE
STREETS -- LET ME TALK.
>> EXPLAIN YOUR PLAN, PLEASE.
>> MY PLAN IS SIMPLE.
WE'LL HAVE PRIVATE HEALTH CARE,
BUT I WILL NOT ALLOW PEOPLE TO
DIE ON THE SIDEWALKS AND THE
STREETS OF OUR COUNTRY IF I'M
PRESIDENT.
YOU MAY LET IT AND YOU MAY BE
FINE WITH IT --
>> SO DOES THE GOVERNMENT PAY
FOR EVERYONE'S HEALTH CARE?
>> WE ARE GOING --
>> YES OR NO.
JUST ANSWER THE QUESTION?
>> EXCUSE ME.
WE ARE GOING TO TAKE THOSE
PEOPLE AND THOSE PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO BE SERVICED BY DOCTORS
AND HOSPITALS.
WE'RE GOING TO MAKE GREAT DEALS
ON IT, BUT WE'RE NOT GOING TO
LET THEM DIE IN THE STREETS.
>> WHO PAYS FOR IT?
>> I WANT TO CLARIFY
SOMETHING --
>> GENTLEMAN, PLEASE.
>> THAT ATTACK ABOUT LETTING
PEOPLE DIE IN THE STREETS --
>> GENTLEMAN, GENTLEMAN.
ALL OF YOU HAVE AGREED --
>> SENATOR CRUZ --
>> CALL IT WHAT YOU WANT.
>> IT'S A YES OR NO?
>> CALL IT WHAT YOU WANT, PEOPLE
ARE NOT GOING TO BE DYING ON THE
SIDEWALK.
>> ALL OF YOU HAVE AGREED TO THE
RULES.
I WANT TO MOVE ON.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT THE ECONOMY
RIGHT NOW.
MR. TRUMP, YOU WANT TO CUT TAXES
MORE THAN PRESIDENT RONALD
REAGAN DID, MORE THAN PRESIDENT
GEORGE H.W. BUSH DID.
THE INDEPENDENT TAX FOUNDATION
SAYS THE COST TO THE COUNTRY OF
YOUR PROPOSAL WOULD BE ABOUT $10
TRILLION AND THAT TAKES INTO
ACCOUNT THE ECONOMIC GROWTH THAT
WOULD EMERGE FROM YOUR PROPOSED
TAX CUTS.
HOW WOULD YOU CUT $10 TRILLION
OVER TEN YEARS, BUT MAKE SURE
THE COUNTRY ISN'T SADDLED WITH
EVEN MORE DEBT?
>> BECAUSE THE COUNTRY WILL
BECOME A DYNAMIC ECONOMY.
IT WILL BE DYNAMIC AGAIN.
IF YOU LOOK AT WHAT'S GOING ON,
WE HAVE THE HIGHEST TAXES
ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD.
WE PAY MORE BUSINESS TAX, WE PAY
MORE PERSONAL TAX.
WE HAVE THE HIGHEST TAXES IN THE
WORLD.
IT'S SHUTTING OFF OUR ECONOMY.
WE HAVE TRILLIONS OF DOLLARS WE
CAN'T GET IN.
WE WILL DO MY TAX PLAN AND IT
WILL BE GREAT.
WE WILL HAVE A DYNAMIC ECONOMY
AGAIN.
>> WHAT SPECIFIC CUTS WILL YOU
MAKE TO PAY FOR THAT TAX CUT?
>> WE'RE GOING TO MAKE MANY CUTS
IN BUSINESS.
WE'RE GOING TO GET RID OF SO
MANY DIFFERENT THINGS.
THE DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION,
COMMON CORE IS OUT, WE'RE GOING
LOCAL.
HAVE TO GO
ENVIRONMENTAL PROTECTION.
WE WASTE ALL OF THIS MONEY.
WE'RE GOING TO BRING THAT BACK
TO THE STATES B.
WE ARE GOING TO CUT MANY OF THE
AGENCIES, WE WILL BALANCE OUR
BUDGET AND BE --
>> MR. TRUMP, IF YOU ELIMINATE
THOSE TWO AGENCIES, THAT'S A $76
BILLION.
THE CURRENT DEFICIT IS $544
WHERE ARE YOU GOING TO COME UP
WITH THE MONEY?
>> WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE ALL
OVER THE PLACE.
WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE.
YOU LOOK AT WHAT'S HAPPENING
WITH SOCIAL SECURITY, LOOK AT
WHAT'S HAPPENING WITH EVERY
AGENCY, WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE.
WE WILL CUT SO MUCH, YOUR HEAD
WILL SPIN.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH.
WHEN YOU WERE IN CONGRESS, YOU
WERE CHAIRMAN OF THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE, YOU HELPED CRAFT THE
LAST BALANCED BUDGET THE UNITED
STATES HAD.
CAN MR. TRUMP'S PLAN WORK?
>> I THINK IT TAKES THREE
THINGS, WOLF.
I'VE DONE IT.
IN ORDER TO GET THIS ECONOMY
MOVING AGAIN, YOU HAVE TO GROW
THE ECONOMY AND YOU HAVE TO
RESTRAIN THE SPENDING.
WHEN I WAS CHAIRMAN, WE CUT THAT
CAPITAL GAINS TAX AND INSTITUTED
A SIGNIFICANT PROGRAM TO GET THE
BALANCE.
WE HAD THE BALANCED BUDGET FOUR
YEARS IN A ROW, HAD TO TAKE ON
EVERY INTEREST GROUP IN
WASHINGTON, EVERY SINGLE ONE OF
THEM AND WE PAID DOWN A HALF A
TRILLION OF THE NATIONAL DEBT.
WHY DO YOU DO IT?
BECAUSE YOU WANT JOB GROWTH.
IF YOU DON'T HAVE REGULATORY
REFORM, COMMON SENSE
REGULATIONS, REASONABLE TAX
CUTS, WHICH I HAVE, AND A FISCAL
PLA
PLAN, YOU WON'T DO IT.
I INHERITED AN AN $8 BILLION
HOLE IN OHIO, I HAVE COMMON
SENSE REGULATIONS, I HAVE TAX
CUTS, THE BIGGEST OF ANY
GOVERNOR IN THE COUNTRY AND WE
HAVE A FISCAL PLAN.
IT'S NOT ALWAYS CUTTING. INNOVA.
I'VE GOT A PLAN TO TAKE TO
WASHINGTON AND I WILL HAVE IT
THERE IN THE FIRST HUNDRED DAYS
AND IT WILL SHIP WELFARE,
SHIPPING, TRANSPORTATION BACK TO
US SO WE CAN BEGIN TO BE THE
LABORATORY OF INNOVATION.
I'VE DONE IT IN OHIO, WE'RE
GROWING, THE JOBS ARE UP AND
PEOPLE ARE HAVING OPPORTUNITY
AND I WILL GO BACK TO WASHINGTON
AND DO IT AGAIN FOR THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
I PROMISE YOU THAT.
WITHIN THE FIRST HUNDRED DAYS WE
WILL HAVE THE PLAN TO GET THIS
DONE.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
SPEAKING OF TAXES --
>> I JUST WANT TO SAY, AND I'M A
BIG FAN OF THE GOVERNOR BUT THEY
WILL STRUCK OIL.
THAT HELPED A LOT.
>> LET ME TALK ABOUT THAT.
OF THE OVER 400,000 JOBS THAT
WE'VE CREATED IN THE STATE, WE
THINK MAYBE 15,000 ARE CONNECTED
TO THIS INDUSTRY BECAUSE IT'S
EARLY STAGE.
WHAT WE'VE DONE IN OHIO AND WHAT
A PRESIDENT NEEDS DO IS TO HAVE
A CABINET AND A WHOLE OPERATION
THAT'S JOBS FRIENDLY BEEP HAVE
DIVERSIFIED OUR ECONOMY.
WE HAVE ENERGY, WE HAVE MEDICAL
DEVICES, I.T., WE JUST GOT
AMAZON, THEIR CLOUD COMPUTING IN
THE MIDWEST P.
YOU KNOW WHY IT'S HAPPENING?
WE'RE BALANCED BUDGETS, WE'RE
STRONG, WE DON'T RAISE TAXES.
WE WILL GET THE ECONOMIC GROWTH
AND THAT IS WHAT THIS COUNTRY
NEEDS.
JOBS, JOBS AND JOBS, PERIOD.
>> MR. TRUMP, YESTERDAY THE LAST
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL NOMINEE
MITT MILROMNEY CALLED ON YOU TO
RELEASE YOUR BACKS RETURN SAYING
THERE WAS GOOD REASON TO BELIEVE
THERE WAS A BOMBSHELL, HE SAID
YOU'RE NOT AS WEALTHY AS YOU
SAID YOU WERE OR YOU HAVEN'T
BEEN GIVING THE MONEY TO
VETERANS OR DISABLED PEOPLE.
ARE ANY OF THOSE ACCUSATIONS
THAT HE HAS LEVELED TRUE?
>> LET ME JUST EXPLAIN.
I WAS THE FIRST ONE TO FILE A
FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE FORM,
ALMOST 100 PAGES.
YOU DON'T LEARN ANYTHING ABOUT
SOMEBODY'S WEALTH ABOUT A
TELECOMMUNICATION RETURN.
YOU LEARN IT FROM STATEMENT.
I FILED WHICH SHOWS I'M WORTH
OVER $10 BILLION.
I BUILT A GREAT COMPANY WITH
VERY LITTLE DEBT.
PEOPLE WERE SHOCKED, THE PEOPLE
IN THE BACK, THE REPORTERS THEY
WERE SHOCKED WHEN THEY WENT
DOWN.
I FILED IT ON TIME.
I DIDN'T ASK FOR FIVE 40-DAY
EXTENSIONS, WHICH I WOULD HAVE
BEEN ENTITLED TO.
THAT'S HOW YOU FIND OUT WHAT
KIND OF COMPANY.
YOU DON'T LETTER ANYTHING FROM A
TAX RETURN.
I WILL SAY THIS.
MITT ROMNEY LOOKED LIKE A FOOL
WHEN HE DELAYED AND DELAYED AND
DELAYED AND HARRY REID BAITED
HIM AND MITT ROMNEY DIDN'T FILE
UNTIL A MONTH AND A HALF BEFORE
THE ELECTION AND IT COST HIM BIG
LEAGUE.
AS FAR AS MY RETURN, I WANT TO
FILE IT EXCEPT FOR MANY YEARS,
I'VE BEEN AUDITED EVERY YEAR.
12 YEARS OR SOMETHING LIKE THAT.
EVERY YEAR THEY AUDIT ME, AUDIT
ME, AUDIT ME.
I HAVE FRIENDS THAT ARE VERY
WEALTHY PEOPLE.
I WILL ABSOLUTELY GIVE MY RETURN
BUT I'M BEING AUDITED NOW FOR
TWO OR THREE NOW SO I CAN'T DO
IT UNTIL THE AUDIT IS FINISHED
OBVIOUSLY AND I THINK PEOPLE
WOULD UNDERSTAND THAT.
HUGH, GO AHEAD.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> ARE YOU GOING TO ASK ANYBODY
ELSE THAT QUESTION?
>> AMEN, AMEN.
I KNOW I'M HERE FOR THE RATINGS
BUT IT'S A LITTLE BUIT
RIDICULOUS.
>> A YEAR AGO YOU TOLD ME ON MY
RADIO SHOW THAT YOU WOULD
RELEASE YOUR TAX RETURNS.
>> TRUE.
>> ARE YOU GOING BACK ON WHY ARE
COMMITMENT?
>> FIRST OF ALL, VERY FEW PEOPLE
LISTEN TO YOUR RADIO SHOW.
THAT'S THE GOOD NEWS.
WHICH HAPPENS TO BE TRUE.
CHECK OUT THE RATINGS.
LOOK, LET ME JUST TELL YOU
SOMETHING.
I WANT TO RELEASE MY TAX RETURNS
BUT I CAN'T RELEASE IT WHILE I'M
UNDER AN AUDIT.
WE'RE UNDER A ROUTINE AUDIT.
OBVIOUSLY IF I'M BEING AUDITED,
I'M NOT GOING TO RELEASE THE
RETURN.
AS SOON AS THE AUDIT IS DONE, I
LOVE IT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, MITT ROMNEY
ALSO CALLED UPON TO YOU RELEASE
YOUR TAX RETURNS.
YOUR CAMPAIGN SAID LAST SPRING
YOU WOULD RELEASE YOUR RETURNS
YOU HAD NOT PREVIOUSLY RELEASED.
YOU SAY COMING OUT ANY DAY
MOMENTARILY.
WHEN ARE WE GOING TO SEE YOUR
RETURNS?
>> TOMORROW OR SATURDAY.
THERE'S NOTHING WHAT INTERESTING
IN THEM.
I HAVE NO PROBLEM RELEASING
THEM.
LUCKILY I'M NOT BEING AUDITED.
BUT I WANT TO GO BACK TO THE
QUESTION YOU ASKED ABOUT THE
DEBT.
THIS IS AN IMPORTANT ISSUE.
IT A HUGE ISSUE.
THIS LESS THAN FIVE YEARS, 38%
OF OUR ENTIRE BUDGET WILL BE
MADE UP OF SOCIAL SECURITY,
MEDICARE, MEDICAID AND THE
INTEREST ON THE DEBT.
THAT MEANS ONLY 17% OF OUR
BUDGET WILL BE FOR THINGS LIKE
THE MILITARY OR THE DEPARTMENT
OF EDUCATION OR ENVIRONMENTAL
PROTECTION ISSUES .
YOU CANNOT BALANCE OUR BUDGET
UNLESS YOU DEAL WITH THAT 83%.
WHICH I'VE BEEN REPEATEDLY
TALKING ABOUT SINCE MY TIME IN
THE SENATE, IN FLORIDA, WHERE
THERE ARE A LOT OF PEOPLE LIKE
MY MOTHER WHO NEED THOSE
PROGRAMS, BY REFORMING THE
PROGRAM FOR FUTURE GENERATIONS.
WOLF, YOU DID NOT GET AN ANSWER
TO YOUR QUESTION.
THIS DEBT ISSUE -- THE NEXT
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
WILL NOT BE ABLE TO SERVE FOUR
TO EIGHT YEARS WITHOUT DEALING
WITH THE NATIONAL DEBT.
IT IS NOT A QUESTION OF IF.
IT IS A QUESTION OF WHEN WE HAVE
A DEBT CRISIS B.
WE SHOULD NOT LEAVE THE STAGE
HERE TONIGHT WITHOUT HEARING A
SERIOUS ANSWER FROM EVERY ONE OF
US ABOUT HOW WE ARE GOING TO
DEAL WITH THE NATIONAL DEBT ONCE
AND FOR ALL.
>> I'M BEING FAIR TO ALL OF THE
CANDIDATES.
SENATOR CRUZ, TUESDAY IS FIVE
DAYS AWAY.
WHY HAVEN'T VOTERS SEEN YOUR
2012, 2013 AND 2014 RETURNS?
>> SO, I'VE RELEASED FIVE YEARS
OF TAX RETURNS ALREADY.
WE WILL HAVE TWO MORE YEARS
AVAILABLE TOMORROW.
AND I WOULD NOTE THAT THIS
QUESTION REALLY GOES -- DONALD
SAYS HE'S BEING AUDITED.
WELL, I WOULD THINK THAT WOULD
UNDERSCORE THE NEED TO RELEASE
THOSE RETURNS.
IF HE HAS SAID SOMETHING THAT IS
FALSE AND THAT AN AUDIT IS GOING
TO FIND IS FRAUDULENT, THE
VOTERS NEED TO KNOW.
LISTEN, PEOPLE ACROSS THIS
COUNTRY, WE RECOGNIZE OUR
COUNTRY'S IN CRISIS.
THE MOST IMPORTANT QUESTION IS
HOW DO WE WIN THE GENERAL
ELECTION IN NOVEMBER 2016 AND
ROUGHLY 65% OF REPUBLICANS THINK
DONALD IS NOT THE RIGHT
CANDIDATE TO GO AGAINST HILLARY
CLINTON.
NOW, PART OF THE REASON -- HE'S
LOST TO HILLARY ON EIGHT OF
THEM.
I EITHER TIED OR BEAT HILLARY
AND THIS IS AN EXAMPLE.
THE MAINSTREAM MEDIA IS LAYING
OFF DONALD NOW.
THEY'RE GOING TO PICK APART HIS
TAXES, PICK APART HIS BUSINESS
DEALS.
AND LET'S TAKE, FOR EXAMPLE, ONE
OF HILLARY AS GREAT
VULNERABILITIES, THE CORRUPTION
AT THE CLINTON FOUNDATION, THE
FACT SHE HAD CEOs AND FOREIGN
COMPANIES GIVING HER MONEY WHILE
SHE WAS SECRETARY OF STATE.
THE NEXT REPUBLICAN NOMINEE
NEEDS TO BE ABLE TO MAKE THAT
CASE AGAINST HILLARY.
IF DONALD TRIED TO DID IT,
HILLARY WOULD TURN TO DONALD AND
SAY, BUT GOSH, DNO DONALD, YOU
$100,000 TO THE CLINTON
FOUNDATION AND I WENT TO YOUR
WEDDING WE CAN'T NOMINATE
SOMEONE WHO LOSES TO HILLARY
CLINTON IN NOVEMBER.
>> AT THE BEGINNING I SAID
OPENLY TO EVERYBODY THAT I
CONTRIBUTE TO MANY, MANY
POLITICIANS, BOTH REPUBLICAN AND
DEMOCRAT.
I HAVE OVER THE YEARS.
I'M A BUSINESSMAN.
I SORT OF HAVE TO LAUGH WHEN TED
MAKES A BIG DEAL OUT OF THE FACT
THAT HE'S DOING WELL IN THE
POLLS.
I'M BEATING HIM IN VIRTUALLY
EVERY POLL.
I'M TIED IN TEXAS, WHICH I
SHOULDN'T BE.
A POLL JUST CAME OUT OF
BLOOMBERG THAT I'M BEATING HIM
SO BADLY THAT IT'S EMBARRASSING
FOR ME TO SAVE I'M BEATING HTHE
THAT BADLY.
I JUST GOT 36% OF THE VOTE, I
JUST GOT 46% ON ANOTHER ONE.
I GOT 38% ON ANOTHER ONE.
AND HE GOT 20 AND 22 AND HE LOST
IN SOUTH CAROLINA SO BADLY, THAT
WAS GOING TO BE HIS STRONG HOLD.
HE SAID A YEAR AGO, I CAN'T LOSE
SOUTH CAROLINA.
I BEAT HIM IN A LANDSLIDE.
LAST WEEK IN NEVADA, I BEAT HIM
IN A LAND SLIDE.
HILLARY CLINTON IRK TAKE A LOOK
AT "USA TODAY," TAKE A LOOK AT
THE Q POLL, I BEAT HER AND BEAT
HER BAD LLY AND I ONLY HAD ONE
LITTLE INTERCHANGE AND THAT WAS
FOUR WEEKS AGO WHEN SHE SAID I
WAS SEXIST AND BELIEVE ME, THEY
HAD A ROUGH WEEKEND THAT WEEKEND
BETWEEN HE AND HILLARY.
>> HE ATTACKED ME.
>> I WAS ABOUT TO SAY TO
RESPOND.
>> HE WENT ON A TIRADE BUT HE
DIDN'T ADDRESS THE SUBSTANTIAL.
HE CAN RELEASE PAST YEAR TAX
RETURNS, HE DOESN'T WANT TO DID
IT.
IT THERE'S NOTHING, RELEASE THEM
TOMORROW.
THEY'RE ALREADY PREPARED.
THE ONLY REASON HE'S NOT
RELEASING THEM --
>> MARCO MADE REFERENCE EARLIER
TO THE LITIGATION AGAINST TRUMP
UNIVERSITY.
IT'S A FRAUD CASE.
HIS LAWYERS HAVE SCHEDULED A
TRIAL FOR JULY.
I YOU WANT TO THINK ABOUT IF
THIS MAN IS THE NOMINEE, HAVING
THE REPUBLICAN NOMINEE ON THE
STAND IN COURT BEING
CROSS-EXAMINED ABOUT WHETHER HE
COMMITTED FRAUD.
YOU DON'T THINK THE MAINSTREAM
MEDIA WILL GO CRAZY ON THAT?
ON SUBSTANCE HOW DO WE NOMINATE
A CANDIDATE WHO HAS SAID HILLARY
CLINTON WAS THE BEST SECRETARY
OF STATE OF MODERN TIMES, AGREED
WITH HER ON FOREIGN POLICY,
AGREED WITH BERNIE SANDERS ON
HEALTH CARE, AGREED WITH BARACK
OBAMA ON THE WALL STREET
BAILOUT.
WE CAN'T WIN THIS ELECTION WITH
A CANDIDATE WHO AGREES HILLARY
CLINTON AND CAN'T TAKE IT TO HER
AND BEAT HER ON THE DEBATE STAGE
AND AT THE POLLS.
M.
>> HOLD ON --
>> FIRST OF ALL, TALKING ABOUT
THE POLLS, I'M BEATING HIM
AWFULLY BADLY IN THE POLLS.
>> BUT YOU'RE NOT BEATING
HILLARY.
>> HEY, IF I CAN'T BEAT HER,
YOU'RE REALLY GOING TO GET
KILLED, AREN'T YOU?
SO LET ME ASK YOU THIS BECAUSE
YOU'RE REALLY GETTING BEATEN
BADLY.
I KNOW YOU'RE EMBARRASSED AND I
KNOW YOU'RE EMBARRASSED BUT KEEP
FIGHTING, SWING FOR THE FENCES.
TRUMP UNIVERSITY IS A CIVIL
CASE.
IT'S A CASE THAT IS NONSENSE.
IT'S SOMETHING I COULD HAVE
SETTLED MANY TIMES, I COULD
SETTLE IT RIGHT NOW FOR VERY
LITTLE MONEY WITH YOU I DON'T
WANT DO IT OUT THE PRINCIPLE.
THE PEOPLE THAT TOOK THE COURSE,
ALL SIGNED REPORT CARDS SAYING
IT WAS FANTASTIC, WONDERFUL,
BEAUTIFUL.
I'LL WIN THAT CASE, EASY CASE.
CIVIL CASE.
NUMBER TWO, AS FAR AS THE TAXES
ARE CONCERNED, I'M BEING
AUDITED.
IT'S A VERY ROUTINE AUDIT AND
IT'S VERY UNFAIR BECAUSE I'VE
BEEN AUDITED FOR I THINK OVER 12
YEARS, EVERY YEAR BECAUSE OF THE
SIZE OF MY COMPANY, WHICH IS
VERY, VERY LARGE, I'M BEING
AUDITED, WHICH IS A VERY LARGE
COMPANY.
I'M BEING AUDITED 12 YEARS IN A
ROW LEAST.
NOW, UNTIL THAT AUDIT'S DONE AND
I DON'T THINK ANYBODY WOULD
BLAME ME, I'M NOT GIVING IT --
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
>> WHAT ABOUT THE YEARS YOU'RE
NOT BEING AUDITED, WOULD YOU
GIVE THOSE?
>> I'M BEING AUDITED --
>> YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT YEARS
YOU'RE BEING AUDITED FOR?
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK.
OUR COV
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
HERE AT THE UNIVERSITY OF
HOUSTON.
GENTLEMEN, I WANT TO TURN OUR
ATTENTION RIGHT NOW TO KEY
ISSUES INVOLVING FOREIGN POLICY
AND NATIONAL SECURITY.
AND, MR. TRUMP, I'LL BEGIN WITH
YOU.
YOU SAID THIS ABOUT THE ONGOING
CONFLICT BETWEEN THE ISRAELI AND
THE PALESTINIANS.
I'M QUOTING YOU NOW, "LET ME BE
SORT OF A NEUTRAL GUY.
I DON'T WANT TO SAY WHOSE FAULT
IT IS.
I DON'T THINK IT HELPS."
>> RIGHT.
>> HOW DO YOU REMAIN NEUTRAL
WHEN THE U.S. CONSIDERS ISRAEL
TO BE AMERICA'S CLOSEST ALLY IN
THE MIDDLE EAST?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I DON'T
THINK THEY DO UNDER PRESIDENT
OBAMA BECAUSE I THINK HE'S
TREATED ISRAEL HORRIBLY.
I WAS THE GRAND MARSHALL DOWN
5th AVENUE A NUMBER OF YEARS AGO
ON THE ISRAELI DAY PREPARED.
I RECEIVED THE TREE OF LIFE
AWARD AND MANY OF THE GREATEST
AWARDS GIVEN BY ISRAEL.
AS PRESIDENT, HOWEVER, THERE IS
NOTHING I WOULD RATHER DO THAN
TO BRING PEACE TO ISRAEL AND ITS
NEIGHBORS GENERALLY.
I THINK IT SERVES NO PURPOSE TO
SAY THAT YOU HAVE A GOOD GUY AND
A BAD GUY.
NOW, I MAY NOT BE SUCCESSFUL IN
DOING IT, IT'S PROBABLY THE
TOUGHEST NEGOTIATION ANYWHERE IN
THE WORLD OF ANY KIND.
IT DOESN'T HELP IF I START
SAYING I'M VERY PRO ISRAEL.
MORE THAN ANYBODY ON THE STAGE
BUT IT DOESN'T DO ANY GOOD TO
START DEMEANING THE NEIGHBORS
BECAUSE WOULD I LOVE TO DID
SOMETHING WITH NEGOTIATING P
PEACE, FINALLY FOR ISRAEL, AND
FOR THEIR NEIGHBORS.
AS A NEGOTIATORS, I CANNOT DOING
THAT IF I'M TAKING BIG, BIG
SIDES.
WITH THAT BEING SAID, I AM
TOTALLY PRO ISRAEL.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> THIS IS ANOTHER AREA ON WHICH
DONALD AGREES WITH HILLARY
CLINTON AND WHICH I DISAGREE
WITH THEM BOTH STRONGLY.
BOTH DONALD AND HILLARY CLINTON
WANT TO BE NEUTRAL BETWEEN
ISRAEL AND THE PALESTINIANS.
IF I'M PRESIDENT, AMERICA WILL
STAND UNAPOLOGETICALLY WITH THE
NATION OF ISRAEL.
AND THE NOTION OF NEUTRALITY IS
BASED UPON THE LEFT BUYING INTO
THIS MORAL RELATIVISM THAT IS
OFTEN PITCHED IN THE MEDIA.
LESSEN, IT IS NOT EQUIVALENT
WHEN YOU HAVE TERRORISTS
STRAPPING DYNAMITE AROUND THEIR
CHEST, EXPLODING AND MURDERING
INNOCENT WOMEN AND CHILDREN, IT
IS NOT EQUIVALENT TO THE IDF
OFFICERS PROTECTING RECALL.
MISSING FROM DONALD'S ANSWER WAS
ANYTHING HE HAS DONE IN HIS
NEARLY 70 YEARS OF LIVING
DEFENDING ISRAEL.
I HAVE OVER AND OVER AGAIN LED
THE FIGHT TO DEFEND ISRAEL, TO
FIGHT FOR ISRAEL AND THIS, IF
YOU WANT TO KNOW WHO WILL STAND
WITH ISRAEL, WE OUGHT TO STAND
WITH WHO HAS STOOD WITH ISRAEL
WHEN THE HEAT WAS ON.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> I CAN ONLY SAY I'VE BEEN A
BIG CONTRIBUTOR TO ISRAEL OVER
THE YEARS.
I'VE SEEN MANY REWARDS FROM
ISRAEL, HAVE I A GREAT
RELATIONSHIP WITH ISRAEL.
I'M GOING TO KEEP IT THAT WAY.
IF I COULD BRING PEACE, THAT
WOULD BE A FANTASTIC THING.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, I WANT YOU
TO WEIGH IN.
>> AFTER 9/11 THE SECRETARY OF
DEFENSE CALLED ME IN TO HELP OUT
WITH SOME THINGS.
I'VE BEEN A SUPPORTER OF ISRAEL,
STRONG SUPPORTER OF ISRAEL
LONGER THAN ANYONE ON THIS
STAGE.
I'VE BEEN STANDING WITH THE
ISRAELIS FOR A VERY LONG TIME.
I THINK THE PROBLEM WE HAVE IN
FOREIGN POLICY IS WE ARE NOT
CERTAIN WITH WHO WE STAND WITH
AND OUR ENEMIES ARE MOVING.
BECAUSE THEY ARE NOT SURE WHAT
WE WILL DO.
IT'S A VERY INTERESTING
DEVELOPMENT HERE WITHIN THE LAST
24 HOURS.
WE SAID TO THE SOUTH KOREANS WE
WOULD GIVE THEM THE HIGH
ALTITUDE DEFENSE SYSTEM.
IT REALLY RATTLED THE CHINESE.
FOR THE FIRST TIME WE TOOK
POSITIVE ACTION, THE CHINESE ARE
BEGINNING TO TAKE ACTION AGAINST
NORTH KOREA.
WHEN WE STAND FIRM AND BRING OUR
ALLIES TOGETHER, THAT IS THE
ROAD FORWARD.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, WHAT'S WRONG
WITH THE U.S. BEING AN HONEST
BROKER IN A NEGOTIATION AS MR.
TRUMP IS PROPOSING?
>> BECAUSE I DON'T KNOW IF
DONALD REALIZES THIS, IT'S NOT
HIS INTENT I SUPPOSE, THE
POSITION HE'S TAKEN IS AN
ANTI-ISRAEL POSITION.
YOU THE PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY
HAS WALKED AWAY FROM MULTIPLE
EFFORTS TO MAKE PEACE.
VERY GENEROUS OFFERS FROM THE
IZsS.
INSTEAD THE PALESTINIANS TEACH
THEIR 4-YEAR-OLD CHILDREN THAT
KILLING JEWS IS A GLORIOUS
THING.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES NEEDS TO BE SOMEONE LIKE
ME WHO WILL STAND FIRMLY ON THE
SIDE OF ISRAELI.
I WILL BE ON ISRAELI'S SIDE
BECAUSE THEY ARE THE ONLY PRO
AMERICAN, FREE ENTERPRISE
DEMOCRACY IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
>> MR. TRUMP.
I'M A NEGOTIATOR.
I'VE DONE VERY WELFARE REFORM
OVER THE YEARS THROUGH
NEGOTIATION.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT THAT WE DO
THAT.
IN ALL FAIRNESS, MARCO IS NOT A
NEGOTIATOR.
I'VE WATCHED HIM MELT DOWN AND
IT'S ONE OF THE SADDEST THINGS
I'VE EVER SEEN.
>> HE THINKS THE PALESTINIANS
ARE A REAL ESTATE DEAL.
THE PALESTINIANS ARE NOT A REAL
ESTATE DEAL.
>> A DEAL IS A DEL.
>> A DEL IS NOT A DEAL WHEN
YOU'RE DEALING WITH TERRORISTS.
>> YOU ARE NOT A INVESTIGATOR.
YOU ARE NOT A INVESTIGATOR.
AND WITH YOUR THINKING, YOU WILL
NEVER BRING PEACE.
YOU WILL NEVER BRING PEACE.
>> DONALD MIGHT ABLE TO BUILD
CONDOS IN THE PALESTINIAN AREAS,
BUT THIS IS NOT A REAL ESTATE
DEAL.
>> HE WILL NEVER BE ABLE TO DO
IT.
I THINK I MAY ABLE TO DID IT,
THOUGH I ARE SAY THIS, PROBABLY
THE TOUGHEST DEAL ANY KIND IS
THAT PARTICULAR DEAL.
>> LET'S MOVE ON TO TALK ABOUT
NORTH KROREA.
THE THREAT POSED BY NORTH KOREA
TO THE UNITED STATES AND ITS
ALLIES.
THE COMMANDER OF FORCES IN SOUTH
KOREA SAID KIM JUNG UN WOULD USE
A WEAPONS OF MASS DESTRUCTION IF
HE FELT THREATENED.
LET'S BE CLEAR, ARE YOU TALKING
ABOUT GETTING RID OF KIM JUNG
UN?
>> REGIME CHANGE MEANS REGIME
CHANGE.
>> THERE'S SO MUCH CHAOS IN
NORTH KOREA RIGHT NOW.
>> THERE'S A LOT OF REPORTS OF
UNCERTAINTY AND INSTABILITY IN
THAT GOVERNMENT.
HERE'S WHAT I THINK WE OUGHT TO
DO IMMEDIATELY AND WE'VE BEEN
KICKING THE CAN DOWN THE ROAD ON
THIS FOR, I DON'T KNOW, 15
YEARS.
WE SHOULD BE INTERCEPTING THE
SHIPS LEAVING SOUTH KOREA SO
THEY'RE NOT SELLING OR GIVING
THIS TECHNOLOGY.
WE NEED TO SLAP TOUGHER
SANCTIONS ON NORTH KOREA BECAUSE
WE DON'T HAVE THE TOUGHEST
SANCTIONS ON NORTH KOREA.
WE OUGHT TO TALK ABOUT ARMING
SOUTH KOREA WITH BALLISTIC
MISSILE TECHNOLOGY AND JAPAN
WITH BALLISTIC MISSILE.
WE HAVE THE ATTENTION OF THE
CHINESE.
THE CHINESE ARE THE BEST WAY TO
CALM THAT REGIME DOWN AND GET
THEM IN A POSITION WHERE THEY
BACK OFF.
BUT WHEN YOU SAY REGIME CHANGE,
I DON'T HAVE TO TALK EXACTLY
WHAT THAT MEANS.
LOOK, I'VE BEEN INVOLVED IN
NATIONAL SECURITY FOR A LONG
TIME.
YOU DON'T HAVE TO SPELL
EVERYTHING OUT.
BUT WHAT I'M TELLING YOU IS YOU
LOOK FOR ANY MEANS YOU CAN TO BE
AIL TO SOLVE THAT PROBLEM IN
NORTH KOREA AND IN THE MEANTIME
PUT THE PRESSURE ON THE CHINESE
AND WHAT WE'RE DOING IS
BEGINNING TO WORK AGAINST THEM.
THEY ARE THE KEY TO BEING ABLE
TO SETTLE THIS SITUATION.
>> I JUST WANT TO BE PRECISE,
GOVERNOR KASICH BECAUSE THIS IS
CRITICALLY IMPORTANT.
THERE A MILLION NORTH KOREAN
TROOPS NORTH OF THE DMZ, 28,000
U.S. TROOPS ALONG THE DMZ RIGHT
IN BETWEEN.
WOULD YOU RISK WAR FOR REGIME
CHANGE?
>> WOLF, AGAIN, IT WOULD DEPEND
EXACTLY WHAT WAS HAPPENING, WHAT
THE SITUATION WAS.
WITH YOU IF THERE WAS AN
OPPORTUNITY TO REMOVE THE LEAD
ARE OF NORTH KOREA AND CREATE
STABILITY -- IF YOU KEEP KICKING
THE CAN DOWN THE ROAD, WE'RE
GOING TO FACE THIS SOONER OR
LATER.
I'M ALSO AWARE OF THE FACT
THERE'S 10 MILLION PEOPLE LIVING
IN SEOUL.
HAVE I PUT TN T ON IT ON THE TA
WOULD LOVE TO SEE REGIME CHANGE
IN NORTH KOREA.
THE FACT IS WE HAVE TO BRING
EVERYTHING TO BARE, WE HAVE BE
FIRM AND UNITE THOSE PEOPLE IN
THAT PART OF THE WORLD TO STAND
FIRMLY AGAINST NORTH KOREA AND
MAKE SURE WE HAVE THE BALLISTIC
MISSILE TECHNOLOGY TO DEFEND
OURSELVES.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> I THINK WE ARE IN A
POSITION -- WE OWE $19 TRILLION
BECAUSE OF THE HORRIBLE OMNIBUS
BUDGET APPROVED, IT'S GOING TO
BE $21 TRILLION.
WE CAN NO LONGER DEFEND ALL OF
THESE COUNTRIES.
YOU ORDER TELEVISIONS, WHETHER
IT'S AM MERCEDES-BENZ OR AIR
CONDITIONING UNIT, THEY'RE
COMING OUT OF THESE COUNTRIES.
WE ARE DEFENDING SAUDI ARABIA.
THEY WERE MAKING $1 BILLION A
DAY.
WE DEFEND ALL OF THESE COUNTRIES
FOR PEANUTS.
YOU TALK ABOUT BUDGETS BE.
WE HAVE TO START GETTING
REIMBURSED FOR TAKING CARE OF
THE MILITARY SERVICES FOR ALL OF
THESE COUNTRIES.
>> DR. CARSON.
>> LET ME JUST SAY THIS BECAUSE
HE MENTIONED THIS.
WE'RE ALL IN AGREEMENT THAT THE
JAPANESE NEED TO DO MORE.
EUROPEANS NEED TO DID MORE.
I HATE TO JUST TELL EVERYBODY WE
ARE THE LEADER OF THE WORLD AND
WE SHOULD PUT THE PRESSURE ON
THEM DO THEIR JOB.
THERE IS NO QUESTION ABOUT IT.
BUT AT THE SAME TIME, WE ALSO
HAVE TO REBUILD THE MILITARY.
I HAVE A BALANCED BUDGET PLAN
THAT CUTS TAXES, REFORMS
REGULATIONS BUT ALSO BUILDS THE
MILITARY, PUTS $100 BILLION MORE
IN DEFENSE.
WE NEED TO REBUILD OUR DEFENSES.
ON
BUT I MUST ALSO TELL YOU, WE
CAN'T HAVE A WEAPONS SYSTEM TAKE
22.5 YEARS.
WE HAVE 800,000 BUREAUCRATS
WORKING FOR D.O.D. WHEN WE OUGHT
TO BE PUTTING THESE RESOURCES
INTO STRENGTHENING THE MILITARY.
SO WE CAN DO IT ALL.
>> HOW WOULD YOU DEAL WITH NORTH
KOREA, DR. CARSON.
>> FIRST OF ALL, PEOPLE SAY I
WHINE A LOT BECAUSE I DON'T GET
TIME.
I'M GOING TO WHINE.
I DIDN'T ASK ABOUT TAXES.
I DIDN'T GO ASKED ABOUT ISRAEL.
I HAVE TO SAY ABOUT TAXES.
>> GO AHEAD.
THIS IS YOUR MOMENT.
>> WE HAVE A SYSTEM OF TAXATION
IN THIS COUNTRY THAT IS HORRIBLY
WRONG.
YOU KNOW, I NEVER HAD AN AUDIT
UNTIL I SPOKE AT THE NATIONAL
PRAYER BREAKFAST AND THEYN ALL F
A SUDDEN THEY CAME IN AND SAILED
WE WANT TO LOOK AT YOUR REAL
ESTATE DEALINGS.
THEY DIDN'T FIND ANYTHING.
SO THEY SAID LET'S LOOK AT THE
WHOLE YEAR.
THEY SAID LET'S LOOK AT THE NEXT
YEAR AND THE NEXT YEAR.
THEY DIDN'T FIND ANYTHING AND
THEY WON'T FIND ANYTHING BECAUSE
I'M AN HONEST PERSON.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS THE
IRS IS NOT HONEST AND WE NEED TO
GET RID OF THEM.
AS FAR AS ISRAEL IS CONCERNED,
WHEN I WAS THERE SEVERAL MONTHS
AGO, I TALKED TO A LOT OF
PEOPLE.
I COULDN'T FIND A SINGLE ONE WHO
DIDN'T THINK THAT WE HAD TURNED
OUR BACKS ON ISRAEL.
YOU KNOW, THEY A STRATEGIC
PARTNER FOR US BUT ALSO
RECOGNIZE THAT WE HAVE A JUDEO
CHRISTIAN FOUNDATION AND THE
LAST THING WE NEED TO DO IS TO
REJECT ISRAEL.
IT DOESN'T MEAN THAT WE CAN'T BE
FAIR TO OTHER PEOPLE.
WE CAN ALWAYS BE FAIR TO OTHER
PEOPLE, BUT, YOU KNOW, IT'S LIKE
WHEN YOU HAVE A CHILD.
YOU WANT TO BE FAIR TO ALL THE
CHILDREN AROUND BUT YOU HAVE A
SPECIAL ATTENTION FOR YOUR OWN
CHILD.
NOW, AS FAR AS NORTH KOREA IS
CONCERNED, YOU KNOW, KIM JUNG
UN IS AN UNSTABLE PERSON BUT HE
DOES UNDERSTAND STRENGTH.
WE HAVE TO PRESENT STRENGTH TO
HIM BEEP SHOULD ENCOURAGE THE
ALLIANCE WITH JAPAN AND SOUTH
KOREA AND THE TERM HIGH AREA OF
DEFENSE, THAT SEEMS TO DISTURB
NOT ONLY THE NORTH KOREANS BUT
THE CHINESE AS WELL.
AND WE ALSO NEED TO HAVE A MUCH
MORE ROBUST NAVAL PRESENCE IN
THAT AREA.
AND I THINK WE NEED TO BE
DEVELOPING STRATEGIC DEFENSE
INITIATIVE.
THIS MAN IS GOING TO HAVE
LONLO
LONG-RANGE MISSILES AND NUCLEAR
CAPABILITIES, WE NEED TO BE ABLE
TO DEFEND OURSELVES.
WE SHOULD MAKE SURE HE KNOWS IF
HE EVER SHOOTS A MISSILE AT US,
IT WILL BE THE LAST THING HE
EVER DOES.
>> THANK YOU.
>> WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE WITH
NATIONAL SECURITY.
>> MR. TRUMP, WE ARE LESS THAN
24 HOURS AWAY FROM A CEASE-FIRE
IN SYRIA THAT HAS BEEN BROKERED
BETWEEN THE U.S. AND RUSSIA.
DO YOU SUPPORT THIS CEASE-FIRE?
>> I REALLY DON'T BECAUSE IT NOT
WORKING AND THE COUNTRIES AREN'T
AGREEING TO IT AND THE REBELS
AREN'T AGREEING AND THE SYRIANS
AREN'T AGREEING.
IT'S A MEANINGLESS CEASE-FIRE.
I LOVE THE IDEA OF A CEASE-FIRE.
IT NOT WORKING.
WE CAN DO WHAT WE WANT WITH
RUSSIA BUT NOBODY ELSE IS
ADHERING TO IT.
I WOULD CERTAINLY LOVE IT, I
WOULD SUPPORT IT BUT ALL PARTIES
HAVE TO AGREE TO IT.
>> RUSSIA HAS ENHANCED ITS
POSITION BECAUSE OF OBAMA'S
WEAKNESS IN THE MIDDLE EAST,
WEAKNESS IN SYRIA.
AS WE'RE HEADED TO NOVEMBER, WE
NEED NO NOMINATE A REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATE THAT CAN LAY OUT A
CLEAR DIFFERENCE WITH BARACK
OBAMA AND HILLARY CLINTON ON
FOREIGN POLICY.
ONE OF THE REAL CHALLENGES WITH
DONALD AND SENATOR RUBIO IS THEY
HAVE AGREED OVER AND OVER AGAIN
WITH BOTH HILLARY CLINTON AND
BARACK OBAMA.
FOR EXAMPLE, IN LIBYA, BOTH OF
THEM AGREED WITH THE
OBAMA/CLINTON POLICY OF TOPPLING
THE GOVERNMENT IN LIBYA.
THAT WAS A DISASTER.
IT GAVE THE COUNTRY OVER TO
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM AND IT
ENDANGERED AMERICA.
ANOTHER EXAMPLE IS JOHN KERRY.
SENATOR RUBIO VOTED TO SUPPORT
JOHN KERRY AND I VOTED AGAINST
HIM.
JOHN KERRY HAS BEEN THE MOST
ANTI-ISRAEL SECRETARY OF STATE
THIS COUNTRY HAS EVER SEEN.
HIS DIPLOMACY HAS BEEN A
DISASTER.
IT WE NOMINATE SOMEONE WHO
AGREED WITH JOHN KERR OO, BARACK
OBAMA AND HILLARY CLINTON ON
FOREIGN POLICY, WE'RE NOT IN A
STRONG POSITION TO WIN THE
GENERAL ELECTION.
>> AGAIN, I THINK I GAVE THEM
BOTH CHECKS TO BE EXACTLY
HONEST, I THINK THEY BOTH LIKED
ME VERY MUCH.
>> BUT YOU GAVE BUSH A CHECK AND
CALLED HIM TO BE IMPEACHED?
>> NO, THIS WAS BEFORE.
THE CHECK CAME EARLY.
SYRIA, HE'S SAYING I WAS IN
FAVOR OF SYRIA.
HE'S SAYING I WAS IN FAVOR OF
LIBYA?
I NEVER DISCUSSED THAT SUBJECT.
I WAS IN FAVOR OF LIBYA?
WE WOULD BE SO MUCH BETTER OFF
IF GADHAFI WERE IN CHARGE RIGHT
NOW.
IF THESE POLITICIANS WEPT TO THE
BEACH AND WE HAD SADDAM HUSSEIN
AND GADHAFI IN CHARGE, INSTEAD
OF HAVING TERRORISM ALL OVER THE
PLACE, AT LEAST THEY KILLED
TERRORISTS.
AND I'M NOT SAYING THEY WERE
GOOD BECAUSE THEY WERE REALLY
BAD BUT WE DON'T KNOW WHAT WE'RE
GETTING.
YOU LOOK AT LIBYA RIGHT NOW,
ISIS AS WE SPEAK IS TAKING OVER
THEIR OIL.
AS WE SPEAK, IT'S A TOTAL MESS
BEEP.
WE WOULD HAVE BEEN BETTER OFF IF
THE POLITICIANS TOOK A DAY OFF
INSTEAD OF GOING TO WAR.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> WE DIDN'T TOPPLE GADHAFI.
THE ONLY QUESTION WAS DOES IT
HAPPEN QUICKLY OR TAKE A LONG
TIME?
IF IT TAKES A LONG TIME, YOU'RE
GOING TO HAVE REBEL FORCES
EMERGE.
THAT'S WHERE THE TERM LEAD FROM
BEHIND CAME.
THAT'S THE FOREIGN POLICY THAT
APPARENTLY SENATOR CRUZ APPEARS
TO AGREE WITH.
EVERY DAY JOHN KERRY WENT
APPOINTED WAS ANOTHER DAY
HILLARY CLINTON WAS STILL IN
CHARGE OF THE STATE DEPARTMENT.
I COULDN'T IMAGINE THEY'D FIND
SOMEONE WORSE THAN HER BUT THIS
PRESIDENT NEVER CEASES TO AMAZE.
AND ON SOUTH KOREA, WE'RE ASKING
TO BE COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
HE'S SAYING THESE GUYS NEED TO
DO MORE.
SOUTH KOREA CONTRIBUTES $8 00
MILLION A YEAR TO THAT EFFORT IF
WE WALK AWAY FROM THEM, JAPAN
AND SOUTH KOREA WILL BECOME
NUCLEAR WEAPON POWERS.
>> I NEVER SAID WALK AWAY.
I WOULDN'T WANT TO WALK AWAY.
I WANT THEM TO PAY US MUCH MORE
MONEY.
WE CANNOT AFFORD TO SUBSIDIZE A
LOT.
I'LL NEGOTIATE A LOT MORE MONEY
THAN YOU'LL EVER GET.
AS FAR AS JOHN KERRY IS CONCERN,
THERE HAS BEEN NO TOUGHER CRITIC
OF THIS MAN, I THINK HE
NEGOTIATED ONE OF THE WORST
DEALS IN THE HISTORY OF OUR
COUNTRY, THE IRAN DEAL, WHERE
THEY GET THEIR $150 BILLION AND
ALL OF THE OTHER THINGS THAT
TAKE PLACE.
IT IS A DISASTER FOR THIS
COUNTRY AND SPEAKING OF ISRAEL,
IT'S A DISASTER FOR ISRAEL.
I'M NOT FAN OF JOHN KERRY.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> IT'S INTERESTING, DONALD JUST
SAID HE NEVER CAME OUT IN FAVOR
OF TOPPLING GADHAFI IN LIBYA PUP
CAN SEE AND HEAR THE EXACT WORDS
FROM DONALD'S MOUTH.
MAYBE HE FORGOT ABOUT IT, I
ASSUME DONALD WILL APOLOGIZE
WHERE HE SEES THAT HE SAID
EXACTLY THAT.
WITH REGARD TO JOHN KERRY, I
WILL SAY JOHN KERR OO'S FOREIGN
POLICY HAS BEEN A DISASTER FOR
DECADES.
THAT'S WHY I VOTED AGAINST HIM
WHEN IT CAME UP.
THE FACT THAT DONALD WOULD WRITE
HIM A CHECK AND SUPPORT HIM FOR
BUSH SHOWS HIS POOR JUDGMENT.
>> I ASKED IS THIS AN ECONOMIC
BOYCOTT AGAINST SISRAEL?
TOGETHER THE HEAT AND LIGHT PUT
ON THE STATE DEPARTMENT WAS SO
GREAT THAT WITHIN 36 HOURS THEY
LIFTED THE BAN ON AIR FLIGHTS
INTO ISRAEL DURING THAT ENTIRE
BATTLE AND I DEED DURING EVERY
BATTLE ON ISRAEL THE NATURAL
QUESTION IS WHERE WAS DONALD?
IF THIS IS SOMETHING HE CARES
ABOUT, WHY HAS HE SUPPORTED
ANTI-ISRAEL POLITICIANS FROM
JIMMY CARTER TO HILLARY CLINTON
TO JOHN KERRY FOR FOUR DECADES?
IN YOU CARE ABOUT ISRAEL, YOU
DON'T WRITE CHECKS TO
POLITICIANS UNDERMINING ISRAEL.
INSTEAD YOU STAND AND SUPPORT
THE NATIONAL SECURITY OF AMERICA
AND --
>> THERE'S A CRITICAL POINT THAT
NEEDS TO BE MADE HERE.
>> GOVERNOR, HE ATTACKED MR.
TRUMP.
MR. TRUMP HAS A RIGHT TO
RESPOND.
>> MY RESPONSE IS VERY SIMPLE.
THERE IS NOBODY ON THIS STAGE
THAT HAS DONE MORE FOR ISRAEL
THAN I HAVE.
NOB
NOBODY.
YOU MIGHT SAY, YOU MIGHT TALK,
YOU POLITICIANS, YOU ARE ALL
TALK AND NO ACTION.
THIS GUY IS A CHOKE ARTIST AND
THAT GUY'S A LIAR.
YOU HAVE A COMBINATION OF
FACTORS.
HE CAN'T DO IT BECAUSE HE
DOESN'T KNOW HOW TO TELL THE
TRUTH.
OTHER IT AND THAT, I REST MY
CASE.
>> THIS IS THE TYPICAL THING HE
DOES.
>> I GET A RESPONSE TO THAT.
>> CAN SOMEBODY ATTACK ME,
PLEASE.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT TO -- I WANT TO POINT
OUT SOMETHING HERE TODAY THAT IS
SO CRITICALLY IMPORTANT ABOUT
HOW THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION HAS
REALLY DONE SUCH A RIDIRIDICULO
FECKLESS JOB HERE IN FOREIGN
POLICY.
WE SHOULD HAVE BEEN SUPPORTING
THE REBELS LONG AGO.
THEY COULD HAVE TAKEN ASSAD OUT
AND BECAUSE WE DID NOTHING, THE
RUSSIANS ARE IN SITTING IN THE
CAT BIRD SEAT.
I'M THANKFUL THE AID TRUCKS ARE
FINALLY GETTING INTO SYRIA.
HAD WE HAD ACTED, WE WOULD HAVE
SOLVED THAT PROBLEM.
LET'S TALK ABOUT LIBYA.
LIBYA DIDN'T GO DOWN BECAUSE
THERE WAS SOME PEOPLE
REVOLUTION.
HILLARY CLINTON AND ALL THESE
OTHER PEOPLE CONVINCED THEM TO
UNDERMINE GADHAFI.
ISIS IS BEGINNING TO GET A FOOT
HOLD IN LIBYA.
WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH IT.
THEY'RE ON THE COAST, MOSTLY
IT'S DESERT BURR IT IT'S A PROB.
WE IS ISIS IN SYRIA AND IN IRAQ.
BECAUSE THIS ADMINISTRATION HAS
NOT HAD A STRONG FOREIGN POLICY,
ONE OF US HERE IS GOING TO HAVE
TO INHERIT A TOTAL MESS.
WE NEED TO ARMING THE UKRAINIANS
AND ASSERT OURSELVES IN AMERICA.
>> LET'S CONTINUE THE
QUESTIONING ON ISIS.
>> WOLF, YOU SAID I GOT A
RESPONSE.
>> YOU'LL HAVE A CHANCE.
MARIA WILL PICK UP --
>> YOU'RE SAYING I CAN'T RESPOND
TO BEING CALLED A LIAR?
>> GO AHEAD AND RESPOND.
THERE WHAT WE'RE SEEING WITH
DONALD IS ACTUALLY THE PATTERN
OF WASHINGTON DEAL MAKERS, WHICH
IS THEY MAKE PROMISE, THEY BREAK
THEIR WORDS AND THEN WHEN ANYONE
CALLS THEM ON IT, THEY CALL YOU
A LIAR.
THAT'S DONALD'S PATTERN OVER AND
OVER AGAIN.
HE SAID, FOR EXAMPLE, SEVEN
MONTHS AGO, I, DONALD TRUMP WAS
A MEMBER OF THE ESTABLISHMENT.
THERE'S A REASON HARRY REID
THINKS HE'S THE BEST REPUBLICAN
UP HERE, A REASON JIMMY CARTER
SAID HE WOULD SUPPORT DONALD
TRUMP OVER ME.
HE SAID DONALD TRUMP IS
MALLEABLE, HE HAS NO FIXED SET
OF BELIEFS AND TED CRUZ IS NOT
MALLEABLE.
ANY TIME ANYONE FOUNTS HIS
RECORD, DONALD YELLS LYING.
FALSELY ACCUSING SOMEONE OF
LYING IS ITSELF A LIE AND
SOMETHING DONALD DOES DAILY.
>> GO AHEAD, MR. TRUMP.
>> I WATCHED -- I WATCHED THE
LOBBYISTS.
I WATCHED WHAT THIS MAN DID TO
DR. BEN CARSON, WHO I RESPECT IN
IOWA WHERE HE SAID THAT BEN
CARSON IS OUT OF THE RACE, HE
HAS LEFT IOWA AND HE'S OUT OF
THE RACE AND I THOUGHT IT WAS
DISGRACEFUL.
AND GOT A LOT OF VOTES BECAUSE
OF THAT, TOOK THEM AWAY FROM BEN
CARSON.
PROBABLY TOOK THEM AWAY FROM ME,
TOO.
BUT I WATCHED IT.
I ALSO WATCHED WHERE HE DID A
FORUM THAT LOOKED LIKE IT CAME
RIGHT OUT OF A GOVERNMENT AGENCY
AND IT SAID ON TOP VOTER
VIOLATION.
AND THEY IT GRADED YOU AND IT
SCARED THE HELL OUT OF PEOPLE
AND IT SAID THE ONLY WAY YOU
CLEAR UP THE VIOLATION
ESSENTIALLY IS TO GO AND VOTE
FOR TED CRUZ.
I WATCHED THAT FRAUDULENT
DIAMONDBACK AND I SAID IT'S THE
WORST THING I'VE EVER SEEN IN
POLITICS.
TO ME THAT WAS EVEN WORSE THAN
WHAT HE DID TO BEN.
I KNOW POLITICIANS, BELIEVE IT
OR NOT, BETTER THAN YOU DO AND
IT'S NOT GOOD.
>> OH, I BELIEVE.
I BELIEVE YOU KNOW POLITICIANS
MUCH BETTER THAN I DO BECAUSE
FOR 40 YEARS YOU'VE BEEN FUNDING
LIBERAL DEMOCRATIC POLITICIANS.
AND BY THE WAY --
>> I FUNDED YOU.
>> CAN YOU HAVE THE CHECK BACK.
>> I GAVE YOU A CHECK.
>> YOU NEVER FUNDED ME.
>> AND, BY THE WAY, LET'S BE
CLEAR.
>> DONALD CLAIMS TO CLEAR.
>> HE SENT ME HIS BACK WITH HIS
AUTOGRAPH.
"MR. TRUMP, YOU'RE DOING A GREAT
JOB."
I HAVE HIS BOOK.
THANK YOU FOR THE BOOK.
>> DONALD, YOU CAN GET BACK --
>> YOU'RE A LOT OF FUN UP HERE
TONIGHT, I HAVE TO TELL YOU.
THANK YOU FOR THE BOOK.
>> DONALD, RELAX.
>> I'M RELAXED.
YOU'RE THE BASKET CASE.
DON'T GET NERVOUS.
>> GO AHEAD.
>> I'VE SEEN YOU.
>> YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT'S
HAPPENING.
>> GENTLEMEN, GENTLEMEN.
>> WOLF, I'M GOING TO ASK MY
TIME NOT BE DEDUCTED WHEN HE'S
YELLING AT ME.
>> HOLD ON, I'M GOING TO GET MY
ANSWER.
THESE ARE THE RULES.
>> WOLF, DO I NOT GET A RESPONSE
IN.
>> YOU'LL GET PLENTY OF RESPONSE
SO STAND BY.
>> MY NAME WAS MENTIONED.
>> I WANT TO TALK ABOUT ISIS
RIGHT NOW AND THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT.
HOW MUCH BEST TO KEEP AMERICANS
SAFE FROM ISIS.
THERE'S A HUGE BATTLE RIGHT NOW
BETWEEN THE TEXT GIANT APPLE AND
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WANTS
APPLE TO UNLOCK THE PHONE USED
BY THAT SAN BERNARDINO TERRORIST
TO PREVENT FUTURE ATTACKS.
APPLE HAS REFUSED SAYING IT
WOULD COMPROMISE THE SECURITY OF
ALL OF ITS CUSTOMERS AND JUST
THIS AFTERNOON THEY WENT TO
COURT TO BLOCK THE JUDGE'S
ORDER.
DANA BASH, PICK UP THE QUESTION.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU SAY IT'S
COMPLICATED AND THAT APPLE ISN'T
NECESSARILY WRONG TO REFUSE THE
COURT ORDER.
WHY SHOULDN'T INVESTIGATORS HAVE
EVERYTHING AT THEIR DISPOSAL?
>> THE FBI MADE THIS CLEAR 48
HOURS AGO.
THE ONLY THING THEY ARE ASKING
OF AND CERTAINLY THAT APPLE
ALLOW THEM TO USE THEIR OWN
SYSTEM IN THE FBI TO TRY TO
GUESS THE PASSWORD OF THE SAN
BERNARDINO KILLER.
APPLE SAID THEY'RE BEING ORDERED
TO CREATE A BACK DOOR PROGRAM
ENCRYPTION DEVICE.
THAT'S NOT TRUE.
I THINK APPLE SHOULD COMPLY.
THEY ARE NOT ASKING APPLE TO
CREATE A BACK DOOR ENCRYPTION.
>> IF YOU ARE PRESIDENT, WOULD
YOU INSTRUCT YOUR JUSTICE
DEPARTMENT TO FORCE APPLE TO
COMPLY OR NOT?
>> TO COMPLY WITH AN ORDER TO
ALLOW THEM TO GUESS THE PA
PASSWORD?
ABSOLUTELY.
THEY'RE ASKING THEM TO DISABLE
THE SELF-DESTRUCT OR ALL THE OWE
ERASE ON ONE PHONE IN THE ENTIRE
WORLD.
THEY DON'T WANT TO DO IT BECAUSE
THEY THINK IT HURTS THEIR BRAND.
THEIR BRAND IS NOT SUPERIOR TO
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, WHERE DO YOU
STAND, NATIONAL SECURITY OR
PERSONAL PRIVACY?
>> WELL, AS YOU KNOW, AT THAT
SAME CNN FORUM, BOTH MARCO AND I
WERE ASKED THIS QUESTION.
HIS ANSWER, HE WAS ON BOTH SIDES
OF THE FENCE.
HE'S NOW AGREEING WITH ME SO I'M
GLAD.
I SAID, YES, APPLE SHOULD BE
FORCED TO COMPLY WITH THE COURT
ORDER.
UNDER THE FOURTH AMENDMENT A
SEARCH AND SEIZURE IS REASONABLE
IF IT HAS JUDICIAL AUTHORIZATION
AND CAUSE.
IN THIS INSTANCE, THE ORDER IS
NOT PUT A BACK DOOR IN EVERYONE
AS CELL PHONE.
IF THAT WAS THE ORDER THAT,
WOULD BE PROBLEMATIC BECAUSE IT
WOULD COMPROMISE SECURITY AND
SAFETY FOR EVERYONE.
BUT ON THE QUESTION OF UNLOCKING
THIS CELL PHONE OF A TERRORIST,
WE SHOULD ENFORCE THE COURT
ORDER AND FIND OUT EVERYONE THAT
TERRORIST M SAN BERNARDINO
TALKED TO ON THE PHONE, TEXTED
WITH, E-MAILED AND ABSOLUTELY
APPLE DOESN'T HAVE A RIGHT TO
DEFY A VALID COURT ORDER IN A
TERRORISM INVESTIGATION.
>> DR. CARSON, TIM COOK, THE CEO
OF APPLE SAYS THAT THIS WOULD BE
BAD FOR AMERICA.
WHAT DO YOU THINK?
>> I THINK ALLOWING TERRORISTS
TO GET AWAY WITH THINGS IS BAD
FOR AMERICA .
YOU KNOW, WE HAVE A
CONSTITUTION, WE HAVE THE FOURTH
AMENDMENT.
IT GUARDS US AGAINST ILLEGAL AND
UNREASONABLE SEARCH AND SEIZURE,
BUT WE HAVE MECHANISMS IN PLACE
WITH A JUDICIAL SYSTEM THAT WILL
ALLOW US TO GAIN MATERIAL THAT
IS NECESSARY TO BENEFIT THE
NATION AS A WHOLE OR THE
COMMUNITY AS A WHOLE.
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE PFIZER COURTS
AND THINGS OF THAT NATURE.
SO ABSOLUTELY I WOULD EXPECT AND
TOLL COMPLY WITH THE COURT
ORDER.
IF THEY DON'T COMPLY WITH THAT,
YOU'RE ENCOURAGING CHAOS IN OUR
SYSTEM.
>> MR. TRUMP --
>> I WANT TO WEIGH IN ON THIS,
PLEASE.
THE PROBLEM IS NOT RIGHT NOW
BETWEEN THE ADMINISTRATION AND
APPLE.
YOU KNOW WHAT THE PROBLEM IS?
WHERE HAS THE PRESIDENT BEEN?
YOU SIT DOWN IN A BACK ROOM WITH
THE PARTIES AND WORK THIS OUT.
UP DON'T LITIGATE THIS IN THE
FRONT OF.
NEWSPAPERS.
YOU KNOW WHAT YOU DO WHEN YOU'RE
THE PRESIDENT?
YOU LOCK THE DOOR AND YOU SAY
YOU'RE NOT COMING OUT UNTIL YOU
REACH AN AGREEMENT THAT BOTH
GIVES THE SECURITY PEOPLE WHAT
THEY NEED AND PROFESSIONAL
TICKETS THE RIGHTS OF AMERICANS.
THIS IS A FAILURE OF HIS
LEADERSHIP TO GET THIS DONE AS
AN EXECUTIVE SHOULD BE DOING IT.
THAT'S WHY YOU WANT A GOVERNOR.
I DO THIS ALL THE TIME.
WE REACH AGREEMENTS ALL THE TIME
BECAUSE IN THE EXECUTIVE YOU'VE
GOT TO SOLVE PROBLEMS INSTEAD OF
FIGHTING ON THE FRONT PAGE OF
THE NEWSPAPER.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> THANK YOU.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU HAVE BEEN VERY
VOCAL ABOUT SECURING THE MEXICAN
BORDER, BUT ISIS HAS CALLED UPON
ITS SUPPORTERS TO CONDUCT
ATTACKS IN OUR NEIGHBOR TO THE
NORTH, CANADA.
AS A MATTER OF FACT, U.S.
OFFICIALS HAVE WARNED THAT IT IS
THE CANADIAN BORDER WHICH IS THE
MOST SIGNIFICANT THREAT.
YOU HAVE SAID THAT YOU WILL NOT
BUILD A WALL IN CANADA.
WHEN IT COMES TO NATIONAL
SECURITY AND THE THREAT OF
TERRORISM, WHY DOES MEXICO NEED
A WALL AND CANADA DOESN'T?
ISN'T THAT LIKE CLOSING THE
FRONT DOOR AND LEAVING THE BACK
DOOR OPEN?
>> FIRST OF ALL, YOU'RE TALKING
ABOUT A BORDER THAT'S MANY,
MANY, MANY TIMES LONGER.
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT A MASSIVE
BORDER.
WE HAVE FAR LESS PROBLEM WITH
THAT BORDER THAN WE DO WITH OUR
SOUTHERN BORDER.
I HAD THE PRIVILEGE OF WINNING
BY A LANDSLIDE, BY THE WAY, NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
YOU GO TO NEW HAMPSHIRE, THE
FIRST THING THEY TALK ABOUT IS
HEROIN AND DRUGS POURING IN.
YOU WOULDN'T THINK THIS
BEAUTIFUL PLACE, BEAUTIFUL WITH
THE TREES AND THE ROADS AND THE
COUNTRYSIDE, THEIR BIGGEST
PROBLEM IS HEROIN.
AND IT'S SUCH A SHAME TO SEE IT.
THEY'RE POURING IN FROM THE
SOUTHERN BORDER.
I'M TALKING ABOUT GREAT
SECURITY, I'M TALKING A TWWALL
THAT CAN ABSOLUTELY BE BUILT.
IT WILL BE A VERY HIGH WALL
AND -- IT'S GOING TO BE PAID FOR
BY CANADA -- IT'S GOING TO BE
PAID FOR BY MEXICO.
YOU'RE TALKING -- THE PROBLEM
WITH BORDER, YOU'RE TALKING
ABOUT A BORDER THAT WOULD BE
FOUR TIME LONGER.
WOULD BE HARDER TO DO.
I DON'T CARE WHAT ANYONE SAYS
IT, IS NOT OUR BIG PROBLEM.
OUR PROBLEM IS NOT ONLY PEOPLE
COMING IN AND IN MANY CASES THE
WRONG PEOPLE, IT'S THE
TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF DROUGS THA
ARE COMING IN.
>> I WANT TO TO YOU, SENATOR
RUBIO, ABOUT PUERTO RICO.
IT IS UNABLE TO PAY ITS DEBT OF
$72 BILLION.
IT IS ASKING FOR BANKRUPTCY
PROTECTION, WHICH WILL GIVE THEM
THE TOOLS TO RESTRUCTURE THE
DEBT THAT IS THE THE SAME DEBT
OTHER 50 STATES HAVE.
YOU OPPOSED GRANTING PUERTO RICO
THE BANKRUPTCY PROTECTION PUP
SAY IT IS ONLY LAST-RESORT
MEASURE BUT THE GOVERNMENT OF
PUERTO RICO HAS SAID THAT
BANKRUPTCY IS ITS LAST RESORT,
THAT THAT'S WHERE HE ARE NOW.
HOW DO YOU EXPLAIN THIS VERY
STRONG STANCE TO THE HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF PUERTO RICANS THAT
VOTE ACROSS THE U.S. AND
PARTICULARLY IN YOUR STATE OF
FLORIDA.
>> SURE.
BECAUSE BANKRUPTCY DOESN'T WORK
UNLESS YOU CHANGE THE WAY YOU'RE
OPERATING AND YOU'RE GOING TO BE
BANKRUPT AGAIN.
AND THE PROBLEM WITH PUERTO
RICO,
GROWING.
IT'S TOO EXPENSIVE TO DO
BUSINESS THERE.
THE TAX RATE IS TOO HIGH.
THIS YEAR ALONE WITH ALL THE
PROBLEMS THEY'RE HAVING, THEY
BARELY CUT THEIR BUDGET FROM ONE
YEAR TO THE NEXT.
THEY HAVE TO PUT THEIR HOUSE IN
ORDER AND PUT IN PLACE MEASURES
TO ALLOW THE ECONOMY TO GROW
AGAIN.
IF THE ECONOMY DOESN'T GROW,
THEY WILL NEVER GENERATE THE
REVENUE TO PAY THIS DEBT OR THE
UNFUNDED LIABILITIES THEY HAVE
OF PROMISES TO FUTURE
GENERATIONS.
IT WILL NOT SOLVE THE PROBLEMS
ON THE ISLAND AND YOU'RE GOING
TO CONTINUE TO SEE HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE LEAVE THAT
BEAUTIFUL PLACE AND COMING TO
THE MAINLAND.
THEY'RE UNITED STATES CITIZENS,
THEY'RE ENIT TITLED TO DO SO ANE
WE WELCOME.
THE LEADERS NOW ARE DOING A
TERRIBLE JOB AND THE PREVIOUS
GOVERNOR WAS DOING A GREAT JOB
UNTIL HE BARELY LOST THAT
ELECTION.
>> I WANT OUR VIEWERS TO STAY
WITH US RIGHT NOW.
THERE'S STILL MORE TO
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE
UNIVERSITY OF HOUSTON.
IT'S TIME NOW FOR CLOSING
STAT
STATEMENTS.
ALL OF YOU WILL HAVE 30 SECONDS.
DR. CARSON, WE'LL START WITH
YOU.
>> WHAT KIND OF LEADER DO YOU
WANT AND WHAT KIND OF PERSON DO
YOU WANT YOUR KIDS TO EMULATE.
THINK ABOUT THAT.
SECONDLY, SEVERAL YEARS AGO A
MOVIE WAS MADE ABOUT THESE
HANDS.
THESE HANDS BY THE GRACE OF GOD
HAVE SAVED MANY LIVES AND HEALED
MANY FAMILIES.
I'M ASKING YOU TONIGHT, AMERICA,
TO JOIN HANDS WITH ME TO HEAL,
INSPIRE AND REVIVE AMERICA.
IF NOT US, WHO?
AND IF NOT NOW, WHEN?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR KASICH.
>> THE LAST "USA TODAY" POLL HAD
ME BEATING HILLARY CLINTON BY 11
POINTS, MORE THAN ANYBODY ON
THIS STAGE.
SECONDLY, I HOPE YOU SAW TONIGHT
THAT EXECUTIVE EXPERIENCE REALLY
MATTERS.
IT MATTERS IN TERMS OF GROWING
OUR ECONOMY, BALANCING BUDGETS,
CUTTING TAXES, REFORMING
REGULATIONS.
I'VE DONE IT IN WASHINGTON, I'VE
DONE IT IN HAOHIO.
I HOPE YOU'VE NOTICED I DO HAVE
THE FOREIGN POLICY EXPERIENCE,
AND WORKING WITH SOME OF THE
GREAT MINDS TO DEVELOP THE
CONFIDENCE, THE FIRMNESS AND
TOUGHNESS AND THE ABILITY TO
BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER.
I HOP YOU ALL THINK ABOUT GIVING
ME YOUR VOTE.
I WOULD APPRECIATE IT VERY MUCH.
I TELL YOU, WE WON'T HAVE TO
SPEND TIME FIGURING WHAT WE'RE
GOING TO DO.
I WILL HIT THE GROUND RUNNING
AND WE WILL GET AMERICA MOVING
AGAIN.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> THANK YOU FOR HAVING US
TONIGHT.
YOU KNOW, THIS CAMPAIGN HAS COME
A LONG WAY.
IT WAS JUST A FEW MONTHS AGO
THERE WERE 15 OR 11 US ON THE
STAGE AND NOW THE VOTES ARE
STARTING TO COUNT.
WE INCREDIBLE DECISION TO MAKE,
NOT JUST ABOUT THE DIRECTION OF
AMERICA BUT THE IDENTITY OF OUR
PARTY AND CONSERVATIVE MOVEMENT.
THE TIME FOR GAMES IS OAF.
HAD YOU A LOT OF CHOICES TO MAKE
AND I'M ASKING TO GET MIND ME,
GO ON OUR WEB SITE AND JOIN YOU
ARE EFFORT, MARCORUBIO.COM SO WE
CAN BRING AN END TO THIS SI
SILLINESS AND LUNINESS.
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> WASHINGTON DEALS ARE
BANKRUPTING THIS COUNTRY.
THERE ARE SEVERAL DEAL MAKERS ON
THIS STAGE BUT THERE IS ONLY ONE
PERSON WHO HAS STOOD UP FOR US
PIP WILL RESCIND EVERY SINGLE
ILLEGAL AND UNCONSTITUTIONAL
EXECUTIVE ACTION.
I WILL INSTRUCT THE DEPARTMENT
OF JUSTICE TO OPEN AN
INVESTIGATION INTO PLANNED
PARENTHOOD AND PROSECUTE ANY
CRIMINAL VIOLATIONS.
I WILL INSTRUCT EVERY FEDERAL
AGENCY THAT THE PERSECUTION OF
RELIGIOUS LIBERTY ENDS TODAY.
I WILL RIP TO SHREDS THE --
CATASTROPHIC IRANIAN NUCLEAR
DEAL AND BEGIN THE PROCESS OF
MOVING THE AMERICAN EMBASSY TO
ISRAEL.
WE WILL ABOLISH OF IRS, SECURE
THE BORDER AND BRING BACK JOBS.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> THANK YOU.
NOBODY KNOWS POLITICIANS BETTER
THAN I DO.
THEY'RE ALL TALK, THEY'RE NO
ACTION, NOTHING GETS DONE.
I'VE WATCHED IT FOR YEARS.
TAKE A LOOK AT WHAT'S HAPPENING
TO OUR COUNTRY.
ALL OF THE THINGS THAT I'VE BEEN
TALKING ABOUT, WHETHER IT'S
TRADE, BUILDING UP OUR DEPLETED
MILITARY, WHETHER IT'S TAKING
CARE OF OUR VETS, WHETHER IT'S
GETTING RID OF COMMON CORE,
WHICH A DISASTER OR KNOCKING OUT
OBAMA CARE AND COMING UP WITH
SOMETHING SO MUCH BETTER.
I WILL GET IT DONE.
POLITICIANS WILL NEVER, EVER GET
IT DONE AND WE WILL MAKE AMERICA
GREAT AGAIN.
THANK YOU.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU AND
THANK YOU TO EACH OF THE
CANDIDATES ON BEHALF OF
TELEMUNDO AND MY THANKS