>> TONIGHT, THE DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATES ON ONE STAGE IN IOWA.
>> HELP ME MAKE IT HAPPEN.
>> EVERYBODY READY TO MAKE A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION?
>> THE FINAL FORUM BEFORE THE
FIRST PRESIDENTIAL VOTES, JUST
ONE WEEK AWAY.
>> ARE YOU EXCITED ABOUT THE
FUTURE?
>> HILLARY CLINTON, BERNIE
SANDERS AND MARTIN O'MALLEY
TAKING TOUGH QUESTIONS FROM
VOTERS ON THE HOTTEST ISSUES
WITHIN THEIR PARTY AND ACROSS
THE HEARTLAND.
>> I AM NOT GOING TO LET THE
REPUBLICANS RIP PUUP OBAMACARE.
>> IF A BANK IS TOO BIG TO FAIL,
IT'S TOO BIG TO EXIST.
>> WE SHOULD MAKE IT HARD FOR
CRIMINALS TO GET GUNS AND EASY
FOR ALL AMERICANS TO VOTE.
>> WITH IOWA UP FOR GRABS, THEIR
DIFFERENCES ARE CLEARER, AND
MISTAKES ARE EVEN HIGHER.
>> WHAT WE DO NOT ALLOW, DONALD
TRUMP AND THE OTHERS TO DIVIDE
US UP.
THERE IS NOTHING, NOTHING THAT
WE CANNOT ACCOMPLISH.
>> THIS IS A CNN DEMOCRATIC TOWN
HALL EVENT.
A CHANCE FOR IOWA VOTERS TO
DRIVE THE PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
WITH DECISION DAY AROUND THE
CORNER.
>> WE'RE GETTING INTO THAT
PERIOD BEFORE THE CAUCUS THAT I
KIND OF CALL THE LET'S GET REAL
PERIOD.
>> IOWANS ARE CHOOSING.
THE NATION IS WATCHING.
AND CANDIDATES ARE TRYING TO
CLOSE THE DEAL WITH VOTERS RIGHT
NOW.
¶
>>> ALL RIGHT.
WE ARE LIVE AT DRAKE UNIVERSITY
IN DES MOINES, IOWA, TO HEAR
FROM THE DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES AND THE PEOPLE WHO
MATTER MOST IN THIS ELECTION.
THE VOTERS.
WELCOME TO OUR VIEWERS IN THE
UNITED STATES AND AROUND THE
WORLD.
OF COURSE, HERE IN IOWA, WHERE
WE'RE BEING SEEN ON OUR CNN
AFFILIATES ACROSS THE STATE.
WE ALSO WANT TO WELCOME OUR
SERVICEMEN AND WOMEN WHO ARE
WATCHING ON THE AMERICAN FORCES
NETWORK AROUND THE WORLD.
AND TO OUR LISTENERS ON THE
WESTWOOD ONE RADIO NETWORK AND
SIRIUS XM CHANNEL 116.
I'M CHRIS CUOMO.
WE REALLY ARE THRILLED TO HAVE
YOU ALL WITH US.
NOW THERE HAVE BEEN DEBATES.
THERE HAVE BEEN INTERVIEWS.
TONIGHT, SOMETHING DIFFERENT.
A CHANCE FOR THE PEOPLE WHO WILL
DECIDE TO ASK THE QUESTIONS
THEMSELVES.
AS YOU KNOW, THE PEOPLE OF THIS
STATE ARE THE FIRST IN THE
NATION TO HAVE A SAY ON WHO WILL
SERVE IN THE OVAL OFFICE.
THEY ONLY HAVE SEVEN DAYS LEFT
TO MAKE UP THEIR MINDS.
IN THIS HALL TONIGHT, IOWA
VOTERS WHO PLAN TO ATTEND THE
DEMOCRATIC CAUCUSES NEXT MONDAY
NIGHT.
THEY WERE INVITED BY CNN AND OUR
PARTNERS, THE IOWA DEMOCRATIC
PARTY AND DRAKE UNIVERSITY.
AUDIENCE MEMBERS SUBMITTED
QUESTIONS TO US.
WE HAVE SCREENED THEM TO MAKE
SURE THEY COVER A VARIETY OF
IMPORTANT ISSUES AND THEY DO.
HOWEVER, THE CANDIDATES DO NOT
KNOW WHAT THE QUESTIONS WILL BE.
MANY OF THE VOTERS JOINING US
TONIGHT ARE UNDECIDED.
SOME ARE LEANING TOWARD A
PARTICULAR CANDIDATE.
NOW IN A BIT, WE'LL TALK WITH
GOVERNOR MARTIN O'MALLEY AND
SECRETARY HILLARY CLINTON, BUT
FIRST, PLEASE WELCOME SENATOR
BERNIE SANDERS OF VERMONT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HI, CHRIS.
HOW ARE YOU?
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU, SENATOR.
BUSY DAY?
>> YES.
MY WIFE TOLD ME TO BUTTON MY
COAT BUT I'M TOO FAT, SO --
>> I'LL DO THE SAME THEN.
I'LL DO THE SAME.
SO DO YOU REMEMBER WHEN WE FIRST
STARTED TALKING ABOUT THIS
ELECTION MANY MONTHS AGO, YOU
WEREN'T SURE THAT YOU WANTED TO
RUN.
YOU WERE NOT SURE, YOU SAID,
THAT THERE WAS AN APPETITE IN
THIS COUNTRY TO DISCUSS THE
PROBLEMS BETWEEN RICH AND POOR.
HOW SURPRISED ARE YOU BY
#FEELTHEBURN AND ALL THAT HAS
FOLLOWED?
>> CHRIS, OUR MESSAGE HAS
RESONATED MUCH FASTER, MUCH
FURTHER THAN I THOUGHT IT WOULD.
AND I THINK WHAT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE ARE PERCEIVING IS THERE
IS SOMETHING VERY WRONG IN THIS
COUNTRY WHEN ORDINARY AMERICANS
ARE WORKING LONGER HOURS FOR
LOWER WAGES, WHEN WE HAVE THE
HIGHEST RATE OF CHILDHOOD
POVERTY OF ANY MAJOR COUNTRY ON
EARTH AND ALMOST ALL NEW INCOME
AND WEALTH IS GOING TO THE TOP
1%.
AND THEN ON TOP OF THAT, PEOPLE
SEE THAT THAT RIGGED ECONOMY IS
SUSTAINED BY A CORRUPT -- AND I
USE THAT WORD ADVISEDLY -- A
CORRUPT CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM
THAT ALLOWS BILLIONAIRES TODAY
TO SPEND AS MUCH MONEY AS THEY
WANT THROUGH SUPERPACS TO ELECT
THE CANDIDATES OF THEIR CHOICE.
AND ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY -- AND
IT'S NOT JUST DEMOCRATS.
IT IS CONSERVATIVES.
IT IS REPUBLICANS THAT ARE
SAYING THAT IS NOT WHAT AMERICA
IS SUPPOSED TO BE ABOUT.
SO IF YOU ARE ASKING ME, WHY IS
IT THAT OUR CAMPAIGN HAS CREATED
THE KIND OF MOMENTUM THAT IT
HAS, I THINK WE ARE TOUCHING A
NERVE WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
WHO UNDERSTAND THAT
ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS IS JUST
NOT GOOD ENOUGH.
WE NEED BOLD CHANGES.
WE NEED A POLITICAL REVOLUTION.
>> SO YOU HAVE CENTERED --
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU HAVE CENTERED YOUR CAMPAIGN
ON THIS IDEA OF INCOME
INEQUALITY.
INTERESTINGLY, PRESIDENT OBAMA
TALKING ABOUT THE JOB JUST THIS
MORNING SAYS YOU DO NOT HAVE THE
LUXURY OF FOCUSING ON JUST ONE
THING WHEN YOU ARE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES.
YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO HANDLE
MANY DIFFERENT PRIORITIES.
DO YOU THINK YOU ARE UP TO THE
WHOLE JOB?
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA IS OBVIOUSLY
RIGHT.
BEING PRESIDENT IS AN ENORMOUSLY
DIFFICULT JOB.
IT'S A JOB THAT ENTAILS DEALING
WITH A MILLION DIFFERENT ISSUES.
I THINK I HAVE THE BACKGROUND.
I THINK I HAVE THE JUDGMENT TO
DO THAT.
I WOULD REMIND YOU AND REMIND
THE VIEWERS THAT IN 2002 WHEN
GEORGE W. BUSH AND DICK CHENEY
SAID WE SHOULD GO TO WAR IN
IRAQ, BERNIE SANDERS LISTENED
VERY CAREFULLY AND I SAID NO.
I THINK THAT WAR IS A DUMB IDEA.
I HELPED LEAD THE OPPOSITION TO
THAT WAR.
AND IF YOU GO TO MY WEBSITE,
LISTEN TO WHAT I SAID, AND SADLY
ENOUGH, IT GIVES ME NO JOY, MUCH
MUCH WHAT I FEARED WOULD HAPPEN,
DID HAPPEN.
I DO BELIEVE I HAVE THE
BACKGROUND FOR THE JOB.
>> WELL IT IS TIME FOR YOU TO
MAKE THE CASE.
LET'S DO IT WITH THE PEOPLE THAT
MATTER.
THE FIRST QUESTION COMES FROM
JERRY ODIE.
SHE'S AN UNDECIDED VOTER.
JERRY?
>> YES, SENATOR, SOME OF YOUR
DETRACTORS HAVE CALLED YOU A
SOCIALIST ON OCCASIONS.
AND YOU DON'T SEEM TO TROUBLED
BY THAT.
AND SOMETIMES EMBRACE IT.
I WONDER IF YOU CAN ELABORATE ON
THAT.
AND TO SHOW US THE COMFORT LEVEL
YOU HAVE, YOUR DEFINITION OF IT
SO IT DOESN'T CONCERN THE REST
OF US CITIZENS.
>> WHAT DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM
MEANS, TO ME, IS THAT ECONOMIC
RIGHTS, THE RIGHT FOR ECONOMIC
SECURITY IS -- SHOULD EXIST IN
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
IT MEANS TO ME THAT THERE'S
SOMETHING WRONG WHEN WE HAVE
MILLIONS OF SENIOR CITIZENS
TODAY TRYING TO GET BY ON
$11,000, $12,000 A YEAR, SOCIAL
SECURITY.
IT MEANS THERE'S SOMETHING WRONG
WHEN THE RICH GET RICHER AND
ALMOST EVERYBODY ELSE GETS
POORER.
IT MEANS THERE IS SOMETHING
WRONG, AND GOVERNMENT SHOULD
PLAY A ROLE IN MAKING SURE THAT
ALL OF OUR KIDS, REGARDLESS OF
THEIR INCOME, ARE ABLE TO GET A
HIGHER EDUCATION.
WHICH IS WHY I'M CALLING FOR
FREE TUITION AT PUBLIC COLLEGES
AND UNIVERSITIES.
AND WHY WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH
THIS HORRENDOUS LEVEL OF STUDENT
DEBT THAT PEOPLE ARE HAVING.
NOW WHAT'S GOING ON IN COUNTRIES
AROUND THE WORLD, IN
SCANDINAVIA, AND IN GERMANY, THE
IDEAS THAT I AM TALKING ABOUT
ARE NOT RADICAL IDEAS.
SO WHAT DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM
MEANS TO ME IN ITS ESSENCE IS
THAT WE CANNOT CONTINUE TO HAVE
A GOVERNMENT DOMINATED BY THE
BILLIONAIRE CLASS AND A CONGRESS
THAT CONTINUES TO WORK FOR THE
INTEREST OF THE PEOPLE ON TOP
WHILE IGNORING WORKING FAMILIES.
WHAT THIS CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT AND
WHAT I BELIEVE IN IS CREATING A
GOVERNMENT THAT WORKS FOR ALL OF
US, NOT JUST A HANDFUL OF PEOPLE
ON THE TOP.
THAT'S MY DEFINITION OF
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALISM.
>> NEXT QUESTION, RENE SEAGRAM.
SHE'S A NURSE.
SHE'S UNDECIDED.
SHE SEES HOW HEALTH CARE PLAYS
OUT EVERY DAY.
SHE HAS A CONCERN FOR YOU.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU HAVE
BRANDED YOUR PROGRAM, YOUR
SINGLE PAYER HEALTH PROGRAM AS
MEDICARE FOR ALL.
AND MEDICARE HAS A REPUTATION OF
HAVING SOME PROBLEMS.
LET ME CITE ONE EXAMPLE.
A MAN IN OUR CLINIC WENT IN TO
THE DOUGHNUT HOLE IN SEPTEMBER
AND COULD NOT AFFORD THE $1,200
A MONTH IT WOULD COST HIM FOR
INSULIN.
SO HE HAD TO DECREASE HIS DOSE
TO MAKE ITS INSULIN STRETCH.
SO WHAT DO YOU -- WHY DO YOU
THINK THAT PEOPLE WOULD SUPPORT
YOUR MEDICARE FOR ALL PROGRAM?
>> WELL, I THINK PEOPLE WILL
SUPPORT MY MEDICARE FOR ALL
PROGRAM BECAUSE THE UNITED
STATES TODAY IS THE ONLY MAJOR
COUNTRY ON EARTH THAT DOESN'T
GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE AS A RIGHT.
NOW I'M ON THE COMMITTEE THAT
WROTE THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT,
AND I THINK THE AFFORDABLE CARE
ACT HAS DONE A LOT OF GOOD
THINGS.
BUT, YES, WE HAVE 29 MILLION
PEOPLE WITHOUT ANY HEALTH
INSURANCE.
YOUR POINT IS THERE ARE SENIORS
TODAY, AND I MEET THEM EVERY
DAY, WHO CANNOT AFFORD THE
OUTRAGEOUSLY HIGH COST OF
PRESCRIPTION DRUGS BECAUSE IN
AMERICA, EVERYBODY SHOULD KNOW
THIS.
WE PAY BY FAR THE HIGHEST PRICES
IN THE WORLD FOR PRESCRIPTION
DRUGS.
LAST YEAR, WHILE 1 OUT OF 5
AMERICANS CANNOT AFFORD THE
PRESCRIPTIONS THEIR DOCTORS
WRITE, LAST YEAR THE THREE MAJOR
DRUG COMPANIES MADE $45 BILLION
IN PROFIT BECAUSE THEY SPENT
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
ON LOBBYING AND CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS.
SO I BELIEVE WE SHOULD JOIN THE
REST OF THE WORLD.
I BELIEVE AS A PRINCIPLE,
EVERYBODY SHOULD BE ENTITLED TO
HEALTH CARE AS A RIGHT,
COMPREHENSIVE HEALTH CARE.
AND BY THE WAY, IF WE MOVE
TOWARD A MEDICARE FOR ALL, NOT
ONLY DO WE COVER THE NEEDS OF
ALL PEOPLE, INCLUDING THAT
GENTLEMAN, WE WILL SAVE MIDDLE
CLASS PEOPLE THOUSANDS OF
DOLLARS A YEAR ON THEIR HEALTH
CARE BILLS BECAUSE NOW WE PAY,
BY FAR, PER CAPITA, MUCH, MUCH
MORE THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY ON
EARTH.
IT IS TIME IN MY VIEW, FOR US TO
HAVE THE COURAGE TO TAKE ON THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES, TAKE ON THE
DRUG COMPANIES, AND PROVIDE
HEALTH CARE TO ALL PEOPLE AT AN
AFFORDABLE COST.
>> THE CRITICISM IS -- THE
CRITICISM IS TO PAY FOR THIS,
WHAT YOU ARE REALLY ASKING FOR
IS ONE OF THE BIGGEST TAX HIKES
IN HISTORY.
AND THAT IS THE CRITICISM.
>> BUT, CHRIS, THAT'S IS AN
UNFAIR CRITICISM FOR THE
FOLLOWING REASON.
IF YOU ARE PAYING NOW $10,000 A
YEAR TO A PRIVATE HEALTH
INSURANCE COMPANY, AND I SAY TO
YOU HYPE TOTHETHYPOTHETICALLY, G
TO PAY $5,000 MORE IN TAXES OR
ACTUALLY LESS THAN THAT, BUT
YOU'LL NOT PAY ANY MORE PRIVATE
HEALTH INSURANCE, ARE YOU GOING
TO BE COMPLAINING ABOUT THE FACT
THAT I'VE SAVED YOU $5,000 IN
YOUR TOTAL BILLS?
SO TO SAY YOU'RE PAYING MORE IN
TAXES, LET'S ALSO TALK ABOUT
WE'RE GOING TO ELIMINATE PRIVATE
HEALTH INSURANCE PREMIUMS AND
PAYMENTS, NOT ONLY FOR
INDIVIDUALS, BUT FOR BUSINESSES
AS WELL.
AGAIN, WE ARE THE ONLY COUNTRY
ON EARTH THAT ALLOWS PRIVATE
INSURANCE COMPANIES TO RIP US
OFF.
WE SPEND THREE TIMES MORE THAN
THE BRITISH, 50% MORE THAN THE
FRENCH.
WE CAN DO BETTER THAN WE'RE
DOING RIGHT NOW.
>> BUT JUST TO BE CLEAR, YOU ARE
GOING TO RAISE TAXES TO DO THIS?
>> YES.
WE WILL RAISE -- WE WILL RAISE
TAXES.
YES, WE WILL.
BUT ALSO LET US BE CLEAR, CHRIS.
BECAUSE THERE'S A LITTLE BIT OF
DISINGENUITY OUT THERE.
WE MAY RAISE TAXES, BUT WE ARE
ALSO GOING TO ELIMINATE PRIVATE
HEALTH INSURANCE PREMIUMS FOR
INDIVIDUALS AND FOR BUSINESSES.
>> NEXT QUESTION, SHAWN
COLLISON, LAW STUDENT AT DRAKE.
SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED.
WHAT DO YOU?
>> I THINK YOU'VE INTRODUCED A
LOT OF PROGRAMS THAT COULD HELP
A LOT OF PEOPLE.
MY QUESTION IS, REALISTICALLY,
HOW DO WE FUND THOSE PROGRAMS?
WHERE CAN WE REALLOCATE OR CUT
SPENDING ON OTHER PROGRAMS.
>> GREAT QUESTION AND A VERY
FAIR QUESTION.
I START OFF WITH THE PREMISE
THAT IN THE LAST 30 YEARS,
ALTHOUGH MY REPUBLICAN FRIENDS
DON'T LIKE THE TERM, THERE'S
BEEN A MASSIVE REDISTRIBUTION OF
WEALTH IN THIS COUNTRY.
IT'S GONE FROM WORKING FAMILIES,
TRILLIONS OF DOLLARS, TO THE TOP
ONE-TENTH OF 1%.
SO, YES, WHAT THIS CAMPAIGN IS
ABOUT IS TO SAY TO PROFITABLE
CORPORATIONS WHO IN SOME YEARS
DON'T PAY A NICKEL IN TAXES, TO
THE WEALTHIEST WHO SOMETIMES
HAVE AN EFFECTIVE TAX RATE THAN
TRUCK DRIVERS OR NURSES, YEAH,
YOU ARE GOING TO START PAYING
YOUR FAIR SHARE OF TAXES.
NOW HOW AM I GOING TO PAY TO
MAKE CERTAIN THAT PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES ARE
TUITION-FREE AND WE
SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER INTEREST
RATES ON STUDENT DEBT?
I PAY FOR THAT BECAUSE WE'RE
GOING TO ASK WALL STREET TO PAY
A TAX ON SPECULATION.
WE ARE ALSO BELIEVING -- I
BELIEVE THAT AFTER THE WORKING
FAMILIES OF THIS COUNTRY BAILED
OUT WALL STREET, MAYBE IT'S
THEIR TIME TO HELP THE MIDDLE
CLASS OF THIS COUNTRY.
NOW I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE AN
INFRASTRUCTURE THAT IS
CRUMBLING.
ROADS, BRIDGES, RAIL, AIRPORTS,
LEVEES, DAMS.
WE ALL KNOW WHAT'S HAPPENING IN
FLINT, MICHIGAN.
WATER SYSTEMS, WASTE WATER
PLANTS.
I BELIEVE THAT IF WE END THIS
ABSURDITY OF ALLOWING
CORPORATIONS WHO MAKE BILLIONS
OF DOLLARS A YEAR IN PROFITS TO
STASH THEIR MONEY IN THE CAYMAN
ISLANDS, BERMUDA AND OTHER TAX
HAVENS, WE ELIMINATE THAT, WE'RE
GOING TO BRING $100 BILLION INTO
THE TREASURY.
THAT MONEY GOES INTO REBUILDING
OUR INFRASTRUCTURE, CREATING 13
MILLION JOBS IN FIVE YEARS WITH
A TRILLION-DOLLAR INVESTMENT.
I HAVE PAID FOR ALL OF OUR
PROPOSALS.
>> SENATOR, THE PUSHBACK BECOMES
HOW YOU PAY.
IN THIS ROOM, YOU ARE PREACHING
TO THE CONVERTED SOMEWHAT.
PRESUMPTIVELY DEMOCRATS.
BUT YOU'LL HEAR PEOPLE SAY
THAT'S YOUR PAYING FOR IT IS
PUNITIVE.
YOU'RE GOING TO PUNISH PEOPLE
WHO MAKE MONEY.
YOU'RE GOING TO PUNISH THE
FINANCIAL DISTRICT.
YOU'RE GOING TO PUNISH AND WIND
UP CHANGING THE IDEA OF AN OPEN
AND FREE ECONOMY BECAUSE YOU'RE
GOING TO PUNISH THEM FOR
SPECULATING, WHICH MEANS THEY
WON'T SPECULATE AS MUCH WHICH
MEANS YOU WON'T GET AS MUCH
ACTIVITY.
AND IF YOU DO A CHECKLIST OF HOW
YOU PAY FOR EVERYTHING, WHAT YOU
ARE DOING IS AMASSING THE
BIGGEST GOVERNMENT EVER AFTER
PRESIDENT CLINTON SAID THE ERA
OF BIG GOVERNMENT WAS OVER.
SEEMS LIKE BERNIE SANDERS IS
SAYING NOT ONLY IS IT OVER, I'M
GOING TO DO IT BIGGER THAN EVER.
>> WE HAVE TO PUT WHAT I AM
DOING IN CONTEXT.
HERE'S THE CONTEXT.
TODAY IN AMERICA, WE HAVE MORE
INCOME AND WEALTH INEQUALITY
THAN WE'VE HAD SINCE 1928.
THERE HAS, CHRIS, BEEN A MASSIVE
TRANSFER OF WEALTH.
I'M TALKING ABOUT TRILLIONS OF
DOLLARS, FROM THE POCKETS OF
WORKING FAMILIES INTO THE HANDS
OF THE TOP 0.1%.
THAT'S A FACT.
SO IF YOU ARE TELLING ME THAT AT
A TIME WHEN WALL STREET'S
RECKLESSNESS, GREED AND ILLEGAL
BEHAVIOR BROUGHT THIS COUNTRY TO
ITS KNEES, THAT I AM GOING TO
SAY TO THEM THAT THEY'RE GOING
TO HAVE TO START PAYING THEIR
FAIR SHARE OF TAXES, FINE.
IF THAT'S THE CRITICISM, I
ACCEPT IT.
I DEMAND THAT WALL STREET START
PAYING ITS FAIR SHARE OF TAXES.
SECOND OF ALL --
>> N WHAT ABOUT THE IDEA THAT
YOU ARE BRINGING BACK THE ERA OF
BIG GOVERNMENT AND MAKING IT
BIGGER THAN EVER?
>> AGAIN, I BELIEVE, YOU KNOW,
AND IOWA HAS PLAYED AN
INTERESTING ROLE IN THE FIGHT
FOR PUBLIC EDUCATION.
AND FOR 100-PLUS YEARS, WHAT'S
WE HAVE BELIEVED PUBLIC
EDUCATION TO BE IS UP TO THE
12th GRADE.
FREE PUBLIC EDUCATION UP TO THE
GUESS WHAT?
THE WORLD HAS CHANGED.
A COLLEGE DEGREE TODAY IS THE
EQUIVALENT OF WHAT A HIGH SCHOOL
DEGREE WAS 50 YEARS AGO.
PEOPLE WANT TO CRITICIZE ME,
FINE.
I BELIEVE THAT EVERY KID IN THIS
COUNTRY WHO HAS THE ABILITY AND
THE DESIRE SHOULD BE ABLE TO GET
A HIGHER EDUCATION, REGARDLESS
OF THE INCOME OF HIS FAMILY.
AND I WILL PAY FOR THAT THROUGH
A TAX ON WALL STREET
SPECULATION.
>> THEY DON'T CRITICIZE THE
GOAL.
THEY CRITICIZE THE METHOD OF HOW
YOU ACHIEVE THAT.
IS THE ERA OF BIG GOVERNMENT
BACK WITH PRESIDENT SANDERS?
>> THE ERA OF PROTECTING THE
MIDDLE CLASS AND WORKING
FAMILIES IS CERTAINLY SOMETHING
THAT I WILL MAKE HAPPEN.
I BELIEVE, FOR EXAMPLE, THAT
WHEN MY REPUBLICAN COLLEAGUES
TALK ABOUT CUTTING SOCIAL
SECURITY, I SAY WHEN YOU LIVING
ON $12,000 A YEAR SOCIAL
SECURITY, NO, WE SHOULDN'T CUT
IT.
WE SHOULD EXPAND SOCIAL
SECURITY, AND WE CUT THAT BY
LIFTING THE CAP ON TAXABLE
INCOME.
SO, CHRIS, THIS IS WHAT I THINK.
THIS IS WHAT I THINK.
WHEN WE LIVE IN A NATION OF SO
MUCH INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY, WHERE THE TOP 0.1%
OWNS AS MUCH WEALTH AS THE
BOTTOM 90%, WHEN THE 20
WEALTHIEST PEOPLE OWN MORE
WEALTH THAN THE BOTTOM HALF OF
AMERICA, THAT IS NOT, TO ME,
WHAT THE AMERICAN ECONOMY SHOULD
BE ABOUT.
SO, YES, PEOPLE WANT TO
CRITICIZE ME, OKAY.
I WILL TAKE ON THE GREED OF
CORPORATE AMERICA AND THE GREED
OF WALL STREET AND FIGHT TO
PROTECT THE MIDDLE CLASS.
>> NEXT QUESTION, ROD EDWARDS
SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED.
>> GIVEN THE ONGOING GRIDLOCK IN
WASHINGTON AND THE CONTINUING
REPUBLICAN RESISTANCE TOWARD
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S INITIATIVES,
AND THE LIKELIHOOD THAT
REPUBLICANS WILL WIN CONTROL
OVER AT LEAST ONE HOUSE OF
CONGRESS, AS PRESIDENT, WHAT
SPECIFICALLY WILL YOU DO TO
OVERCOME THE RESISTANCE, CURE
THE GRIDLOCK AND GARNER THE
NECESSARY SUPPORT TO IMPLEMENT
YOUR INITIATIVES AND ACTUALLY
GET SOMETHING DONE IN
WASHINGTON?
>> GREAT QUESTION.
LET ME ANSWER IT, IF I MIGHT, IN
TWO WAYS.
I AM PROBABLY THE MOST
PROGRESSIVE MEMBER IN THE U.S.
SENATE.
BUT I HAVE, OVER THE YEARS, NOT
ONLY IN THE SENATE, BUT IN THE
HOUSE, WORKED WITH REPUBLICANS
WHEN THERE WAS COMMON GROUND.
WHEN I WAS IN THE HOUSE.
IN A NUMBER OF YEARS, I GOT MORE
AMENDMENTS PASSED ON THE FLOOR
OF THE HOUSE WORKING WITH
REPUBLICANS THAN ANYBODY ELSE.
NUMBER ONE AND NUMBER TWO.
IN THE SENATE JUST A COUPLE OF
YEARS AGO IN A DYSFUNCTIONAL
CONGRESS, I WORKED WITH PEOPLE
LIKE JOHN McCAIN.
PEOPLE LIKE JEFF MILLER OVER IN
THE HOUSE TO PASS THE MOST
COMPREHENSIVE VETERANS HEALTH
CARE LEGISLATION IN THE MODERN
HISTORY OF THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
I HAVE WORKED WITH REPUBLICANS
WHEN THERE IS COMMON GROUND
THROUGHOUT MY CAREER.
BUT THIS IS WHAT I ALSO WANT TO
SAY.
IN MY VIEW, YOU HAVE A CONGRESS
TODAY THAT IS MUCH MORE WORRIED
ABOUT PROTECTING THE INTEREST OF
THE WEALTHY AND THE POWERFUL AND
MAKING SURE THEY GET CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS FROM THE WEALTHY
AND THE POWERFUL.
IF WE ARE SERIOUS ABOUT
REBUILDING THE AMERICAN MIDDLE
CLASS, IF WE ARE SERIOUS ABOUT
PROVIDING PAID FAMILY AND
MEDICAL LEAVE TO ALL OF OUR
PEOPLE, IF WE ARE SERIOUS ABOUT
ENDING THE DISGRACE OF HAVING SO
MANY OF OUR CHILDREN LIVE IN
POVERTY, THE REAL WAY TO DO IT
IS TO HAVE MILLIONS OF AMERICANS
FINALLY STAND UP AND SAY, ENOUGH
IS ENOUGH.
FOR PEOPLE TO GET ENGAGED IN THE
POLITICAL PROCESS.
TO FINALLY DEMAND THAT
WASHINGTON REPRESENT ALL OF US,
NOT JUST A HANDFUL OF VERY
WEALTHY PEOPLE.
THAT'S THE WAY YOU BRING ABOUT
REAL CHANGE.
>> NEXT QUESTION, ALEXIS
COULASH, DRAKE UNIVERSITY
STUDENT, A BULLDOG, LEANING IN
FAVOR OF HILLARY CLINTON, BUT
SHE WANTS TO EXPLAIN WHY.
>> GIVE ME A SHOT HERE, ALEXIS.
>> YOU NAMED PLANNED PARENTHOOD
AND THE HUMAN RIGHTS CAMPAIGN AS
PART OF THE POLITICAL
ESTABLISHMENT YOU PLAN TO TAKE
ON.
HOW ARE YOU GOING TO FIGHT FOR
WOMEN'S RIGHTS, MORE EFFECTIVELY
THAN A FEMALE CANDIDATE WITH
ENDORSEMENTS FROM ORGANIZATIONS
LIKE THAT.
>> THAT'S NOT QUITE ACRATS.
I HAVE A 100% PRO-CHOICE VOTING
RECORD.
IN EVERY SPEECH THAT I GIVE,
WHAT I SAY IS NOT ONLY DO WE
STOP THE REPUBLICAN EFFORTS TO
TRY TO DEFUND PLANNED
PARENTHOOD, WE SHOULD EXPAND
FUNDING FOR PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
NOW WHAT I SAID, WHAT I SAID ON
A TELEVISION PROGRAM, AND I DID
NOT SAY IT WELL, IS THAT
SOMETIMES THE BASE OF AN
ORGANIZATION LOOKS AT THE WORLD
A LITTLE BIT DIFFERENTLY THAN
THE LEADERSHIP.
SO IF YOU HAVE 100% PLANNED
PARENTHOOD VOTING RECORD, 100%
PRO-CHOICE VOTING RECORD, PEOPLE
ARE ASKING, WHY IS THE
LEADERSHIP NOT EITHER SUPPORTING
BERNIE SANDERS OR WHY ARE THEY,
YOU KNOW, OPPOSING HIM?
AND MY POINT IS THAT I WILL --
THESE ARE GREAT ORGANIZATIONS.
I MET WITH PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
THEY DO A FANTASTIC JOB, NOT
ONLY IN DEFENDING WOMEN'S RIGHTS
IN GENERAL, BUT TALKING ABOUT
SEXUALITY IN AMERICA.
THEY ARE A FANTASTIC
ORGANIZATION.
COUNT ME IN AS SOMEONE WHO
STRONGLY SUPPORTS THEM.
SO THIS WAS SIMPLY A QUESTION OF
ENDORSEMENT POLICY, NOT WHETHER
OR NOT I STRONGLY SUPPORT THESE
ORGANIZATIONS.
DO I HAVE YOUR VOTE YET?
>> CORRECT SHE'S SAYING AS TO
THE PURPOSE OF THE QUESTION, NOT
ON WHETHER YOU HAVE HER VOTE.
>> I'M JUST KIDDING, BUT THAT IS
THE DIFFERENCE.
I SUPPORT THE ORGANIZATION.
>> SECOND ASPECT TO YOUR
QUESTION.
YOU SAID THEN THE FIRST FEMALE
PRESIDENT.
HOW DO YOU THINK YOU'D BE AS
HELPFUL TO WOMEN AS A WOMAN
PRESIDENT WOULD?
WHAT ABOUT THAT ASPECT?
THAT'S WHAT HILLARY CLINTON
REPRESENTS ON ONE LEVEL TO
VOTERS, THAT'S SHE WOULD BE THE
FIRST FEMALE PRESIDENT, AND
THERE IS SOMETHING SPECIAL IN
THAT WHEN IT COMES TO WOMEN'S
ISSUES.
>> OF COURSE, I UNDERSTAND THAT.
BUT I THINK IF YOU LOOK AT MY
RECORD, IN TERMS OF FIGHTING FOR
WOMEN'S RIGHTS, I THINK THERE
ARE VERY FEW MEMBERS OF CONGRESS
WHO HAVE A STRONGER RECORD.
IT'S 100% LIFETIME THAT I'VE
BEEN THERE FOR A WHILE.
IN ADDITION TO THAT, YOU KNOW,
THERE HAVE -- AS YOU KNOW, WOMEN
ARE MAKING 79 CENTS ON THE
DOLLAR COMPARED TO MEN.
THAT IS NOTHING BUT
OLD-FASHIONED SEXISM, AND I AM A
STRONG ADVOCATE AND WILL FIGHT
FOR PAY EQUITY FOR WOMEN.
I BELIEVE THAT -- AND IT'S NOT
ONLY WOMEN, ALTHOUGH IT IMPACTS
WOMEN AND WOMEN OF COLOR EVEN
GREATER, THIS LEVEL OF PAY
INEQUALITY, INEQUITY, IS
EXTRAORDINARY.
WE'RE GOING TO FIGHT FOR PAY
EQUITY, MAKE SURE THAT EVERYBODY
EARNS THE SAME AMOUNT FOR THE
SAME WORK.
ALSO, WHAT WE HAVE GOT TO DO IS
PEOPLE CANNOT MAKE IT ON $8, $9,
10 BUCKS AN HOUR.
WE'VE GOT TO RAISE THE MINIMUM
WAGE TO A LIVING WAGE.
THAT WILL IMPACT ALL PEOPLE.
IT WILL IMPACT WOMEN MORE THAN
MEN AS WE RAISE THE MINIMUM WAGE
TO 15 BUCKS AN HOUR.
>> ALL RIGHT.
SO --
>> ONE MORE POINT.
I'M TRYING TO WIN HER VOTE.
LEAVE ME ALONE HERE.
ALL RIGHT.
HILLARY CLINTON AND I HAVE A
DISAGREEMENT ON A VERY IMPORTANT
ISSUE THAT IMPACTS EVERYONE BUT
ESPECIALLY WOMEN.
I BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD EXPAND
SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS BY
LIFTING THE CAP ON TAXABLE
INCOME.
THAT WILL HELP MILLIONS OF
LOW-INCOME SENIORS, ESPECIALLY
WOMEN.
ASK HILLARY CLINTON IF SHE'S
PREPARED TO LIFT THE CAP ON
TAXABLE INCOME.
>> ALL RIGHT, ALEXIS.
I WANT TO PUT YOU A LITTLE BIT
ON THE SPOT.
NOW THAT YOU HEARD THE ANSWER --
WHAT DO YOU THINK NOW?
HE LOOKS LIKE THAT EVEN WHEN
HE'S HAPPY, SO DON'T WORRY ABOUT
HIS PARTICULAR REACTION.
SO, AFTER THE ANSWER, WHERE ARE
YOU?
SAME PLACE?
OPEN-MINDED?
>> DEFINITELY MEANS I'M GOING TO
HAVE SOME HARD THINKING TO DO.
BUT IT REASSURES ME, AND IT WAS
A GOOD PLAN TO SPEAK ABOUT.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> TAKE PROGRESS WHERE YOU FIND
IT.
WE'LL GIVE ALEXIS SOME TIME TO
THINK.
THE REST OF YOU AS WELL.
WE HAVE MORE QUESTIONS FOR
SENATOR SANDERS AND HIS FINAL
PITCH TO THESE IOWA VOTERS WHEN
WE COME BACK.
STAY WITH US.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL HERE AT DRAKE UNIVERSITY IN
DES MOINES, IOWA.
WE'RE HERE WITH SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS.
WE'VE BEEN TALKING ABOUT THE
ISSUES.
YOU WERE WORKING ON A YOUNG
WOMAN THERE TRYING TO GET HER
VOTE.
I HAVE ANOTHER WOMAN.
I THINK YOU HAVE SOME WORK LEFT
TO DO ON.
HER NAME IS SECRETARY CLINTON.
SHE HAS AN AD OUT NOW.
YOU BOTH PUT OUT BIG ADS.
I KNOW HOW YOU FEEL ABOUT YOURS.
LET'S LOOK AT SECRETARY
CLINTON'S AD AND GET YOUR TAKE
ON IT.
>> THE WORLD A PRESIDENT HAS TO
GRAPPLE WITH.
SOMETIMES YOU CAN'T EVEN
IMAGINE.
THAT'S THE JOB.
AND SHE'S PREPARED FOR IT LIKE
NO OTHER.
A TIRELESS SECRETARY OF STATE
STANDING UP AGAINST THE ABUSE OF
WOMEN AND GIRLS.
NEGOTIATING A CEASE-FIRE IN
GAZA.
LEADING THE DIPLOMACY THAT KEEPS
US OUT OF WAR.
THE PRESIDENCY IS THE TOUGHEST
JOB IN THE WORLD, AND SHE'S THE
ONE LEADER WHO HAS WHAT IT TAKES
TO GET EVERY PART OF THE JOB
DONE.
>> I'M HILLARY CLINTON, AND I
APPROVE THIS MESSAGE.
>> THE ARGUMENT IS, SURE,
BERNIE'S GOT THE HEART, BUT I
HAVE THE HEAD.
YOU HAVE TO BE EXPERIENCED, HAVE
TO KNOW WHAT TO DO.
IS SECRETARY CLINTON SIMPLY
BETTER PREPARED FOR THE JOB THAN
YOU, SIR?
DON'T LEAVE.
WE HAVE ANOTHER 15 MINUTES.
>> THIS CALLS FOR A STANDING UP
RESPONSE.
LET ME SHOCK EVERYBODY HERE.
THIS IS TRUE.
I HAVE KNOWN HILLARY CLINTON FOR
25 YEARS.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
I LIKE HILLARY CLINTON, AND I
RESPECT HILLARY CLINTON.
AND HILLARY CLINTON HAS THE
DEVOTED HER LIFE TO PUBLIC
SERVICE, AND I HAVE TRIED, AS I
HOPE YOU ALL KNOW, NOT TO RUN A
NEGATIVE CAMPAIGN.
NOT TO BE ATTACKING EVERY OTHER
DAY, TO KEEP THIS DISCUSSION ON
A HIGH LEVEL WHERE WE DEBATE THE
ISSUES FACING THIS COUNTRY.
AND BY THE WAY, WITH A FEW
EXCEPTIONS, WE'RE DOING A LOT
BETTER THAN THE REPUBLICANS IN
THAT REGARD.
BUT ON THE OTHER HAND, THAT'S
NOT A VERY HIGH BAR TO REACH,
SO -- ALL RIGHT.
WHAT IS THIS.
ALL RIGHT.
WHAT DO I THINK?
LET ME GIVE YOU A COUPLE OF
EXAMPLES.
THE TRUTH IS THAT THE MOST
SIGNIFICANT VOTE AND ISSUE
REGARDING FOREIGN POLICY THAT WE
HAVE SEEN IN THIS COUNTRY IN
MODERN HISTORY WAS THE VOTE ON
THE WAR IN IRAQ.
OKAY?
THAT'S THE FACT.
I VOTED AGAINST THE WAR IN IRAQ,
AND IF YOU GO TO MY WEBSITE,
LISTEN TO THE SPEECH THAT I GAVE
WHEN I WAS IN THE HOUSE IN 2002
SAYING, YEAH, IT'S EASY TO GET
RI
RID OF A DICTATOR LIKE SADDAM
HUSSEIN BUT THERE WILL BE A
PLITICAL VACUUM.
AND IT GIVES ME NO PLEASURE TO
TELL YOU THAT MUCH OF WHAT I
FEARED HAPPENED.
HILLARY CLINTON VOTED FOR THE
WAR IN IRAQ.
ALL RIGHT.
IN TERMS OF WALL STREET, I
FOUGHT AGAINST DEREGULATION.
LED THE OPPOSITION TO DOING AWAY
WITH THE GLASS/STEAGALL
LEGISLATION.
UNFORTUNATELY, MY SIDE LOST.
WALL STREET BECAME DEREGULATED.
THE REST IS HISTORY.
WALL STREET HAS OPERATED IN A
VERY SIGNIFICANT WAY IN A
FRAUDULENT WAY.
AND, OBVIOUSLY, THEIR GREED AND
RECKLESSNESS HELPED DESTROY OUR
ECONOMY AND CREATE THE WORST
RECESSION SINCE THE GREAT
DEPRESSION.
I LED THE EFFORT AGAINST WALL
STREET DEREGULATION.
SEE WHERE HILLARY CLINTON WAS ON
THIS ISSUE.
IN TERMS OF CLIMATE CHANGE,
WHICH EVERYBODY HERE KNOWS AND
APPARENTLY EVERYBODY IN THE
WORLD KNOWS EXCEPT REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES FOR PRESIDENT, IS ONE
OF THE GREAT ENVIRONMENTAL
CRISES FACING THIS NATION.
ON DAY ONE, I SAID THE KEYSTONE
PIPELINE IS A DUMB IDEA.
>> SENATOR --
>> I THINK THE BALKAN PIPELINE
AND PIPELINES IN VERMONT AND NEW
HAMPSHIRE ARE DUMB.
WE'VE GOT TO BREAK OUR
DEPENDENCE ON FOSSIL FUEL.
WHY DID IT TAKE HILLARY CLINTON
SUCH A LONG TOIME BEFORE SHE CAE
INTO OPPOSITION TO THE KEYSTONE
PIPELINE.
TRADE POLICY.
I'VE UNDERSTOOD THAT OUR TRADE
POLICIES HAVE COST US.
NAFTA, CAFTA, MILLIONS OF DECENT
PAYING JOBS.
I DIDN'T HAVE TO THINK HARD
ABOUT OPPOSING THE TRANS-PACIFIC
PARTNERSHIP.
TOOK HILLARY CLINTON A LONG TIME
TO COME ON BOARD THAT.
>> SO --
>> IN OTHER WORDS, YEAH, I DO
THINK I HAVE THE BACKGROUND AND
THE JUDGMENT TO TAKE THIS VERY,
VERY DIFFICULT JOB OF BEING
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
>> ONE POINT OF PUSHBACK.
WE ARE IN THE FINAL STRETCH
HERE.
INTENSITY GETS HIGHER IN THE
FINAL STRETCH LIKE WE ARE NOW.
ON JANUARY 19th, YOU WERE
TALKING ABOUT HILLARY CLINTON'S
EXPERIENCE ARGUMENT AND REFERRED
TO DICK CHENEY.
YOU SAID HE HAD A LOT OF
EXPERIENCE, TOO.
NOW, REFERRING TO DICK CHENEY
WHEN TALKING ABOUT HILLARY
CLINTON, NOT EXACTLY THE MOST
HIGH BROW WAY TO CONDUCT THE
ELECTION.
>> MY ONLY POINT WAS SECRETARY
CLINTON WAS SECRETARY OF STATE
OF THIS COUNTRY FOR FOUR YEARS.
THAT IS A LOT OF EXPERIENCE.
THERE'S NO DEBATE ABOUT THAT.
I WAS NOT SECRETARY OF STATE.
BUT EXPERIENCE IS IMPORTANT, BUT
JUDGMENT IS ALSO IMPORTANT.
AND MY OWN POINT WAS IN TALKING
ABOUT DICK CHENEY, HE HAD A LOT
OF EXPERIENCE, TOO.
HIS POLICIES WITH REGARD TO
FOREIGN AFFAIRS WAS AN ABSOLUTE
DISASTER.
SO EXPERIENCE IS IMPORTANT, BUT
IT IS NOT THE ONLY THING.
AND I WOULD URGE PEOPLE TO CHECK
OUT MY VIEWS ON FOREIGN POLICY,
HOW WE DEAL WITH ISIS, AND I
THINK THEY'LL MAKE A LOT OF
SENSE TO THE PEOPLE OF IOWA AND
THE PEOPLE OF OUR COUNTRY.
>> LEASE GET A QUESTION.
CARRIE CRAWFORD SAYS SHE'S
UNDECIDED.
MOTHER OF THREE GROWN KIDS.
WHAT IS YOUR QUESTION?
>> HELLO, SENATOR SANDERS.
IN LIGHT OF THE RECENT MASS
SHOOTINGS, I'M INTERESTED TO
KNOW HOW YOU ARE GOING TO MAKE
INROADS WITH THE POWERFUL GUN
LOBBY TO ESTABLISH MORE
EFFECTIVE GUN CONTROL
LEGISLATION?
AND THE SECOND PART OF MY
QUESTION IS, HOW WILL YOU
SUPPORT EASIER ACCESS TO MENTAL
HEALTH CARE IN CLINICS?
>> GOOD.
EXCELLENT QUESTIONS.
NOW I HAVE BEEN ATTACKED.
IN FACT, THIS IS AN ISSUE THAT
HILLARY CLINTON HAS, YOU KNOW,
FOCUSED ON, AND THAT'S POLITICS,
AND THAT'S FINE.
ALTHOUGH SOME OF YOU MIGHT
RECALL THAT BACK IN 2007 WHEN
SHE WAS RUNNING AGAINST BARACK
OBAMA, SHE ALSO FOCUSED ON THAT
ISSUE BUT THOUGHT THAT OBAMA WAS
TOO STRONG ON GUN ISSUES.
YOU MAY REMEMBER HIM REFERRING
TO HER AS ANNIE OAKLEY.
ALL RIGHT?
TODAY, HILLARY CLINTON IS
RUNNING A LOT OF ADVERTISEMENTS
ON GUN ISSUES.
INTERESTINGLY ENOUGH, SHE'S
RUNNING MOST OF THEM IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE WHERE SHE THINKS IT
WILL WORK, NOT RUNNING SO MANY
OF THEM IN RURAL IOWA.
YOU CAN FORM YOUR OWN JUDGMENT
AS TO WHY THAT IS THE CASE.
BUT TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, IN
1988, I RAN VERMONT'S LONE SEAT
IN THE U.S. HOUSE OF
REPRESENTATIVES.
I RAN AS AN INDEPENDENT AGAINST
A DEMOCRAT AND REPUBLICAN.
THE GUN LOBBY SAID VOTE FOR
EITHER THE DEMOCRAT OR
REPUBLICAN.
DON'T VOTE FOR BERNIE SANDERS.
THIS IS 1988.
BECAUSE BERNIE THINKS THAT WE
SHOULD NOT BE SELLING MILITARY
STYLE ASSAULT WEAPONS IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
BACK IN 1988.
I LOST THAT ELECTION BY THREE
PERCENTAGE POINTS.
I CANNOT TELL YOU THAT THAT IS
THE ONLY REASON, BUT I HAD THE
GUN GROUPS WORKING AGAINST THE
BACK THEN.
SINCE THEN, I HAVE SUPPORTED
INSTANT BACKGROUND CHECKS, THE
EXPANSION OF INSTANT BACKGROUND
CHECKS BECAUSE I BELIEVE OUR
JOB, IF WE'RE GOING TO END THESE
HORRIFIC MASS MURDERS, OR AT
LEAST HAVE SOME IMPACT IN
LESSENING THE OCCURRENCE OF
THEM, WE HAVE GOT TO DO OUR BEST
TO MAKE SURE THAT GUNS DO NOT
GET INTO THE HANDS OF PEOPLE WHO
SHOULD NOT HAVE THEM.
CRIMINALS, PEOPLE WITH MENTAL
INSTABILITY.
I BELIEVE, AS PRESIDENT OBAMA
DOES THAT WE'VE GOT TO DEAL WITH
THE GUN SHOW LOOPHOLE.
AND THAT'S WHAT HE'S WORKING ON
WITH HIS EXECUTIVE ORDER.
PEOPLE SHOULD NOT BE ABLE TO
CIRCUMVENT THE INSTANT
BACKGROUND CHECK THROUGH THE GUN
SHOW OR THROUGH THE INTERNET.
I BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD MAKE A
FEDERAL CRIME OF THE SO-CALLED
STRAW MAN SITUATION WHERE PEOPLE
ARE BUYING GUNS LEGALLY, GOING
THROUGH THE INSTANT BACKGROUND
CHECK AND THEN SELLING THEM TO
CRIMINALS.
>> ADDRESS YOUR SHIFT ON
MANUFACTURERS AND LIABILITY.
TELL THEM WHERE YOU WERE 50FIRS.
>> I VOTED FOR THE BILL.
THE REASON I VOTED FOR THE BILL,
A BILL WHICH HAS A NUMBER OF
ELEMENTS IN IT.
AMONG OTHER THINGS IT HAS A
SECTION WHICH SAYS WE SHOULD NOT
BE SELLING AMMUNITION WHICH WILL
PIERCE POLICEMAN'S ARMOR AND
PROTECTION.
I THINK THAT'S THE RIGHT THING.
AND ONE THAT SAID WE WANT TO
HAVE SAFETY LOCKS FOR CHILDREN
ON GUNS.
THAT MAKES SENSE TO ME.
IT ALSO HAD A PROVISION IN IT
WHICH SAYS THE FOLLOWING, AND
PEOPLE MAY DISAGREE WITH ME.
THIS IS MY VIEW.
IF YOU ARE A SMALL GUN SHOP IN
VERMONT AND I LEGALLY SELL YOU A
WEAPON, OKAY, YOU GO OUT, BUY
THAT GUN LEGALLY AND YOU GO OUT
AND KILL SOMEBODY.
I THINK THE GUN SHOP OWNER
SHOULD NOT BE HELD LIABLE FOR
YOUR CRIMINAL ACT.
THAT'S WHAT I BELIEVE.
NOW WITHIN THAT BILL ALSO, THERE
WAS SOME ONEROUS PROVISIONS.
NOT GOOD PROVISIONS.
WHAT HAPPENS IF A GUN
MANUFACTURER IS SELLING A WHOLE
LOT OF GUNS INTO AN AREA FAR
MORE GUNS THAN THAT AREA CAN
CONSUME?
AND WHAT HAPPENS IF THAT GUN
OWNER, THAT GUN MANUFACTURER
SHOULD KNOW THAT THOSE GUNS ARE
GOING INTO CRIMINAL HANDS.
SHOULD THAT GUN MANUFACTURER BE
HELD LIABLE?
YES, HE SHOULD.
SO I AM WILLING NOW TO LOOK AT
THAT LEGISLATION, MAINTAIN WHAT
WAS GOOD IN IT, GET RID OF WHAT
IS BAD IN IT.
>> BUT ISN'T THAT HAVING IT BOTH
WAYS?
EITHER THEY HAVE LIABILITY AS A
MANUFACTURER OR THEY DON'T.
THE FIRST ARGUMENT SEEMS TO MAKE
SENSE.
WHY WOULD THEY BE EXPOSED TO
LIABILITY.
WHY HAVING IT BOTH WAYS?
>> IF YOU ARE A SMALL GUN SHOP
OWNER AND SELL SOMEONE A GUN,
LEGALLY, YOU DON'T DO ANYTHING
WRONG.
YOU SELL GUNS.
SOMEBODY BUYS THE GUN AND GOES
OUT AND KILLS SOMEBODY, DO I
THINK THAT GUN SHOP OWNER SHOULD
BE HELD LIABLE?
I DON'T.
>> WHAT'S THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
SELLING ONE OR SELLING 1,000.
>> BUT HERE'S THE POINT.
IF A GUN SHOP OWNER SHOULD KNOW,
WHY SHOULD SOMEBODY BE BUYING
1,000 GUNS, SOMEBODY SHOULD BE
THINKING THAT DOES NOT MAKE A
LOT OF SENSE.
IN THAT CASE, THAT GUN SHOP
OWNER OR THE GUN MANUFACTURER
SHOULD BE HELD LIABLE.
OKAY?
AND THAT'S THE ISSUE.
NOW YOU'RE ASKING ALSO ABOUT
MENTAL HEALTH.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT HEALTH CARE
FOR ALL, I ABSOLUTELY INCLUDE IN
THAT THE FACT THAT MENTAL HEALTH
SHOULD BE TREATED AS PART OF
HEALTH CARE.
SHOULD BE AVAILABLE TO ALL
PEOPLE.
I GET CALLS -- I HAVE GOTTEN
CALLS IN MY OFFICE, AND I'M SURE
OTHER SENATORS HAVE AS WELL.
THIS IS THE CALL.
SOMEBODY CALLS US UP AND SAYS
I'M VERY WORRIED ABOUT MY
BROTHER.
I'M WORRIED WHAT HE MIGHT DO TO
HIMSELF OR, TO ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION, TO SOMEBODY ELSE.
HE MAY BE HOMICIDE OL.
HE MAY BE SUICIDAL.
WE HAVE SEARCHED DESPERATELY TO
FIND HEALTH CARE -- MENTAL
HEALTH TREATMENT FOR HIM.
WE CANNOT FIND MENTAL HEALTH
TREATMENT WHICH IS AFFORDABLE,
WHICH IS ACCESSIBLE.
IN MY VIEW, WE HAVE GOT TO MOVE
IN THE DIRECTION OF MAKING SURE
THAT EVERYBODY IN THIS COUNTRY
WHO HAS A MENTAL HEALTH CRISIS
GETS HEALTH CARE WHEN THEY NEED
IT, NOT TWO MONTHS FROM TODAY.
>> CARRIE, HOW DO YOU FEEL ABOUT
THE ANSWER?
>> I LIKE THE ANSWER.
THAT'S SUFFICIENT.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> HAVE A SEAT, SENATOR.
I'M TIRED FOLLOWING YOU AROUND
THERE.
>> YOU FOLLOW ME AROUND TODAY,
YOU'D BE A LOT MORE TIRED.
>> "CNN TODAY," YOUR BROTHER WAS
ON.
GAVE A GREAT INTERVIEW.
HE SAID BACK IN THE DAY YOU WERE
A GREAT ATHLETE.
IS THAT TRUE, AND WHAT WAS THE
SPORT?
I'M NOT SAYING I DON'T BELIEVE
IT TO BE TRUE.
IS IT TRUE AND WHAT WAS THE
SPORT?
>> YOU KNOW FAMILIES EXAGGERATE
A LITTLE BIT.
I WAS A VERY GOOD ATHLETE.
I WOULDN'T SAY GRADUATE.
PRETTY GOOD BASKETBALL PLAYER.
MY ELEMENTARY SCHOOL IN BROOKLYN
WON THE BOROUGH CHAMPIONSHIP.
HARDLY WORTH MENTIONING, BUT WE
DID, YES.
AND, YES, I DID TAKE THIRD PLACE
IN THE NEW YORK CITY INDOOR ONE
MILE RACE.
OKAY, WELL, YOU KNOW, I -- I WAS
A VERY GOOD LONG-DISTANCE
RUNNER.
NOT A GREAT RUNNER, BUT CAPTAIN
OF MY TRACK TEAM AND WON A
NUMBER OF CROSS-COUNTRY MEETS
AND WON A WHOLE LOT OF RACES.
GOOD, VERY GOOD, NOT GREAT.
>> NOW THIS IS WHAT THEY CALL A
BAIT AND SWITCH.
I DON'T REALLY CARE ABOUT YOUR
ATHLETIC --
IF YOU WERE ELECTED PRESIDENT,
YOU ARE 75 NOW.
>> 74.
>> 74 GOING ON 75.
YOU ARE CLOSE TO 75.
>> I'M GOING ON 75.
SO ARE YOU.
>> THAT'S TRUE.
THAT'S TRUE.
YOU WOULD BE THE OLDEST PERSON
ELECTED PRESIDENT.
YOU HAVE MEDICAL RECORDS.
YOU SAY YOU'RE GOING TO RELEASE
THEM.
SHOULD YOU RELEASE THEM TO BE
FAIR TO THE VOTERS OF IOWA
BEFORE THEY VOTE?
>> WHERE ARE THEY?
ON OUR TABLE RIGHT NOW?
ALL RIGHT.
WE WILL RELEASE THEM.
THAT'S MY WIFE.
YES, OF COURSE, WE'LL RELEASE
THEM.
>> BEFORE IOWA?
>> YEAH, SURE.
AND I AM -- IF THERE'S WOOD
HERE, I WOULD KNOCK ON IT.
>> MY HEAD IS CLOSE ENOUGH.
>> I HAVE BEEN BLESSED WITH GOOD
HEALTH AND GOOD ENDURANCE, AND
THERE'S NOTHING IN THE MEDICAL
RECORDS THAT IS GOING TO
SURPRISE ANYBODY AND WE'LL GET
THEM OUT AS SOON AS POSSIBLE.
>> THANK YOU FOR CLAARIFYING
THAT.
SOMETHING ELSE YOUR BROTHER
SAID.
HE GOT EMOTIONAL.
HE WAS SAYING, BOY, WOULD OUR
PARENTS BE PROUD OF THE SUCCESS
THAT BERNIE HAS HAD.
YOU HAVE TO THINK ABOUT THAT AS
WELL.
WHEN YOU THINK ABOUT WHY YOU ARE
DOING THIS AND WHAT IT MEANS,
WHAT DOES IT MEAN TO YOU ABOUT
WHAT YOUR PARENTS WOULD THINK IF
THEY SAW YOU NOW?
>> THAT THEY WOULDN'T BELIEVE
IT.
WE GREW UP -- MY DAD CAME FROM
POLAND AT THE AGE OF 17 WITHOUT
A NICKEL IN HIS POCKET.
COULDN'T SPEAK ENGLISH AND NEVER
MADE A WHOLE LOT OF MONEY.
MY BROTHER AND I AND MOM AND DAD
GREW UP IN A 3 1/2-ROOM
RENT-CONTROLLED APARTMENT IN
BROOKLYN, NEW YORK.
AND WE NEVER HAD A WHOLE LOT OF
MONEY.
AND IF YOU ASK ME, CHRIS, THIS
WOULD BE SO UNIMAGINABLE, THE
FACT THAT I'M A UNITED STATES
SENATOR WOULD HAVE BEEN REALLY
BEYOND ANYTHING THAT THEY WOULD
HAVE THOUGHT POSSIBLE.
THE FACT THAT I AM RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES,
YOU KNOW, I DO THINK ABOUT IT.
AND I THINK THEY ARE VERY PROUD,
BUT IT'S CERTAINLY SOMETHING
THAT I DON'T THINK THEY EVER
BELIEVED WOULD HAVE HAPPENED.
>> YOU GOT 30 SECONDS.
TELL THE VOTERS OF IOWA WHAT YOU
WANT THEM TO KNOW.
>> LOOK.
HILLARY CLINTON IS A VERY GOOD
PERSON.
MARTIN O'MALLEY IS A DECENT GUY.
THIS IS NOT A PERSONAL STUFF.
IT JUST SEEMS TO ME THAT THE
CRISES THAT WE FACE AS A COUNTRY
TODAY -- AND WE DIDN'T EVEN GET
INTO CLIMATE CHANGE TO A
SIGNIFICANT DEGREE --
INEQUALITY, POVERTY IN AMERICA.
AN OBSCENE AND UNFAIR CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM.
THESE PROBLEMS ARE SO SERIOUS
THAT WE HAVE GOT TO GO BEYOND
ESTABLISHMENT POLITICS AND
ESTABLISHMENT ECONOMICS.
IN MY VIEW, WE NEED A POLITICAL
REVOLUTION WHERE MILLIONS OF
PEOPLE STAND UP AND SAY, YOU
KNOW WHAT?
THAT GREAT GOVERNENT OF OURS
BELONGS TO ALL OF US, NOT JUST
THE FEW.
THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT.
THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU
FOR TAKING THE OPPORTUNITY.
GOOD LUCK TO YOU IN THE IOWA
CAUCUSES NEXT WEEK.
>>> ALL RIGHT.
OUR THANKS TO SENATOR SANDERS.
COMING UP, HILLARY CLINTON AND
MARTIN O'MALLEY GET THEIR TURNS
ON STAGE.
AND OUR AUDIENCE OF IOWA VOTERS
IS READY WITH A NEW SLATE OF
QUESTIONS.
STAY WITH US.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL HERE AT DRAKE UNIVERSITY IN
DES MOINES, IOWA.
THIS IS THE LAST, BEST CHANCE
FOR THE CANDIDATES TO FACE IOWA
VOTERS, AND ANSWER THEIR
QUESTIONS DIRECTLY BEFORE THEY
CAUCUS NEXT MONDAY.
NOW, WE'VE HEARD FROM SENATOR
SANDERS, IN A BIT SECRETARY
CLINTON, BUT RIGHT NOW, THE
FLOOR BELONGS TO FORMER MARYLAND
GOVERNOR, MARTIN O'MALLEY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HEY.
CHRIS, HOW ARE YOU?
GOOD TO SEE YOU TOO, MAN.
THANKS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THANKS A LOT.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> HOW ARE YOU FEELING A WEEK
OUT?
>> I'M EXCITED.
IT'S IOWA CAUCUS TIME, AND
CHRIS, I'VE SEEN THIS BEFORE.
ONCE IOWANS GET INTO THAT
DECISION-MAKING POCKET, NONE OF
THE POLLSTERS BACK EAST CAN TELL
YOU HOW IT'S GOING TO TURN OUT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I WISH YOU COULD BE OUT
THERE WITH ME.
I HAVE BEEN CAMPAIGNING THE IOWA
CAUCUS, I'VE BEEN TO OVER 120
EVENTS AND GETTING UP ON THE
CHAIR, DOING TOWN HALLS LIKE
THIS.
AND WE'RE SEEING LARGER AND
LARGE EARL CROWDS.
AND THE BEAUTY OF THE PEOPLE OF
IOWA IS, THEY'RE NOT INTIMIDATED
BY POLLS.
THEY'RE NOT INTIMIDATED BY
PUNDITS, AND THEY HAVE THIS
BIRTHRIGHT, THEY FEEL, TO UPSET
THE APPLE CART.
AND WITH ONLY THREE OF US IN
THIS DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY, THERE'S
ONLY ONE OF US WHO CAN STILL
UPSET THE APPLE CART.
COME ON NOW.
>> THE DES MOINES REGISTER, THEY
GAVE THE NOMINATION THEIR
ENDORSEMENT TO SECRETARY
CLINTON.
OKAY.
THEY GIVE THEIR ENDORSEMENT TO
HER.
IN IT THEY TALK ABOUT YOU ARE
BETTER SUIT Z AS CABINET
SECRETARY THAN AS PRESIDENT.
WHAT DO YOU WANT TO SAY TO
IOWANS TO PROVE THAT THEIR
BIGGEST PAPER IS WRONG?
>> WELL, THIS IS WHAT I HAVE TO
SAY.
LOOK, I'M IN THIS CHRIS, TO WIN
THIS.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
AND THE REASON I'M RUNNING IS
THIS.
OUR COUNTRY IS FACING BIG
CHALLENGES.
AND WE HAVE DEEP DIVISIONS IN
OUR COUNTRY.
AND WE NEED A CANDIDATE WHO CAN
ACTUALLY PULL US TOGETHER.
WHO CAN HEAL THESE DIVISIONS,
WHO CAN GET THINGS DONE.
THAT'S WHAT OOIFZ DONE ALL MY
LIFE.
I'M NOT A DIVIDER.
IF I WERE, I WOULD NOT HAVE BEEN
ABLE TO ACCOMPLISH THE THINGS WE
ACCOMPLISH IN A VERY TROUBLED
CITY OR IN OUR STATE THROUGH A
RECESSION.
AND THAT'S WHAT I BELIEVE THE
PEOPLE OF IOWA ARE LOOKING FOR.
A PRESIDENT WHO WILL MOVE US
FORWARD.
WHO WILL BUILD ON THE GOOD
THINGS THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS
DONE, AND ACTUALLY TAKE THAT JOB
CREATION LEGACY AND TURN IT INTO
RI
RISING WAGES AGAIN FOR EVERY
AMERICAN FAMILY.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED.
AND WE NEED NEW LEADERSHIP TO DO
THAT AND BREAK THROUGH THE
GRIDLOCK OF WASHINGTON.
>> YOU MENTION PRESIDENT OBAMA,
HE WAS SPEAKING THIS MORNING
ABOUT THE ELECTION MORE DEEPLY
THAN IN THE PAST.
HE WAS DON AN ANALYSIS OF
SECRETARY CLINTON AND SENATOR
SANDERS.
HE DESCRIBED THE SENATOR AS A
FASCINATION OF PEOPLE.
I THOUGHT YOU WERE SUPPOSED TO
BE THE BRIGHT, SHINY NEW OBJECT
IN THIS?
WHAT HAPPENED?
>> I'M HONORED TO BE ABLE TO
OFFER MY CANDIDACY IN THE
COMPANY OF SECRETARY CLINTON AND
SENATOR SANDERS.
IF YOU LOOK AT OUR DEMOCRATIC
PRIMARY AND THE DEBATES WE'VE
HAD, WE'RE CERTAINLY DOING A
MUCH BETTER JOB TO SPEAKING TO
THE GOODNESS IN OUR COUNTRY THAN
TO FEAR, ANGER, AND LOATHING IN
THE OTHER GUYS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> ARE YOU READY TO TAKE YOUR
CASE TO THE PEOPLE?
LET'S TAKE A QUESTION.
SHE'S ORIGINALLY FROM ST. LOUIS.
HER PARENTS WORK IN FERGUSON.
SHE'S UNDECIDED.
WHAT'S YOUR QUESTION FOR THE
GOVERNOR?
>> Q & A TIME, AM I ALLOWED TO
SOUND?
>> I'M NOT CAPABLE OF DOING Q &
A IN IOWA FROM A SEAT.
>> IT'S FINE.
>> GOOD EVENING.
>> HI.
>> YOUR HISTORY AS MAYOR OF
BALTIMORE AND GOVERNOR OF
MARYLAND SHOW THAT YOU PUSH FOR
ZERO TOLERANCE POLICING AND
FELONY PUNISHMENTS FOR LOW LEVEL
DRUG OFFENDERS WHICH AFFECTS THE
BLOCK POPULATION.
HOW CAN YOU ENSURE RACIAL
EQUALITY WHEN YOUR HISTORY IS
NOT FIGHTING STRUCTURAL RACISM?
>> SURE.
WELL LOOK, LET'S TALK ABOUT
THIS.
IN 1999, OUR CITY OF BALTIMORE
HAD BECOME THE MOST VIOLENT, THE
MOST ADDICTED, AND THE MOST
ABANDONED CITY IN AMERICA.
AND WHEN VERY FEW OTHER PEOPLE
WOULD STEP UP WHO COULD BRING US
TOGETHER AND TURN IT AROUND, I
DID.
AND THAT YEAR, AND FOR ABOUT THE
12 YEARS LEADING UP TO THAT
POINT, WE WERE BURYING OVER 300
YOUNG, POOR, BLACK MEN EVERY
SINGLE YEAR.
AND YES, BLACK LIVES MATTER, AND
I TOLD THE PEOPLE OF MY CITY,
LOOK, WE DO NOT HAVE TO ACCEPT A
REALITY OF 24/7 DRUG DEALER
OCCUPATION OVER OUR POOR
NEIGHBORHOOD.
WHEN YOU CALL FROM A POOR
NEIGHBORHOOD FOR POLICE SERVICE,
THEY SHOULD RESPOND THE SAME WAY
THAT THEY DO IN WEALTHIER
NEIGHBORHOODS, BLACK AND WHITE.
THERE ARE A LOT OF THINGS WE GOT
RIGHT.
THERE WERE A LOT OF LIVES THAT
WE SAVED.
I PROMISE TO IMPROVE HOW WE
POLICE THE POLICE.
WE ACTUALLY DID START CLOSING
DOWN OPEN AIR DRUG MARKETS, AND
IN THE COURSE OF MY EXECUTIVE
SERVICE, BOTH AS MAYOR AND AS A
GOVERNOR, I NEVER STOP SEARCHING
FOR THE THINGS THAT WORK SO WE
CAN DO MORE OF THEM TO SAVE AND
REDEEM LIVES, AND THE THINGS
THAT DON'T WORK SO WE CAN STOP
DOING THEM.
SOP WE GREATLY INCREASE DRUG
TREATMENT.
WE SAVED HUNDREDS AND HUNDREDS
OF LIVES FROM OVERDOSE DEATHS.
WE STARTED TRACKING DISCOURTESY,
EXCESSIVE FORCE.
I DROVE DOWN USE OF FATAL
POLICE-TO THREE OF THEIR FOUR
LOWEST YEARS IN BALTIMORE HISRY.
>> AND AS GOVERNOR, I RESTORED
VOTING RIGHTS TO 52,000 PEOPLE.
I REPEALED, AS A CRIME, A
DECRIMINALIZED THE POSSESSION OF
MARIJUANA.
I BANNED THE BOX ON PEOPLE WHO
ARE IMPLYING FOR STATE
EMPLOYMENT, AND --
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND NOT THE FIRST TIME, NOT THE
SECOND TIME, BUT THE THIRD TIME,
BY BRINGING PEOPLE TOGETHER,
INCLUDING A FEW REPUBLICAN
VOTES, I MADE MY STATE THE FIRST
STATE SOUTH OF THE MASON DIXON
LINE TO REPEAL THE DEATH PENALTY
IN AMERICA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SO --
>> GOVERNOR.
>> IT'S HARD TO APPRECIATE AT
THE TIME, BUT, ONE TRUE STORY,
QUICKLY, CHRIS.
>> ALL RIGHT.
>> THERE IS A FAMILY OF SEVEN
PEOPLE.
A MOM, DAD, AND FIVE KIDS.
WHO IN EAST BALTIMORE WERE
FIRE-BOMBED IN THEIR SLEEP AND
KILLED BY A DRUG DEALER.
AND THE REASON, BECAUSE THEY
WERE PICKING UP THE PHONE AND
CALLING 911 AND ASKING FOR
RELIEF FOR THEIR KIDS FROM THIS
SORT OF 24/7 DRUG DEALER
OCCUPATION.
LOOK, I THINK ALL OF US HAVE A
RESPONSIBILITY, I KNOW I FEEL A
RESPONSIBILITY TO CONSTANTLY
LOOK FOR THE THINGS THAT WORK
AND THE THINGS THAT DON'T WORK.
BY THE END OF MY TIME AS
GOVERNOR, WE DRIVEN DOWN VIOLENT
CRIME TO A 30-YEAR LOW, AND WE
HAD ALSO DRIVEN DOWN OUR
INCARCERATION RATE TO A 20-YEAR
LOW.
YOU CAN DO BOTH OF THEM AT THE
SAME TIME BY DOING GOOD THINGS
AT WORK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> NEXT QUESTION, DAN, OWNS TWO
SMALL BUSINESSES IN DES MOINES.
HE'S LEARNING TOWARDS BERNIE
SANDERS, HE HAS A QUESTION, WHAT
IS IT?
>> HELLO, QUESTION, I'M A SMALL
BUSINESS OWNER --
>> TELL ME YOUR NAME AGAIN.
>> DANIEL.
>> AND YOU KNOW, YOU RUN THE
NUMBERS AND YOU TRY TO FIGURE
OUT OKAY, AT THE END OF THE DAY
WHEN YOU'RE SPENDING AS MUCH ON
YOUR HEALTH CARE EVERY MONTH AS
YOU DO YOUR MORTGAGE, WHAT WAYS
WOULD YOU CHOOSE TO TRY TO
LESSEN THAT BURDEN ON THE MIDDLE
CLASS AND, YOU KNOW, SMALL
BUSINESS OWNERS LIKE MYSELF?
>> YEAH.
LOOK, I THINK WE NEED TO BUILD
UPON THE GOOD THINGS THAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS DONE WITH
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
AND -- BUT NO PROGRAM EVER CAME
INTO EXISTENCE IN A PERFECT
CONDITION.
SOP WE HAVE TO IMPROVE IT.
ONE OF THE WAYS I THINK WE NEED
TO IMPROVE IT IS BY COVERING THE
HIGH-VALUE, SORT OF EARLY, OUT
OF POCKET EXPENSES THAT PEOPLE
ARE EXPERIENCING.
WHAT I HEAR FROM FOLKS ALL OVER
IOWA IS MA MAYBE WHILE THEIR
PREMIUMS LEVELLED OFF, THEY'RE
PAYING MORE OUT OF POCKET AND
DEDUCTIBLES ARE HIGHER.
SOP WE NEED TO, WE NEED TO PUSH
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES TO
ACTUALLY OFFER, OFFER PRODUCTS
THAT PAY FOR THOSE EARLY, THOSE
FIRST OUT OF POCKET EXPENSES,
BUT LET ME TAKE YOU UP TO A
SLIGHTLY LARGER AND HIGHER
LEVEL, AND IT IS THIS.
LOOK, WE NEED TO, WE NEED TO
CHANGE WHAT IT IS THAT WE
ACTUALLY PAY FOR TO PUT WILLNESS
AT THE CENTER.
IN MY OWN STATE, WE MOVED ALL 46
OF OUR ACUTE CARE HOSPITALS OUT
OF FEE FOR SERVICE AND STARTED
PAYING THEM GLOBAL PAYMENT FOR
ALL OF THEIR MEDICARE AND
MEDICAID PATIENTS.
WHY?
BECAUSE THE BIGGEST DRIVER OF
YOUR HIGH HEALTH INSURANCE COSTS
AND THROUGHOUT OUR COUNTRY IS
THE HOSPITAL COST AT THE CENTER.
AND WE TOLD OUR HOSPITALS THAT
IF YOU REDUCE AVOIDABLE HOSPITAL
REEMISSIONS, YOU CAN SHARE IN
THOSE SAVINGS.
AND THE NEW ENGLAND JOURNAL OF
MEDICINE DID AN ARTICLE ABOUT
FOUR WEEKS AGO AND SAID, I'LL BE
DAMNED, IT ACTUALLY WORKED, WE
CAN DIAL UP WELLNESS, REDUCE THE
EXPENSE HERE, AND THAT'S THE
FUTURE, I BELIEVE, AND EVERY
STATE HAS A ROLE TO PLAY IN
MOVING THAT WAY BECAUSE CLEARLY
WE'RE STILL PAYING TOO MUCH FOR
HEALTH INSURANCE.
OUR SYSTEMS CALLED ON ALL PAYER
SYSTEM.
WE HAVE A RATE SETTING
COMMISSION, AND WE'RE ABLE TO
REPLACE THE INSTITUTIONAL
PROFITABILITY, I MEAN THE
HOSPITALS AREN'T GOING BANKRUPT
BY ANY MEANS, BUT WE'RE ABLE TO
PUT WELLNESS AT THE CENTER.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO AS A
COUNTRY TO BRING DOWN THE HIGH
COST OF HEALTH CARE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU, DANIEL.
ANOTHER QUESTION FOR YOU.
JENNA BISHOP, DRAKE UNIVERSITY,
SHE'S UNDECIDED ON WHAT
CANDIDATE SHE'S SUPPORTING AND
SHE HAS A QUESTION ABOUT YOUNG
VOTERS FOR YOU.
>> IT'S STILL EARLY, THERE'S SIX
DAYS.
>> HI GOVERNOR.
I'M 23 YEARS OLD.
AND I CARE ABOUT A LOT OF
ISSUES, OTHER THAN JUST THE COST
OF COLLEGE.
I'D LIKE TO KNOW WHAT ISSUE YOU
THINK SHOULD BE MOST IMPORTANT
TO YOUNG VOTERS AND WHY.
>> THANK YOU.
GREAT QUESTION.
I HAVE PUT FORWARD A PLAN FOR
DEAD-FREE COLLEGE WITHIN THE
NEXT FIVE YEARS, AND AS THE ONE
CANDIDATE AMONG THE THREE OF US
WITH 15 YEARS OF EXECUTIVE
EXPERIENCE, WE WENT FOUR YEARS
IN A ROW IN MY STATE WITHOUT A
PENNY'S INCREASE TO COLLEGE
TUITION SO YOU CAN CHECK OUT MY
PLAN FOR THAT ON MY WEBSITE,
MARTINOMALLEY.COM.
YOU KNOW WHAT I BELIEVE IS THE
BIGGEST ISSUE YOU SHOULD BE
CONCERNED ABOUT AS A YOUNG
PERSON WHO HAS MORE TIME ON THIS
PLANET THAN I DO, AND THAT IS
CLIMATE CHANGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
CLIMATE CHANGE IS THE GREATEST
BUSINESS OPPORTUNITY TO COME TO
THE UNITED STATES IN 100 YEARS.
AND I AM THE FIRST CANDIDATE IN
EITHER PARTY TO PUT FORWARD A
PLAN TO MOVE US TO A 100% CLEAN,
ELECTRIC ENERGY GRID BY 2050,
AND CREATE FIVE MILLION JOBS
ALONG THE WAY.
AND THIS IS ANOTHER ONE OF THOSE
INSTANCES, CHRIS, WHERE IOWA IS
POINTING THE WAY FORWARD.
LOOK AT WHAT YOU HAVE ALREADY
DONE IN YOUR STATE.
30 TO 35% OF YOUR ENERGY NOW
COMES FROM CLEAN, IOWA WIND.
WHICH WASN'T THERE 15 YEARS AGO.
AND YOU EMPLOY 5,000 PEOPLE IN
THE NEW INDUSTRY, AND THE GREAT
THING ABOUT THOSE BIG COMPONENT
PARTS YOU SEE RUMBLING DOWN THE
HIGHWAY ON I-80 IS YOU'RE TOO
DARN BIG TO MAKE SENSE TO IMPORT
THEM FROM OTHER COUNTRIES.
SO YOU HAVE TO BUILD THOSE HERE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND IT'S A BIG, AND IT'S A BIG
DIFFERENTIATOR AMONG THE THREE
OF US.
AND WE'RE ALL, WE'RE ALL DECENT
PEOPLE, WE ALL WANT TO DO THE
RIGHT THING FOR OUR PLANET, BUT
THERE IS A GENERATIONAL
PERSPECTIVE HERE, AND WE'RE NOT
GOING TO GET TO 100% CLEAN,
ELECTRIC GRID WITH ALL OF THE
ABOVE STRATEGY MORE THAN THE
MOON WITH ALL OF THE ABOVE
STRATEGY.
IT WAS AN ENGINEERING CHALLENGE
AND WE ARE UP TOP THIS AS
AMERICANS.
INCREMENTALISM, HALF STEPS,
SPLITTING THE LOAF, THAT'S NOT
GOING TO GET US.
AND THAT'S NOT WHAT YOUR
GENERATION WANTS, YOU WANT THE
STRAIGHT TRUTH AND FACE OUR
CHALLENGES FEARLESSLY AND MAKE
THIS NEW REALITY OURS.
>> WHAT WORKS FOR YOU, YOU LIKE
THE ANSWER?
>> I THINK THAT'S GREAT.
I THINK THE ENVIRONMENT'S HUGE,
OBVIOUSLY, ESPECIALLY FOR THOSE
OF US THAT ARE GOING TO BE
LIVING A LOT OF YEARS,
HOPEFULLY.
SO THANKS.
>> HOPEFULLY WE'LL STILL BE
THERE.
>> ARNOLD WOODS, HE IS THE
PRESIDENT OF THE DES MOINES
NAACP, AIR FORCE VETERAN IN
VIETNAM AND UNDECIDED.
YOUR QUESTION, SIR.
>> YES, I AM UNDECIDED.
AND QUESTION I HAVE IS BECAUSE
OF THE EXTREME NUMBER OF OUR
MILITARY PERSONNEL RETURNING
FROM WAR ZONES, COMBAT ZONES
WITH PTSD, WHAT IS YOUR FEELING
TOWARD REESTABLISHING THE
MILITARY DRAFT?
AND FOR THOSE WHO ARE NOT DEEMED
WORTHY TO GO TO MILITARY DRAFT
OR TO BE DRAFTED INTO THE
MILITARY, DO YOU HAVE ANY
OPTIONS FOR THEM WHERE THEY CAN
SERVE OUR COUNTRY ZPR A COUPLE
YEARS, PRIOR TO GOING TO
COLLEGE?
>> HEY, THANK YOU.
I HAVE PUT FORWARD IN YOUR STATE
15 STRATEGIC GOALS TO MOVE OUR
COUNTRY FORWARD AGAIN.
TO REBUILD THE TRUTH OF THE
AMERICAN DREAM TO GET WAGES TO
GO UP, TO MAKE COLLEGE MORE
AFFORDABLE AND DEBT-FREE WITHIN
THE NEXT FIVE YEARS.
CUT DRUG OVERDOSES IN HALF IN
THE NEXT TEN YEARS, GUN DEBTS IN
HALF IN THE NEXT TEN YEARS, BUT
ONE OF THE GOALS IS TO CUT YOUTH
UNEMPLOYMENT IN HALF IN THE NEXT
THREE YEARS.
AND I PROPOSED TO DO THAT BY
MAKING NATIONAL SERVICE A
UNIVERSAL OPTION FOR EVERY KID
IN AMERICA TO SERVE THEIR
COUNTRY IN ENVIRONMENTAL
RESTORATION OR IN PUBLIC HEALTH
OR OTHER AVENUES IN ADDITION TO
THE MILITARY.
AND I BELIEVE THAT THAT WILL NOT
ONLY ALLOW OUR KIDS TO GO TO
COLLEGE IN A MORE AFFORDABLE
WAY, GIVING THEM AN INCREASED
PELL GRANT BENEFIT, BUT I KNOW
IT'LL DO A GREAT DEAL TO TAP
THAT GOODNESS WITHIN THE NEXT
GENERATION.
AND BRING IT FORWARD.
BRING THEIR ETHIC FORWARD.
LET ME TALK ABOUT VETERANS
BECAUSE ANOTHER ONE OF OUR, MY
STRATEGIC GOALS IS TO FULL
EMPLOYMENT FOR THE VETERANS OF
OURS WHO COME HOME FROM IRAQ AND
AFGHANISTAN.
WE DO A VERY POOR JOB OF
TRANSITIONING OUR VETERANS BACK
TO CIVILIAN LIFE.
AND I HAVE FOUND, AS A GOVERNOR,
ATTACKING THIS PROBLEM, THAT THE
KEY IS, EMPLOYMENT.
TALKING TO OUR VETERANS ABOUT
EMPLOYMENT.
THERE IS ABSOLUTELY NO HAND-OFF
BETWEEN THE DEFENSE DEPARTMENT
AND VETERANS AFFAIRS, LET ALONE
OUR STATE DEPARTMENTS OF
VETERAN'S AFFAIRS.
AND IN FACT, ON THE DD-214 THE
DISCHARGE FORM THAT VETERANS
FILL OUT.
THERE'S NOT EVEN A BOX FOR AN
E-MAIL ADDRESS.
AND A LOT OF OUR VETERANS BECOME
GHOST PEOPLE.
WE MIGHT CATCH UP EVENTUALLY AT
THE HOSPITAL.
WE MIGHT CATCH UP WITH THEM AT A
COUNTY JAIL.
WE'RE A BETTER NATION THAN THIS
AND WE NEED TO HAVE A TRANSITION
PROGRAM SO THAT NO VETERANS SLIP
THROUGH THE CRACKS AND MAKE THE
FIRST GOAL SO WE CAN THEN GET TO
THE POSTTRAUMATIC STRESS ISSUES,
MENTAL HEALTH, AND OTHER THINGS,
FIRST GOAL NEEDS TO BE FOR
EMPLOYMENT.
BECAUSE EVERY PERSON NEEDS TO BE
NEEDED.
AND WE NEED OUR VETERANS BACK
HERE, EVERY BIT AS MUCH AS WE
NEEDED THEM ABROAD.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOT ANOTHER QUESTION FOR YOU,
GOVERNOR, DEBORA PLUMBER, FROM
DRAKE UNIVERSITY, UNDECIDED.
AS HAS A QUESTION ABOUT THE
KPLI.
>> GOOD EVENING, GOVERNOR.
>> HI.
>> DO YOU HAVE ANY SPECIFIC
PLANS TO GROW BE THE ECONOMY AT
A RATE THAT WILL INCREASE JOB
GROWTH FOR THOSE, SO THAT NOSE
WHO ARE LONG-TERM UNEMPLOYED OR
FALLEN OUT OF THE WORK FORCE
WILL HAVE AN OPPORTUNITY TO GET
BACK IN?
>> SURE.
YES.
LET ME TALK ABOUT OUR ECONOMY.
PRIOR TO PRESIDENT OBAMA'S GOOD
WORK, AND HE'S DONE GREAT WORK,
SAVED US FROM A SECOND GREAT
DEPRESSION, FROM THE
RECKLESSNESS AND GREED ON WALL
STREET, OUR NATION'S CREATING
JOBS AGAIN, AND WE'RE THE ONLY
SPECIES ON THE PLANET WITHOUT
FULL EMPLOYMENT.
JOBS ARE IMPORTANT.
WITHOUT JOBS, NOTHING WORKS
WELL.
HERE'S ANOTHER THING THAT
DOESN'T WORK WELL IN AMERICA,
UNLESS IT'S GOING IN THE RIGHT
DIRECTION.
AND THAT IS WAGES.
FOR THE FIRST TIME THIS SIDE OF
WORLD WAR II, 70% OF US ARE
EARNING THE SAME OR LESS THAN 12
YEARS AGO.
SO, AS I LOOK AT THIS, I BELIEVE
THAT WE NEED TO FIRST AND
FOREMOST REMEMBER THAT OUR
ECONOMY IS NOT MONEY.
IT IS PEOPLE.
IT IS ALL OF OUR PEOPLE.
AND WE NEED TO RESTORE COMMON
SENSE WAGE AND LABOR POLICIES
THAT MAKE WAGES RISE AGAIN.
THINGS WE USED TO DO, DEMOCRATS
AND REPUBLICANS TOGETHER, ALL
THE TIME, LIKE KEEPING THE
MINIMUM WAGE ABOVE THE POVERTY
LINE.
PAYING OVERTIME PAY FOR OVERTIME
WORK.
HOW ABOUT THIS?
THE PROMISE OF EQUAL PAY FOR
EQUAL WORK FOR MEN AND WOMEN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
MAKING IT EASIER FOR PEOPLE TO
JOIN LABOR UNIONS INSTEAD OF
HARDER --
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND THEN, HERE'S ANOTHER ONE TO
MAKE WAGES GO UP INSTEAD OF
BEING A DRAG ON WAGES, LET'S GET
11 MILLION OF OUR NEIGHBORS OUT
OF THE UNDERGROUND SHADOW
ECONOMY BY PASSING COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION PERFORM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
GET A PATHWAY TO CITIZENSHIP.
>> GOVERNOR --
>> BUT THERE'S -- CHRIS, AND TWO
OTHER BRIEF ONES ON THIS.
IM THE FIRST CANDIDATE TO PUT
FORWARD A NEW AGENDA FOR
AMERICA'S CITIES.
AMERICA'S CITIES ARE WHERE WE
HAVE SOME OF THE WORST PROBLEMS
OF STRUCTURAL UNEMPLOYMENT AND
WHERE WE CAN DO THE MOST GOOD
WITH INVESTMENT, MOBILITY, MASS
TRANSIT, NEW AREA OF WORK FORCE
HOUSING, CITIES THE LEADING EDGE
TO THE CLEAN, GREEN ENVIRONMENT
AND SQUARING OUR SHOULDERS TO
CLIMATE CHANGE AND TRAINING
PEOPLE TO ACTUALLY BE PART OF
THE RETROFITTING AND THE
DISTRIBUTED ENERGY FUTURE THAT
IS AMERICAS.
>> GOVERNOR.
>> THANK YOU.
>> TALK TO THE AUDIENCE ABOUT
POINTS OF CONTRAST BETWEEN YOU
AND SENATOR SANDERS WHEN IT
COMES TO THE ECONOMIC PLAN.
SO MUCH IS MADE OF HIM BEING A
SELF-DESCRIBED DEMOCRATIC
SOCIALIST.
DO YOU SEE YOURSELF AS THAT
DIFFERENT FROM HIM WHEN IT COMES
TO THE ECONOMY?
>> YEAH, LOOK, MY STORY IS NOT
THE STORY OF A, OF OF A
DEMOCRATIC CONVERSION.
MY STORY IS THE STORY OF A
DEMOCRATIC UPBRINGING.
AND MY PARENTS TAUGHT ME THAT
THE STRONGER WE MAKE OUR
COUNTRY, THE MORE OUR COUNTRY
CAN GIVE BACK TO OURSELVES AND
TO OUR CHILDREN.
AND SO I BELIEVE IN FAIR MARKET
AMERICAN CAPITALISM.
AND I ALSO AS PART OF THOSE 15
STRATEGIC GOALS BELIEVE ASWOOD
ROW WILSON BELIEVES THAT
FREEDOM, ECONOMIC FREEDOM ALSO
MEANS FREEDOM FROM MONOPOLY.
I WOULD AGREE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I WOULD ACTUALLY AGREE WITH
SENATOR SANDERS IN THIS SENSE,
CHRIS, WE HAVE REACHED THE POINT
WHERE THERE'S BEEN SUCH A
CONCENTRATION OF CORPORATE
WEALTH AND POWER IN THE HANDS OF
SO FEW THAT IT'S TAKING
OPPORTUNITY OUT OF THE HOMES OF
THE MEN.
AND WHENEVER THAT HAPPENS,
THERE'S ONLY TWO PATHS FORWARD,
AND ONLY ONE OF THEM IS GOOD.
AND THAT IS A SENSIBLE
REBALANCING BASED ON THE COMMON
GOOD WE SHARE.
WE NEED TO PUSH BACK ON THESE
CONCENTRATIONS OF CORPORATE
POWER, WALL STREET, BIG BANKS,
BUT OTHER PLACES AS WELL.
YOU KNOW HERE IN IOWA, A FARMER
TOLD ME THAT 12 YEARS AGO, THEY
USED TO HAVE ABOUT A DOZEN
PACKING HOUSES.
NOW THEY ONLY HAVE FOUR OR FIVE.
HOG FARMERS ARE MORE PRODUCTIVE
THAN EVER, BUT GETTING A LOWER
PRICE THAN EVER.
ECONOMY IS AN ECOSYSTEM, YOU
KNOW, AND THE CENTER OF THAT
ECOSYSTEM IS A STRONGER MIDDLE
CLASS.
IN OTHER WORDS, THE STRONGER WE
MAKE OUR MIDDLE CLASS, THE MORE
OUR ECONOMY GROWS.
AND THAT'S WHAT WE'VE LOST TRACK
OF.
UNTIL THESE 30 YEARS OF TRICKLE
DOWN ECONOMICS.
THE MORE OUR WORKERS EARN, THE
MORE THEY SPEND, THE MORE OUR
ECONOMY GROWS.
AND SO, NO, I WILL SAY THIS
THOUGH, CHRIS, I THINK THAT -- I
DO BELIEVE THAT THE FUNDAMENTALS
OF AMERICAN CAPITALISM ARE STILL
ZRONG.
BUT WE NEED TO SHAKE OURSELVES
OUT OF THIS TRICKLE DOWN
NONSENSE THAT SAYS CONCENTRATE
WEALTH, REMOVE REGULATION, AND
KEEP WAGES LOW.
LOW WAGES FOR AMERICA IS NOT AN
AMERICA THAT'S WORKING.
WE NEED WAGE POLICIES TO MAKE
WAGES GOES UP AGAIN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GENTLEMAN STANDING UP IS
BRIAN CARLSON, STUDENT AT DRAKE
UNIVERSITY, HE'S LEANING TOWARDS
SUPPORTING HILLARY CLINTON.
HE SAYS HE WANTS TO TALK ABOUT
DISCRIMINATION IN THE WORKPLACE.
AND HE HAS A QUESTION ABOUT IT.
WHAT DO YOU HAVE?
>> LAST YEAR'S SUPREME COURT
DECISION GRANTING FULL MARRIAGE
EQUALITY WAS TRULY MONUMENTAL
FOR THE LGBT COMMUNITY ACROSS
THE NATION.
UM -- UM, BUT WE STILL FACE A
HARD BATTLE AHEAD.
SFAESHLLY IN THE AREAS OF
EMPLOYMENT AND HOUSING.
IN MANY STATES WE STILL FACE
DISCRIMINATION.
I WAS WONDERING WHAT WOULD YOU
DO AS PRESIDENT TO HELP US TO
ACQUIRE FULL EQUALITY IN THOSE
AREAS ON THE FEDERAL LEVEL?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I BELIEVE THAT THE GENIUS OF
THIS AMERICAN EXPERIMENT OF OURS
IS THAT IN EVERY GENERATION, WE
TAKE ACTION TO INCLUDE MORE
PEOPLE, MORE FULLY IN THE
ECONOMIC, THE SOCIAL, AND THE
POLITICAL LIFE OF OUR COUNTRY.
THAT'S THE BROADER ARK OF
AMERICAN HISTORY.
WE'VE YET TO ARRIVE AT A PERFECT
UNION, BUT, EVERY GENERATION, WE
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO MAKE IT
A MORE PERFECT UNION.
IN MY OWN STATE, WE WERE ONE OF
THE VERY FIRST TO PASS, AT THE
BALLOT, MARRIAGE EQUALITY.
I ALSO PASSED A TRANSGENDER
ANTIDISCRIMINATION BILL IN THE
STATE OF MARYLAND AS WELL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND IT'S INTERESTING, YOU KNOW,
THE COMMON GROUND WE FOUND TO
GET THESE THINGS DONE WAS THIS,
IT'S REALLY ABOUT OUR KIDS.
IT'S ABOUT ALL OUR KIDS.
AND TLRN SOME PEOPLE IN MARYLAND
WHO SAID WE MIGHT NOT BE ABLE TO
PASS MARRIAGE EQUALITY.
AND WE MADE THE ARGUMENT ALL
ABOUT THE TRUTH THAT THERE IS
DIGNITY IN EVERY CHILD'S HOME.
AND EVERY CHILD'S HOME NEEDS TO
BE PROTECTED EQUALLY UNDER THE
LAW.
ONE OF THE MOST POWERFUL BELIEFS
WE SHARE IS OUR BELIEF IN THE
DIGNITY OF EVERY PERSON.
THAT'S WHAT'S MOTIVATED ME AND
THE COMMON GOOD THAT WE SHARE.
AND I WILL DO EVERYTHING IN MY
POWER TO MOVE US FORWARD AS A
NATION AND MAKE US MORE
INCLUSIVE IN EVERY POSSIBLE WAY
I CAN.
ACROSS THE BOARD BECAUSE THAT'S
WHAT MAKES US STRONGER AS A
COUNTRY.
>> THANK YOU.
>> GOVERNOR, YOU WERE TALKING
ABOUT FARMING EARLIER AND THE
STATUS HERE IN IOWA, WE HAVE A
QUESTION ABOUT THAT.
THIS IS PRESIDENT OF THE IOWA
FARMERS UNION.
SHE'S LEANING TOWARDS CLINTON,
BUT SHE'S A FOURTH GENERATION
FARMER AND SHE HAS A QUESTION.
>> FIRST I WANT TO THE SAY, I
LOVE THAT YOU MENTIONED THE
PROBLEM OF MARKET
CONCENTRATION --
>> YEAH, NOT GOOD FOR FAMILY
FARMS, IS IT?
>> NOT TOO GREAT.
NOT NEARLY AS MANY AS THERE USED
TO BE.
MY KBE IS ABOUT BEGINNING
FARMERS.
I'M A BEGINNING FARMER.
THE AVERAGE AGE OF FARMERS IN
THE UNITED STATES RIGHT NOW IS
ABOUT 57 YEARS OLD.
AND THAT NUMBER GOES UP A LITTLE
BIT EACH YEAR FOR BEGINNING
FARMERS.
A GROUP THAT INCLUDES A GROWING
NUMBER OF VETERANS, WOMEN
FARMERS LIKE ME AND OTHER
GROUPS.
WE DO HAVE SOME DOESN'TS WITH
INNOVATIVE BUSINESS MODELS THAT
INCLUDE GERS IF IED FARMS, MORE
SUSTAINABLE FARMING PRACTICE,
BUT NOT NEARLY ENOUGH OF US.
WE KNOW THAT LOT ARE GOING TO BE
RETIRING IN THE NEXT DECADE AND
THERE AREN'T ENOUGH PEOPLE TO
REPLACE THEM.
MY QUESTION IS, AFTER DECADES OF
RURAL OUT MIGRATION AND FARM
CONSOLIDATION, WHAT WOULD YOU DO
TO PROVIDE OPPORTUNITIES AND
INVEST IN A NEW GENERATION OF
FAMILY FARMERS FOR THE COUNTRY?
>> YEAH, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I THINK THIS IS A BIG, BIG
PART OF THE FUTURE FOR RURAL
AMERICA.
SUSTAINABLE ECONOMIES.
THE ABILITY TO CONSUME AND TO
GROW AND TO DO THAT WITHIN THE
FOOTPRINT OF OF THIS PLACE THAT
WE CALL HOME.
AND SO, I WOULD LIKE TO WORK
WITH CONGRESS AND I PLAN TO WORK
WITH CONGRESS TO DO MORE IN THE
FARM BILL TO REDUCE THE BARRIER
OF ENTRY, TO NEW FARMERS AS THEY
START UP.
HUGE CAPITAL COSTS THAT GO INTO
BUYING THE LAND AND BUYING THE
EQUIPMENT, BUT IT'S ALSO WHAT'S
BEST FOR KEEPING OUR RURAL
ECONOMIES AND IT'S BEST FOR
AMERICA.
SOP I'VE SEEN IN MY OWN STATE A
WHOLE MOVEMENT TO THE BILOCAL
MOVEMENT AND THE SORT OF FARMING
THAT YOU DESCRIBE.
WE NEED TO DO MORE AS A NATION
TO ENCOURAGE YOUNG FARMERS TO GO
INTO FARMING, TO REDUCE THOSE
BARRIERS, AND THOSE CAPITAL
COSTS, EVEN AT THE SAME TIME
THAT WE PUSHED BACK AGAINST THE
CONCENTRATION OF MONOPOLY POWER
IN THE AGRICULTURAL SECTOR, AND
THAT'S WHAT I INTEND TO DO.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT.
ANOTHER QUESTION FOR YOU.
WE KNOW THAT YOU ARE WORKING
THIS WHOLE STATE AND GOING FOR
THE GOLD.
YOU'RE IN IT TO WIN IT, I
UNDERSTAND THAT.
BUT YOU CAN MAKE AN ARGUMENT
THAT YOU ARE THE MOST IMPORTANT
PERSON THAT WE'RE GOING TO HAVE
IN THIS ROOM TONIGHT, WHETHER OR
NOT YOU WIN OR NOT.
HERE'S WHY.
AS OWE KNOB, THERE'S A 15% RULE
IN A LOT OF THESE CAUCUSES, IF
YOU DON'T HAVE 15 IN THE ROOM,
THOSE WOMEN HAVE TO GO TO A
DIFFERENT CANDIDATE.
SO IF YOU DON'T HAVE THAT, AND
YOUR FOLLOWERS HAVE TO GO
SOMEWHERE ELSE, THE PEOPLE WHO
SUPPORT YOU.
WHAT IS YOUR SUGGESTION TO THEM?
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> THIS SOUNDS LIKE A PROCESS
QUESTION.
LOOK, HERE'S MY SUGGESTION TO
THEM.
I HAVE PUT TOGETHER A TERRIFIC
ORGANIZATION WHERE WE HAVE PUT
TOGETHER A TERRIFIC ORGANIZATION
ALL ACROSS THIS STATE, CHRIS.
AND ONE OF THE REASONS WHY, WHY
THE POLLS BACK EAST CAN NEVER
FIGURE OUT HOW THE CAUCUSES WORK
IS BECAUSE IT'S A VERY OR GAJIC
THING.
MY MESSAGE TO THE O'MALLEY
SUPPORTERS ACROSS THIS STATE IS
THIS, HOLD STRONG AT YOUR
CAUCUS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
HOLD STRONG AT YOUR CAUCUS
BECAUSE AMERICA'S LOOKING FOR A
NEW LEADER.
AMERICA'S SCANNING THE HORIZON.
WE CANNOT BE THIS FED UP WITH
OUR GRIDLOCK DYSFUNCTIONAL,
NATIONAL POLITICS AND THINK THAT
A RESORT TO OLD IDEOLOGIES ARE
OLD NAMES IS GOING TO MOVE US
FORWARD.
I TELL MY PEOPLE, HOLD STRONG.
I KNOLL THIS IS A TOUGH FIGHT.
BUT I'VE ALWAYS BEEN DRAWN TO IT
TOUGH FIGHT.
I BELIEVE THE TUFZNESS OF THE
FIGHT IS THE WAY THE HIDDEN GOD
HAS OF TELLING US WE'RE FIGHTING
FOR SOMETHING WORTH SAVING.
OUR COUNTRY'S WORTH SAVING, THE
AMERICAN DREAM IS WORTH SAVING,
THIS PLANET IS WORTH SAVING.
AMERICA NEEDS NEW LEADERSHIP,
AND I NEED THE O'MALLEY
SUPPORTERS OUT THERE ON CAUCUS
NIGHT TO HOLD STRONG AND MAUVE
FORWARD LIKE IOWA DOES.
I LOVE THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ALL RIGHT, LET'S BRING IN
BENJAMIN, GREW UP IN IOWA, HE'S
NOW A LAW STUDENT.
HE'S LEANING TOWARDS SUPPORTING
YOU ON MONDAY, HE HAS AN
IMPORTANT QUESTION FOR YOU.
>> YES, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
THIS IS GOING TO GIVE YOU A
CHANCE TO WRAP UP YOUR MAIN
PITCH.
WE'LL GIVE YOU 30 SECONDS, SAME
THING WE GAVEL TO SENATOR
SANDERS, BUT GO AHEAD.
>> RIGHT ON CUE WITH THAT,
YOU'RE AWARE THAT NATIONAL POLLS
CONTINUE SHOW YOU TRAILING
SECRETARY CLINTON AND SENATOR
SANDERS.
SO TO THOSE THAT ARE STILL, YOU
KNOW, UNDECIDED LIKE ME OR MAYBE
JUST LESS INFORMED ABOUT
POLITICS, ON TOP OF WHAT YOU'VE
ALREADY TALKED ABOUT, WHAT'S THE
LAST THING THAT YOU WOULD TRY TO
TELL THEM TO CONVINCE THEM THAT
YOU ARE IN FACT THE BEST
CANDIDATE FOR THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY?
>> THANK YOU.
THIS IS WHAT I WOULD SAY.
I WOULD SAY THAT TIME AND TIME
AGAIN IN THE HISTORY OF THE
STATE OF IOWA, IOWA HAS FOUND A
WAY TO SORT THROUGH THE NOISE
AND TO SORT THROUGH THE NATIONAL
POLLS.
AND TO LIFT UP OF A NEW LEADER
FOR OUR COUNTRY.
AT TIMES, WHEN THAT WAS CRITICAL
AND ESSENTIAL.
THAT'S WHEN YOU DO EIGHT YEARS
AGO WHEN YOU LIFTED UP BARACK
OBAMA TO LEAD OUR COUNTRY
FORWARD.
AND WE NEED TO BUILD UPON HIS
GOOD WORK.
BY CONTINUING TO MOVE FORWARD.
AND, I AM THE ONLY -- I AM THE
ONLY ONE OF THE THREE OF US WHO
HAS A TRACK RECORD, NOT OF BEING
A DIVIDER, BUT OF BRINGING
PEOPLE TOGETHER TO GET
MEANINGFUL THINGS DONE.
RAISING THE LIVING WAGE, MAKING
COLLEGE MORE AFFORDABLE.
CREATING JOBS, HEALING WOUNDS
AND DIVISIONS.
THAT'S WHAT OUR COUNTRY NEEDS
RIGHT NOW.
WE ARE A GREAT PEOPLE.
WE ARE A GENEROUS, AND WE ARE A
COMPASSIONATE PEOPLE.
AND WE ARE FAR BETTER THAN THE
SORT OF FASCIST RHETORIC THAT
YOU HEAR SPEWED OUT BUSINESS
DONALD TRUMP, THE ENDURING
SYMBOL OF OUR COUNTRY IS NOT A
BARBED WIRE FENCE, IT IS STATUE
OF LIBERTY.
AND WE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- SEEN I'M NOT HERE TO PRAISE
YOU, IOWA, I'M HERE TO CHALLENGE
YOU.
LIFT UP A NEW LEADER.
BECAUSE YOU CAN CHANGE THE
COURSE OF THIS PRESIDENTIAL
RACE.
YOU CAN SHIFT THIS DYNAMIC ON
CAUCUS NIGHT.
I KNOW YOU CAN, I'VE SEEN YOU DO
IT BEFORE.
THERE IS NOTHING SO DIVIDED
ABOUT OUR NATIONAL POLITICS THAT
IT CANNOT BE HEALED WITH THE
RENEWED FAITH IN ONE ANOTHER AND
NEW LEADERSHIP.
THAT'S WHAT I HAVE TO OFFER.
MY CANDIDACY IS IN YOUR HANDS.
DO WITH IT AS YOU WILL.
BUT I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT IN
ORDER TO MOVE OUR COUNTRY
FORWARD THAT ONCE AGAIN, I IOWA
LIFT UP A NEW LEADER SO WE CAN
MAKE AMERICA THE COMPASSIONATE,
GENEROUS, AND INCLUSIVE PLACE
THAT WE NEED IT TO BE.
THANKS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
>> ALL RIGHT, THANKS TO GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY, HILLARY CLINTON IS IN
THE WINGS.
SHE'S READY TO FACE THESE IOWA
VOTERS, NEXT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL TOWN
HALL HERE AT DRAKE UNIVERSITY IN
DES MOINES, IOWA.
AS YOU'VE SEEN TONIGHT IS
SOMETHING DIFFERENT.
IT IS A CHANCE FOR THE VOTERS OF
IOWA TO QUESTION THE CANDIDATES
DIRECTLY.
NEXT UP, FORMER SECRETARY OF
STATE, HILLARY CLINTON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> HOW ARE YOUED?
GREAT TO THE SEE YOU.
HI, EVERYBODY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> INTERESTING WEEKEND FOR YOU.
BOSTON GLOBE, ENDORSEMENT.
DES MOINES REGISTER,
ENDORSEMENT.
MAYBE THE BEST ACCOLADE,
PRESIDENT OBAMA GAVE AN
INTERVIEW, TALKED ABOUT THIS
RACE, SEEMED TO GET MORE INTO IT
THAN HE HAS IN THE PAST.
HE SAID, YOU'RE QUOTE, WICKED
SMART.
KNOWS EVERY POLICY INSIDE AND
OUT.
SOUNDS LIKE AND ENDORSEMENT TO
ME.
>> WELL, I WAS REALLY TOUCHED
AND GRATIFIED WHEN I SAW THAT.
YOU KNOW, PEOPLE HERE IN IOWA
REMEMBER, WE RAN A REALLY HARD
RACE AGAINST EACH OTHER, AND
THEN I HAD THE OPPORTUNITY WHEN
HE ASKED ME TO SERVE AS HIS
SECRETARY OF STATE, AND IT NOT
ONLY WAS A GREAT WORKING
RELATIONSHIP, BUT TURNED INTO A
REAL FRIENDSHIP.
AND HE KNOWS HOW HARD THE JOB
IS.
AND HE KNOWS IT FIRSTHAND.
SO I REALLY APPRECIATED WHAT HE
SAID AND HOW HE SAID IT BECAUSE
IT WAS A POSITIVE, REFLECTION ON
WHAT WE HAVE TO GET DONE AND HOW
HARD IT'S GOING TO BE, AND
THEREFORE, THE STAKES IN THE
ELECTION ARE REALLY HIGH.
AND I THINK THAT'S WHAT VOTERS
ARE BEGINNING TO REALLY TUNE
INTO STARTING HERE IN IOWA.
>> HE SAYS ALSO IN THERE, YOU
GET UNDUE CRITICISM.
BY THE WAY, I HAVE REGRETS ABOUT
MY CAMPAIGN AND SOME OF THE
THINGS WE DID.
WAS THAT SURPRISING?
>> YES, THAT WAS SURPRISING.
YOU KNOW, I REALLY APPRECIATED
HIM SAYING THAT BECAUSE HE HAD
THAT GREAT LINE, WHICH I LOVE, I
THINK HE SAID SOMETHING LIKE,
YOU KNOW, SHE HAD TO DO, HE SAID
I WAS LIKE FRED ASTAIR, SHE WAS
GINGER ROGER DOING IT BACKWARDS
IN HIGH HEELS.
AND I THOUGHT THAT WAS A REALLY
TOUGH, A VERY SWEET REMARK, BUT
YOU KNOW, I UNDERSTAND THAT YOU
GET INTO THE ARENA AND YOU AR
GOING TO GET PULMMELLED AND
PUSHED AND CRITICIZED.
I WOULDN'T BE DOING IT IF I
DIDN'T THINK IT WAS ABSOLUTELY
NECESSARY TO TRY TO BUILD ON THE
PROGRESS THAT WE'VE MADE.
THAT WE'VE MADE UNDER PRESIDENT
OBAMA AGAINST GREAT ODDS, AND
THAT WE'VE GOT TO DO EVERYTHING
WE POSSIBLY CANNOT TO LET THE
REPUBLICANS RIP AWAY THE
PROGRESS AND TURN US BACKWARDS.
THAT WOULD BE SUCH A LOSS FOR
OUR COUNTRY.
WE NEED TO BUILD ON IT AND GO
FURTHER, AND THAT'S WHAT I'M
TRYING TO DO IN MY CAMPAIGN AND
TALKING ABOUT ALL THE ISSUES
THAT I THINK ARE ON THE MINDS OF
THE PEOPLE I SPEAK TO ACROSS THE
STATE.
>> AND YOU GET TO DO THAT
TONIGHT.
WE'RE GOING TO GET QUESTIONS
RIGHT FROM THE VOTERS.
2008, WE'RE TALKING ABOUT.
HERE YOU ARE AGAIN, ANOTHER
ELECTION.
PRAISE AND PROMISE COMING YOUR
WAY, BUT ANOTHER NAIL-BITER --
>> RIGHT.
>> WITH A SELF-DESCRIBED
SOCIALIST, NAMED BERNIE.
>> RIGHT.
>> HOW DID THAT HAPPEN?
>> LOOK, IT'S A GREAT COUNTRY,
DESPITE WHAT ONE OF THE
REPUBLICAN SAYS, IT'S A GREAT
COUNTRY, AND WE ARE ALL ON THE
DEMOCRATIC SIDE, HAVING A
SPIRITED DEBATE ABOUT THE ISSUES
WE CARE ABOUT.
I'M SO PROUD -- YOU'VE SEEN MY
TWO DEMOCRATIC OPPONENTS, AND
THE THREE OF US HAVE RUN A
CAMPAIGN TALKING ABOUT THE
DIFFERENCES WE HAVE ON ISSUES.
THAT'S TOTALLY FAIR.
THAT'S WHAT WE WANT YOU TO KNOW.
THE OTHER SIDE IS NOT TALKING
ISSUES, THEY'RE TALKING INSULTS.
SO I'M PROUD OF THE CAMPAIGN
WE'VE RUN AND WHAT WE'VE PUT OUT
THERE BEFORE THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
AND IT'S A TOUGH CAMPAIGN.
AND IT SHOULD BE BECAUSE IT'S
THE HARDEST JOB IN THE WORLD.
YOU HAVE TO PICK A PRESIDENT AND
A COMMANDER IN CHIEF, AND YOU
WANT TO REALLY VET THE PEOPLE
THAT ARE RUNNING.
AND I'M REALLY HAVING A GOOD
TIME GOING AROUND TALKING AND
LISTENING TO FOLKS ON MONDAY,
THE PEOPLE IN IOWA GET TO BE THE
FIRST PEOPLE IN THE WORLD,
CHRIS, TO EXPRESS AN OPINION
ABOUT WHO SHOULD BE PRESIDENT
AND COMMANDER IN CHIEF, AND WHAT
THEY WANT TO SEE AS OUR NOMINEE
TO GO UP AGAINST THE
REPUBLICANS.
>> IT FEELS LIKE LOT OF YOUNG
PEOPLE, WE'RE PASSIONATE
SUPPORTERS OF BERNIE SANDERS,
AND I DON'T SEE THE SAME
ENTHUSIASM FROM YOUNGER PEOPLE
FOR YOU.
IN FACT, I'VE HEARD FROM QUITE A
FEW PEOPLE MY AGE THAT THEY
THINK YOU'RE DISHONEST, BUT I'D
LIKE TO HEAR FROM YOU AND WHY
YOU FEEL THE ENTHUSIASM ISN'T
THERE.
>> WELL, I THINK IT REALLY
DEPENDS UPON WHO YOU'RE SEEING
AND TALKING TO.
YOU KNOW, TODAY IN OSKALOOSA, I
SPENT TIME WITH ABOUT TEN HIGH
SCHOOL STUDENTS WHO ARE
ENTHUSIASTICALLY WORKING FOR ME.
I SEE YOUNG PEOPLE ACROSS THE
STATE WHO ARE DOING THE SAME.
BUT I'M TOTALLY HAPPY TO SEE
YOUNG PEOPLE INVOLVED IN ANY
WAY.
THAT'S WHAT WE WANT.
AND WE WANT TO HAVE A GOOD
PRIMARY, TO PICK A NOMINEE, AND
THEN WE WANT TO HAVE EVERYBODY
JOIN TOGETHER TO MAKE SURE WE
WIN IN NOVEMBER.
WHICH AFTERALL IS THE PURPOSE OF
THIS WHOLE CAMPAIGN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND SO --
YOU KNOW, LOOK, I'VE BEEN AROUND
A LONG TIME.
PEOPLE HAVE THROWN ALL KINDS OF
THINGS AT ME.
AND YOU KNOW, I CAN'T KEEP UP
WITH IT.
I JUST KEEP GOING FORWARD.
THEY FALL BY THE WAYSIDE, THEY
COME UP WITH THE OUTLANDISH
THINGS, THEY MAKE THESE CHARGES,
I JUST KEEP GOING FORWARD
BECAUSE THERE'S NOTHING TO IT.
THEY THROW ALL THIS STUFF AT ME,
AND I'M STILL STANDING.
BUT IF YOU'RE NEW TO POLITICS
WITH IF IT'S THE FIRST TIME
YOU'VE REALLY PAID ATTENTION,
YOU GO OH MY GOSH, LOOK AT ALL
OF THIS.
AND YOU HAVE TO SAY TO YOURSELF,
WHY ARE THEY THROWING ALL OF
THAT?
WELL I'LL TELL YOU WHY BECAUSE
I'VE BEEN ON THE FRONTLINES OF
CHANGE AND PROGRES SINCE I WAS
YOUR AGE.
I HAVE BEEN FIGHTING TO GIVE
KIDS AND WOMEN AND THE, AND THE
PEOPLE WHO ARE LEFT OUT AND LEFT
BEHIND A CHANCE TO MAKE THE MOST
OUT OF THEIR OWN LIVES.
AND I'VE TAKEN ON THE STATUS
QUO, TIME AND TIME AGAIN, I HAVE
HAD MANY, MANY MILLIONS OF
DOLLARS SPENT AGAINST ME.
WHEN I WORKED ON HEALTH CARE
BACK IN '93 AND '94, AND I DON'T
KNOW IF YOU WERE BORN THEN, I
CAN'T QUITE TELL, BUT, IF YOU'D
BEEN AROUND AND HAD BEEN ABLE TO
PAY ATTENTION, I WAS TRYING TO
GET US TO UNIVERSAL HEALTH CARE
COVERAGE, WORKING WITH MY
HUSBAND.
BOY, THE INSURANCE COMPANIES,
THE DRUG COMPANIES, THEY SPENT
MILLIONS, NOT JUST AGAINST THE
ISSUE, BUT AGAINST ME.
AND I KEPT GOING.
AND WHEN WE WEREN'T SUCCESSFUL,
I TURNED AROUND AND SAID, AT
LEAST WE'RE GOING TO GET HEALTH
CARE FOR KIDS.
AND WE GOT THE CHILDREN'S HEALTH
INSURANCE PROGRAM WORKING WITH
BOTH DEMOCRATS AND REPUBLICANS,
AND EIGHT MILLION KIDS HAVE
INSURANCE BECAUSE OF THAT TODAY.
SO YOU'VE GOT TO KEEP GOING.
YOU CAN'T GIVE UP.
YOU CAN NEVER GET KNOCKED OFF
COURSE.
THAT'S MY, THAT'S MY HOPE FOR
YOU AND FOR ALL THE YOUNG PEOPLE
WHO ARE GETTING INVOLVED THIS
FIRST TIME.
DON'T GET DISCOURAGED.
IF IT WERE EASY, HEY, THERE
WOULDN'T BE ANY CONTEST, BUT
IT'S NOT EASY.
THERE ARE VERY DIFFERENT
VISIONS, DIFFERENT VALUES,
DIFFERENT FORCES AT WORK.
AND YOU HAVE TO HAVE SOMEBODY
WHO IS A PROVEN, PROVEN FIGHTER.
SOMEBODY WHO HAS TAKEN THEM ON
AND WON.
AND KEPT GOING AND WILL DO THAT
AS PRESIDENT.
THAT'S WHY I HOPE YOU'LL
RECONSIDER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WE HAVE ANOTHER VOTER FOR YOU
TO WORK ON, AN IOWA NATIVE,
FIRST TIME CAUCUS GOER, SHE'S
ALSO LEANING TOWARDS BERNIE BUT
A CHANCE WITH A QUESTION.
>> GREAT.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, EARLIER
THIS MONTH, VICE PRESIDENT JOE
BIDEN SAID YOU ARE A NEW-COMER
TO THE ISSUE OF INCOME AND
EQUALITY WHILE PRAISING SENATOR
SANDERS FOR HIS AUTHENTIC VOICE
ON THE ISSUE.
HOW DO WE KNOW YOU'LL KEEP THIS
A TOP PRIORITY?
>> AND NOT ONLY ECONOMIC
INEQUALITY.
RABL INEQUALITY.
SEXIST INEQUALITY, HOMOPHOBIC
INEQUALITY.
THE KINDS FZ THINGS THAT GO
AFTER PEOPLE TO PUT THEM DOWN
AND PUSH THEM BACK.
SO SINCE I WAS A YOUNG LAWYER,
MY FIRST JOB IN THE CHILDREN'S
DEFENSE FUND I WENT BY MYSELF
DOWN TO ALABAMA, TO DO
INVESTIGATION BECAUSE AGAIN,
INEQUALITY STOCKS OUR EDUCATION
SYSTEM.
I WAS ON THE LEGAL SERVICES
CORPORATION.
I CHAIRED THE BOARD.
INEQUALITY'S ALSO NOT ABOUT
BEING ABLE TO GET A LAWYER.
YOU CAN'T AFFORD THEM.
YOU CAN'T STAND UP AND HAVE YOUR
VOICE HEARD AND HAVE YOUR CASE
ACUED E JUD DATED.
I HAVE A REALLY LONG HISTORY OF
TAKING ON ALL KINDS OF
INEQUALITY.
WHEN I WENT TO BEIJING IN 1995
AND HUMAN RIGHTS WERE WOMEN
RIGHT, THAT WAS A STATEMENT
ABOUT INEQUALITY.
ECONOMIC INEQUALITY, EVERY KIND
OF INEQUALITY YOU CAN IMAGINE.
NOW, WHEN, WHEN YOU FOCUS JUST
NARROWLY ON ECONOMIC IMEQUAL,
I'VE ALSO BEEN IN THAT FIGHT.
I WAS IN THAT FIGHT DURING MY
HUSBAND'S ADMINISTRATION.
AND LET'S REMEMBER WHAT HAPPENED
THERE.
AT THE END OF EIGHT YEARS, WE
NOT ONLY HAD 23 MILLION NEW
JOBS, WHAT WAS MOST IMPORTANT IS
INCOMES GREW FOR EVERYBODY.
NOT JUST THOSE AT THE TOP, MORE
PEOPLE WERE LIFTED OUT OF
POVERTY, INCOMES ROSE, IN THE
MIDDLE AND WORKING PEOPLE, AND
TODAY IN KNOXVILLE, IN MY TOWN
HALL.
I CALLED O AN MAN, HE SAID WE
NEVER HAD IT SO GOOD EXCEPT WHEN
YOUR HUSBAND WAS PRESIDENT
BECAUSE WE TACKLED INCOME
EQUALITY AND PRODUCED RESULTS,
NOT TALK, ACTION, AND THAT'S
WHAT I WILL DO AS PRESIDENT.
>> ANOTHER QUESTION FOR YOU.
SECRETARY, DICK GOODSON, HE'S
THE CHAIRMAN OF THE DES MOINES
COMMITTEE ON FOREIGN RELATIONS,
HE'S LIKELY GOING TO CAUSE KU
FOR YOU NEXT WEEK, UNLESS YOU
MESS IT UP RIGHT NOW --
>> I'LL TRY NOT TO.
HI.
>> YOUR QUESTION, SIR.
>> MADAME SECRETARY, BEFORE I
ASK MY QUESTION, I HAVE A QUICK
COMMENT, AND THAT IS THAT I WAS
A LUKEWARM PERSON FOR YOU BEFORE
THE BENGHAZI HEARINGS, I WATCHED
ALL 11 HOURS, EVERY SECOND OF IT
AND CAME AWAY FROM THAT A GUNG
HO SUPPORTER OF YOURS.
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WOKE UP ONE NIGHT THINKING
THAT MAYBE I COULD SEE IF DONALD
TRUMP WAS SITTING HERE, MAYBE
HE'D PUNCH GOWDY OUT.
OKAY.
HERE'S THE QUESTION, PRACTICALLY
ALL OF THE COMMENTS THAT HAVE
BEEN SAID FOR BOTH -- ALL THREE
CANDIDATES TONIGHT, ABOUT 99%,
HAVE BEEN ON SOME FORM OF
DOMESTIC POLICY.
AND YET, YOU KNOW, AS THE FORMER
WIFE OF A PRESIDENT AND AS THE
SECRETARY OF STATE, THAT THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
IS GOING TO JUST SPEND MORE THAN
50% OF HIS OR HER TIME ON
FOREIGN POLICY ISSUES.
SO THEREFORE, I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT FOR THE PUBLIC TO KIND
OF GET A SENSE OF WHERE YOU MAY
BE COMING FROM ACROSS THE BOARD,
PHILOSOPHICALLY, AND THE WAY I
LOOK AT IT THE, IS YOU COULD
HAVE A SCALE OF SAY, ONE TO 100,
AND ON THAT SCALE, YOU WOULD
HAVE NONE INTERVENTIONISTS ON
ONE SIDE AND TOTAL
INTERVENTIONISTS ON THE OTHER
SIDE AS TEN.
AS YOU THINK ABOUT ALL THE
ISSUESES THAT YOU'VE CONFRONTED
AS SECRETARY OF STATE, AND THEN
AS THE POSSIBILITY OF LOOKING AT
ISSUES INTO THE FUTURE, WHERE DO
YOU THINK YOU'LL LAND ON THAT
SCALE OF ONE TO TEN?
>> I'LL TELL YOU WHAT.
I WANT TO START BY SAYING THANK
YOU FOR ASKING ABOUT FOREIGN
POLICY BECAUSE YOU'RE ABSOLUELY
RIGHT.
IN FACT, PRESIDENT OBAMA IN HIS
INTERVIEW SAID SOMETHING ABOUT
THAT.
HE SAID YOU KNOW, YOU DON'T GET
TO THE PICK THE ISSUES YOU WORK
ON WHEN YOU'RE PRESIDENT.
A LOT OF THEM COME AT YOU.
THEY COME IN THE DOOR WHETHER
YOU OPEN IT OR NOT, AND EVEN
GAVE THE EXAMPLE OF WORKING ON A
STATE OF THE UNION, BEING AT THE
DESK IN THE OVAL OFFICE WHEN ONE
OF HIS AIDS CAME IN AND SAID,
THE IRANIANS HAVE JUST CAPTURED
TWO OF OUR NAVAL VESSELS AND
HAVE TAKEN OUR SAILORS PRISONER.
YOU CAN'T SAY OH, OKAY, DON'T
BOTHER ME NOW, I'LL DEAL WITH
THAT LATER.
YOU HAVE TO IMMEDIATELY BE ABLE
TO SWITCH GEARS.
YOU'VE GOT TO DO ALL ASPECTS OF
JOB.
SO LET ME TELL YOU HOW I THINK
ABOUT IT.
I THINK IT'S IMPERATIVE YOU DO
YOUR VERY BEST, EVERY PRESIDENT,
AND CERTAINLY, I WILL.
TO AVOID MILITARY ACTION.
IT SHOULD BE THE LAST RESORT,
NOT THE FIRST CHOICE.
TO USE DIPLOMACY, EVEN IF IT'S
SLOW, BORING, HARD TO CONTINUE
TO PERSIST AND BE PATIENT TO GET
RESULTS.
AND THAT YOU ALSO SHOULD USE THE
ENORMOUS CAPABILITIES THAT WE
HAVE TO PROJECT OUR VALUES
AROUND THE WORLD.
OUR CULTURAL VALUES, OUR
FREEDOMS, OUR HUMAN RIGHTS AND
RESPECT FOR THE DIGNITY OF ALL
PEOPLE.
I WANT TO GIVE YOU TWO QUICK
EXAMPLES.
WHEN I BECAME SECRETARY OF
STATE, WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA AND
I FOUND WAS THAT THE IRANIANS
WERE ON THEIR WAY TO A NUCLEAR
WEAPONS PROGRAM.
THIS DESPITE ALL OF THE BLUSTER
FROM THE GEORGE W. BUSH, DICK
CHENEY ADMINISTRATION.
THEY MASTERED THE CYCLE, BUILT
COVERT FACILITIES AND STOCKED
THEM WITH CENTRIFUGES THAT WERE
RAPIDLY WHIRLING ALONG TRYING TO
CREATE ENOUGH RICH URANIUM TO
HAVE A WEAPON.
NOW, OUR CHOICES WERE, OH MY
GOSH, OR TURN OUR BACKS AND JUST
FIGURE OUT THAT SOMEBODY ELSE IS
GOING TO DO SOMETHING OR TRY TO
GET UP A NEW STRATEGY.
WE CHOSE THE THIRD.
WE SAID LOOK, WE'VE GOT TO GET
THE WORLD BEHIND US TO FORCE
THEM TO THE NEGOTIATING TABLE.
SO I SPENT 18 MONTHS PUTTING
TOGETHER THE COALITION THAT
IMPOSED INTERNATIONAL SANCTIONS
ON THE IRANIANS.
THAT FORCED THEM, FINALLY, TO
BEGIN NEGOTIATING WITH US TO GET
AN END TO THEIR NUCLEAR WEAPONS
PROGRAM.
TO PUT A LIDDEN TO.
IT TOOK 18 MONTHS TO GET THE
SANCTIONS.
IT TOOK ME ABOUT ANOTHER YEAR TO
TRAVEL AROUND THE WORLD
CONVINCING OTHER COUNTRIES TO
ACTUALLY OBEY THE SANCTIONS, AND
THEN I BEGAN THE NEGOTIATIONS.
TESTING WHETHER THE IRANIANS
WOULD ACTUALLY COME AND
SERIOUSLY NEGOTIATE, AND THEN
SECRETARY KERRY AND THE
PRESIDENT DID A GREAT JOB
BRINGING THE AGREEMENT INTO
FRUITION.
YOU CANNOT, YOU CANNOT IMAGINE
HOW TENSE IT WAS BECAUSE A LOT
OF OUR FRIENDS, AND PARTNERS IN
THE REGION, BASICALLY JUST
WANTED TO END THAT PROGRAM BY
BOMBING THEM.
JUST BOMB THEM.
SEND THEM BACK A COUPLE OF
YEARS.
JUST STOP IT.
I SPENT A LOT OF MY TIME
EXPLAINING TO OUR FRIENDS, WHY
THAT WAS NOT A GOOD IDEA.
AND WE GOT THE NEGOTIATIONS
SUCCESSFULLY DONE, WE DID PUT
THE LID ON.
SO THAT'S HOW I THOUGHT ABOUT.
ANOTHER QUICK EXAMPLE, WE HAD
ANOTHER UNFORTUNATE SPADE OF
ROCKETS GOING FROM GAZA INTO
ISRAEL IN 2012.
I'M ON THE PHONE WITH THE
ISRAELIS, THEY'RE TRYING TO
KNOCK THEM OUT OF THE SKY WITH
THEIR MISSILE DEFENSE SYSTEM,
BUT THEY'RE STILL LANDING AND
EVERYBODY IS REALLY WORRIED
THAT, YOU KNOW, ONE OF THEM'S
GOING TO HIT A BIG GROUP OF
PEOPLE, TAKE OUT A BIG BUILDING
SOMEWHERE, SO THE ISRAELIS ARE
TELLING ME, LOOK, WE'VE GOT TO
GO BACK IN.
WE HAVE TO HAVE A GROUND
INVASION AGAIN IN GAZA.
I'M SAYING NO, PLEASE, DON'T DO
THAT, LET'S TRY TO RESOLVE IT.
WE DON'T THINK WE CAN RESOLVE
IT.
I FLEW FROM CAMBODIA WITH THE
PRESIDENT TO ISRAEL, MIDDLE OF
THE NIGHT, GO SEE THE ISRAELI
CABINET, WORK WITH THEM ON WHAT
THEY WOULD ACCEPT AS AN OFFER,
GO SEE THE PALESTINIAN
PRESIDENT, WORK WITH HIM TO MAKE
SURE HE'D BACK IT UP, GO BACK TO
JERUSALEM, FINALIZE THE DEAL,
FLY TO CAIRO, MEET WITH
PRESIDENT MORSI, THE MUSLIM
BROTHERHOOD PRESIDENT OF THE
EGYPT, HAMMER OUT THE AGREEMENT,
ANNOUNCE IT AT ABOUT AN HOUR
BEFORE THE DEADLINE THAT WE WERE
FACING.
THEY GOT AL CEASEFIRE.
THERE WAS NO INVASION.
THAT'S WHAT YOU HAVE TO DO.
SO, EVERY SITUATION IS
DIFFERENT.
SO I WANT TO MAKE SURE I STAY AS
CLOSE AS POSSIBLE TO THE
NONINTERVENTION.
THAT'S WHY I SAY, NO AMERICAN
GROUND TROOPS IN SYRIA OR IRAQ,
SPECIAL FORCES, TRAINERS, YES,
PLANES, TO BOMB, YES, NO GROUND
FORCES.
EVERY PART OF THIS HAS TO BE
DONE IN ACCORDANCE WITH VALUES,
INTERESTS, AND OUR SECURITY IN
PARTNERSHIP WITH OTHER
COUNTRIES.
>> ALL RIGHT.
TWO POINTS OF SECRETARY, TWO
POINTS OF PUSHBACK, ONE GENERAL,
ONE SPECIFIC.
CRITICS WILL SAY THEY SEE THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION WHICH OF
COURSE YOU WERE A PART OF AS
SECRETARY OF STATE AS A PERIOD
WHERE NOW THINGS ARE LESS STABLE
AROUND THE WORLD, CERTAINLY IN
THE WAR ON TERROR.
SPECIFICALLY, SENATOR SANDERS,
EARLIER TONIGHT SAID YES, A LOT
OF EXPERIENCE, BUT DID DOESN'T
ALWAYS TRANSLATE INTO THE BEST
JUDGMENT, AND HE CITED YOUR VOTE
ON THE WAR IN IRAQ.
HOW DO YOU RESPOND TO THOSE TWO
CRITICISMS?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, AFTER I
MUCH LONGER HISTORY THAN ONE
VOTE WHICH I SAID WAS A MISTAKE
BECAUSE OF THE WAY THAT THAT WAS
DONE AND HOW THE BUSH
ADMINISTRATION HANDLED IT.
BUT I THINK THE AMERICAN PUBLIC
HAS SEEN ME EXERCISING JUDGMENT
IN A LOT OF OTHER WAYS, AND IN
FACT, WHEN THAT HARD PRIMARY
CAMPAIGN WAS OVER, AND I WENT TO
WORK FOR PRESIDENT OBAMA AND HE
ENDED UP ASKING ME TO BE
SECRETARY OF STATE, IT WAS
BECAUSE HE TRUSTED MY JUDGMENT.
AND WE WORK SIDE BY SIDE OVER
THOSE FOUR YEARS.
AND THINK ABOUT WHERE WE WERE
WHEN HE BECAME PRESIDENT.
AS I JUST SAID, IRAN ON THE WAY
TO A NUCLEAR WEAPON, WHICH WOULD
HAVE DESTABILIZED THE ENTIRE
MIDDLE EAST, CREATED AN ARMS
RACE, THE LIKE OF WHICH WE HAVE
NEVER SEEN, WE HAVE THUNS OF
THOUSANDS OF AMERICAN TROOPS IN
IRAQ AND AFGHANISTAN.
OUR BEST ALLIES IN FRIENDS IN
EUROPE AND ASIA WERE REALLY PUT
OUT WITH US BECAUSE OF THE WAY
THEY'D BEEN TREATED BY THE BUSH
ADMINISTRATION, AND WERE VERY
SKEPTICAL THAT THE UNITED STATES
WAS A GOOD ALLY ANY LONGER AND
WANTED TO LEAVE THE WORLD TOWARD
PEACE AND PROSPERITY AND
SECURITY.
I SPENT SO MUCH OF MY TIME
GETTING BACK THE CONFIDENCE AND
THE TRUST OF OUR FRIENDS AND
ALLIES AROUND THE WORLD.
SO, I THINK WE MADE A LOT OF
PROGRESS.
NOW, DO WE HAVE A TERRORIST
THREAT?
YES, WE HAVE HAD A TERRORIST
THREAT ON 9/11.
BEFORE PRESIDENT OBAMA TOOK
OFFICE.
YES, WE WERE ATALKED.
SO, THIS IS NOT SOMETHING NEW.
THIS IS A LONG TERM CHALLENGE.
THAT'S WHY I'VE LAID OUT A PLAN
TO DEFEAT ISIS AND THE RADICAL
JIHADIST TERRORIST NETWORKS THAT
I THINK HAS THE BEST CHANCE OF
ACHIEVING THAT.
THERE IS NO TIME IN HUMAN
HISTORY WHERE EVERYTHING IS
GOING WELL.
AND WE NOW LIVE IN A VERY
INTERCONNECTED WORLD WHERE WE
KNOW EVERYTHING THAT IS GOING
ON.
AND WHERE PEOPLE LOOK TO THE
UNITED STATES TO HELP.
SO WE HAVE TO BE LEADING AND
THAT MEANS, WE'VE GOT TO BE
SMART ABOUT HOW WE TRY TO ASSERT
OUR POWER SO THAT IS
CONSTRUCTIVE, MAKES A
DIFFERENCE, AND DOES LEAD TO
GREATER PEACE AND PROSPERITY,
BUT I AM VERY PROUD OF MY RECORD
AS SECRETARY OF STATE AND WHAT
WE ACCOMPLISHED.
NOT ONLY ON SPECIFIC TROUBLE
SPOTS, BUT ADVANCING WOMEN'S
RIGHTS, ADVANCING GAY RIGHTS,
ADVANCING RELIGIOUS FREEDOM,
INTERNET FREEDOM, AND SO MANY OF
THE OTHER VALUES THAT WE HOLD
DEAR.
>> WE HAVE ANOTHER QUESTION FOR
YOU ABOUT THE EXAMPLE THAT THE
UNITED STATES PROVIDES ON OUR
LEFT, ERIN IS AN AMERICAN MUSLIM
FEDERAL OUTSIDE DES MOINES,
SERVED IN THE U.S. AIR FORCE.
SHE'S UNDECIDED, SHE HAS A
QUESTION.
>> HI.
>> HI SECRETARY CLINTON, AMERICA
TODAY IS FORMED BY A VERY
DIVERSE GROUP OF PEOPLE.
AND WITH THE CURRENT RISE IN
ISLAM PHOBIA AND THE BLACK LIVES
MATTER MOVEMENT, HOW CAN WE MAKE
SURE THAT THE UNITED STATES
TODAY IS, THAT WE PROTECT THE
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS OF ALL
GROUPS OF PEOPLE WITH THAT
MARGINALIZING ANY ONE COMMUNITY,
SPECIFICALLY AS A MOTHER OF
THREE YOUNG CHILDREN AS AN
AMERICAN MUSLIM, HOW CAN I MAKE
SURE THAT THIS COUNTRY IS THE
BEST PLACE ON EARTH TO RAISE MY
FAMILY?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU FOR YOUR SERVICE IN
THE MILITARY.
>> IT'S MY PLEASURE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND ONE OF THE --
ONE OF THE MOST DISTRESSING
ASPECTS OF THIS CAMPAIGN HAS
BEEN THE LANGUAGE OF REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES, PARTICULARLY THEIR
FRONT RUNNER, THAT INSULTS
DEMEANS, DENIGRATES DIFFERENT
PEOPLE.
HE HAS CAST A WIDE NET.
HE STARTED WITH MEXICANS, HE'S
CURRENTLY ON MUSLIMS.
BUT I FOUND IT PARTICULARLY
HARMFUL THE WAY THAT HE HAS
TALKED ABOUT MUSLIMS.
AMERICAN MUSLIMS, AND MUSLIMS
AROUND THE WORLD.
AND I HAVE CALLED HIM OUT
CONTINUOUSLY ABOUT THAT.
IT'S NOT ONLY SHAMEFUL AND
CONTRARY TO OUR VALUES, TO SAY
THAT PEOPLE OF A CERTAIN
RELIGION SHOULD NEVER COME TO
THIS COUNTRY OR TO CLAIM THAT
THERE ARE NO REAL PEOPLE OF THE
MUSLIM FAITH WHO SHARE OUR
VALUES, AND WHO HAVE THE KIND OF
DISMISSIVE AND INSULTING
APPROACH.
IT'S NOT ONLY SHAMEFUL AND
OFFENSIVE, WHICH IT IS, I THINK
IT'S DANGEROUS.
AND IT'S DANGEROUS IN SEVERAL
WAYS.
IT'S DANGEROUS BECAUSE AMERICAN
MUSLIMS DESERVE BETTER, AND NOW
THEIR CHILDREN AND THEY ARE THE
TARGET OF ISLAM PHOBIA, OF
THREATS, I'VE MET A NUMBER YOU
HAVE PARENTS WHO HAVE SAID THEIR
CHILDREN ARE AFRAID TO GO TO
SCHOOL BECAUSE THEY ARE WORRIED
ABOUT HOW THEY WILL BE TREATED.
AND WE CANNOT TOLERATE THIS.
AND WE MUST STAND UP AND SAY,
EVERY PERSON IN THIS COUNTRY
DESERVES TO BE TREATED WITH
RESPECT.
AND WE MUST STAND UP AGAINST THE
BULLYING --
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT THERE'S ANOTHER ELEMENT TO
THIS THAT I WANT TO MENTION.
I WAS RECENTLY IN MINNEAPOLIS
WHERE I MET WITH A BIG GROUP OF
SOMALI AMERICANS.
AND I SAT DOWN AND TALKED WITH
THEM AND THEY SHARED SOME OF THE
VERY SAME CONCERNS YOU JUST DID.
BUT THEY ARE ALSO ON THE FRONT
LINES OF TRYING TO PROTECT THEIR
CHILDREN FROM RADICALIZATION,
THEY ARE ON THE FRONT LINES IN
MINNEAPOLIS OF WORKING WITH LAW
ENFORCEMENT TO MAKE SURE THAT
WHAT THEY SEE AND HEAR, THEY
REPORT, IN CASE THERE ARE ANY
PROBLEMS.
WE HAVE TO PROTECT OURSELVES IN
AMERICA IN A UNIFIED WAY.
THAT MEANS MAKING SURE OUR
MUSLIM FRIENDS AND NEIGHBORS ARE
PART OF US.
THEY ARE WITH US.
THEY ARE ON THE FRONT LINES OF
DEFENDING THEMSELVES, THEIR
FAMILIES, THEIR CHILDREN, AND
ALL THE REST OF US.
AND THE SAME IS TRUE WITH
MUSLIMS AROUND THE WORLD.
WE NEED A COALITION THAT
INCLUDES MUSLIM NATIONS TO
DEFEAT ISIS.
AND IT'S PRETTY HARD TO FIGURE
OUT HOW YOU'RE GOING TO MAKE A
COALITION WITH THE VERY NATIONS
YOU NEED, IF YOU SPEND YOUR TIME
INSULTING THEIR RELIGION.
SO, WE NEED TO STAND UP AND
POINT OUT HOW WRONG THIS IS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ALL RIGHT.
WE HAVE ANOTHER QUESTION FOR
YOU, SECRETARY.
MARIA DIAZ, DRAKE LAW SCHOOL
STUDENT WHO SAYS SHE'S DECIDING
BETWEEN YOU AND SENATOR SANDERS.
MARIA, YOU HAVE A QUESTION.
>> HI.
>> GOOD EVENING, SECRETARY.
SECRETARY CLINTON, WHEN YOU ARE
ELECTED THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES, WHAT WILL YOU
SAY TO REPUBLICAN VOTERS?
>> THAT I WANT TO BE THE
PRESIDENT FOR EVERYONE.
AND I BELIEVE THAT IS EXACTLY
WHAT ANY PRESIDENT SHOULD DO.
YOU KNOW, CHRIS CUOMO'S, CHRIS
CUOMO'S FATHER SAID ONE OF THE
SMARTEST THINGS, MANY SMART
THINGS ABOUT POLITICS, YOU
CAMPAIGN IN POETRY, YOU GOVERN
IN PROBES.
YOU KNOW, YOU CAN SAY ALL THE
KINDS OF THINGS YOU WANT IN A
CAMPAIGN, AND WE ARE DRAWING
DISTINCTIONS WITH THE
REPUBLICANS, AND WE SHOULD
BECAUSE I HAVE VERY DEEP
DISAGREEMENTS AS I JUST POINTED
OUT WITH A LOT OF WHAT THEY'RE
SAYING AND DOING.
BUT ONCE THE ELECTION IS OVER,
WE MUST COME TOGETHER TO WORK TO
SOLVE THE PROBLEMS FACING OUR
COUNTRY.
THAT IS WHAT I DID.
I DID IT AS A FIRST LADY WHEN I
WORKED, AS I SAID, TO GET THE
CHILDREN'S HEALTH INSURANCE
PROGRAM.
I DID IT TO REFORM THE FOSTER
CARE AND ADOPTION SYSTEM WITH
ONE OF THE MOST PARTISAN
REPUBLICANS IN THE HOUSE, TOM
DELAY.
I DID IT WHEN I WAS IN THE
SENATE, AND NEARLY EVERY
REPUBLICAN I SERVED WITH
COSPONSORED LEGISLATION THAT I
INTRODUCED AND WE WORKED TO
PASS.
AND I DID IT AS SECRETARY OF
STATE.
REACHING OUT, TALKING WITH
REPUBLICANS ALL THE TIME ABOUT
WHAT WE WERE DOING AND LISTING
THEIR SUPPORT, GETTING THEIR
ADVICE.
SO, I KNOW IN ORDER TO DEAL WITH
THE PROBLEMS I WANT TO, TO GET
THE KMIZ WORKING, CREATING MORE
GOOD JOBS, GETTING INCOMES
RISING, MAKING SURE WE BUILD ON
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, GET
COSTS DOWN, BUT IMPROVE IT, GET
TO 100% COVERAGE, EVERYTHING I
WANT TO DO, I WANT TO START FROM
THE BELIEF THAT WE CAN FIND
COMMON GROUND.
AND THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT I
INTEND TO DO.
AND I SEE MY FRIEND TOM HARKIN
SITTING THERE, AND HE KNOWS FROM
HIS YEARS IN THE CONGRESS, YOU
ALWAYS HAVE TO HOPE YOU CAN FIND
COMMON GROUND.
YOU'VE GOT TO BRING PEOPLE
TOGETHER.
LIKE HE DID.
THE AMERICANS WITH DISABILITIES
ACT, WHAT AN AMAZING
ACCOMPLISHMENT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND --
>> I HAVE A QUESTION FOR YOU AS
A POINT OF PUSHBACK.
YOU WERE TALKING EARLIER ABOUT
HOW IT'S DIFFICULT TO FORM A
COALITION ABOUT BEING INSULTED.
LET'S APPLY THAT TO THE
DEMOCRATS AND REPUBLICANS.
YOU WANT TO WORK WITH THEM, BUT
YOU WERE QUOTED WHEN YOU WERE
LISTING PEOPLE THAT YOU SAW AS
ADVERSARIES, NRA, HEALTH
INSURANCE COMPANIES, PROBABLY
THE REPUBLICANS.
>> YES.
>> THEY DID NOT LIKE THAT WHEN
YOU SAID THAT.
AND IT MAKES THEM FEEL THAT WELL
SECRETARY CLINTON DOESN'T LIKE
US, WHY WOULD SHE WORK US WITH,
UNDERSTANDABLY?
>> WELL, IT WAS TONGUE AND
CHEEK.
AND I CONSIDER THEM WORTHY
ADVERSARIES, BECAUSE THEY ARE,
THEY HAVE THEIR SET OF
OBJECTIVES, WE HAVE OURS ON THE
DEMOCRATIC SIDE.
BUT THAT'S WHY I GAVE YOU A
SHORT OVERVIEW.
I WORKED WITH ALL OF THEM -- YOU
KNOW WHEN I'M ACTUALLY IN
OFFICE, THEY SAY, REALLY NICE
THINGS ABOUT ME.
WE HAVE A WHOLE, LONG LIST OF
THE NICE THINGS THEY SAY, WHAT A
GOOD COLLEAGUE I AM, HOW EASY I
AM TO WORK WITH, HOW WILLING I
AM TO FIND COMMON GROUND, THEN
WHEN I RUN, OH MY GOODNESS, IT'S
UNBELIEVABLE.
SO I HAVE NO -- I HAVE NO
PROBLEM IN SAYING, YEAH, WE HAVE
POLITICAL DIFFERENCES, WE'RE ON
OPPOSITE SIDES, BUT, WEIR GOING
TO WORK AS HARD AS WE CAN.
AND HERE'S WHAT I KNOW ABOUT HOW
TO GET THAT DONE.
IT TAKES BUILDING RELATIONSHIPS,
AND THAT IS ONE OF THE HARDEST
THINGS TO DO IN POLITICS, OVER
IDEOLOGICAL AND PARTISAN LINES.
SO I'M GOING TO BE JUST GIVING
THEM ALL BEAR HUGS WHETHER THEY
LIKE IT OR NOT.
WE'RE GOING TO GET TOGETHER,
WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT ABOUT
WHAT WE CAN DO, MAYBE WE CAN GET
SOMETHING DONE TOGETHER, IF NOT,
MAYBE I CAN FIND THAT SLICE OF
COMMON GROUND TO FIND SOMEBODY
WHO WILL WORK WITH ME ON
ACHIEVING A GOAL THAT WE WANT.
SO, THAT'S THE WAY THE PROCESS
SHOULD WORK.
CONSTANTLY LOOKING FOR WAYS TO
MAKE A DIFFERENCE AND PUTTING
TOGETHER THE COALITIONS WITHIN
THE CONGRESS TO PASS LAWS.
>> SO WHAT IS IT INSIDE YOU THAT
CAN SEPARATE THE HUMAN FEELING
OF DOING THE BENGHAZI HEARINGS,
THEN GOING BACK TO THAT SAME
GROUP OF PEOPLE AND SAYING,
OKAY, YOU KNOW WHAT, LET'S PUT
THAT IN THE PAST?
IT SOUNDS HARD TO DO.
>> WELL, I DON'T KNOW, I CAME
OUT PRETTY WELL, SO I THINK IT'D
BE VERY -- IT WOULD BE VERY
GRACIOUS OF ME TO GO BACK AND
TALK TO THEM.
>> LET'S GET YOU ANOTHER
QUESTION, ZACK PIPER, WEST DES
MOINES, HE'S UNDECIDED.
>> KIND OF ON THE SAME ISSUE AS
THE BEAR HUGS, I THINK ONE TIME
THEY MIGHT HAVE A HARD TIME BEAR
HUGGING WITH THE OTHER SIDE AND
CERTAINLY A CONCERN THAT ARE A
LOT OF DEMOCRATIC VOTERS HAVE AT
THIS POINT AS FAR AS GOING TO
THE GENERAL ELECTION AND LOOKING
FORWARD TO WORKING WITH CONGRESS
IS THE BENGHAZI ISSUE.
SO HOW ARE YOU PLANNING ON
DEALING WITH THAT GOING FORWARD,
NOT ONLY IN THE GENERAL
ELECTION, BUT ALSO IF YOU BECAME
PRESIDENT WORKING WITH CONGRESS.
>> WELL, LOOK, THIS IS ONLY
STILL AN ISSUE BECAUSE THE
REPUBLICANS WANT TO KEEP IT AN
ISSUE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THEY KNOW IT, I KNOW IT, AND I
THINK IT'S VERY EASY TO ANSWER,
AND AS THE GENTLEMAN WHO STOOD
UP BEFORE SAID, IF YOU WATCHED
ANY OF IT, I ANSWERED EVERY
QUESTION.
AND AT THE END OF IT, THE
CHAIRMAN SAID NO, WE DIDN'T
LEARN ANYTHING NEW.
BECAUSE THERE WAS NOTHING NEW TO
LEARN.
WHY?
THERE'D ALREADY BEEN EIGHT
INVESTIGATIONS.
MOST OF THEM BY REPUBLICANS IN
THE CONGRESS.
THE HOUSE INTELLIGENCE
COMMITTEE, THE HOUSE ARMED
SERVICES COMMITTEE.
AND WHAT DID THEY CONCLUDE?
THAT THERE WERE PROBLEMS THAT
NIGHT, BUT, THEY WERE ONES THAT
WE SHOULD LOOK AT, NOT FROM THE
PERSPECTIVE OF PLACING BLAME OR
POINTING FINGERS, BUT HOW DO WE
MAKE SURE THAT NEVER HAPPENS
AGAIN?
THAT IS WHAT I SAID IMMEDIATELY
AFTER IT HAPPENED.
THAT'S WHY I PUT TOGETHER AN
INDEPENDENT BOARD TO TELL ME AS
SECRETARY OF STATE WHAT I NEEDED
TO KNOW, AND WHAT WE COULD DO TO
FIX IT.
AND I ACCEPTED ALL 29 OF THEIR
RECOMMENDATIONS.
AND WE WERE ON THE WAY TO
IMPLEMENTING THEM WHEN I LEFT
AND THAT HAS CONTINUED.
SO I AM WELL AWARE THAT FOR
PARTISAN POLITICAL PURPOSES THIS
CONTINUES, LET ME TELL YOU WHY
THIS MAKES ME -- IT MAKES ME
SAD.
IT MAKES ME SAD BECAUSE WE'VE
HAD, WE'VE HAD TERRORIST
ATTACKS, MANY TIMES BEFORE IN
OUR COUNTRY, HAVEN'T WE?
AND WE'VE HAD AMERICAN,
CIVILIANS AND MILITARY
PERSONNEL, THE SUBJECT OF
ATTACKS.
WHEN RONALD REAGAN WAS PRESIDENT
IN 1983, OUR MARINE BARRACKS,
OUR EMBASSY, WERE ATTACKED IN
BEIRUT.
MORE THAN 250 AMERICANS WERE
KILLED.
THE DEMOCRATS DIDN'T MAKE THAT A
PART SEASON ISSUE.
WE WERE HORRIFIED.
WE WERE HEARTSICK THAT AMERICANS
DOING THE WORK THEY WERE SENT TO
DO, CIVILIANS AND MILITARY WERE
MURDERED BY TERRORISTS.
SO, THE DEMOCRATIC CONGRESS
WORKED WITH THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENT TO SAY WHAT CAN WE DO?
HOW DO WE FIX THIS?
FAST FORWARD, MY HUSBAND WAS
PRESIDENT, AL QAEDA ATTACKED TWO
OF OUR EMBASSIES IN TANZANIA AND
KENYA, CAR BOMBS BLEW THEM UP,
KILLED 12 AMERICANS, AND
HUNDREDS OF KENYANS AND
TANZANIANS,ED ANIMAL LIN
ALBRIGHT WAS SECRETARY, WE HAVE
TO GET TO THE BOTTOM OF THIS.
SHE DID THE SAME AS I DID,
COMMISSION AN INDEPENDENT
REPORT.
WHEN THE REPORT CAME OUT, SHE
MADE IT PUBLIC.
I MADE THE REPORT I COMMISSIONED
PUBLIC.
THAT'S THE ONLY TWO TIMES THOSE
REPORTS HAVE EVER BEEN MADE
PUBLIC.
SO, AGAIN, IT WAS TERRIBLE, WHAT
CAN WE DO?
HOW DO WE FIX IT?
IT WASN'T THE SUBJECT OF THIS
KIND OF PARTISAN, MEDIA-DRIVEN
ATTACK.
PEOPLE WANTED TO COME TOGETHER.
AND EVEN AFTER 9/11 WHEN NEARLY
3,000 AMERICANS AND OTHERS WHO
WERE WORKING IN NEW YORK CITY,
THE PENTAGON, ON THAT PLANE THAT
CRASHED IN PENNSYLVANIA WERE
KILLED, WE FORMED A COMMISSION.
WE SAID WHAT WENT WRONG?
WHAT CAN WE LEARN?
AND THEN WE MOVED ON TO TRY TO
DO BETTER.
SO LOOK, I UNDERSTAND THAT THEY
WILL TRY TO MAKE THIS AN ISSUE.
LY I WILL CONTINUE TO ANSWER YOU
WILL HEAR THE TRUTH FROM NOW
UNTIL I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ON THAT ISSUE, DES MOINES
REGISTER GAVE YOU AN
ENDORSEMENT.
THEY QUESTIONED YOUR JUDGMENT
WHEN IT CAME TO THE E-MAIL
ISSUE, AND YOU KNOW THIS, BUT
FOR THE AUDIENCE IN 2008, QUOTE,
WHEN SHE SAYS, WHEN SHE MAKES A
MISTAKE, JUST SAY SO.
THIS WEEKEND THEY SAID, THAT'S A
LESSON THAT YOU HAVE NOT
LEARNED.
YES, YOU APOLOGIZED, BUT ONLY
WHEN YOU NEEDED TO.
NOT WHEN YOU FIRST COULD HAVE.
FAIR CRITICISM?
>> WELL, I THINK THAT, YOU KNOW,
LOOK, I WAS DELIGHTED TO GET THE
REGISTER'S ENDORSEMENT.
AND IT WAS A VERY GENEROUS ONE.
AND YES, I THINK THAT'S A FAIR
CRITICISM.
YOU KNOW, I, I HAD, I HAD NO
INTENTION OF DOING ANYTHING
OTHER THAN HAVING A CONVENIENT
WAY OF COMMUNICATING AND IT
TURNED OUT NOT TO BE SO
CONVENIENT.
SO AGAIN, WE'VE ANSWERED EVERY
QUESTION AND WE WILL CONTINUE TO
DO SO.
BUT YOU KNOW, MAYBE BEING
FASTER, TRYING TO SCRAMBLE
AROUND TO FIND OUT WHAT ALL OF
THIS MEANS, I PROBABLY SHOULD
HAVE DONE THAT QUICKER.
>> YOU'RE WILLING TO SAY IT WAS
AN ERROR IN JUDGMENT, SHOULD
HAVE APOLOGIZE --
>> NO, I'M NOT SAYING IT WAS AN
ERROR IN JUDGMENT.
NOTHING I DID WAS WRONG.
IT WAS NOT IN ANY WAY
PROHIBITED --
>> NOT APOLOGIZING SOONER --
>> WELL APOLOGIZING SOONER.
AS SOON AS YOU CAN, BUT PART OF
THE PROBLEM, AND I WOULD JUST
SAY THIS AS NOT AN KBUS, BUT AN
EXPLANATION, WHEN YOU'RE FACING
SOMETHING LIKE THAT, YOU'VE GOT
TO GET THE FACTS.
AND IT TAKES TIME TO GET THE
FACTS.
SO WHEN I SAID, HEY, TAKE ALL MY
E-MAILS, MAKE THEM PUBLIC, THAT
HAD NEVER BEEN DONE BEFORE,
EVER, BY ANYBODY.
AND SO WE'VE BEEN SORTING OUR
WAY THROUGH THIS BECAUSE IT IS
KIND OF A UNIQUE SITUATION, I'M
HAPPY PEOPLE ARE LOOKING AT THE
E-MAILS.
SOME OF THEM ARE FRANKLY A
LITTLE, A LITTLE EMBARRASSING.
YOU KNOW, YOU FIND OUT THAT
SOMETIMES I'M NOT THE BEST ON
TECHNOLOGY AND THINGS LIKE THAT,
BUT LOOK, I THINK IT'S GREAT.
LET PEOPLE SORT THEM THROUGH AND
AS WE HAVE SEEN, THERE IS A LOT
OF, YOU KNOW, A LOT OF INTEREST,
TIME TO GET DONE.G THAT TOOK -
>> EARLIER TONIGHT WE PLAYED
SENATOR SANDERS YOUR AD.
>> UH-HUH.
>> ASKED HIM A QUESTION.
ONE OF THE ADS THAT YOU'RE
PUTTING OUT HERE IN THE RUN-UP
TO THE CAUCUSES.
WE'LL DO THE SAME FOR YOU.
HERE'S THE SENATOR'S AD.
¶
NOTES
>> I'M BERNIE SANDERS, AND I
PROOF THIS MESSAGE.
>> I THINK THAT'S GREAT.
I THINK THAT'S FABULOUS.
I LOVED IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU KNOW, LOOK, YOU CAMPAIGN IN
POETRY, YOU GOVERN IN PROS.
AND WE NEED A LOT MORE POETRY IN
THIS CAMPAIGN.
AND IN OUR COUNTRY.
SO, I APPLAUD THAT.
I LOVE THE FEELING.
I LOVE THE ENERGY.
I OBVIOUSLY RESPECT SENATOR
SANDERS GREATLY AND APPRECIATE
WHAT HE HAS DONE IN THIS
CAMPAIGN.
BUT I BELIEVE THAT I'M THE
BETTER PERSON TO BE THE
DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE, AND TO BE
THE PRESIDENT AND COMMANDER IN
CHIEF OF THE COUNTRY BECAUSE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ANOTHER QUESTION FOR YOU.
H'S FROM LOGAN, IOWA, GOING TO
SCHOOL, WORKINGS AS A SUPERVISOR
FOR A JANUARY TOMORROW COMPANY.
SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED, HAS A
QUESTION.
>> GREAT.
>> SECRETARY -- OH, CLINTON,
SORRY.
>> THAT'S OKAY.
>> I CAN SEE WHY THEY GAVE YOU
THIS QUESTION, I JUST WANTED TO
KNOW WHICH OF OUR PREVIOUS
PRESIDENTS HAS INSPIRED YOU MOST
AND WHY.
>> YOU CAN ONLY PICK ONE.
ONE.
YOU CAN PICK.
SORRY.
LET ME JUMP YOUR QUESTION, ONE
PRESIDENT, ONE.
>> OKAY.
>> JUST ONE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> OKAY.
SORRY, PRESIDENT OBAMA, SORRY,
BILL, ABRAHAM LYINCOLNLINCOLN.
YOU KNOW, I -- WOW, WHEN I THINK
ABOUT HIS CHALLENGES, THEY
PALEED IN COMPARISON TO ANYTHING
WE CAN FACE OR IMAGINE, YOU
KNOW, MORE AMERICANS DIED IN THE
CIVIL WAR THAN, YOU KNOW, THE
WARS OF THE 20th CENTURY PUT
TOGETHER.
SO HERE WAS A MAN WHO WAS A REAL
POLITICIAN.
I MEAN, HE WAS A GREAT STATSMAN,
HE UNDERSTOOD POLITICS AND HE
HAD TO WORK TO PUT TOGETHER, THE
SUPPORT HE NEEDED TO BE ABLE TO
HOLD THE COUNTRY TOGETHER DURING
THE WAR, AND WHILE HE WAS
PROSECUTING THAT WAR TO KEEP THE
UNION TOGETHER, HE WAS BUILDING
AMERICA, WHICH I FOUND JUST AN
ASTONISHING PART OF HIS LEGACY.
TRANSCONTINENTAL RAIL SYSTEM,
LAND GRANT COLLEGES, HE WAS
THINKING ABOUT THE FUTURE WHILE
IN THE MIDDLETON OF TRYING TO
DECIDE WHICH GENERAL HE CAN
TRUST TO TRY TO FINISH THE WAR.
THAT'S WHAT I MEAN, WHEN YOU'VE
GOT TO DO A LOT OF THINGS AT
ONCE, WHAT COULD BE MORE
OVERWHELMING THAN TRYING TO WAGE
AND WIN A CIVIL WAR?
AND YET, HE KEPT HIS EYE ON THE
FUTURE AND HE ALSO TRIED TO KEEP
SUMMONING UP THE BETTER ANGELS
WAS OUR NATURE.
YOU KNOW, HE WAS WILLING TO
RECONCILE AND FORGIVE, AND I
DON'T KNOW WHAT OUR COUNTRY
MIGHT HAVE BEEN LIKE HAD HE NOT
BEEN MURDERED, BUT I BET THAT IT
MIGHT HAVE BEEN A LITTLE LESS
RANK REDUCE, A LITTLE MORE
FORGIVING AND TOLERANT THAN
MIGHT POSSIBLY HAVE BROUGHT
PEOPLE BACK TOGETHER.
MORE QUICKLY.
BUT INSTEAD, YOU KNOW, WE HAD
RECONSTRUCTION, WE HAD THE REINS
GRADUATION OF SEGREGATION AND
JIM CROW.
WE HAD PEOPLE IN THE SOUTH
FEELING TOTALLY DISCOURAGED AND
DEFIANT.
SO, I REALLY DO BELIEVE HE COULD
HAVE VERY WELL PUT US ON A
DIFFERENT PATH.
AND, AS I SAY, OUR CHALLENGES
ARE NOTHING LIKE WHAT HE FACED,
BUT LET'S THINK OURSELVES ABOUT
NOT ONLY WHAT WE HAVE TO DO
RIGHT NOW, ESPECIALLY TO GET THE
INCOME RISING IN AMERICA,
ESPECIALLY TO MAKE COLLEGE
AFFORDABLE, DO SOMETHING ABOUT
STUDENT DEBT, KEEP HEALTH CARE
GROWING UNTIL 100% COVERAGE AND
SO MUCH ELSE, BUT LET'S ALSO
THINK ABOUT HOW WE DO TRY TO
SUMMON UP THOSE BETTER ANGELS.
AND TO TREAT EACH OTHER, EVEN
WHEN WE DISAGREE, FUNDAMENTALLY
DISAGREE, TREAT EACH OTHER WITH
MORE RESPECT.
AND AGREE TO DISAGREE MORE
CIVILLY AND TRY TO BE INSPIRED
BY, I THINK, THE GREATEST OF OUR
PRESIDENTS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THANK YOU
VERY MUCH FOR TAKING THE TUNT.
>> GREAT TO SEE YOU.
>> APPRECIATE IT.
>> YOU DOING OKAY?
>> EVERYTHING'S GREAT.
THANK YOU.
WE WANT TO WANT THANK SECRETARY
CLINTON, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY AND
SENATOR SANDERS, AND EVERYONE
WHO MADE THIS TOWN HALL
POSSIBLE.
THANKS TO OUR PARTNERS, THE IOWA
DEMOCRATIC PARTY, AND DRAKE
UNIVERSITY, OF COURSE, AND THANK
YOU ALL, OUR AUDIENCE FOR
WATCHING AND PARTICIPATING.
THE CAUCUSES JUST ONE WEEK FROM
TONIGHT.
WE'LL BE HERE, CNN WILL HAVE
COMPLETE COVERAGE.
I'M CHRIS CUOMO IN DES MOINES,
DON LEMON