>>> AND GOOD EVENING FROM
MILWAUKEE.
EXACTLY ONE WEEK BEFORE
WISCONSIN'S PRESIDENTIAL PRIMARY
IN THE MIDDLE OF A
HISTORY-MAKING RACE FOR THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINATION.
>> TONIGHT, THREE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES FACE THE
VOTERS.
TWO OF THEM FACING OFF LIKE
NEVER SEEN BEFORE.
>> LYIN' TED CRUZ.
>> YOU'RE A SNIVELING COWARD.
>> DONALD TRUMP, TED CRUZ.
FOR THEM, IT'S PERSONAL.
WITH THEIR SPOUSES IN THE MIDDLE
OF THE FIGHT.
>> LEAVE HEIDI THE HELL ALONE.
>> THEY'RE DEFENDING THEIR WIVES
AND TRYING TO WIN OVER A PARTY
THAT'S SKEPTICAL OF BOTH AND
COULD BE PLANNING FOR A
CONTESTED CONVENTION.
>> WE'VE ALWAYS BEEN THE LITTLE
ENGINE THAT CAN.
>> OHIO WINNER JOHN KASICH
TRYING TO PLAY SPOILER.
HE CAN'T WIN ENOUGH DELEGATES TO
WIN OUTRIGHT, BUT HE CAN SEE
HIMSELF WINNING IN A CONTESTED
CONVENTION.
>> I'M THE ONLY PERSON THAT CAN
WIN IN THE FALL.
>> WILL WISCONSIN BE THE NEXT
STEP IN HIS PLAN TO STOP TRUMP
AND CRUZ AND BECOME THE LAST
REPUBLICAN STANDING?
AFTER A PRIMARY LIKE THIS, WILL
THE REPUBLICAN PARTY, ITSELF,
BORN IN WISCONSIN IN 1854, STILL
BE STANDING?
WITH ISIS ATTACKING, THE SUPREME
COURT IN FLUX, AND THE FUTURE UP
FOR GRABS, THE PARTY KNOWS IT
COUNTS.
VOTERS KNOW IT COUNTS.
THE CANDIDATES KNOW IT COUNTS.
>> WISCONSIN IS A BATTLEGROUND.
>> IT'S ALL ON THE LINE IN
WISCONSIN TONIGHT.
THIS IS AN ANDERSON COOPER "360"
CNN REPUBLICAN TOWN HALL.
VOTERS SEEKING ANSWERS BEFORE
MAKING A CHOICE THAT COULD MAKE
HISTORY.
>> AND GOOD EVENING FROM THE
RIVERSIDE THEATER IN MILWAUKEE,
WISCONSIN,S WE'RE SIMULCASTING
LIVE NOW ON CNN, CNNES PAN YOL,
CNN INTERNATIONAL, AND XM SIRIUS
CHANNEL 117.
WE'RE HERE WITH THE THREE
REMAINING REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES.
IN THE AUDIENCE TONIGHT,
REPUBLICANS AND INDEPENDENTS ALL
OF WHOM ARE VOTING IN NEXT
WEEK'S REPUBLICAN PRIMARY.
SOME HAVE ALREADY MADE THEIR
DECISIONS ON A CANDIDATE, OTHERS
STILL UNDECIDED.
THEY CAME UP WITH THE QUESTIONS
YOU'LL HEAR TONIGHT.
WE REVIEWED THEM TO MAKE SURE
THE QUESTIONS DON'T OVERLAP.
I'M GOING TO ASK A FEW QUESTIONS
AS WELL BUT TONIGHT THIS TOWN
HALL IS A CHANCE FOR VOTERS TO
HEAR AT LENGTH FROM THE
CANDIDATES.
SO LET'S GET RIGHT TO IT.
JOINING US RIGHT NOW, THE U.S.
SENATOR FROM TEXAS, PLEASE
WELCOME TED CRUZ.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
HEY, SENATOR, WELCOME.
>> ANDERSON.
>> NICE TO SEE YOU.
HAVE A SEAT.
WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU.
GOOD TO BE WITH YOU.
>> CONGRATULATIONS ON A BIG
ENDORSEMENT FROM THE GOVERNOR OF
THE STATE, SCOTT WALKER.
OBVIOUSLY A BIG THING FOR YOUR
CAMPAIGN.
WE'RE GOING TO HEAR A LOT OF
QUESTIONS TONIGHT FROM THE
VOTERS ON A LOT OF ISSUES.
I WANT TO START BY TALKING TO
YOU ABOUT A COUPLE ISSUES OF THE
DAY.
YOU TALKED A LITTLE BIT TONIGHT
ABOUT DONALD TRUMP'S CAMPAIGN
MANAGER COREY LOO
LEWANDOWSKI.
IF YOU WERE HIS CAMPAIGN
MANAGER, WOULD YOU ASK HIM TO BE
RESIGN?
>> OF COURSE.
IT SHOULDN'T BE COMPLICATED.
MEMBERS OF THE CAMPAIGN STAFF
SHOULD NOT BE PHYSICALLY
ASSAULTING THE PRESS.
I MEAN, THAT SHOULDN'T BE A
COMPLICATED DECISION.
>> I MEAN, HE SAYS SHE'S
INNOCENT OF ALL THE CHARGES.
YOU BELIEVE IT WAS ASSAULT?
>> YOU KNOW, HE'S JUST BEEN
CHARGED.
I KNOW THAT THE REPORTER ALLEGED
THAT SHE WAS PHYSICALLY
ASSAULTED.
THAT -- I WILL SAY IT'S
CONSISTENT WITH A PATTERN OF THE
TRUMP CAMPAIGN.
>> YOU THINK IT SAYS SOMETHING
ABOUT THE CAMPAIGN, ITSELF,
ABOUT THE LEADERSHIP?
>> THE CULTURE OF THE CAMPAIGN
HAS BEEN A CAMPAIGN BUILT ON
ATTACKS, ON INSULTS, AND I THINK
THERE IS NO PLACE IN POLITICS
FOR INSULTS, FOR PERSONAL
ATTACKS, FOR GOING TO THE GUTTER
AND THERE SHOULD BE NO PLACE FOR
PHYSICAL VIOLENCE, EITHER.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU ABOUT THE
PATH AHEAD FOR YOU.
YOU NEED 85% OF THE REMAINING
DELEGATES TO SECURE THE
NOMINATION.
NOT IMPOSSIBLE, BUT HIGHLY
IMPROBABLE.
WILL YOU ADMIT TONIGHT THAT A
CONTESTED CONVENTION IS YOUR
BEST BET TO GET THE NOMINATION?
>> NOT REMOTELY BECAUSE MOST --
>> YOU THINK YOU CAN GET 85% --
>> ABSOLUTELY.
OUR PATH GOING FORWARD IS TO GET
1,237.
MOST OF THE RACES COMING UP ARE
EITHER WINNER TAKE ALL OR WINNER
TAKE MOST.
>> BUT YOU'VE ONLY GOTTEN 30% OF
THE DELEGATES SO FAR.
WE'RE HALF OVER.
>> WELL --
>> HOW DO YOU GO FROM 30% TO
85%?
>> I TELL YOU, WAY YOU DO
THAT -- IT'S THE SITUATION.
IF TWO GUYS ARE HIKING IN THE
WOODS AND A BEAR STARTS CHASING
THEM, YOU KNOW THE OLD JOKE THE
FELLOW SITS DOWN, STARTS TO PUT
ON HIS RUNNING SHOES AND THE GUY
TURNS TO HIS FRIENDS AND SAID,
WHAT ARE YOU DOING?
YOU CAN'T OUTRUN THE BEAR.
THE GUY SAY, I DON'T HAVE TO
OUTRUN THE BEAR, I HAVE TO J
OUTRUN YOU.
THAT PRINCIPLE IS THE SAME THING
GOING FORWARD, IF WE CONTINUE TO
BEAT DONALD TRUMP, YOU KNOW, WE
JUST HAD A FEW DAYS AGO IN UTAH
A MASSIVE VICTIMORY AGAINST DOND
TRUMP AND GOT ALL THE DELEGATES
IN UTAH.
IF WE CONTINUE TO BEAT DONALD
TRUMP GOING FORWARD, MOST OF THE
STATES ARE WINNER TAKE ALL OR
WINNER TAKE MOST AND WE GET
NORTH OF 80% OF THE DELEGATES,
SIMPLY BY BEATING DONALD TRUMP
GOING FORWARD.
>> DONALD TRUMP IS STILL WAY OUT
AHEAD OF YOU.
HE WON LOUISIANA.
YOU GOT MORE DELEGATES OUT OF
LOUISIANA WHICH HE IS OBVIOUSLY
UPSET ABOUT.
85% IN THE REMAINING RACES IS
MORE THAN YOU'VE EVER GOTTEN
ANYWHERE.
>> BUT YOU DON'T HAVE TO WIN
85%, ANDERSON.
THE WAY IT WORKS, YOU HAVE TO
WIN THE RACES GOING FORWARD BUT
WHEN YOU WIN, YOU GET MOST OF
ALL THE DELEGATES.
HERE'S THE DYNAMIC THAT PLAYED
OUT.
A YEAR AGO THERE WERE 17
CANDIDATES.
FANT
FANTASTIC, DIVERSE, FIELD.
THE FIELD HAS NARROWED NOW.
WHAT DONALD BENEFITS FROM IS
DIVISION BECAUSE DONALD HAS HAD
PRETTY CONSISTENTLY A FLOOR OF
ABOUT 20% TO 25% BUT HE'S GOT A
HARD CEILING OF ABOUT 35% TO 40%
THAT HE HAS A REAL HARD TIME
BREAKING.
AND SO WHEN THERE ARE TWO OR
THREE OR FOUR OTHER CANDIDATES
AND THEY DIVIDE THE VOTE, HE CAN
WIN STATE AFTER STATE WITH 30%,
35%, EVEN 40%, HEAD TO HEAD,
DONALD HAS AN INCREDIBLY
DIFFICULT TIME BREAKING 50%.
>> THE KASICH CAMPAIGN HAS MADE
AN EFFORT TO REACH OUT TO YOUR
CAMPAIGN TO STRIKE SOME SORT OF
A PACK IN ORDER TO DEFEAT DONALD
TRUMP.
WOULDN'T THAT MAKE SENSE?
APPARENTLY ALL THE REPORTS ARE
SO FAR YOU'VE NOT RESPONDED.
>> IT MAKES NO SENSE AT ALL.
JOHN KASICH HAS TO PATH TO WIN.
WE'RE COMPETING TO WIN.
WE'RE NOT COMPETING TO STOP
TRUMP.
WE'RE COMPETING TO WIN THE
NOMINATION.
JOHN KASICH WENT 0 FOR 27.
LOST 27 STATES IN A ROW.
>> HE ADMITS IT'S GOING TO GO TO
A CONTESTED CONVENTION, THAT'S
WHERE HE SAYS HE CAN WIN.
>> I UNDERSTAND, EXCEPT IT'S
AGAINST THE RULES FOR JOHN
KASICH TO BE ON THE BALLOT.
THE RULES APPLY IN ORDER TO BE
ON THE BALLOT IF NO ONE HAS
1,237 YOU HAVE TO HAVE WON AT
LEAST 8 STATES.
NOW, THERE ARE ONLY TWO
CANDIDATES WHO ARE GOING TO MEET
THAT THRESHOLD, DONALD TRUMP AND
ME.
OUR PREFERRED OPTION IS WIN
1,237 DELEGATES BEFORE THE
CONVENTION.
WE ARE WORKING HARD TO DO THAT
AND I'LL MENTION WISCONSIN'S
GOING TO BE CRITICAL IN THAT,
BUT THE SECOND OPTION, WHICH IS
ENTIRELY POSSIBLE, WE COULD GET
TO A CONVENTION WHERE NOBODY HAS
1,237 DELEGATES AND WE COME IN
WITH A TON OF DELEGATES, DONALD
TRUMP COMES IN WITH A TON OF
DELEGATES AND IF THAT HAPPENS,
THEN IT BECOMES A BATTLE FOR THE
DELEGATES, BUT THE ONLY TWO
NAMES ON THE BALLOT ARE GOING TO
BE DONALD TRUMP AND ME.
ON THE RULES, THOSE ARE THE ONLY
TWO PEOPLE THAT CAN BE VOTED ON.
I THINK IN THAT SITUATION, WE'RE
IN A VERY STRONG POSITION TO
EARN THE 1,237 VOTES FROM THE
DELEGATES ELECTED BY THE PEOPLE.
>> I WANT TO TALK ABOUT POLICY.
IN THE WAKE OF THE HORRIBLE
ATTACKS WE SAW IN BRUSSELS, YOU
PROPOSED SECURING OUR BORDERS,
CRUSHING ISIS, STOPPING
REFUGEES.
YOU ALSO STUGGESTED LAW
ENFORCEMENT PATROL MUSLIM
NEIGHBORHOODS BEFORE THEY BECOME
RADICALIZED.
JOHN KASICH SAID, QUOTE, WHAT WE
WANT TO DO IS START POLICING
MUSLIM NEIGHBORHOODS, CREATE
MORE DIVISIONS, START POLICING
NEIGHBORHOODS IN LACROSSE?
THIS IS POLITICS TRYING TO
APPEAL TO PEOPLE'S BASE
INSTINCTS AND FEARS.
IS THAT WHAT YOU'RE DOING?
>> WHAT I BELIEVE WE SHOULD DO,
WE NEED A COMMANDER IN CHIEF
WHO'S FOCUSED ON KEEPING THIS
COUNTRY SAFE.
>> WHAT DOES IT MEAN PATROL AND
SECURE MUSLIM NEIGHBORHOODS?
HOW DO YOU DECIDE --
>> LET ME ANSWER YOUR QUESTION.
WE HAD A TERROR ATTACK IN
BRUSSELS LAST WEEK.
IT WAS A HORRIFIC ATTACK.
PRESIDENT OBAMA COULD BARELY BE
BOTHERED TO STOP HIS BASEBALL
GAME WITH COMMUNIST DICTATORS TO
SAY ANYTHING ABOUT IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND WHEN HE DID, HE FOLLOWED
THIS BIZARRE PATTERN THAT HE HAS
FOLLOWED FOR YEAR AFTER YEAR
AFTER YEAR WHERE HE REFUSES TO
SAY THE WORDS "RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM."
INSTEAD WHAT HE DOES, WHAT HE
DID AFTER THE PARIS TERROR
ATTACK, WHAT HE DID AFTER SAN
BERNARDINO IS HE GOES ON
TELEVISION AND HE LECTURES
AMERICANS ABOUT ISLAMOPHOBIA.
ENOUGH IS ENOUGH.
HOW ABOUT A PRESIDENT THAT
ACTUALLY STANDS UP AND DEFENDS
THIS COUNTRY?
WE NEED A COMMANDER --
>> WHAT DOES THAT MEAN PATROL
MUSLIM NEIGHBORHOODS?
>> WHAT IT MEANS IS THAT WE
TARGET THE ENEMY.
NOW, THERE IS A DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN ISLAM AND ISLAMISM.
ISLAMISM IS A POLITICAL AND
THEOCRATIC PHILOSOPHY THAT
COMMANDS ITS ADHERENCE TO WAGE
VIOLENT JIHAD, TO MURDER OR TO
FORCIBLY CONVERT ALL INFIDELS.
BY INFED DELLS, I MEAN EVERY ONE
OF THE REST OF US.
ISLAMISM IS OUR ENEMY.
WHEN PRESIDENT OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON AND THE MODERN
DEMOCRATIC PARTY PLAY THIS
POLITICALLY CORRECT GAME OF
DENYING IT, IT MEANS THEY DON'T
FIGHT IT EFFECTIVELY.
FOR EXAMPLE, LET'S TALK ABOUT
THE CONSEQUENCES OF IT.
OBAMA AND HILLARY BOTH ADVOCATE
BRINGING TENS OF NOWS OF SYRIAN
MUSLIM REFUGEES --
>> YOU WANT TO STOP THAT, BUT
YOU DID TALK ABOUT PATROLLING
MUSLIM NEIGHBORHOODS.
>> SURE, ABSOLUTELY.
>> A LOT OF FOLKS Y, YOU KEPT
SAYING THAT WORKED IN NEW YORK,
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS MADE THE
POLICE SOLVE THAT.
CHIEF BRATTON SAYS THAT COMPLETE
BUNK.
I WANT TO READ YOU WHAT, IN
FACT -- THE GUY WHO RAN THAT
PROGRAM YOU SAY WAS SUCH A BIG
SUCCESS SAYS IT DIDN'T LEAD TO
ANY PROSECUTIONS, THERE WERE NO
LEADS FROM IT.
>> LISTEN, YOU ARE RIGHT THAT
AFTER I CALLED FOR INCREASED
VIGILANCE PROTECTING US THAT
BARACK OBAMA, HILLARY CLINTON,
AND NEW YORK'S MAYOR BILL de
BLASIO ALL ATTACKED ME.
I WEAR THAT AS A BADGE OF PRIDE.
I'M NOT GOING TO APOLOGIZE --
>> BILL BRATTON, WORKED FOR RUDY
GIULIANI.
>> I UNDERSTAND THE COMMISSIONER
WHO WORKS FOR BILL de BLASIO HAS
A POLITICAL IMPERATIVE.
de BLASIO IS A LEFT-WING
RADICAL.
>> THE COMMANDER WHO OVERSAW THE
VERY PROGRAM THAT YOU CLAIM WAS
A SUCCESS IN NEW YORK TESTIFIED
UNDER OATH THAT IT DIDN'T LEAD
TO ANY INVESTIGATIONS IN THE SIX
YEARS.
>> ANDERSON, IN NEW YORK, THIS
WAS A SUCCESSFUL PROGRAM.
SET UP UNDER MAYOR MICHAEL
BLOOMBERG TO MONITOR AND TO WORK
COOPERATIVELY WITH THE MUSLIM
COMMUNITY TO PREVENT
RADICALIZATION AND TO STOP
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM
PLOTS --
>> CAN YOU NAME ONE CASE --
>> THERE ARE A NUMBER OF CASES.
IDENTIFIED A BOOKSTORE THAT WAS
A LOCUST FOR RADICALIZATION AND
ALLOWED LAW ENFORCEMENT TO GO
AFTER THAT BOOKSTORE AND WHAT
HAPPENED WAS WHEN MAYOR BILL de
BLASIO GOT ELECTED, HE GAVE IN
TO POLITICAL CORRECTNESS AND
SHUT THE UNIT DOWN.
LISTEN, IF YOU WANT TO STOP
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM, THE
ANSWER ISN'T TO GO HANG OUT IN
RANDOM NEIGHBORHOODS.
IT IS, INSTEAD, TO FOCUS ON
COMMUNITIES ARE RADICALIZATION
IS A RISK.
I'LL TELL YOU WHAT EUROPE HAS
DONE.
EUROPE HAS FOLLOWED THE PATH
THAT BARACK OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON WANT TO PUT US ON THAT
THE TRAGEDIES, THESE TERROR
ATTACKS IN EUROPE ARE A RESULT
OF FAILED IMMIGRATION POLICIES
WHERE THEY'VE ALLOWED VAST
NUMBERS OF ISLAMIC TERRORISTS TO
COME INTO EUROPE AND THEY'RE IN
COMMUNITIES THAT ARE ISOLATED.
THEY'RE CALLED NO H-GO
COMMUNITIES WHERE THE LAW
ENFORCEMENT DOESN'T ENGAGE IN
THOSE COMMUNITIES.
ONE IN BRUSSELS, MOLENBEEK HAS
BEEN AN INCUBATOR FOR RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
MANY OF THESE TERRORIST PLOTS
TRACE BACK TO MOLENBEEK.
MY PLAN IS VERY SIMPLE.
AMERICA SHOULD NOT MAKE THE
MISTAKES OF EUROPE.
WE SHOULD NOT DISENGAGE.
WE SHOULD HAVE LAW ENFORCEMENT
ACTIVELY ENGAGE TO STOP
RADICALIZATION BEFORE IT
STOPS -- AND I RECOGNIZE THAT
THE MEDIA AND THE DEMOCRATS HATE
IT WHEN SOMEONE ACTUALLY
DESCRIBES WHO THE ENEMY IS.
I'LL TELL YOU AS PRESIDENT,
EVERY SINGLE DAY, I WILL WAKE UP
FIGHTING RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM AND WORKING TO DEFEAT
IT.
>> TURNING BACK TO THE CAMPAIGN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IT'S OBVIOUSLY BEEN A VERY ROUGH
AND TUMBLE WEEK BETWEEN YOU AND
DONALD TRUMP.
A SALACIOUS STORY ABOUT YOU WAS
PUBLISHED IN "NATIONAL
ENQUIRER."
YOU SAY DONALD TRUMP, PEOPLE
AROUND HIM WERE RESPONSIBLE FOR
PLANTING THAT STORY.
DO YOU HAVE PROOF OF THAT?
>> SURE.
THE STORY ON ITS FACE QUOTED ONE
PERSON ON THE RECORD, ROGER
STONE.
>> FORMER ADVISER --
>> ROGER STONE HAS BEEN DONALD
TRUMP'S CHIEF POLITICAL ADVISER.
HE PLANNED AND RAN HIS
PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN AND HE'S
BEEN HIS HATCHET MAN.
HE SPENT 40 YEARS AS A HATCHET
MAN BUT NOT ONLY THAT, THE HEAD
OF THE "NATIONAL ENQUIRER," GUY
NAMED DAVID PEICKER, IS GOOD
FRIENDS WITH DONALD TRUMP.
>> YOU DON'T KNOW THAT HE
PLANTED THAT STORY.
>> THE "NATIONAL ENQUIRER" IN
ITS HISTORY NEVER ENDORSED A
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE UNTIL
DONALD TRUMP.
NOW, DONALD TRUMP SUGGESTED THE
HEAD OF THE "NATIONAL ENQUIRER"
SHOULD TAKE OVER "TIME"
MAGAZINE.
WHO IN THEIR RIGHT MIND SHOULD
SUGGEST THE HEAD OF THE
"NATIONAL ENQUIRER" SHOULD TAKE
OVER "TIME" MAGAZINE?
>> EARLY ON IN THE CAMPAIGN IT
SEEMS LIKE YOU MADE A POLITICAL
CALCULATION NOT TO GO AFTER HIM.
JUST LAST WEEK ON A RADIO
PROGRAM, YOU SAID ESSENTIALLY
THOSE CANDIDATES WHO WENT AFTER
HIM EARLY ON WERE ROAD KILL, YOU
NEEDED TO BUILD YOUR BASE.
BACK IN DECEMBER YOU TWEETED
"THE ESTABLISHMENT'S ONLY HOPE,
TRUMP AND ME IN A CAGE MATCH,
SORRY TO DISAPPOINT, DONALD
TRUMP IS TERRIFIC."
THAT WAS AFTER HE'D ALREADY MADE
FUN OF CARLY FIORINA'S FACE,
AFTER HE'D GONE AFTER MEGYN
KELLY.
AT THAT POINT, DID YOU REALLY
BELIEVE DONALD TRUMP WAS
TERRIFIC?
>> WHAT I KNEW WAS THE MEDIA WAS
EN DA
ENGAGED IN A LOVE FEST.
>> SOUNDS LIKE YOU WERE ENGAGED
IN A LOVE FEST.
>> HOW MANY HOURS OF FREE MEDIA
DO CNN, FOX, OTHER STATIONS, LET
YOU CALL IN --
>> WE ASKED YOU FOR INTERVIEWS
PRETTY MUCH EVERY DAY AND
DECLINED EVERY OFFER ON MY
PROGRAM.
>> I'LL POINT OUT I'VE BEEN
INVITING DONALD TRUMP FOR
SEVERAL DAYS TO COME AND MAKE
THIS DEBATE.
HE'S COMING LATER AND HE'S
TERRIFIED TO MAKE IT A DEBATE
BECAUSE HE DOESN'T WANT TO
ACTUALLY STAND AND HAVE HIS
RECORD CHALLENGED.
>> WHEN YOU CALLED HIM TERRIFIC
BACK IN DECEMBER, DID YOU
BELIEVE THAT OR WAS THAT
POLITICAL CALCULATION?
>> LET ME MAKE A POINT.
THERE'S BEEN A DISTINCTION I
HAVE FOLLOWED THROUGHOUT WHICH
IS I KEEP THE FOCUS ON ISSUES
AND SUBSTANCE.
I'M HOPE TO DRAW A DISTINCTION
WITH DONALD TRUMP ON THE ISSUES,
WHETHER IT IS ECONOMIC POLICY
THAT HE DOESN'T HAVE A POLICY TO
BRING JOBS BACK TO AMERICA,
WHETHER IT IS NATIONAL SECHE IS
ADVOCATING FOR A FAR TOO WEAK
FOREIGN POLICY THAT LEAVES US
VULNERABLE.
WHAT I'M NOT INTERESTED IN DOING
IS WHAT DONALD'S PATTERN HAS
BEEN, THE PERSONAL ATTACKS, IT'S
GOING TO THE GUTTER, IT'S
ATTACKING FAMILY MEMBERS.
NONE OF THAT HAS ANY PLACE IN
POLITICS.
WE OUGHT TO BE DISCUSSING TAX
POLICY, OUGHT TO BE DISCUSSING
NATIONAL SECURITY.
OUGHT TO BE DISCUSSING
SUBSTANCE, NOT ENGAGE --
>> LET'S DO THAT RIGHT NOW.
LET'S GO TO OUR FIRST MEMBER OF
THE AUDIENCE.
THIS IS THOMAS DOUGHERTY, A
STUDENT FROM BOOKFIELD WHO SAYS
HE'S STILL MAKING UP HIS MIND.
YOU COULD PICK UP A VOTE HERE.
>> HI, THOMAS.
>> HI, SENATOR CRUZ.
MY QUESTION FOR YOU, HOW AND WHY
DOES YOUR RELIGION PLAY A PART
IN YOUR POLITICAL
DECISION-MAKING?
DON'T YOU THINK IT SHOULD BE
MORE OF A MORAL BELIEF AND NOT
SOMETHING THAT COULD INTERFERE
WITH YOUR DECISION-MAKING WHEN
YOU'RE MAKING DECISIONS FOR ALL
RELIGIONS IN THE UNITED STATES?
>> WELL, THOMAS, THANK YOU FOR
THAT QUESTION.
ME, MANY PEOPLE IN AMERICA, MY
FAITH IS AN INTEGRAL PART OF WHO
I AM.
I'M A CHRISTIAN.
I'M NOT GOING TO HIDE THAT AND
TREAT IT LIKE IT'S SOMETHING YOU
CAN'T ADMIT PUBLICLY AND
ACKNOWLEDGE IT'S AN IMPORTANT
PART OF WHO YOU ARE.
I ALSO THINK THOSE IN POLITICS
HAVE AN OBLIGATION NOT TO WEAR
THEIR FAITH ON THEIR SLEEVE.
THERE HAVE BEEN FAR TOO MANY
POLITICIANS THAT RUN AROUND
BEHAVING LIKE THEY'RE HOLIER
THAN THOU, AND I'LL TELL YOU, MY
ATTITUDE AS A VOTER WHEN SOME
POLITICIAN STANDS UP AND SAYS
I'M RUNNING BECAUSE GOD TOLD ME
TO VOTE -- TO RUN, MY REACTION
AS A VOTER IS, GREAT, WHEN GOD
TELLS ME TO VOTE FOR YOU, WE'LL
BE ON THE SAME PAGE.
AND SO, LISTEN, I'M NOT ASKING
YOU TO DEVOTE FOR ME BECAUSE OF
MY PERSONAL FAITH WITH JESUS
CHRIST.
I'M ASKING YOU TO VOTE FOR ME
BECAUSE I'VE SPENT A LIFETIME
FIGHTING TO DEFEND THE
CONSTITUTION AND BILL OF RIGHTS,
FIGHTING TO DEFEND THE AMERICAN
FREE ENTERPRISE SYSTEM AND WE
NEED A LEADER WHO WILL STAND UP
EVERY DAY AND PROTECT THE RIGHTS
OF EVERYONE, WHETHER THEY'RE
CHRISTIANS OR JEWS OR MUSLIMS OR
ANYONE ELSE.
THE BILL OF RIGHTS PROTECTS ALL
AMERICANS.
IT PROTECTS ATHEISTS.
THAT'S THE BEAUTY OF THE BILL OF
RIGHTS IS THAT WE HAVE THE
FREEDOM TO SEEK OUT GOD, TO
WORSHIP AND TO LIVE ACCORDING TO
OUR FAITH AND OUR CONSCIENCE AND
I THINK THE CONSTITUTION AND
BILL OF RIGHTS IS A UNIFYING
PRINCIPLE THAT CAN BRING US
TOGETHER ACROSS FAITHS, ACROSS
RACES, ACROSS ETHNICITY.
AND WE NEED TO COME TOGETHER
BEHIND THE UNIFYING PRINCIPLES
THAT BUILT AMERICA.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WANT YOU TO MEET -- THIS IS
TIM MATSON.
HIS SON, JORDAN, TRAVELED TO
SYRIA IN 2014, FOUGHT ALONGSIDE
KURDISH FORCES TAKING ON ISIS.
TIM SAYS HE IS UNDECIDED.
TIM, WELCOME.
>> SENATOR, WHEN JORDAN LEFT FOR
SYRIA, I WAS FURIOUS WITH HIM.
I COULDN'T UNDERSTAND HOW HE
COULD DO THIS.
THEN I FOLLOWED HIS STEPS ON THE
INTERNET AND SAW THE MASS
MURDERS AND BEHEADINGS,
SOMETIMES OF YOUNG CHILDREN AND
I UNDERSTOOD.
I KNOW WE CAN'T BE POLICE OF THE
WORLD BUT THERE'S LINES THAT
HAVE BEEN CROSSED THAT NO
CIVILIZED NATION SHOULD IGNORE.
WE HAVE A NATION THAT'S OFTEN
SAID, NEVER AGAIN, BUT THERE
AGAIN, HERE WE ARE.
AS COMMANDER IN CHIEF, WILL YOU
SEND AN OVERWHELMING FORCE WITH
UNRESTRICTED USE OF POWER TO
OBLITERATE ISIS AND SEND A
MESSAGE TO THOSE WHO WANT TO DO
EVIL UPON THE INNOCENCE OF THEIR
FAITH IN THEY DO THIS?
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR SON,
JORDAN, SERVING AND THANK YOU
FOR HIS SACRIFICE.
YOU KNOW, THE QUESTION OF WHEN
TO COMMIT U.S. ARMED FORCES TO
COMBAT IS THE MOST SERIOUS
DECISION ANY PRESIDENT CAN MAKE.
AND I BELIEVE THE DECISION TO
USE MILITARY FORCE SHOULD BE
KEYED TO THE VITAL NATIONAL
SECURITY INTEREST OF THIS
COUNTRY.
FAR TOO OFTEN WE'VE SEEN IN THE
LAST SEVEN YEARS WHERE PRESIDENT
OBAMA HAS NOT FOCUSED ON OUR
NATIONAL SECURITY INTERESTS.
SO, FOR EXAMPLE, WE SAW IN LIBYA
MOAMMAR GADHAFI, THE DICTATOR
THERE, WAS A BAD MAN.
HE HAD A HORRIBLE HUMAN RIGHTS
RECORD.
HE HAD BEEN A STATE SPONSOR OF
TERRORISTS.
BUT GADHAFI IN HIS LATTER YEARS
ACTUALLY SHAPED UP HIS CONDUCT
PRETTY DRAMATICALLY IN RESPONSE
TO U.S. STRENGTH AND HAD BECOME
AN ACTIVE PARTICIPANT WORKING
WITH AMERICA STOPPING RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISTS.
TRACKING THEM DOWN, APPREHENDING
THEM, HANDING THEM OVER TO US.
AND WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA AND
HILLARY CLINTON DID IS THEY
ENDED UP JOINING WITH AND
LEADING MANY WORLD FORCES IN
TOPPLING GADHAFI, ULTIMATELY
KILLING GADHAFI AND THE
CONSEQUENCE IN LIBYA IS THAT
COUNTRY WAS HANDED OVER TO
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISTS.
IT'S BECOME A WAR ZONE OF
BATTLING WAR LORDS.
>> THE QUESTION IS ABOUT U.S.
TROOPS, THOUGH, U.S. FORCES ON
THE GROUND TO DEFEAT ISIS.
>> I UNDERSTAND.
I'M ANSWERING THE QUESTION,
ANDERSON.
THANK YOU.
THAT WAS AN ENORMOUS MISTAKE.
AND THE REASON THEY MADE THE
MISTAKE IS THEY WEREN'T FOCUSED
ON U.S. NATIONAL SECURITY
INTERESTS.
THEY WERE IN THE INTEREST OF
PROMOTING DEMOCRACY AND TOPPLING
A GOVERNMENT THAT ENDS UP
HANDING IT OVER TO RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISTS IS A MUCH
WORSE OUTCOME.
WE SAW A SIMILAR THING IN EGYPT
WHERE OBAMA AND HILLARY BOTH
CHEERED THE TOPPLING OF HOSNI
MUBARAK, THE HEAD OF EGYPT.
EGYPT WAS HANDED OVER TO THE
MUSLIM BROTHER HE'D.
MUHAMMAD MORSI.
IT'S A TERRORIST ORGANIZATION.
THAT WAS PROFOUNDLY HARMFUL FOR
U.S. NATIONAL SECURITY
INTERESTS.
THANKFULLY PRESIDENT AL SISSI IS
IN CHARGE OF EUROPE.
WITH REGARD TO SYRIA, ASSAD IS A
MONSTER.
I AGREE WITH YOU.
HE'S A HORRIBLE MAN.
HE HAS MURDERED HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF HIS OWN CITIZENS.
HE'S MURDERED WOMEN.
HE'S MURDERED CHILDREN.
HE'S USED CHEMICAL WEAPONS
AGAINST THEM.
BUT THE PROBLEM IS, IF WE SIMPLY
TOPPLE ASSAD, THE MOST LIKELY
OUTCOME IS THAT ISIS TAKES OVER
SYRIA.
AND HANDSING SYRIA OVER TO ISIS
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISTS
WAGING WAR WITH US IS A MISTAKE.
YOUR QUESTION OF WHAT WE SHOULD
DO, OUR FOCUS, I BELIEVE, IN
SYRIA SHOULD NOT BE ON TOPPLING
ASSAD.
OUR FOCUS SHOULD BE ON UTTERLY
AND COMPLETELY DESTROYING ISIS
BECAUSE ISIS IS OUR ENEMY AND
ISIS DECLARED WAR ON AMERICA AND
POSE A DIRECT THREAT TO OUR
NATIONAL SECURITY INTERESTS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> IN ORDER TO TOPPLE ISIS,
WOULD YOU BE -- I MEAN, HIS
QUESTION IS SENDING AN
OVERWHELMING GROUND FORCE.
WOULD YOU BE WILLING TO SEND
U.S. TROOPS ON THE GROUND?
NOT JUST SPECIAL FORCES AS IS
CURRENTLY BEING DONE.
>> LOOK, I WILL DO WHATEVER IS
NECESSARY MILITARILY TO DEFEAT
ISIS.
NOW, DEFEATING ISIS IS GOING TO
HAVE A LOT OF COMPONENTS.
ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT
COMPONENTS IS OVERWHELMING AIR
POWER.
>> YOU'VE TALKED ABOUT CARPET
BOMBING AND JUST RECENTLY YOU
SAID "CARPET BOMB THEM INTO
OBLIVION."
LIEUTENANT GENERAL BROWN JR.
SAID CARPET BOMBING IS NOT
EFFECTIVE FOR THE OPERATION THAT
WE'RE ACTUALLY EXECUTING BECAUSE
WE'RE USING PRECISION-GUIDED
MUNITIONS ON A REGULAR BASIS
AND, IN FACT, CARPET BOMBING
CIVILIAN AREAS IS A VIOLATION OF
THE GENEVA CONVENTIONS.
>> NOBODY HAS TALKED ABOUT
TARGETING CIVILIAN AREAS.
WHAT I HAVE SUGGESTED WE SHOULD
DO IS USE OVERWHELMING AIR
POWER.
LET'S TALK SOME SPECIFICS.
>> WHAT DOES CARPET BOMBING
MEAN?
>> I'M TRYING TO ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION, ANDERSON.
>> FOR EFFECT, ISIS IS IN MANY
CIVILIAN AREAS.
>> LET'S TALK SPECIFIC FACTS.
THE FIRST PERSIAN GULF WAR, A
LITTLE OVER 25 YEARS AGO, WE
WERE LAUNCHING ROUGHLY 1,100 AIR
ATTACKS A DAY.
WE WERE USING OVERWHELMING
AIRPOWER.
IT'S ONE OF THE GREAT STRENGTHS
OF THE TREMENDOUS AMERICAN
MILITARY IS OUR AIR SUPERIORITY
IS SECOND TO NONE.
RIGHT NOW, TODAY, OBAMA IS
LAUNCHING BETWEEN 15 AND 30 AIR
ATTACKS A DAY.
>> BUT --
>> HOLD ON.
LET ME MAKE MY POINT, SIR.
IF YOU COMPARE THOSE NUMBERS, WE
DID THAT FOR 37 DAYS THEN OUR
TROOPS WENT IN AND IN A DAY AND
A HALF MOPPED UP WHAT WAS LEFT
OF THE IRAQI ARMY.
IT DOES CRUSHING DEBILITATING
DAMAGE.
15 TO 30 A DAY IS PHOTO OP
FOREIGN POLICY.
>> I TALKED TO COMMANDERS WHO
ACTUALLY DID THE AIR CAMPAIGN
WHO SAID, LOOK, IT'S EASY WHEN
YOU'RE TRYING TO TAKE OUT -- NOT
EASY, IT'S ONE THING WHEN YOU
TAKE OUT THE MILITARY, BOMB
THEIR COMPLEX, BOMB FACTORIES,
BOMB THEIR CENTERS OF COMMAND
AND CONTROL, YOU CAN BOMB
BARRACKS.
ISIS IS A COMPLETELY DIFFERENT
KIND OF ENEMY.
>> YOU CAN USE ALL OF THOSE
TOOLS SO YOU CAN TAKE OUT
COMMAND AND CONTROL
HEADQUARTERS, TAKE OUT THEIR
COMMUNICATION, YOU CAN TAKE OUT
THEIR MEANS OF TRANSPORTATION,
INGRESS AND EGRESS.
YOU CAN TAKE OUT THEIR OIL
FIELDS.
REFINING CAPACITY.
YOU CAN TAKE OUT THEIR
INFRASTRUCTURE.
YOU CAN TARGET THEIR TROOPS AND
THEIR TROOP MOVEMENTS.
AND WE'RE NOT DOING THAT RIGHT
NOW.
OVERWHELMING AIRPOWER IS THE
FIRST STEP, IT'S NOT THE ONLY
STEP, BUT OVERWHELMING AIRPOWER
IS THE FIRST STEP.
THE NEXT STEP IS ARMING THE
KURDS.
THE KURDS, THE PESHMERGA,
FIGHTING FORCES OF THE KURDS ARE
EFFECTIVE FIGHTERS.
THEY'RE LONGTIME ALLIES OF
AMERICA.
THEY'RE FIGHTING ISIS.
ISIS IS USING U.S. MILITARY
EQUIPMENT THAT THEY SEIZED IN
IRAQ.
THE KURDS ARE USING EQUIPMENT
AND THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION
REFUSES TO ARM THEM BECAUSE OF
POLITICAL REASONS.
THAT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE.
WE OUGHT TO BE ARMING THE KURDS
AND LET THEM KILL ISIS AND
BEYOND THAT THE QUESTION OF
SPECIAL FORCES AND GROUND
TROOPS.
WE SHOULD DO WHATEVER IS
NECESSARY TO WIN, BUT I'LL TELL
YOU WHAT I WON'T DO IS I WILL
NOT SEND OUR TROOPS INTO COMBAT
THE WAY BARACK OBAMA IS DOING
WITH RULES OF ENGAGEMENT SO
STRICT THAT THEY CANNOT FIGHT,
THEY CANNOT WIN AND THEY CANNOT
DEFEAT THE ENEMY.
IF WE'RE GOING TO USE OUR
TROOPS, WE'RE GOING TO DEFEAT
THE ENEMY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT TO GO TO OUR NEXT
QUESTIONER.
SHE'S SHANNON O'CONNELL.
SHE WORKS IN HEALTH CARE.
SHE'S AN INDEPENDENT VOTER.
SHE SAYS SHE IS STILL UNDECIDED.
SHANNON, WELCOME.
>> HI, SHANNON.
>> THANK YOU.
MY QUESTION IS MORE PERSONAL IN
NATURE.
WHAT WOULD YOU REGARD AS YOUR
GREATEST PERSONAL FAILURE AND
WHAT DID YOU LEARN FROM IT?
>> YOU KNOW, THOSE ARE ALWAYS --
WHETHER IN POLITICAL CAMPAIGN OR
A JOB INTERVIEW -- THOSE ARE
ALWAYS TRICKY QUESTIONS.
YOU KNOW, ANY TIME YOU GO FOR A
JOB INTERVIEW, YOU SIT DOWN AND
YOU'RE LIKE, OKAY, WHAT'S YOUR
GREATEST WEAKNESS?
THE CLASSIC ANSWER PEOPLE GIVE
AT A JOB INTERVIEW, MY GREATEST
WEAKNESS IS I WORK TOO HARD, I'M
SUCH A DISCIPLINED EMPLOYEE, I
PUT MY WORK IN FRONT OF
EVERYTHING ELSE.
LOOK, THERE ARE PROS AND CONS TO
IT.
WHAT I WILL SAY IS I'M A PRETTY
DRIVEN GUY.
THAT HAS PROS AND CONS.
I HAVE ALWAYS BEEN A VERY DRIVEN
GUY.
I BELIEVE PASSIONATELY IN FREE
MARKET PRINCIPLES AND THE
CONSTITUTION.
MY WHOLE LIFE, I MEAN, WHEN I
WAS A TEENAGER, I STUDIED AND
MEMORIZED A SHORTENED VERSION OF
THE CONSTITUTION AND TRAVELED
AROUND AS PART OF A NON-PROFIT
ORGANIZATION IN HOUSTON SPEAKING
ABOUT THE CONSTITUTION, SPEAKING
ABOUT FREE MARKET PRINCIPLES.
AND, YOU KNOW, A LOT OF THAT, I
THINK THE REASON THAT I'M SO
DRIVEN ON THIS FRONT HAS TO DO
WITH MY FAMILY BACKGROUND.
MY FATHER WAS IMPRISONED AND
TORTURED IN CUBA AND WHEN MY DAD
CAME TO AMERICA, HE HAD NOTHING
AND IT REALLY IS -- IT'S AN
AMAZING THING WHEN YOU GROW UP
IN THE HOUSE WITH SOMEONE WHO'S
FLED OPPRESSION BECAUSE I
REMEMBER WHEN I WAS A LITTLE
KID, WE'D BE WATCHING TV AND
THERE WAS AN URGENCY TO
POLITICS.
IT WASN'T, OH, THAT'S
INTERESTING, COUPLE OF
CANDIDATES.
IT WAS HAVING PRINCIPLED MEN AND
WOMEN IN OFFICE IS HOW YOU
PROTECT YOURSELF FROM TYRANNY.
NOW, I'LL CONFESS, GROWING UP IN
A CUBAN-AMERICAN HOUSEHOLD,
YOU'RE RAISED WHERE THERE ARE
TWO FAMILIES -- THERE ARE TWO
PARTIES.
THE REPUBLICANS AND THE
COMMUNISTS.
AND ANYONE WHO IS CUBAN-AMERICAN
WILL UNDERSTAND I'M NOT KIDDING
REALLY WITH THAT.
NOW, I WAS REALLY SADDENED TO
SEE BARACK OBAMA GO AND PAL
AROUND WITH THE CASTROS AND POSE
UNDER A PICTURE.
IT DROVE THAT POINT HOME.
BUT AS A KID, THAT GIVES YOU AN
URGENCY.
AND SO AT TIMES, LISTEN, I'M
HARD CHARGING.
THAT MEANS I'VE STEPPED ON SOME
TOES.
THAT MEANS I'VE BEEN FOCUSED
VERY HARD ON FIGHTING THOSE
FIGHTS AND MAYBE I SHOULD HAVE
PULLED BACK IN SOME
CIRCUMSTANCES.
SO IT IS A STRENGTH AND A
WEAKNESS.
I WILL SAY THIS, I AM SOMEONE
WHO WHAT YOU SEE IS WHAT YOU
GET.
YOU KNOW WHAT I'M GOING TO DO IN
OFFICE.
IT'S WHAT I'VE DONE EVERY DAY.
IT'S WHAT I BELIEVE.
IT'S WHAT I'VE SPENT MY LIFE
FIGHTING FOR.
AND I THINK WE'RE AT A TIME
WHERE WE NEED A PRESIDENT WHO WE
KNOW WHAT HE WILL DO AND WE KNOW
THAT WE CAN TRUST THEM TO FOLLOW
THROUGH ON WHAT THEY'RE SAYING.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
THIS IS WILLIAM WAKE.
HE'S GOT ONE OF THE TOUGHEST
JOBS, I THINK THERE IS.
HE'S A MIDDLE SCHOOL SOCIAL
STUDIES TEACHER.
HE SAYS HE'S LEANING TOWARD
VOTING FOR YOU.
WILLIAM?
>> SENATOR CRUZ --
>> FOLLOW YOUR INSTINCTS.
>> RIGHT.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> MY STUDENTS WILL OFTEN ASK
ME, YOU KNOW, THEY'LL SAY, HAVE
YOU SEEN OR HEARD WHAT THE
CANDIDATES ARE SAYING?
OFTENTIMES IT'S NOT ABOUT
SUBSTANCE.
IT'S ABOUT WHAT NAME WE'VE BEEN
CAL
CALLING EACH OTHER.
IS IT A GOOD EXAMPLE TO SET FOR
OUR YOUTH OF AMERICA AND SHOULD
WE STAY ON SUBSTANCE INSTEAD OF
CALLS EACH OTHER NAMES?
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION
AND THANK YOU FOR THE DIFFERENCE
YOU MAKE TEACHING KIDS AND
TEACHING MIDDLE SCHOOL.
MIDDLE SCHOOL IS OBVIOUSLY A
REALLY PIVOTAL AGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WORRY ABOUT THAT QUESTION.
WHAT LESSON TO OUR KIDS TAKE
WATCHING THIS?
YOU KNOW, HEIDI AND I, OUR GIRLS
ARE 5 AND 7.
AND THEY'RE WATCHING
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES
INSULTING EACH OTHER, YELLING,
CURSING, ATTACKING FAMILY
MEMBERS.
I MEAN, IT'S GOTTEN REALLY UGLY
AND JUST WHEN YOU DON'T THINK IT
CAN GET ANY UGLIER, IT GETS
UGLIER.
I THINK THAT HAS NO PLACE IN
POLITICS, AND MY VIEW -- I HAVE
NO ABILITY TO CONTROL WHAT
ANOTHER CANDIDATE DOES.
BUT WHAT I CAN CONTROL IS MY
APPROACH.
I'LL TELL YOU THE PROMISE THAT I
MADE TO THE PEOPLE WHO JOINED
OUR CAMPAIGN FROM THE BEGINNING,
THE SUPPORTERS WHO WERE WITH US
FROM THE BEGINNING.
I SAID, LISTEN, I CAN'T PROMISE
WE'RE GOING TO WIN, I THINK WE
WILL, BUT I CAN PROMISE YOU TWO
THINGS.
ONE, WE'RE GOING TO WORK EVERY
DAY WITH A JOYFUL SPIRIT, WE'RE
GOING TO WORK EVERY DAY AND PUT
EVERYTHING WE HAVE INTO THIS
CAMPAIGN.
AND NUMBER TWO, WE'RE GOING TO
DO SO WITH INTEGRITY.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO GO INTO THE
GUTTER.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO ATTACK PEOPLE
PERSONALLY.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO MALIGN THEIR
CHARACTER.
WE'RE GOING TO FOCUS ON ISSUES
AND SUBSTANCE.
NOW IN THE COURSE OF THE
CAMPAIGN, THERE HAVE BEEN A
BUNCH OF CANDIDATES ENGAGING IN
PERSONAL INSULTS.
I'VE WORKED VERY, VERY HARD TO
STAY OUT OF THAT AND SAY, I'M
NOT GOING INTO THE GUTTER.
IF YOU ATTACK ME PERSONALLY, I'M
NOT GOING TO RESPOND IN KIND.
NOW, IF YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT
YOUR TAX PLAN, I'LL COMPARE MY
TAX PLAN TO YOUR TAX PLAN.
THAT SHOULD BE THE BREAD AND
BUTTER OF POLITICS.
AND IT IS MY HOPE THAT AT THE
END OF THE DAY THAT THAT IS THE
APPROACH THAT PREVAILS.
I THINK IT'S WHAT THE PEOPLE OF
WISCONSIN WANT.
AMERICA WANT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> OVER HERE WE HAVE JASON, HE'S
A DAIRY FARMER FROM RANDOM LAKE,
WISCONSIN.
HE SAYS HE'S VOTING FOR YOU,
SENATOR CRUZ.
>> THANK YOU, JASON.
>> I AM A DAIRY FARMER HERE IN
WISCONSIN AND DAIRY FARMING IN
MY FAMILY GOES BACK TO THE 1800s
WHEN MY GREAT-GREAT GRANDPARENTS
STARTED FARMING WITH SIX COWS.
TODAY WE HAVE 2,800 COWS.
>> WOW.
>> IT'S A 24-HOUR OPERATION.
WE OFFER A COMPETITIVE WAGE AND
OFFER FULL BENEFITS TO ALL OUR
EMPLOYEES.
MOST FARMS IN THE DAIRY INDUSTRY
CANNOT FIND AMERICAN-BORN
WORKERS TO MILK THE COWS AND
TAKE CARE OF THEM.
THE ONLY ONES WILLING TO DO THIS
HARD WORK ARE LATINO IMMIGRANTS
WHO, IF WE DIDN'T HAVE THEM FOR
EIGHT HOURS, THERE WOULD BE A
CRISIS ACROSS THE COUNTRY IN OUR
INDUSTRY.
WHAT IS THE SHORT-TERM SOLUTION
TO KEEP OUR CURRENT LABOR FORCE
IN TACT, AND WHAT IS THE
LONG-TERM SOLUTION MOVING
FORWARD?
>> RIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR SHARING YOUR
EXPERIENCE AS A DAIRY FARMER,
AND, YOU KNOW, THERE ARE FARMERS
ACROSS THIS COUNTRY WHO ARE
REALLY HURTING.
AND FARMERS ARE HURTING FROM A
LOT OF THINGS.
THEY'RE HURTING FROM A FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT WHOSE POLICIES HAVE
BEEN MAKING IT HARDER AND HARDER
FOR FARMERS TO SURVIVE.
THEY'RE HURTING FROM AN EPA WHO
IS IMPOSING MASSIVE BURDENS ON
FARMS.
FOR EXAMPLE, THE WATERS OF THE
UNITED STATES RULE WHERE THE EPA
HAS TRIED TO DEFINE A PUDDLE OR
A DRAINAGE DITCH ON YOUR FARM TO
BE NAVIGABLE WATERS AND THUS
SUBJECT TO MASSIVE ENVIRONMENTAL
REGULATIONS.
AND I THINK WE NEED A PRESIDENT,
WE NEED AN ADMINISTRATION THAT
TAKES THE BURDENS OFF FARMERS SO
THAT IT IS EASIER TO DO YOUR JOB
WHICH IS INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT.
NOW, WHEN IT COMES TO LABOR, I
UNDERSTAND THE NEED TO HAVE
LABOR AND THAT IT CAN BE HARD TO
HAVE AGRICULTURAL LABOR.
YOU KNOW, I'LL TELL YOU, ONE OF
THE CONSEQUENCES OF OUR
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM RIGHT NOW,
WHEN WE'VE GOT 12 MILLION PEOPLE
WHO ARE HERE ILLEGALLY, THAT HAS
AN EFFECT OF DRIVING DOWN WAGES
FOR AMERICANS ACROSS THIS
COUNTRY.
THERE WAS A VERY INTERESTING
ARTICLE, IT WAS ABOUT, OH, A
MONTH, MAYBE SIX WEEKS AGO IN
"THE WALL STREET JOURNAL," IT
WAS FOCUSING ON ARIZONA.
YOU'LL RECALL SEVERAL YEARS AGO
ARIZONA PUT IN PLACE REALLY
TOUGH LAWS ON ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION AND THEY WERE
CRITICIZED LOUDLY FOR PUTTING
N
THOSE LAWS IN PLACE.
IT WAS INTERESTING THIS "WALL
STREET JOURNAL" ARTICLE BECAUSE
IT TALKED ABOUT WHAT HAPPENED IN
THE WAKE OF THE LAW.
A GREAT MANY OF THE ILLEGAL
IMMIGRANTS LEFT.
THEY LEFT THE STATE AND WENT
ELSEWHERE.
AND IT ACTUALLY QUOTED A FARMER,
AND THAT'S THE REASON I'M
BRINGING UP THIS EXAMPLE, IT
QUOTED A FARMER, A FELLOW IN
ARIZONA WHO WAS GROWING PEPPERS
AND HE COMPLAINED, SAID LISTEN,
ALL PEOPLE WE HAD PICKING
PEPPERS, THEY LEFT.
HE SAID, I DIDN'T KNOW WHAT TO
DO.
I DIDN'T KNOW WE WERE GOING TO
BE ABLE TO PICK OUR PEPPERS AND
WHAT IT DESCRIBED THAT HE DID IS
HE ACTUALLY WENT AND INVENTED A
NEW TOOL TO HELP PICK THE
PEPPERS AND THEN HE WENT DOWN TO
THE LOCAL COMMUNITY COLLEGE AND
HE ENDED UP HIRING AMERICANS
COMING OUT OF THE COMMUNITY
COLLEGE.
HE HAD TO PAY THEM MORE, PAID
THEM ABOUT $15 AN HOUR BUT HE
CONTINUES PICKING HIS PEPPERS
EXCEPT HE'S DOING SO IN A
SITUATION WHERE WHAT HAS
HAPPENED IN ARIZONA, THE PUBLIC
EXPEN
EXPENDITURES HAVE PLUMMETED.
ARIZONA IS SPENDING HUNDREDS OF
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS LESS ON
PRISONS, ON EDUCATION, ON
HOSPITALS, FOR THOSE HERE
ILLEGALLY.
THAT MEANS THAT'S HUNDREDS OF
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS AVAILABLE TO
TAKE CARE OF U.S. CITIZENS AND
ALSO UNEMPLOYMENT HAS GONE DOWN
AND MEDIAN WAGES FOR AMERICANS
HAVE GONE UP IN THE CONSTRUCTION
INDUSTRY, CARPENTERS.
WE'RE SEEING WAGES GOING UP, AND
I THINK THE VIEW -- OUR
IMMIGRATION LAWS SHOULD BENEFIT
AMERICAN WORKERS.
THAT SHOULD BE THE FOCUS OF
IMMIGRATION LAWS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND SO WHAT I INTEND TO DO AS
PRESIDENT, NUMBER ONE, WE'RE
GOING TO SECURE THE BORDER.
WE'RE GOING TO END ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION.
WE KNOW HOW TO DO IT.
WHAT'S MISSING IS THE POLITICAL
WILL TO GET IT DONE.
THE DIFFERENCE IS I WILL GET IT
DONE.
BEYOND THAT, WHEN IT COMES TO
LEGAL IMMIGRATION, LISTEN, I
THINK ON IMMIGRATION THE
PRINCIPLES ARE REALLY SIMPLE.
LEGAL, GOOD.
ILLEGAL, BAD.
IT'S AMAZING HOW MANY -- HOW
MANY FOLKS IN POLITICS, HOW MANY
FOLKS IN THE MEDIA HAVE TROUBLE
UNDERSTANDING THAT.
I'M REMINDED, YOU GUYS REMEMBER
FORMER CONGRESSMAN SONNY BONO
FROM "SONNY & CHER"?
HE WAS ASKED, WHAT'S YOUR VIEW
ON ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION, HE SAID,
WELL, IT'S ILLEGAL, ISN'T IT?
WE'RE GOING TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM
BY SECURING THE BORDER AND
ENDING ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION.
ONCE WE DO THAT, THAT'S GOING TO
DRIVE UP WAGES FOR AMERICANS
ACROSS THIS COUNTRY AND IN THE
AGRICULTURE WORLD, I THINK THE
FIRST OPTION SHOULD BE TRYING TO
FIND AMERICAN WORKERS.
NOW THAT MAY MEAN WAGES COME UP.
IT MAY MEAN WE HAVE TO USE MORE
TOOLS.
WE'VE SEEN IN ARIZONA THAT'S
HAPPENED.
AND BEYOND THAT, OUR LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM, IF THERE ARE
NEEDS IN THE LABOR FORCE AND
AMERICAN WORKERS NOT AVAILABLE
TO DO IT, THAT'S WHERE LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SHOULD COME IN, BUT
IT SHOULD BE IN A SITUATION
WHERE YOU'RE VETTING THE PEOPLE
RATHER THAN JUST HAVING PEOPLE
COME IN THAT WE DON'T KNOW WHO
THEY ARE, WE DON'T KNOW THEIR
CRIMINAL HISTORY, WE DON'T KNOW
THEIR BACKGROUND.
IT SHOULD BE THROUGH THE LEGAL
SYSTEM TARGETED IN A WAY THAT
PROTECTS AMERICAN WORKERS.
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE MORE WITH
SENATOR CRUZ IN JUST A MOMENT.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A SHORT
BREAK.
ALSO AHEAD TONIGHT IN MILWAUKEE,
JOHN KASICH AND DONALD TRUMP.
MORE WITH TED CRUZ COMING UP
NEXT.
>>> AND WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE HERE AT THE RIVERSIDE
THEATER IN DOWNTOWN MILWAUKEE
TAKING VOTER QUESTIONS FOR
SENATOR TED CRUZ.
JOHN KASICH, DONALD TRUMP COMING
UP.
MORE VOTER QUESTIONS NOW FOR
SENATOR CRUZ.
I WANT TO START, THOUGH, MORE
THAN SIX MONTHS AGO YOU PLEDGED
TO SUPPORT THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE.
WHEN THINGS STARTED GETTING
ROUGH FOR DONALD TRUMP YOU SAID
YOU WERE GOING TO STICK WITH
THAT PLEDGE BECAUSE YOU'D GIVEN
YOUR WORD.
I SAW IN AN INTERVIEW WITH MY
COLLEAGUE SUNLEN SERFATY
YESTERDAY, YOU'RE NOT IN A HABIT
OF SUPPORTING PEOPLE WHO ATTACK
YOUR WIFE AND ATTACK YOUR
FAMILY.
DO YOU STILL STAND BY THE PLEDGE
TO SUPPORT WHOEVER THE NOMINEE,
EVEN IF IT'S DONALD TRUMP?
>> WELL, ANDERSON, AS YOU
MENTIONED, WHAT I SAID IS TRUE.
I'M NOT IN THE HABIT OF
SUPPORTING SOMEONE WHO ATTACKS
MY WIFE AND ATTACKS MY FAMILY.
I THINK THAT IS GOING BEYOND THE
LINE.
I THINK OUR WIVES, I THINK OUR
KIDS SHOULD BE OFF LIMITS.
THEY DON'T BELONG IN THE
ATTACKS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND LISTEN, I'M NOT AN EASY
PERSON TO TICK OFF, BUT WHEN YOU
GO AFTER MY WIFE, WHEN YOU GO
AFTER MY DAUGHTERS, THAT DOES
IT.
AND I THINK -- I WANT THIS RACE
TO STAY FOCUSED ON POLICY AND
ISSUES AND SOLUTIONS TO THE REAL
PROBLEMS FACING AMERICA.
THAT'S WHERE I'M GOING TO STAY
FOCUSED.
BUT IF OTHER CANDIDATES DON'T, I
THINK THAT'S BEYOND THE PALE.
>> I HAVE TO FOLLOW-UP, IF
DONALD TRUMP IS THE GOP NOMINEE,
WOULD YOU SUPPORT HIM?
>> LET ME TELL YOU MY SOLUTION
TO THAT.
[ LAUGHTER ]
DONALD IS NOT GOING TO BE THE
GOP NOMINEE.
WE'RE DOGOING TO BEAT HIM.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WOULD REMISS IF I DIDN'T
FOLLOW-UP.
THAT'S MY GREATEST FAILING.
MY GREATEST FAILING IS SOMETIMES
I DON'T GIVE UP.
I WOULD ASSUME BY YOU SAYING YOU
WOULD NOT SUPPORT HIM, THE
ANSWER IS YOU WOULD NOT SUPPORT
HIM IF HE IS THE NOMINEE?
>> I GAVE YOU MY ANSWER.
LISTEN, I THINK NOMINATING
DONALD TRUMP WOULD BE AN
ABSOLUTE TRAIN WRECK.
I THINK IT WOULD HAND THE
GENERAL ELECTION TO HILLARY
CLINTON.
POLL AFTER POLL AFTER POLL SHOWS
DONALD TRUMP LOSING 10, 11, 12
POINTS OR MANORE.
I DON'T WANT TO SEE THE WHITE
HOUSE GIVEN OVER TO HILLARY
CLINTON, I DON'T WANT TO SEE US
LOSE THE SENATE, HOUSE, LOSE THE
SUPREME COURT FOR A GENERATION,
LOSE THE BILL OF RIGHTS.
I THINK NOMINATING DONALD TRUMP
IS A DISASTER, SO THE ANSWER TO
THAT IS NOT TO SCREAM AND YELL
AND CRY AND ATTACK HIM, THE
ANSWER TO THAT IS TO BEAT HIM AT
THE BALLOT BOX.
THAT'S WHAT WE'RE WORKING EVERY
DAY TO DO.
IT'S WHAT WE'RE CAMPAIGNING
EVERY DAY HERE IN WISCONSIN TO
DO.
>> THIS IS BENJAMIN MILLER, A
STUDENT AT UNIVERSITY OF
WISCONSIN.
HE SAYS HE'S VOTING FOR YOU NEXT
WEEK.
BEN
BENJAMIN, WELCOME.
>> GOOD EVENING, SENATOR.
BOTH PARIS AND NOW BRUSSELS HAVE
SUFFERED BLINDSIDE ATTACKS BY
ISLAMIC TERRORISTS.
ALTHOUGH I FEAR A TERRORIST
ATTACK ON THE UNITED STATES, I
HAVE A GREATER FEAR OF THE
GOVERNMENT TAKING AWAY MY
CONSTITUTIONAL FREEDOMS AND
PRIVACY IN THE NAME OF SECURITY.
>> YES.
>> AS PRESIDENT, HOW WILL YOU
ENSURE THAT AMERICA IS NOT
BLINDLY ATTACKED WHILE ALSO
MAINTAINING THE PRIVACY OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE?
>> WELL, BENJAMIN, THANK YOU FOR
THAT QUESTION, AND IT'S A VERY
IMPORTANT QUESTION.
YOU KNOW, THERE ARE SOME IN
POLITICS WHO SAY IT'S AN
EITHER/OR CHOICE.
WE CAN EITHER PROTECT AMERICA OR
PROTECT OUR CIVIL LIBERTIES.
I DON'T ACCEPT THAT CHOICE.
I THINK IT IS POSSIBLE TO WALK
AND CHEW GUM AT THE SAME TIME.
I THINK IT IS POSSIBLE -- AND
THE DIFFERENCE -- SOMETHING THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION IS NOT VERY
GOOD AT, THEY'RE NOT VERY GOOD
AT DISTINGUISHING BETWEEN BAD
GUYS AND GOOD GUYS.
SO OVER AND OVER AGAIN, THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION'S SOLUTION,
FOR EXAMPLE, WHEN IT COMES TO
SURVEILLANCE, WAS TO MONITOR THE
PHONE CALLS OR THE E-MAILS OF
MILLIONS OF LAW-ABIDING
CITIZENS, BUT BECAUSE OF THEIR
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS, BECAUSE
THEY WON'T FOCUS ON AND IDENTIFY
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISTS, THEY
DON'T ACTUALLY TARGET THE BAD
GUYS.
IT'S WHY IT'S SO IMPORTANT --
YOU KNOW, IT'S INTERESTING,
BENJAMIN, PEOPLE IN THE MEDIA,
SOMETIMES THEY ASK, WHY DOES IT
MATTER WHETHER OBAMA WILL SAY
THE WORDS "RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM"?
IT MATTERS BECAUSE IF YOU DON'T
IDENTIFY THE PROBLEM, YOU DON'T
DEVOTE, YOU DON'T DIRECT LAW
ENFORCEMENT AND NATIONAL
SECURITY RESOURCES TO STOPPING
IT.
I'LL GIVE A SPECIFIC EXAMPLE.
MY HOME STATE OF FLORIDA, FT.
HOOD, NADAL HASSAN COMMITTED A
HORRIFIC TERRORIST ATTACK THERE.
NOW, THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION
KNEW BEFORE THE ATTACK THAT
NADAL HASSAN COMMUNICATED WITH
ANWAR AL AWLAKI.
A KNOWN CLERIC.
HE ASKED ABOUT THE PER MISBLT OF
WAGING JIHAD AND MURDERING
FELLOW SOLDIERS.
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS, OR WHAT
HAVE YOU, THEY DIDN'T DO
ANYTHING.
IF WE FIND OUT THAT A MEMBER OF
THE ARMED SERVICES IS TALKING
WITH A RADICAL ISLAMIC CLERIC
AND ASKING ABOUT WAGING JIHAD
AGAINST HIS FELLOW SOLDIERS,
WITHIN MINUTES, MPs SHOULD SHOW
UP AT HIS DOOR AND PUT HIM IN
HANDCUFFS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT THEY DIDN'T DO THAT AND
NADAL HASSAN MURDERED 14
INNOCENT SOULS INCLUDING AN
UNBORN CHILD YELLING ALLUHAH ING
A AKBAR.
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION DEFINED
THAT AS WORKPLACE VIOLENCE.
WE NEED TO DIRECT OUR RESOURCES
AT GOING AFTER THE NADAL HA
HASSANS, GOING AFTER THE RADICAL
TERRORISTS AND DO THAT AT THE
SAME TIME NOT INFRINGING THE
LAW-ABIDING AMERICANS,
DISTINGUISHING BETWEEN THE BAD
GUYS AND GOOD GUYS.
THAT'S WHAT THIS ADMINISTRATION
HADN'T BEEN DOING.
>> THANK FEW YOU FOR YOUR QUEST.
THIS IS VICTORIA.
SHE'S ALSO VOTING FOR YOU NEXT
WEEK.
>> HI, SENATOR CRUZ.
>> HI, VICTORIA.
>> WOMEN ARE MORE THAN 40% OF
THE VOTING ELECTORATE.
WHAT HAVE YOU DONE AND WHAT ARE
YOU GOING TO DO TO CONVINCE AND
PERSUADE WOMEN TO VOTE FOR YOU?
>> WELL, VICTORIA, THANK YOU FOR
THAT QUESTION, AND YOU'RE
ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
YOU KNOW, I WILL SAY ONE OF THE
THINGS I'VE REALLY BEEN BLESSED
IN MY LIFE IS THAT I HAVE GROWN
UP SURROUNDED BY STRONG WOMEN.
MY MOM IS SOMEONE WHO I ADMIRE
IMM
IMMENSELY.
MY MOM IS IRISH-ITALIAN.
SHE GREW UP IN WILMINGTON,
DELAWARE.
SHE GREW UP IN A WORKING-CLASS
FAMILY.
HER MOM WAS THE SECOND YOUNGEST
OF 17 KIDS, AND MY MOM BECAME
THE FIRST PERSON IN HER FAMILY
EVER TO GO TO COLLEGE.
AND THAT WAS NOT EASY FOR HER
BECAUSE MY GRANDFATHER, HER DAD,
HE WAS NOT AN EASY MAN.
HE WAS A DRUNK AND HE DIDN'T
THINK WOMEN SHOULD BE EDUCATED.
AND SO MY MOM STOOD UP TO HER
FATHER.
SHE TODAY UP TO HIM, CONFRONTED
HIM AND SHE ENDED UP GOING, SHE
MAJORED IN MATH IN 1956 AND SHE
GOT HIRED AT SHELL AS A COMPUTER
PROGRAMMER.
NOW, YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT TWO
INDUSTRIES, COMPUTER SCIENCE AND
OIL AND GAS, NEITHER ONE OF
WHICH WERE WELCOMING TO WOMEN,
AND MY MOM WAS AT THE
INTERSECTION OF THEM BOTH.
AND I REMEMBER MY MOM USED TO
TELL ME A LOT WHEN I WAS A KID,
SHE SAID, SHE VERY DELIBERATELY
DIDN'T LEARN HOW TO TYPE.
SHE SAID, LOOK, IT WAS THE
1950s, I UNDERSTOOD THE WORLD I
WAS LIVING IN.
SHE DIDN'T WANT TO BE WALKING
DOWN THE HALL AND HAVE SOME MAN
STOP HER AND SAY, SWEETHEART,
WOULD YOU TYPE THIS FOR ME?
SHE WANTED TO BE ABLE TO RESPOND
WITH A CLEAN CONSCIENCE AND
SMILE AND SAY, I WOULD LOVE TO
HELP YOU OUT, BUT I DON'T KNOW
HOW TO TYPE.
I GUESS YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE TO
USE ME AS A COMPUTER PROGRAMMER
INSTEAD.
AND WHETHER IT'S MY MOM, WHO WAS
A PIONEER COMPUTER PROGRAMMER,
SHE'S 81 NOW.
SHE'S BEEN A BEST FRIEND TO ME
WHY WHOLE LIFE.
AMAZING GRANDMOTHER TO MY LITTLE
GIRLS.
WHETHER IT'S MY WIFE, HEIDI,
CHRISTIAN MISSIONARY, SHE LIVED
IN AFRICA AS A KID SEVERAL
TIMES.
SHE'S SOMEONE WHO HAS BEEN AN
INCREDIBLE BUSINESSWOMAN.
SHE'S STRONG.
LISTEN, WHEN YOU'RE MARRIED TO A
STRONG WOMAN PROFESSIONAL, YOU
SEE THE NONSENSE THAT WOMEN DEAL
WITH IN THE BUSINESS
ENVIRONMENT.
YOU SEE THE GARBAGE THEY PUT UP
WITH.
AND IT MAKES YOU MAD.
I'VE BEEN BLESSED MY WHOLE LIFE
TO BE SURROUNDED BY STRONG
WOMEN.
I THINK WOMEN RIGHT NOW ARE
PARTICULARLY CONCERNED ABOUT THE
DIRECTION OF THIS COUNTRY.
ARE PARTICULARLY CONCERNED ABOUT
WHAT KIND OF FUTURE OUR KIDS ARE
GOING TO HAVE.
WHAT KIND OF COUNTRY WE'RE
GIVING TO THE NEXT GENERATION.
I THINK WOMEN QUITE RIGHTLY ARE
VERY CONCERNED ABOUT SAFETY AND
SECURITY AND A PRESIDENT THAT'S
NOT PROTECTING US FROM
TERRORISTS.
AND I BELIEVE WHAT PROTECTS
WOMEN, YOU KNOW, THE DEMOCRATS
LOVE TO PUT EVERYONE IN A LITTLE
PIGEON HOLE AND SO THIS IS A
WOMEN'S ISSUE, THIS IS A
HISPANIC ISSUE, THIS IS AN
AFRICAN-AMERICAN ISSUE.
LISTEN, I BELIEVE EVERY ISSUE IS
A WOMEN'S ISSUE AND THE FOCUS OF
MY CAMPAIGN IS ON THREE THINGS.
IT'S ON JOBS, FREEDOM, AND
SECURITY.
BRINGING BACK THE OPPORTUNITY,
RAISING WAGES, BRINGING JOBS
BACK TO AMERICA.
I THINK THAT IS RESONATING
POWERFULLY WITH WOMEN AND
FIGHTING TO PROTECT THE BILL OF
RIGHTS AND EQUAL OPPORTUNITY FOR
WOMEN AND MEN AND EVERYONE, AND
I'LL TELL YOU, THERE'S NO ONE I
FIGHT HARDER FOR THAN OUR TWO
LITTLE GIRLS, CAROLINE AND
CATHERINE, WHO ARE THE LOVES OF
MY LIFE AND WHO CAN DO ANYTHING
AND I WANT TO MAKE SURE THEY
HAVE A WORLD THEY CAN LIVE IN
WHERE THEY HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY
TO DO ANYTHING.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
I'M GOING TO TRY TO GET TIME FOR
TWO MORE QUESTIONS.
I WANT YOU TO MEET MARV, SHE'S
FROM STEVENS POINT.
HE SAYS AT THIS POINT HE'S
UNDECIDED.
MARV, WELCOME.
>> THANK YOU BOTH.
MY SON, JASON, WAS A FORMER
MARINE KILLED BY
OVERPRESCRIPTION OF MEDICATION
WHILE AN IN-PATIENT AT THE V.A.
FACILITY IN TOMO, WISCONSIN.
EVERY DAY YOU SEE STORIES AND
NEWS ABOUT PEOPLE ALL OVER
WISCONSIN, PEOPLE FROM RURAL
AREAS, BIG CITIES AND SMALL
TOWNS ADDICTED TO OPIOIDS AND
HEROIN.
STRONGER OPIATE PRESCRIBING
GUIDELINES FOR V.A. PROVIDERS.
WILL YOU SUPPORT THIS BIPARTISAN
LEGISLATION AND DO YOU SUPPORT
REQUIRING STRONG ER OPIATE
PRESCRIBING GUIDELINES NOT ONLY
FOR THE V.A. BUT DOCTORS ACROSS
THIS COUNTRY?
>> WELL, MARV, THANK YOU FOR
SHARING YOUR STORY, AND THANK
YOU FOR YOUR SON'S SERVICE AND
HIS SACRIFICE.
I'M SORRY THAT YOU LOST YOUR
SON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THIS IS A TRAGEDY WE'RE SEEING
ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
WE'RE SEEING VETERANS COMING
BACK STRUGGLING WITH PTSD.
STRUGGLING TO GET THEIR HEALTH
CARE NEEDS TREATED.
TREATED PROPERLY.
WE'RE SEEING A V.A. THAT IS
DYSFUN
DYSFUNCTIONAL.
A V.A. THAT IS LYING.
ONE OF THE THINGS WE NEED IS WE
NEED REAL ACCOUNTABILITY IN THE
V.A.
I GIVE YOU MY WORD, IF I AM
PRESIDENT, THERE WILL BE
ACCOUNTABILITY IN THE V.A.
THOSE THAT HAVE LIED, THOSE THAT
HAVE WRONGFULLY DENIED CARE,
THEY WILL BE TERMINATED.
IF THEY BROKE THE LAW, THEY WILL
BE PROSECUTED.
WE ALSO NEED REFORM IN THE V.A.
SO THAT VETERANS HAVE THE POWER
TO CHOOSE THEIR OWN DOCTORS.
WHETHER THEY WANT TO CHOOSE THE
V.A. OR A PRIVATE DOCTOR,
THERE'S NO REASON YOUR SON,
JASON, COULDN'T HAVE GONE TO THE
DOCTOR DOWN THE STREET.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW, I AGREE WITH YOU, WE NEED
GREATER SCRUTINY, GREATER
INVOLVEMENT PREVENTING OPIOID
ABUSE.
YOU LOOK AT THE PREVALENCE OF
HEROIN AND I WOULD NOTE THIS IS
A TRAGEDY, ROUGHLY 50,000 PEOPLE
A YEAR DIE OF DRUG OVERDOSES.
MORE PEOPLE IN AMERICA DIE OF
DRUG OVERDOSES THAN DIE IN CAR
CRASHES.
AND MARV, I'M SORRY TO SAY, YOU
AND I ARE BOTH MEMBERS OF A
HORRIBLE CLUB BECAUSE I LOST MY
SISTER, MIRIAM, TO A DRUG
OVERDOSE SO I'VE SEEN FIRST HAN
AND IT STARTED WHEN SHE WAS IN A
CAR ACCIDENT AND SHE GOT
PRESCRIBED PAINKILLERS.
SHE KEPT ON TAKING THE
PAINKILLERS AND KEPT ON TAKING
STRONGER.
MIRIAM LIVED A DIFFICULT AND
TROUBLED LIFE.
SHE MADE A LOT OF VERY POOR
DECISIONS.
THEN JUST A FEW YEARS AGO, SHE
TOOK TOO MANY PILLS ONE NIGHT
AND HER SON CAME IN AND FOUND
HER DEAD.
THIS IS AN EPIDEMIC THAT IS
DESTROYING FAMILIES.
ACROSS AMERICA.
I'M SORRY FOR YOUR FAMILY'S
LOSS.
I'M SORRY, MY NEPHEW, JOEY, HER
SON, SOMEONE I'M REALLY PROUD
OF.
HE'S ENDURED HIS MOM'S DIFFICULT
JOURNEY AND HE'S WORKING A GOOD
JOB, HE'S A RESPONSIBLE, HE'S A
TERRIFIC YOUNG MAN.
BUT WE NEED A FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
THAT FOCUSES ON STOPPING THIS
DRUG ABUSE, WHETHER IT IS
PRESCRIPTION DRUG ABUSE OR
WHETHER IT IS ILLEGAL NARCOTICS
LIKE HEROIN, AND ONE OF THE MOST
IMPORTANT WAYS TO STOP THAT, YOU
KNOW, UNFORTUNATELY MY SISTER,
MIRIAM, ENDED UP GOING DOWN THAT
PATH, GOING DOWN THE PATH OF
CRACK COCAINE AND DRUGS THAT
DESTROYED HER LIFE.
ONE OF THE WAYS TO PREVENT THAT
IS WE NEED TO SECURE THE BORDER.
WE NEED TO GET SERIOUS ABOUT
STOPPING THE INCREDIBLE FLOW
FROM MEXICAN DRUG CARTELS THAT
ARE POISONING OUR KIDS.
YOU HAVE MY COMMITMENT AS
PRESIDENT, I'M NOT GOING TO TALK
EMPTY PROMISES BUT WE ARE GOING
TO DEVOTE THE FULL RESOURCES OF
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT TO
FINALLY, FINALLY, FINALLY
SECURES THE BORDER, STOPPING
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION, STOPPING
THE DELUGE OF DRUGS THAT IS
COMING INTO THIS COUNTRY AND
DESTROYING THE LIVES OF PEOPLE
ALL ACROSS THIS COUNTRY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THIS IS TIM OMER.
HE SAYS HE IS LEANING IN YOUR
FAVOR.
TIM, WELCOME.
>> HEY, TIM.
>> WELCOME TO WISCONSIN,
SENATOR.
>> THANK YOU.
>> AS A GROWING COMPANY, OUR
BIGGEST CHALLENGE IS FINDING
TALENTED AND QUALIFIED PEOPLE TO
FILL ALL THE POSITIONS THAT WE
HAVE OPEN IN OUR COMPANY.
AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, WHAT COULD YOU DO TO
HELP US FIND THOSE TALENTED
PEOPLE, FIND THOSE QUALITY
PEOPLE, BUILD UP THE POOL OF
PEOPLE SO THAT WE CAN FILL THOSE
POSITIONS AND CONTINUE TO GROW
OUR BUSINESS?
>> TIM, TELL ME WHAT KIND OF
COMPANY YOU HAVE.
>> WE'RE WISCONSIN CHEESE.
>> WISCONSIN CHEESE, FABULOUS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WILL CONFESS SOMETHING, AND AS
MY WIFE, HEIDI, IS MY WITNESS,
MY FAVORITE FOOD IN ALL THE
WORLD IS CHEESE.
AND I AM NOT SAYS THAT TO PANDER
IN WISCONSIN.
BUT IF YOU WOULDN'T POINT IT OUT
HERE, WHERE WOULD YOU POINT IT
OUT?
LISTEN, IT IS A HUGE PROBLEM WE
SEE OF A NEED FOR A TRAINED
WORKFORCE AND A NEED FOR A
WORKFORCE THAT'S PREPARED AND
WANTS TO WORK.
YOU KNOW, AS I MEET WITH SMALL
BUSINESSOWNERS ALL ACROSS THE
COUNTRY, I HEAR THOSE CONCERNS
OVER AND OVER AND OVER AGAIN
THAT IT'S HARD TO GET PEOPLE WHO
ARE QUALIFIED AND WHO WANT TO
WORK AND ARE PREPARED TO WORK
AND THAT'S A REAL CHALLENGE.
AND, YOU KNOW, THE KEY TO JOBS
AND JOB CREATION IS SMALL
BUSINESSES, IS DOING WHAT YOU
DO.
HOW MANY EMPLOYEES DO YOU GUYS
HAVE?
>> ABOUT 300.
I MEAN, THAT'S WHERE JOB
CREATION COMES FROM.
IT COMES FROM SMALL BUSINESSES.
2/3 OF ALL NEW JOBS COME FROM
SMALL BUSINESSES.
NOW, IN TERMS OF GETTING NEW AND
ABLE WORKER, WE NEED TO DO
SEVERAL THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, WE NEED TO TREFORM
EPGS.
THE STEP TO HAVING WELL TRAINED
WORKERS IS A STRONG EDUCATION
PROGRAM.
IF YOU LOOK AT EDUCATION RIGHT
NOW, NUMBER ONE, I THINK THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT NEEDS TO GET
THE HECK OUT OF IT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IT'S ONE OF THE REASONS I
PROMISED ON THE VERY FIRST DAY
IN OFFICE THAT I'M GOING TO
DIRECT THE DEPARTMENT OF
EDUCATION THAT COMMON CORE ENDS
THAT DAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I THINK WHAT WE OUGHT TO BE
DOING IS ABOLISHING THE FEDERAL
DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION AND
BLOCK GRANTING THAT MONEY TO
SEND IT BACK TO WISCONSIN.
I THINK THE PEOPLE OF WISCONSIN
KNOW MUCH BETTER WHAT TO DO WITH
THAT MONEY.
AND PART OF THAT MONEY, I THINK,
SHOULD BE DIRECTED AT SCHOOL
CHOICE PROGRAMS.
ALLOWING PEOPLE WHO ARE TRAPPED
IN FAILING SCHOOLS TO HAVE THE
OPTION OF GOING TO PRIVATE
SCHOOLS.
GOING TO PAROCHIAL SCHOOLS.
INJECTING COMPETITION IN FAILING
SCHOOLS TO EMPOWER PARENTS AND
EMPOWER STUDENTS.
I THINK SCHOOL CHOICE IS THE
CIVIL RIGHTS ISSUE OF THE 20th
CENTURY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND PART OF THAT MONEY AS WELL
IN WISCONSIN OUGHT TO BE
DIRECTED TO VOCATIONAL TRAINING,
OUGHT TO BE DIRECTED TO
DIFFERENT NONTRADITIONAL WAYS
WHERE PEOPLE CAN EARN SKILLS,
WHETHER IT'S DISTANCE LEARNING,
WHETHER IT IS USING THE
INTERNET, USING OPTIONS WHERE
YOUR ONLY OPTION ISN'T SPENDING
$50,000 A YEAR AT A 4-YEAR
COLLEGE BUT EXPANDING THE
OPTIONS FOR PEOPLE TO GET
EDUCATION.
I THINK THAT IS A CRITICAL PIECE
TO IMPROVING THE ENVIRONMENT,
AND ANOTHER CRITICAL PIECE IS
CHANGING OUR WELFARE PROGRAM.
YOU KNOW, OUR WELFARE PROGRAM
RIGHT NOW TRAPS PEOPLE IN
DEPENDENCY.
NOW, MY VIEW ON WELFARE IS THE
SOCIAL SAFETY NET, IT SHOULD BE
A TRAMPOLINE AND NOT A HAMMOCK.
THAT THE WHOLE PURPOSE OF THE
SOCIAL SAFETY NET SHOULD BE TO
GET YOU BACK ON YOUR FEET.
EVERYONE FALLS ON HARD TIMES,
BUT YOU'RE NOT HELPING SOMEONE
TRAPPING THEM IN DEPENDENCE.
I TELL YOU, I VISITED WITH A
FELLOW WHO OWNS A COOKIE
FACTORY.
TELL YOU, BETWEEN COOKIES AND
CHEESE, YOU REALLY HAVE A GREAT
PARTY RIGHT THERE.
HE OWNS A COOKIE FACTORY.
HE TALKED TO ME ABOUT WHERE IN
THE 1990s WHEN CONGRESS PASSED
WELFARE REFORM, CONGRESS PUT IN
PLACE A STRONG WORK REQUIREMENT
FOR WELFARE AND YOU RECALL THE
LIBERALS IN THE MEDIA WERE
SAYING, YOU'RE GOING TO THROW
PEOPLE ON THE STREET, PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO BE STARVING, IT'S GOING
TO BE TERRIBLE.
IT'S ONE OF THE MOST SUCCESSFUL
PUBLIC POLICY REFORMS WE'VE EVER
SEEN.
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE LEFT WELFARE
AND GOT JOBS.
THE FELL EMPOW WHO OWNS THE COO
FACTORY, SUDDENLY THEY HAD
PEOPLE LINING UP TO WORK.
THEY WEREN'T GETTING PAID IN
PERPETUITY TO STAY AT HOME AND
WATCH "GILLIGAN'S ISLAND."
THEY HAD TO GO GET A JOB.
YOU KNOW WHAT, IF YOU HELP
SOMEONE GET A JOB, ULTIMATELY
THAT IS GIVING THEM THE DIGNITY
OF WORK.
I BELIEVE EVERY AMERICAN WANTS
TO HAVE THAT DIGNITY.
TO PROVIDE FOR THEIR FAMILIES.
>> WE GOT TO WRAP IT UP.
I WANT TO THANK SENATOR CRUZ
VERY MUCH FOR BEING WITH US.
THANK YOU, SENATOR.
WE WHEN COME BACK, DONALD TRUMP
AS OUR TOWN HALL CONTINUES HERE
IN DOWNTOWN MILWAUKEE.
THANK YOU.
>>> AND WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE COMING TO YOU TONIGHT FROM
THE RIVERSIDE THEATER IN
DOWNTOWN MILWAUKEE.
WITH THE "360" TOWN HALL.
THE THREE REMAINING REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES CAMPAIGNING HARD WITH
THE PRIMARY HERE JUST A WEEK
AWAY.
WE HEARD SO FAR FROM SENATOR TED
CRUZ.
RIGHT NOW THE GOP FRONT-RUNNER,
NEW YORK BUSINESSMAN, DONALD
TRUMP.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
>> HEY, HOW YOU DOING, SIR?
NICE TO SEE YOU.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SO WE GOT A LOT OF QUESTIONS
FROM THE AUDIENCE FOR YOU ON A
LOT OF POLICY ISSUES.
I GOT TO START OFF WITH SOME
NEWS OF THE DAY TOPICS.
YOUR CAMPAIGN MANAGER, COREY
LEWANDOWSKI CHARGED WITH SIMPLE
BATTERY FOR GRABBING A REPORTER
BY THE ARM.
WILL HE CONTINUE AS YOUR
CAMPAIGN MANAGER?
>> YES, HE WILL.
I LOOKED AT THE TAPE.
MY TAPE.
IT WAS AT ONE OF MY PLACES.
I HAVE GREAT SECURITY AND GREAT
SECURITY CAMERA.
I GAVE THE TAPE, AND FRANKLY, IF
YOU LOOK AT THAT, PEOPLE HAVE
LOOKED AT IT, IN FACT, I JUST
LEFT ANOTHER AREA OF WISCONSIN,
WE HAD A WHOLE BIG MEETING WITH
A WHOLE GROUP OF PEOPLE.
BIG AUDIENCE.
TREMENDOUS AUDIENCE.
AND THEY'RE ALL SHAKING THEIR
HEADS, GIVE ME A BREAK, GIVE ME
A BREAK.
>> LET ME ASK YOU, THOUGH --
>> THE ANSWER IS YES.
BY THE WAY, SPEAKING OF
SOMETHING ELSE, I WATCHED TED
CRUZ.
HIS HOME STATE IS NOT FLORIDA.
HIS HOME STATE IS TEXAS.
IT MAY BE CANADA.
BUT TO THE BEST OF MY KNOWLEDGE,
IT'S TEXAS.
SO HE MADE THAT -- I WAS
SURPRISED YOU DIDN'T CORRECT
HIM, ACTUALLY.
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT
LEWANDOWSKI.
INITIALLY YOUR CAMPAIGN SAID
THIS NEVER HAPPENED, THERE WAS
NO VIDEO OF IT.
YOU CAME OUT AND SAID YOU
THOUGHT THIS PERSON WAS,
PERHAPS, MAKING IT UP, THIS
REPORTER.
LEWANDOWSKI, HIMSELF, TWEETED
SAYING "I NEVER MET THIS
REPORTER, I NEVER TOUCHED THIS
PERSON."
NOW THE VIDEOTAPE SHOWS HE
CLEARLY DID TOUCH THIS PERSON.
WHETHER OR NOT YOU THINK IT WAS
BATTERY OR NOT --
>> TOUCH, I DON'T KNOW WHAT
TOUCH MEANS.
>> HE SAYS I DIDN'T TOUCH THIS
PERSON.
DID HE MISLEAD YOU AT ALL?
>> NO, NOT AT ALL.
LOOK, I DIDN'T KNOW WE HAD ALL
THESE SECURITY CAMERAS ALL OVER.
THE TIME I FOUND OUT, I SAID,
WELL, THIS IS REALLY WONDERFUL,
THIS EXONERATES HIM TOTALLY.
NOW --
>> LIE OR MAKE A MISTAKE?
>> SOMETHING TO THE EFFECT SHE
ALMOST WENT TO THE GROUND.
SHE WAS IN PAIN.
SHE WENT TO THE GROUND.
WHEN SHE FOUND OUT THAT THERE
WAS A SECURITY CAMERA, AND THAT
THEY HAD HER ON TAPE, ALL OF A
SUDDEN THAT STORY CHANGED.
>> THAT'S NOT TRUE.
HE SAID HER STORY HAS REMAINED
EXACTLY THE SAME.
>> REALLY?
DO YOU MIND IF I READ YOU HER
STATEMENT?
I MEAN, GIVE ME A BREAK.
YOU KNOW, THE PROBLEM IS
EVERYBODY DUMPS PEOPLE WHEN
THERE'S, LIKE, A SIGN OF
POLITICAL INCORRECTNESS.
I'M JUST GOING TO READ, IF I CAN
FIND IT --
>> SHE SAID SHE WAS ALMOST
KNOCKED OFF BALANCE.
HERE'S WHAT SHE SAID.
YOU WANT TO READ IT?
YOU WANT ME TO DO IT?
YOU'RE A PROFESSIONAL
ANNOUNCEMENT.
WHY DON'T YOU READ IT.
THE BOTTOM PART.
NOW THAT'S AN EXACT QUOTE FROM
HER PRIOR TO SEEING THE CAMERAS
AND NOW SHE SAYS I BETTER CHANGE
MY STORY, I GUESS.
>> THIS QUOTE SAYS "I WAS JOLTED
BACKWARDS, SOMEONE GRABBED ME
TIGHTLY BY THE ARM AND YANKED ME
DOWN.
I ALMOST KNEFELL TO THE GROUND,S
UNABLE TO MAINTAIN MY BALANCE
NONETHELESS.
I WAS SHAKEN.
CAMPAIGN MANAGERS AREN'T
SUPPOSED TO TRY TO FORCEFULLY
THROW REPORTERS TO THE GROUND."
NO, SHE DID NOT GO DOWN ON THE
GROUND.
>> LOOK, BEFORE SHE KNOWS --
FOLKS, LOOK, I'M A LOYAL PERSON.
I'M GOING TO BE LOYAL TO THE
COUNTRY, I'M GOING TO BE LOYAL
TO WISCONSIN.
WE HAVE TO TELL IT LIKE IT IS.
IT WOULD BE SO EASY FOR ME TO
TERMINATE THIS MAN, RUIN HIS
LIFE, RUIN HIS FAMILY, FOUR
BEAUTIFUL CHILDREN IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE, RUIN HIS WHOLE
EVERYTHING AND SAID YOU'RE
FIRED.
OKAY?
I FIRED MANY PEOPLE, ESPECIALLY
ON "THE APRPRAPPRENTICE."
LOOK AT WHAT SHE SAYS, MICHELLE
FIELDS, BY THE WAY, IS NOT A
BABY.
IN HER OWN WORLDS, EXACTLY "I
WAS JOLTED BACKWARDS."
SHE'S STANDING THERE.
SOMEONE HAD GRABBED ME TIGHTLY
BY THE ARM.
TIGHTLY.
AND YANKED ME DOWN."
SHE WASN'T YANKED DOWN.
SHE DIDN'T HAVE AN EXPRESSION.
IF SOMEBODY IN THIS AUDIENCE
GETS WHACKED, GETS HURT,
INCLUDING ME, YOU GET HURT.
THERE'S NO EMOTION.
WAIT A MINUTE.
"I ALMOST FELL TO THE GROUND."
SHE DIDN'T ALMOST FALL TO THE
GROUND.
HE GOT IN HER WAY.
BY THE WAY, SHE WAS GRABBING ME.
AM I SUPPOSED TO PRESS CHARGES
AGAINST HER?
ANDERSON, MY ARM IS JUST KILLING
ME.
IT'S NEVER BEEN THE SAME.
>> YOU SUGGESTED YOU MIGHT --
>> EXCUSE ME, EXCUSE ME.
I DIDN'T SUGGEST.
>> YEAH, YOU DID.
>> I TWEETED.
NO, NO, I TWEETED.
>> A TWEET IS A SUGGESTION.
>> SHOULD I PRESS CHARGES?
>> ARE YOU GOING TO?
>> I DON'T KNOW.
MAYBE I SHOULD, RIGHT?
BECAUSE YOU KNOW WHAT, SHE WAS
GRABBING ME.
AND JUST SO YOU UNDERSTAND, SHE
WAS OFF BASE BECAUSE SHE WENT
THROUGH THE SECRET SERVICE.
SHE HAD A PEN IN HER HAND WHICH
SECRET SERVICE IS NOT LIKING
BECAUSE THEY DON'T KNOW WHAT IT
IS, WHETHER IT'S A LITTLE BOMB
OR --
>> DOES THAT CONCERN YOU
INITIALLY COREY LEWANDOWSKI SAID
HE NEVER TOUCHED HER AND TURNS
OUT NOT TO BE TRUE?
>> I DON'T THINK HE KNEW HER.
BASED ON WHAT I HEARD, I DON'T
THINK HE KNEW WHO SHE WAS.
LISTEN TO THIS, "I ALMOST FELL
TO THE GROUND" WHICH IS UNTRUE
"BUT WAS ABLE TO MAINTAIN MY
BALANCE."
SHE HAD NO TROUBLE WITH HER
BALANCE BECAUSE IT'S RIGHT ON
TAPE.
"NONETHELESS, I WAS SHAKEN.
CAMPAIGN MANAGERS AREN'T
SUPPOSED TO TRY TO FORCEFULLY
THROW REPORTERS TO THE GROUND."
SHE DIDN'T GO TO THE GROUND.
SHE DIDN'T EVEN HAVE AN
EXPRESSION ON HER FACE.
>> YOU THINK THIS IS POLITICALLY
MOTIVATED?
>> IT COULD BE.
I DON'T KNOW.
I LOOK -- I TELL YOU WHAT, A
FRIEND OF MINE WHO'S IN LAW
ENFORCEMENT SAID TO ME, THERE'S
PROBABLY NOT A DETECTIVE IN THE
WORLD THAT WOULD HAVE DONE WHAT
THEY DID TO HIM.
I MEAN, PEOPLE IN SYRIA --
>> THE STATE ATTORNEY'S A
DEMOCRAT.
>> EXCUSE ME, EXCUSE ME.
OH, REALLY?
I'M SHOCKED TO HEAR THAT.
YOU KNOW, YOU KNOW, PEOPLE ARE
CHOPPING OFF HEADS IN THE MIDDLE
EAST.
THEY'RE DROWNING PEOPLE IN CAGES
BY 50s.
THEY'RE DROWNING -- HERE'S A
GUY -- SHOULDN'T HAVE BEEN
TOUCHING ME.
OKAY?
AND YOU SAW THAT SHE DID THAT.
SHE WAS GRABBING ME.
TWICE.
I LOOKED AT HER.
IN FACT, ONE OF THE GREAT
PICTURES IS ME GOING LIKE THIS
LIKE GET AWAY FROM ME, WHO IS
THIS PERSON?
OKAY?
MY ARM, IT'S NEVER BEEN THE
SAME, FOLKS.
NEVER BEEN THE SAME.
SO LET ME JUST TELL YOU, SHE
WENT THROUGH SECRET SERVICE,
BOOM, SHE GRABBED ME AND HE
REALLY STEPPED IN FRONT OF HER.
I DIDN'T -- HE STEPPED IN FRONT
OF HER.
SHE WASN'T SUPPOSED TO BE ASKING
QUESTIONS BECAUSE THE PRESS
CONFERENCE LASTED FOR 45 MINUTES
AND ALL QUESTIONS WERE DONE AND
I WAS WALKING RAPIDLY OUT.
>> SECOND TIME LEWANDOWSKI HAS
TOUCHED SOMEBODY.
HE DID THIS TO A PROTESTER,
GRABBED A GUY BY THE COLLAR.
WHICH YOU ACTUALLY BACK UP ON.
ANOTHER TWEET YOU SENT, YOU SENT
A TWEET ABOUT THE DEATH TOLL,
THE HORRIBLE TERROR ATTACK IN
PAKISTAN OVER THE WEEKEND.
>> RIGHT.
>> YOU TALKED AN THE DEATH TOLL.
YOU SAID I ALONE CAN SOLVE.
>> I KNOW MY COMPETITION.
LOOK, I KNOW MY COMPETITION.
>> YOU, ALONE, AMONG THE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES.
>> I SEE HILLARY WITH BENGHAZI,
THE FAMOUS AD, 3:00 IN THE
MORNING, GUESS WHAT, THE PHONE
RANG, SHE WASN'T THERE.
UNLESS SYDNEY CALLED.
>> YOU'RE THE ONLY ONE WHO CAN
SOLVE TERROR PROBLEMS IN
PAKISTAN?
>> OF THE ONES WHO ARE RUNNING,
I KNOW THE COMPETITION.
I WATCHED TED CRUZ.
SO PHONY.
I KNOW YOU HAVE COUPLE PEOPLE
OUT THERE BECAUSE HE PUT THEM IN
THE AUDIENCE.
IT'S SO FALSE.
THE WHOLE THING -- WITH THE
FIVE -- WITH THE FIVE-SECOND
INTERMISSIONS BETWEEN SENTENCES.
NO.
YES, I THINK I AM THE ONE TO BE
ABLE TO SOLVE THE PROBLEM.
>> BUT, I MEAN, THERE'S PROBLEMS
IN A LOT OF DIFFERENT COUNTRIES.
THE PROBLEMS IN THE UNITED
STATES.
HOW CAN YOU SOLVE THE PROBLEMS
ALL THE WAY OVER IN PAKISTAN
WHEN THE PAKISTANIS, THEMSELVES,
ARE STRUGGLING?
>> LOOK, PAKISTAN IS A VERY,
VERY VITAL PROBLEM AND REALLY
VITAL COUNTRY FOR US BECAUSE
THEY HAVE A THING CALLED NUCLEAR
WEAPONS.
THEY HAVE TO GET AHOLD OF THE
SITUATION.
WHEN I SEE THAT AND SEE IT PUT
IN A PARK BECAUSE IT WAS MOSTLY
CHRISTIANS, ALTHOUGH MANY OTHERS
WERE KILLED OTHER THAN
CHRISTIANS, I THINK IT'S JUST
ABSOLUTELY A HORRIBLE STORY.
BUT I'M TALKING ABOUT RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
I WILL SOLVE IT FAR BETTER THAN
ANYBODY ELSE RUNNING.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT NUCLEAR
ISSUES BECAUSE YOU TALKED ABOUT
THIS IN A REALLY INTERESTING
ARTICLE.
>> ONE OF THE VERY, VERY BIG
ISSUES.
I THINK MAYBE THE BIGGEST ISSUE
OF OUR TIME.
>> THAT'S WHAT YOU SAID TO "THE
NEW YORK TIMES."
YOU SAID YOU WORRIED ABOUT THE
PROLIFERATION OF NUCLEAR
WEAPONS.
>> RIGHT.
>> THE MOST.
YOU ALSO SAID, THOUGH, YOU MIGHT
SUPPORT JAPAN AND SOUTH KOREA
DEVELOPING NUCLEAR WEAPONS OF
THEIR OWN.
ISN'T THAT COMPLETELY
CONTRADICTORY?
>> NOT AT ALL.
NORTH KOREA HAS NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
HE DOESN'T HAVE A CARRY YET BUT
HAS NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
HE SOON WILL HAVE.
WE DON'T WANT TO PULL THE
TRIGGER.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT, FRANKLY,
NOBODY IS AFRAID OF OUR
PRESIDENT.
NOBODY RESPECTS OUR PRESIDENT.
YOU TAKE A LOOK AT WHAT'S GOING
ON THROUGHOUT THE WORLD.
IT'S NOT THE COUNTRY THAT IT
WAS.
>> IF YOU'RE CONCERNED ABOUT
PROLIFERATION, LETTING OTHER
COUNTRIES GET NUCLEAR WEAPONS,
ISN'T THAT --
>> WE OWE $19 TRILLION, WE HAVE
ANOTHER $2 TRILLION BECAUSE OF
THE VERY, VERY BAD OMNIBUS
BUDGET THAT WAS JUST SIGNED.
IT'S A DISGRACE.
WHICH GIVES EVERYTHING THAT
OBAMA WANTED.
WE GET NOTHING.
THEY GET EVERYTHING.
SO THAT'S GOING TO BE $21
TRILLION.
WE ARE SUPPORTING NATIONS NOW,
MILITARILY, WE ARE SUPPORTING
NATIONS LIKE SAUDI ARABIA WHICH
WAS MAKING DURING THE GOOD OIL
DAYS WHICH WAS A YEAR AGO, NOW
THEY'RE MAKING LESS BUT STILL A
LOT.
$1 BILLION A DAY.
WE ARE SUPPORTING THEM, MI
MILITARILY AND PAY US A
FRACTION, A FRACTION OF WHAT
THEY SHOULD BE PAYING US AND OF
THE COST.
WE ARE SUPPORTING IJAPAN.
MOST PEOPLE DIDN'T KNOW WE'RE
TAKING CARE OF JAPAN'S MILITARY
NEEDS.
EXCUSE ME, WE'RE SUPPORTING
GERMANY.
WE'RE SUPPORTING SOUTH KOREA.
I ORDERED THOUSANDS OF
TELEVISION SETS BECAUSE I AM IN
THE REAL ESTATE BUSINESS, YOU
KNOW, IN MY OTHER LIFE, OKAY.
>> IT'S BEEN A U.S. POLICY FOR
DECADES TO PREVENT JAPAN FROM
GETTING WEAPONS.
SOUTH KOREA AS WELL.
>> CAN I BE HONEST ARE YOU?
MAYBE IT'S GOING TO BE TIME TO
CHANGE.
PAKISTAN HAS IT, CHINA HAS IT.
SO MANY OTHER COUNTRIES --
>> SOME PROLIFERATION IS OKAY?
>> NO, NO, NOT SOME.
I HATE PROLIFERATION.
I HATE NUCLEAR MORE THAN ANY.
MY PROFESSOR WAS AN UNCLE
M.I.T. --
>> THAT'S CONTRADICTORY.
>> HOW MANY COUNTRIES HAVE IT?
EXCUSE ME.
ONE OF THE DUMBEST DEALS I'VE
EVER SEEN SIGNED EVER, EVER,
EVER BY ANYBODY.
IRAN IS GOING TO HAVE IT WITHIN
TEN YEARS.
IRAN IS GOING TO HAVE IT.
I THOUGHT IT WAS A VERY GOOD
INTERVIEW.
AT SOME POINT WE HAVE TO SAY
JAPAN IS BETTER OFF IF THEY
PROTECT THEMSELVES AGAINST THIS
MANIAC IN SOUTH KOREA, IF --
>> SAUDI ARABIA, NUCLEAR
WEAPONS?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> YOU'D BE FINE WITH THEM
HAVING NUCLEAR WEAPONS?
>> THAT HAVE TO PROTECT
THEMSELVES OR PAY US.
WITH JAPAN, THEY HAVE TO PAY US
OR LET THEM PROTECT THEMSELVESES
>> YOU'D SAID, JAPAN, YES, IT'S
FINE, YOU GET NUCLEAR WEAPONS,
YOU AS WELL, SAUDI ARABIA SAYS
WE WANT THEM, TOO.
>> CAN I BE HONEST WITH YOU?
IT'S GOING TO HAPPEN, ANYWAY.
IT'S ONLY A QUESTION OF TIME.
THEY'RE GOING TO START HAVING
THEM OR WE HAVE TO GET RID OF
THEM ENTIRELY.
SO MANY COUNTRIES ALREADY,
CHINA, PAKISTAN, SO MANY
COUNTRIES, RUSSIA, SO MANY
COUNTRIES RIGHT NOW THAT HAVE
THEM.
NOW, WOULDN'T YOU RATHER IN A
CERTAIN SENSE HAVE JAPAN HAVE
NUCLEAR WEAPONS WHEN NORTH KOREA
HAS NUCLEAR WEAPONS?
AND THEY DO HAVE THEM.
THEY ABSOLUTELY HAVE THEM.
THEY CAN'T -- THEY HAVE NO
CARRIER SYSTEM YET BUT THEY WILL
VERY SOON.
WOULDN'T YOU RATHER HAVE JAPAN,
PERHAPS, THEY'RE OVER THERE,
THEY'RE VERY CLOSE, VERY FEARFUL
OF NORTH KOREA AND WE'RE
SUPPOSED TO PROTECT.
>> YOU'RE SAYING YOU DON'T WANT
MORE NUCLEAR WEAPONS IN THE
WORLD BUT YOU'RE OKAY WITH JAPAN
AND SOUTH KOREA HAVING NUCLEAR
WEAPONS.
>> WHEN I HEAR OBAMA GET UP AND
SAY THE BIGGEST THREAT TO THE
WORLD TODAY IS GLOBAL WARMING, I
SAY IS THIS GUY KIDDING?
THE ONLY GLOBAL WARMING -- THE
ONLY GLOBAL WARMING I'M WORRIED
ABOUT IS NUCLEAR GLOBAL WARMING
BECAUSE THAT'S THE SINGLE
BIGGEST THREAT.
IT'S NOT THAT I'M A -- WE CAN'T
AIN ORDER IT ANYMORE.
WE'RE SITTING ON A TREMENDOUS
BUBBLE.
AGAIN, $21 TRILLION.
>> DO YOU HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT
JAPAN OR SOUTH KOREA GETTING
NUCLEAR WEAPONS?
>> WHEN YOU SEE THE MONEY OUR
COUNTRY IS SPENDING ON MILITARY,
WE'RE NOT SPENDING IT ON
OURSELVES, WE'RE PROTECTING
THESE NATIONS ALL OVER THE
WORLD.
WE AFFORD TO DO IT
ANYMORE.
NOT BIG ENOUGH TO BANKRUPT AND
DESTROY THE UNITED STATES.
THAT'S WHAT'S HAPPENING.
WE CAN'T AFFORD IT.
IT'S VERY SIMPLE.
I WOULD RATHER SEE JAPAN HAVING
SOME FORM OF DEFENSE AND MAYBE
EVEN OFFENSE AGAINST NORTH
KOREA.
BECAUSE WE'RE NOT PULLING THE
TRIGGER.
THE BOTTOM LINE ON NORTH KOREA,
CHINA, IF THEY WANTED TO,
THEY'RE A TREMENDOUS SUPPLIER OF
NORTH KOREA, HAVE TREMENDOUS
POWER OVER NORTH KOREA.
IF THEY WANTED TO, IF THEY
WEREN'T TOYING WITH US,
ANDERSON, CHINA COULD MAKE A
DEAL IN ONE DAY --
>> I WANT TO BRING A LAST
QUESTION BEFORE WE DO, I WANT TO
ASK YOU ABOUT THE BACK AND FORTH
BETWEEN YOU AND SENATOR CRUZ
ABOUT WIVES.
AFTER SAYING YOU WERE GOING TO
SPILL THE BEANS ABOUT HEIDI
CRUZ, YOU RETWEETED AN
UNFLATTERING PICTURE OF HER NEXT
TO A PICTURE OF YOUR WIFE.
>> I THOUGHT IT WAS A NICE
PICTURE OF HEIDI.
I THOUGHT IT WAS FINE.
SHE'S A PRETTY WOMAN.
>> YOU'RE RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES.
>> EXCUSE ME, I DIDN'T START IT.
>> SIR, WITH ALL DUE RESPECT,
THAT'S THE ARGUMENT OF A
5-YEAR-OLD.
>> NO, IT'S NOT.
>> THE ARGUMENT OF A 5-YEAR-OLD
IS HE STARTED.
>> YOU WOULD SAY THAT.
THAT'S THE PROBLEM WITH OUR
COUNTRY.
>> EVERY PARENT KNOWS A KID WHO
SAYS HE STARTED IT.
>> NO, NO.
THAT'S THE PROBLEM.
EXACTLY THAT THINKING IS THE
PROBLEM THIS COUNTRY HAS.
I DID NOT START THIS.
HE SENT OUT A PICTURE AND HE
KNEW VERY WELL --
>> HE DIDN'T SEND OUT A PICTURE.
IT WAS AN AINTI-TRUMP SUPERPAC
SENT IT OUT.
>> A COVER STORY TAKEN BY ONE OF
THE GREAT PHOTOGRAPHERS OF THE
WORLD, MY WIFE WAS A VERY, VERY
SUCCESSFUL MODEL, LIKE ONE OF
THE MOST.
IT WAS A PICTURE FOR THE COVER
OF "GQ" WHICH IS A VERY GOOD
MAGAZINE.
>> THIS WASN'T EVEN A PRO --
>> THEY WERE ROMNEY PEOPLE.
ROMNEY IS EMBARRASSED HE DID SO
BADLY YEARS AGO.
>> DO YOU HAVE PROOF HE SENT IT
OUT?
>> EVERYBODY KNOWS HE SENT IT
OUT.
HE KNEW THE PEOPLE IN THE
SUPERPAC.
HE KNEW -- I WOULD BE WILLING TO
BET HE WROTE THE PHRASE.
YOU KNOW, THIS IS -- WOULD YOU
LIKE TO HAVE THIS AS YOUR FIRST
LADY?
A LOT OF PEOPLE SAID, YES,
ACTUALLY, IF YOU WANT TO KNOW
THE TRUTH.
BUT SHE WAS A MAGNIFICENT MODEL.
SHE TOOK A PICTURE WITH ONE OF
THE GREAT PHOTOGRAPHERS OF THE
WORLD.
PUT IT ON "GQ."
ALL OF A SUDDEN WE SEE THIS
PICTURE GOING ALL OVER UTAH
BEFORE THE ELECTION.
BY THE WAY, HE SAID WE HAD A BIG
DAY, WE WON UTAH.
EXCUSE ME, I WON ARIZONA WITH
FAR MORE DELEGATES AND AS YOU
PROBABLY SAW, 25 MINUTES AGO, SO
MAYBE YOU DIDN'T SEE IT, THE
VOTE WAS JUST COUNTED IN
MISSOURI AND I WON MISSOURI,
TOO.
>> CONGRATULATIONS.
>> ANOTHER 12 OR 13 DELEGATES.
>> YOUR WIFE IS LOVELY, SHE'S
VERY INTELLIGENT.
HEIDI CRUZ, I HAVEN'T
INTERVIEWED HER, SHE SEEMS LIKE
A VERY INTELLIGENT, VERY
ACCOMPLISHED PERSON AS WELL.
CAN YOU JUST LEAVE WIVES OUT OF
THIS?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
I'D LIKE TO DO IT.
>> BUT WHY RETWEET --
>> I WOULD LOVE TO DO IT.
I REALLY WOULD RATHER TALK ABOUT
NUCLEAR PROLIFERATION.
>> YOU ACT AS IF --
>> LET ME JUST TELL YOU
SOMETHING.
I WOULD LOVE TO DO IT.
I DIDN'T SEND THE PHOTO TO
EVERYBODY IN THE STATE OF UTAH.
HE DID.
HE KNEW ABOUT IT.
IT WAS HIS PEOPLE, HIS FRIENDS.
>> DO YOU HAVE TO RETWEET SOME
RANDOM PERSON SENDING YOU --
>> I DON'T LET THINGS GO SO
EASY.
LET ME TELL YOU SOMETHING.
I DON'T LET THE -- IF I WERE
RUNNING THE COUNTRY, I WOULDN'T
HAVE PEOPLE TAKING ADVANTAGE OF
THE UNITED STATES IN TRADE AND
IN OFFEEVERY OTHER WAY, EITHER.
BELIEVE ME, I WOULDN'T HAVE
CHINA WALKING AWAY WITH TRADE
DEFICITS OF $505 BILLION A YEAR.
I WOULDN'T HAVE MEXICO LAUGHING
AT US HOW STUPID WE ARE WITH
TRADE DEALS AND AT THE BORDER.
I WOULDN'T LET JAPAN GET AWAY
WHAT THEY'RE DOING WITH, YOU
KNOW, DEVALUATION OF THE YEN.
CHINA BIG LEAGUE DEEVALDEVALUAT
>> CAN YOU SAY NO MORE SUCH
ABOUT WIVES?
>> IT'S RIDICULOUS.
>> LET'S GO TO THE AUDIENCE.
I WANT YOU TO MEET RETIRE
LIEUTENANT BRIAN MURPHY, FIRST
OFFICER TO REPORT TO THE SIEKH
TEMPLE IN OAK CREEK.
HIS OFFICER IS STANDING NEXT TO
HIM.
SAM LENDA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
.
>> GREAT.
>> HIS FELLOW OFFICER IS
STANDING NEXT TO HIM, SAM, TOOK
OUT THE SHOOTER THAT DAY, IS
ALSO WITH US.
WE WANT TO JUST FIRST OF ALL
TAKE A MOMENT TO THANK BOTH OF
THEM FOR THEIR SERVICE AND THEIR
ACTIONS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BRIAN HAS A QUESTION FOR YOU
TONIGHT.
HE LIKES GOVERNOR KASICH BUT
HE'S STILL UNDECIDED.
BRIAN?
>> GOOD EVENING, MR. TRUMP.
I HAVE A QUESTION.
IN LIGHT OF THE BRUSSELS AND
PARIS ATTACKS A KNEE-JERK
REACTION IS A BACKLASH AGAINST
SPECIFIC MINORITY RELIGIOUS
GROUPS.
THIS IN TURN BRINGS ABOUT THINGS
THAT CAUSE DAMAGE ALL OVER.
IN MILWAUKEE, YOU HEARD ABOUT
THE SIKH TEMPLE SHOOTING.
SIX PEOPLE WERE KILLED.
99% OF THE MEN IN THE UNITED
STATES WHO WEAR TURBANS ARE
ACTUALLY SIKH AND NOT MUSLIM.
HOW WOULD YOU SUGGEST WE HELP
EDUCATE THE PUBLIC AND NOT
ALIENATE THESE GROUPS AND AT THE
SAME TIME, HOW DO WE PROTECT THE
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS OF
MINORITY GROUPS LIKE THE MUSLIM,
SIKH, HINDU, AND JEWS WHILE
STILL ADDRESSING RADICAL
ISLAMIZATION?
>> THANK YOU FOR THE QUESTION.
WE HAVE A TREMENDOUS PROBLEM
WITH RADICAL ISLAM WHETHER WE
LIKE IT OR DON'T.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO WON'T
TALK ABOUT IT.
TED WAS SAYING THE SAME THING.
WE HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO WON'T
TALK ABOUT IT.
WHY HE WON'T TALK ABOUT IT,
PERHAPS ONLY HE KNOWS.
IT'S A DISGRACE WHAT'S GOING ON.
WE HAVE A SERIOUS, SERIOUS
PROBLEM AND WHEN I CALLED FOR A
TEMPORARY BAN, I THOUGHT THAT
WAS A VERY BAD THING FOR ME TO
DO POLITICALLY, BUT I FELT I
SHOULD DO IT.
I DIDN'T KNOW I WOULD GO UP IN
THE POLL AS OPPOSED TO DOWN.
I REALLY FELT THERE HAD TO BE
SOMETHING DONE.
THAT WAS AFTER THE HORRIBLE SAN
BERNARDINO, CALIFORNIA,
SITUATION.
AFTER OBVIOUSLY PARIS WHICH WAS
TE
T
TERRIBLE.
WE TALK ABOUT PARIS WITH THE
GUN-FREE ZONE AND GUN LAWS.
NOBODY HAD GUNS EXCEPT THE BAD
GUYS.
IF WE WOULD HAVE HAD GUNS ON THE
OTHER SIDE IN TERMS OF 2nd
AMENDMENT, SAME THING WITH SAN
BERNARDINO, IF BULLETS WERE
GOING IN THE OPPOSITE DIRECTION,
YOU WOULDN'T HAVE HAD THE
PROBLEMS YOU HAD IN THOSE TWO
CLAS
PLACES I CAN TELL YOU.
WE HAVE TO CHERISH OUR 2nd
AMENDMENT.
VERY, VERY IMPORTANT.
I CAN SAY THIS, WHEN I CALLED
FOR THE TEMPORARY BANNING, YOU
HAVE TO LOOK AT IT, WE HAVE A
VERY, VERY SERIOUS PROBLEM WITH
RADICAL ISLAM AND IF WE DON'T
WANT TO DISCUSS IT AND IF WE
DON'T WANT TO LOOK AT IT, WE'RE
NEVER GOING TO SOLVE THE
PROBLEM.
WE HAVE TO BE EXTREMELY STRONG
WITH ISIS.
WE HAVE TO WIPE ISIS OFF THE
FACE OF THE EARTH SO FAST AND SO
VIOLENTLY, WE HAVE NO CHOICE.
WE HAVE NO CHOICE.
AND I WAS AGAINST THE WAR IN
IRAQ.
OKAY?
I AM NOT A FAST TRIGGER.
I'M EXACTLY THE OPPOSITE OF
THAT.
WE SHOULD HAVE NEVER GONE IN.
IT DESTABILIZED THE MIDDLE EAST.
I TELL YOU THIS, WE GOT OUT.
OBAMA GOT US OUT VERY BADLY.
INSTEAD OF LEAVING SOME TROOPS,
INSTEAD OF GIVING A DATE, THE
EXACT TIME.
I WOULD SAY THIS, THOUGH.
WE HAVE NO CHOICE BUT TO LOOK AT
THAT.
WE HAVE TO BE VERY, VERY
VIGILANT, VERY SMART AND
FRANKLY, BRIAN, WE HAVE TO BE
VERY, VERY TOUGH.
BECAUSE IT'S ONLY GOING TO GET
WORSE.
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE ARE BEING
ALLOWED INTO THIS COUNTRY OVER
SHORT PERIODS OF TIME COMING
SUPPOSEDLY FROM SYRIA.
WE HAVE NO IDEA WHO THEY ARE,
HAVE NO IDEA WHERE IS THEIR
PAPERWORK.
THEY HAVE NO PAPERWORK, THEY
HAVE NO IDENTIFICATION.
THEY'RE COMING INTO THIS COUNTRY
AND IT'S GOING TO BE A BIG, BIG
PROBLEM.
>> THE OTHER, THOUGH, PART OF
LIEUTENANT MURPHY'S QUESTION WAS
ABOUT PROTECTING THE RIGHTS OF
MINORITY GROUPS, OF MUSLIMS, OF
SIKHS, JEWS, OTHERS INSIDE THE
UNITED STATES.
>> I WANT TO DO THAT ALSO.
AT THE SAME TIME WE HAVE TO
RECOGNIZE WE HAVE A SERIOUS
PROBLEM.
>> LET ME FOLLOW-UP ON THAT.
YOU SAID YOU AGREED THE OTHER
DAY, I THINK YOU SAID YOU AGREED
WITH SENATOR TED CRUZ'S PROPOSAL
IN THE WAKE OF THE BRUSSELS
ATTACKS THAT LAW ENFORCEMENT
SHOULD, I QUOTE, "PATROL AND
SECURE MUSLIM NEIGHBORHOODS
BEFORE THEY BECOME RADICALIZED."
BILL BRATTON, COMMISSIONER,
CHEAP OF POLICE --
>> I LIKE VERY MUCH.
>> IN YOUR HOME CITY.
CHIEF OF POLICE UNDER GIULIANI
AS WELL AS de BLASIO, AGAIN,
ALSO OUT IN L.A.
HE SAID ABOUT TED CRUZ'S
PROPOSAL, "WE DO NOT PATROL AND
SECURE NEIGHBORHOODS BASED ON
SELECTIVE ENFORCEMENT BECAUSE OF
RACE OR RELIGION."
IS HE WRONG?
>> I THINK WE HAVE TO BE
EXTREMELY INDIVIDVIGILANT IN TH
AREAS AND LOOK SERIOUSLY AT THE
AMO
MOSQUES.
LOOK AT WHAT'S GOING ON IN PARIS
WHERE MOSQUES ARE BEING CLOSED,
OKAY, AND HAVE TO LOOK VERY,
VERY SERIOUSLY.
>> A LOT OF MUSLIMS IN AMERICA
HEAR THAT, YOU SAYING WE HAVE TO
LOOK SERIOUSLY AT THE MOSQUE AND
GET WORRIED.
>> IN SAN BERNARDINO, PEOPLE
KNEW WHAT WAS GOING ON.
THESE TWO PEOPLE -- HE PROBABLY
BECAME RADICALIZED THROUGH HER.
WHO KNOWS.
FRANKLY RIGHT NOW IT DOESN'T
MATTER.
THESE TWO PEOPLE KILLED THEIR
CO-WORKERS, ET CETERA, ET
CETERA, IN THEIR APARTMENT,
HOUSE, THE PLACE THEY LIVED.
THEY HAD BOMBS ALL OVER THE
APARTMENT.
>> DO YOU TRUST --
>> EXCUSE ME.
THEY HAD BOMBS ON THE FLOOR.
MANY PEOPLE SAW THIS.
MANY, MANY PEOPLE.
MUSLIMS LIVING WITH THEM IN THE
SAME AREA.
THEY SAW THAT HOUSE.
THEY SAW THAT.
ONE DIDN'T WANT TO TURN -- HE
SAID I DON'T WANT TO TURN HIM IN
BECAUSE I DON'T WANT TO BE
ACCUSED OF RACIAL PROFILING.
HE SAW BOMBS ALL OVER THE
APARTMENT, OKAY?
IT'S JUST AN EXCUSE.
>> DO YOU TRUST MUSLIMS IN
AMERICA?
>> DO I WHAT?
>> TRUST MUSLIMS IN AMERICA.
>> MANY OF THEM I DO.
MANY OF THEM I DO.
SOME I GUESS WE DON'T.
WE HAVE A PROBLEM.
AND WE CAN TRY AND BE VERY
POLITICALLY CORRECT AND PRETEND
WE DON'T HAVE A PROBLEM, BUT
ANDERSON, WE HAVE A MAJOR, MAJOR
PROBLEM.
THIS IS IN A SENSE THIS IS A
WAR.
>> SPECIAL PATROLS IN MUSLIM
NEIGHBORHOODS?
>> EXCUSE ME.
NOBODY WANTS TO CALL IT A WAR.
THERE'S A WAR.
THE DIFFERENCE IS, IT'S NOT LIKE
YOU'RE FIGHTING GERMANY OR
JAPAN, THEY HAVE A UNIFORM, WE
HAVE A UNIFORM, EVERYBODY HAS A
DIFFERENT UNIFORM.
WE DON'T KNOW WHERE THESE PEOPLE
ARE.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET JEFF
JOHNS, A FINANCIAL CONSULTANT.
HE SAID HE IS ON THE TRUMP TRAIN
AS OF THIS POINT.
>> I LIKE HIM.
I LIKE HIM VERY MUCH.
>> I KNEW YOU WOULD.
>> THANK YOU FOR COMING TO THE
GREAT CITY OF MILWAUKEE.
>> THANK YOU, JEFF.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU HAVE A HIGH
NET WORTH IN THE BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS BUT MANY PEOPLE DON'T
THINK THAT YOU'RE A SUCCESSFUL
BUSINESSMAN.
THEY REFER TO YOUR INHERITED
WEALTH AND HOW IT'S JUST A TRACK
THAT PAYS THE AVERAGE MARKET
INDEX.
MR. TRUMP, WHAT DO YOU SAY TO
THOSE PEOPLE THAT DO NOT THINK
THAT YOU'RE A SUCCESSFUL
BUSINESSMAN?
>> I LOVE THE QUESTION BECAUSE
IT'S SUCH A LIE.
I STARTED OFF IN BROOKLYN.
MY FATHER WAS A BUILDER IN
BROOKLYN.
BROOKLYN HAD NOT A LOT OF VALUE.
BROOKLYN WAS NOT A GREAT PLACE
TO BE.
I ALWAYS WANTED TO GO INTO
MANHATTAN.
MY FATHER, MY FIRST DEAL, MY
FIRST LOAN WAS $1 MILLION FROM
MY FATHER WHICH WAS A LOAN, I
HAD TO PAY HIM BACK.
I DID NUMEROUS DEALS IN
MANHATTAN.
MY FATHER SAID DON'T GO INTO
MANHATTAN, IT'S NOT OUR
TERRITORY, WE CAN'T DO THAT,
IT'S NOT FOR US.
I STARTED OFF WITH A VERY, VERY
SMALL AMOUNT OF MONEY.
BY THE WAY, WHEN MY FATHER
PASSED AWAY, REMEMBER, I HAVE
FOUR, A TOTAL OF FIVE IN MY
FAMILY.
WE HAVE BROTHERS, SISTERS,
SPLIT.
WHEN MY FATHER DIED, BY THAT
TIME I HAD ALREADY BUILT A GREAT
FORTUNE AND MY FATHER DIDN'T
LEAVE A GREAT FORTUNE.
IT WAS BROOKLYN AND QUEENS REAL
ESTATE AND IT WASN'T A GREAT
FORTUNE.
NOW WHAT THEY DO IS THEY BUILD
IT UP LIKE, OH, HE LEFT -- I
STARTED OFF -- YOU UNDERSTAND,
YOU KNOW THE TRUE ANSWER BECAUSE
YOU'RE SOMEBODY WHO UNDERSTANDS
ME AND UNDERSTAND WHERE IT
STARTED.
I STARTED OFF WITH $1 MILLION
AND NOW I'M WORTH OVER $10
BILLION.
AND I FILED MY PAPERS WITH THE
ELECTION COMMITTEES, WITH THE
FEDERAL ELECTION, AND PEOPLE IN
YOUR WORLD, IN YOUR PROFESSION,
ARE DOWN THERE, OR HAVE BEEN
DOWN THERE ALL THE TIME AND THEY
CAN'T BELIEVE HOW GREAT THOSE
PAPERS ARE.
VERY LITTLE DEBT.
SOME OF THE GREATEST ASSETS IN
THE WORLD.
AND VERY IMPORTANTLY, TREMENDOUS
CASH FLOW AND I DON'T SAY THAT
IN A BRAGGING WAY.
I SAY THAT BECAUSE THAT'S THE
KIND OF THINKING THAT OUR
COUNTRY NEEDS.
I WANT TO SAY THIS, BEFORE MY
FATHER DIED, HE SAID, EVERYTHING
DONALD TOUCHES TURNS TO GOLD.
IT'S ABSOLUTELY -- HE WAS SO
PROUD OF ME BUT I BORROWED VERY
LITTLE MONEY FROM MY FATHER.
WHAT I DID BORROW AND THE THING
THAT REALLY HELPED ME WITH MY
FATHER WAS HIS KNOWLEDGE.
HE WAS AN EXCELLENT NEGOTIATOR,
EXCELLENT BUILDER.
HE BUILT IN BROOKLYN AND QUEENS,
THERE WASN'T THAT MUCH MONEY IN
BROOKLYN AND QUEENS.
>> A LOT OF OTHER CANDIDATES
HAVE RELEASED TAX RETURNS.
YOU SAY YOU WON'T RELEASE THEM
BECAUSE YOU'RE BEING AUDITED.
SOME PEOPLE DOUBT YOU'RE BEING
AUDITED --
>> WOULD YOU LIKE A LETTER?
I'LL GIVE IT TO YOU.
>> CAN YOU?
>> SURE.
ABSOLUTELY.
>> PEOPLE HAVE RAISED THAT AS A
DOUBT.
>> ONLY A FOOL WOULD GIVE A TAX
RETURN --
>> YOU CAN OFFER EVIDENCE YOU'RE
BEING AUDITED?
>> I'LL GIVE YOU A LETTER FROM
THE BIGGEST FIRM IN WASHINGTON
THAT DOES MY WORK FOR ME.
>> ALL RIGHT.
>> OKAY?
SURE.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET ROBERTS.
HE'S RETIRED FROM THE U.S. ARMY
AFTER SERVING IN IRAQ AND
AFGHANISTAN.
HE'S NOW A STUDENT AT MARQUETTE
UNIVERSITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
ROBERT?
>> GOOD EVENING, MR. TRUMP.
IN YOUR OPINION, WHAT ARE THE
TOP THREE FUNCTIONS OF THE
UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT?
>> SAY IT AGAIN?
>> IN YOUR OPINION, WHAT ARE THE
TOP THREE FUNCTIONS OF THE
UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT?
>> WELL, THE GREATEST FUNCTION
OF ALL BY FAR IS SECURITY FOR
OUR NATION.
I WOULD ALSO SAY HEALTH CARE, I
WOULD ALSO SAID EDUCATION.
THERE ARE MANY, MANY THINGS, BUT
I WOULD SAY THE TOP THREE ARE
SECURITY, SECURITY, SECURITY.
WE HAVE TO HAVE SECURITY FOR OUR
COUNTRY SO WE CAN CONTINUE TO
EXIST AS A COUNTRY.
WE ARE IN DANGER.
THOUSANDS AND THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE ARE INFILTRATING OUR
COUNTRY.
WE DON'T KNOW WHO THEY ARE.
THERE'S A VERY VICIOUS WORLD.
WE'RE LIVING IN A VERY VICIOUS
WORLD AND WE'RE DOING SOMETHING
THAT IS AGAINST A LOT OF VERY
SMART PEOPLE'S WISHES.
I CAN FELL YOU, IT'S TOTALLY
AGAINST MY WISHES.
>> TOP THREE, SECURITY.
>> SECURITY.
I SAY ALL TOP THREE ARE
SECURITY, BUT HEALTH CARE,
EDUCATION, WOULD BE PROBABLY
THREE THAT WOULD BE TOP.
AND THEN YOU CAN GO ON FROM
THERE.
BUT THE MILITARY AND THE SECURE
COUNTRY, SO WE HAVE A COUNTRY.
BELIEVE ME, WE'VE NEVER BEEN IN
A POSITION, IN MY OPINION, WHERE
OUR COUNTRY IS SO VULNERABLE.
OUR MILITARY IS BEING EATEN
AWAY.
WHEN GENERAL ODIERNO LEFT
RECENTLY, A YEAR AGO, I WAS
WATCHING HIM ON MAYBE YOUR SHOW,
ONE OF THE SHOWS AND HE SAID
THAT THE UNITED STATES ARMY, THE
UNITED STATES MILITARY FORCES,
HAVE NEVER BEEN SO -- AND I
THINK HE USED THE WORD DEPLETED.
BASICALLY HE SAID THEY'RE
EXHAUSTED.
>> JUST TO FOLLOW-UP, THOUGH --
>> THAT'S A PRETTY -- THAT'S A
PRETTY SAD COMMENTARY.
AND HONESTLY, EVEN THOUGH HE WAS
RETIRING AT THE TIME AND I HAD A
LOT OF RESPECT FOR HIM, GOOD
MAN, BUT EVEN THOUGH HE WAS
LEAVING AT THE TIME, PEOPLE
SHOULDN'T SAY THAT BECAUSE
YOU'RE GIVING THE ENEMY IDEAS.
BUT IF I GET IN, OUR MILITARY
WILL BE BIGGER, BETTER, STRONGER
THAN EVER BEFORE.
IT'S THE CHEAPEST THING WE CAN
DO.
>> SO IN TERMS OF FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT ROLE, YOU'RE SAYING
SECURITY, BUT YOU ALSO SAY
HEALTH CARE AND EDUCATION SHOULD
BE PROVIDED BY THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT?
>> THOSE ARE TWO OF THE THINGS.
YEAH, SURE.
THERE ARE OBVIOUSLY MANY THINGS,
HOUSING, PROVIDING GREAT
NEIGHBORHOODS --
>> AREN'T YOU AGAINST THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT'S INVOLVEMENT
IN EDUCATION?
DON'T YOU WANT IT TO DEVOLVE TO
STATES?
>> I WANT IT TO GO TO STATE.
ABSOLUTELY.
>> THAT'S NOT PART OF WHAT THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT'S --
>> THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT, BUT
THE CONCEPT OF THE COUNTRY IS
THE CONCEPT THAT WE HAVE TO HAVE
EDUCATION WITHIN THE COUNTRY AND
HAVE TO GET RID OF COMMON CORE
AND IT SHOULD BE BROUGHT TO THE
STATE LEVEL.
>> AND FEDERAL HEALTH CARE RUN
BY THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT?
>> HEALTH CARE.
WE NEED HEALTH CARE FOR OUR
PEOPLE.
WE NEED A GOOD -- OBAMACARE IS A
DISASTER.
>> IS THAT SOMETHING THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE DOING?
>> THE GOVERNMENT CAN LEAD IT
BUT IT SHOULD BE PRIVATELY DONE.
IT SHOULD BE PRIVATELY DONE SO
THAT HEALTH CARE, IN MY OPINION,
WE SHOULD PROBABLY HAVE -- WE
HAVE TO HAVE PRIVATE HEALTH
CARE.
WE DON'T HAVE COMPETITION IN
HEALTH CARE.
THE PROBLEM THAT WE HAVE IN OUR
COUNTRY IS WE DON'T HAVE
COMPETITION.
IT'S MADE BECAUSE THE
POLITICIANS -- BY THE WAY, I'M
SELF-FUNDING.
I AM SELF-FUNDING.
SO THE HEALTH CARE COMPANIES
AREN'T TAKING CARE OF ME.
BUT THEY'RE TAKING CARE OF
EVERYONE ELSE.
WAIT ONE SECOND.
WE DON'T HAVE -- WE DON'T HAVE
BIDDING.
WE DON'T HAVE COMPETITION IN
HEALTH CARE.
AND IT'S A DISASTER.
OBAMACARE, IF YOU TAKE A LOOK AT
YOUR PREMIUMS, GOING UP 35%,
45%, 55% AND THE DEDUCTIBLES ARE
SO HIGH, YOU'LL NEVER GET TO USE
IT.
>> YOU ALWAYS SAY YOU'RE
SELF-FUNDING.
HOW MUCH DO YOU THINK YOUR
CAMPAIGN HAS COST -- IN THE PAST
YOU SAID $25 MILLION.
>> I CAN TELL YOU, I'D SAY I'M
IN RIGHT NOW FOR -- NOW, I'M IN
FOR ABOUT $35 MILLION RIGHT NOW.
>> OKAY.
>> WE TAKE THE SMALL LOANS, THE
PEOPLE THAT SEND $17.50, OR
$250, EVEN $1,000 --
>> YOU SOLICIT THOSE ON YOUR
WEBSITE.
>> NO, I SELL HATS AND SHIRTS --
>> YOU DO SOLICIT DONATIONS ON
YOUR WEBSITE.
>> I DON'T THINK SO.
>> YEAH, YOU DO.
YOU HAVE TWO SPOTS.
>> IT'S PEANUTS.
>> IT'S NOT PEANUTS.
>> I'M IN FOR --
>> A THIRD OF YOUR CAMPAIGN SP
FUNDED BY OTHER PEOPLE.
>> WHATEVER THE HATS ARE, THEY
COST SOMETHING.
>> YOU RAISED $7 MILLION LAST
TIME I CHECKED FROM INDIVIDUAL
DONATIONS.
>> I'M NOT SOLICITING MONEY FROM
INSURANCE COMPANIES AND LUMBER
COMPANIES AND FROM BANKS AND
FROM -- IF I DID, I WOULD HAVE
MADE JEB BUSH LOOK LIKE A BABY.
I HAVE TURNED DOWN MORE $10
MILLION OFFERS.
JUST THE OTHER NIGHT, I'M IN
FLORIDA, AND A VERY, VERY RICH
FRIEND OF MINE COMES UP, DONALD,
I'D LIKE TO GIVE YOU $10
MILLION, I'LL GIVE YOU
ANYTHING --
>> YOU'VE ACTUALLY BEEN LOANING
YOUR CAMPAIGN A LOT OF MONEY.
ARE YOU GOING TO HAVE YOUR
CAMPAIGN PAY YOU BACK?
>> I DOUBT IT.
IT SEEMS TO BE THE WAY --
>> THAT'S A POSSIBILITY?
>> CAN I BE HONEST?
NEVER EVEN THOUGHT ABOUT IT.
JUST SEEMS TO ME THE WAY THE
LAWYERS SET IT UP.
I AM IN RIGHT NOW, I PUT IN MY
MONEY ABOUT $35 MILLION.
I THINK IN TERMS OF SMALL
DONATIONS, I THINK WE'VE
RECEIVED $6 MILLION.
UP UNTIL THIS POINT.
>> I THINK I SAW $7 MILLION.
>> EXCUSE ME.
A LOT OF THAT IS THE SELLING OF
MERCHANDISE AND THINGS LIKE
THAT.
THERE'S NO INFLUENCE OVER ME.
IT'S NOT LIKE THE BANKS ARE
GIVING ME MONEY AND I'M GOING TO
DO FAVORS FOR THE BANKS.
TED CRUZ, THE BANKS ARE GIVING
HIM A LOT OF MONEY, I'MOIL AND
ARE GIVING HIM A LOT OF MONEY.
SUPERPACS ARE A DISASTER.
IF THEY'RE NOT GOTTEN RID OF,
IT'S GOING TO GET WORSE.
>> I WANT TO INTRODUCE YOU TO
AMELIA ROLL AT UNIVERSITY OF
WISCONSIN.
THE FIRST CHOICE IS SENATOR
CRUZ, YOU'RE HER SECOND PICK.
HERE'S YOUR CHANCE TO WIN HER
OVER.
AMELIA?
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU SO MUCH
FOR BEING HERE TONIGHT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> MR. TRUMP, IN A RECENT
INTERVIEW WITH THE "WASHINGTON
POST," YOU SAID THE U.S. SHOULD
BECOME A DIMINISHING PRESENCE IN
NATO.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> WHY DO YOU THINK THE U.S.
SHOULD START TO WITHDRAW THEIR
WORLD PRESENCE FROM NATE DOE,
WHAT WOULD YOU CHANGE ABOUT THE
ORGANIZATION SO WE COULD REMAIN
INVOLVED?
>> I DID TWO INTERVIEWS
RECENTLY, "THE NEW YORK TIMES"
WHICH TREATED ME UNBELIEVABLY
FAIRLY.
THERE WAS A FRONT PAGE STORY ON
SUNDAY I THINK.
IT WAS A GREAT STORY.
PART OF IT WAS -- THE OTHER WAS
THE "WASHINGTON POST."
>> YOU TALKED TO THEM LONGER
THAN ANY OTHER CANDIDATE.
>> DAVID, HE'S A VERY TALENTED
WRITER.
THEY TREATED ME FAIRLY.
THE "WASHINGTON POST," I SAID
SIMILAR THINGS AND SIMILAR
THINGS ABOUT NATO.
LET ME TELL YOU, NATO IS
OBSOLETE.
IT WAS 67 YEARS OR IT'S OVER 60
YEARS OLD.
IT IS -- MANY COUNTRIES, DOESN'T
COVER TERRORISM.
OKAY?
IT COVERS THE SOVIET UNION WHICH
IS NO LONGER IN EXISTENCE.
AND NATO HAS TO EITHER BE
REJIGGERED, CHANGED FOR THE
BETTER.
I'M NOT SAYING -- THE OTHER
THING THAT'S BAD ABOUT NATO,
WE'RE PAYING TOO MUCH.
WE'RE SPENDING A TREMENDOUS,
BILLIONS AND BILLIONS OF DOLLARS
ON NATO.
>> YOU'RE SAYING IT'S OBSOLETE,
THOUGH.
YOU HAVE NOW VLADIMIR PUTIN
IN
INVADING, ANNEXING PART OF
UKRAINE.
ANNEXING CRIMEA.
>> LET ME TELL YOU ABOUT
UKRAINE.
FIRST OF ALL --
>> THERE A LOT OF PEOPLE BELIEVE
NATO --
>> YOU HAVE COUNTRIES THAT
SURROUND UKRAINE.
THEY DON'T TALK.
THEY DON'T SEEM TO HAVE A
PROBLEM.
I'M NOT SAYING GO IN.
I SAY YAW CAN BE VERY STRONG,
STRONG WITHOUT BEING -- THE
MONEY WE SPEND IS ASTRONOMICAL
ON NATO.
OKAY.
UKRAINE --
>> YOU REALLY THINK NATO IS
OBSOLETE?
>> I THINK IT'S LARGELY
OBSOLETE, YEAH.
IT'S GOT TO BE CHANGED.
YOU DON'T TALK ABOUT TERROR.
OUR SINGLE BIGGEST THREAT RIGHT
NOW IS TERROR, OKAY?
NOW THAT'S AN AMORPHOUS TERM BUT
IT'S TERROR.
OUR SINGLE BIGGEST THREAT --
>> YOU'D LIKE TO SEE AN
ORGANIZATION REVAMPED --
>> NOW IF YOU DO THAT, YOU'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO OBVIOUSLY ADD
DIFFERENT NATIONS IN BECAUSE YOU
HAVE NATIONS THAT AREN'T IN NATO
THAT ARE VERY MUCH INTO THE
WORLD OF TERROR.
BOTH IN TERMS OF CAUSING IT AND
RECEIVING IT.
SO YOU PROBABLY HAVE TO EITHER
START SOMETHING OR YOU HAVE TO
DO SOMETHING.
WHEN YOU LOOK AT BRUSSELS, HEY,
LOOK, YOU REMEMBER A COUPLE OF
MONTHS AGO, I MADE A STATEMENT
ABOUT BRUSSELS.
I SAID IT'S A HELL HOLE.
THAT'S BECAUSE IT'S A FINANCIAL,
VERY BIG FINANCIAL CAPITAL.
MANY OF MY FRIENDS ARE THERE.
THEY KNOW EXACTLY WHAT'S GOING
ON.
I HAVEN'T BEEN THERE IN MANY
YEARS.
I WAS THERE.
IT WAS A BEAUTIFUL CITY.
NOW IT'S NOT GOOD.
AND I SAID IT WAS A HE ERKS LRK
LLL HOLE.
"THE NEW YORK TIMES" ATTACKED ME
RATHER VICIOUSLY FOR CALLING A
PLACE A HELL HOLE.
TWO MONTHS LATER WE HAD THE
ATTACK AND IT TURNED OUT I WAS
RIGHT.
IT'S A HELL HOLE.
ON TWITTER, ALL OVER THE PLACE
THEY'RE SAYING TRUMP WAS RIGHT,
TRUMP WAS RIGHT.
I UNDERSTAND THIS STUFF.
I MEAN, I REALLY DO UNDERSTAND
THIS STUFF.
NATO IS OBSOLETE.
NOW, THAT DOESN'T MEAN IT CAN'T
BE REJIGGERED AND IT CAN'T BE
FIXED AND MADE GOOD OR --
>> FOR YOU --
>> IT'S POSSIBLE --
>> A FINANCIAL COMPONENT WHEN
YOU TALK ABOUT --
>> YOU HAVE COUNTRIES IN NATO, I
THINK IT'S 28 COUNTRIES,
COUNTRIES IN NATO ARE GETTING A
FREE RIDE AND IT'S UNFAIR, IT'S
VERY UNFAIR.
THE UNITED STATES CANNOT AFFORD
TO BE THE POLICEMEN OF THE WORLD
ANYMORE, FOLKS.
WE HAVE TO REBUILD OUR OWN
COUNTRY.
WE HAVE TO STOP WITH THIS STUFF.
YOU HAVE AS AN EXAMPLE, UKRAINE,
YOU DON'T HAVE GERMANY TALKING
ABOUT UKRAINE.
YOU DON'T HAVE MANY OF THE
COUNTRIES IN NATO TALKING
ABOUT -- IT'S ALWAYS US.
WE'RE ALWAYS THE FIRST ONE OUT.
WE HAVE VERY BIG PROBLEMS IN OUR
COUNTRY.
VERY, VERY BIG PROBLEMS.
NATO HAS TO BE EITHER CHANGED OR
WE HAVE TO DO SOMETHING.
AND WE SHOULDN'T BE PAYING MOST
OF THE COURSE OF NATE TOE
BEC.
IT'S UNFAIR TO OUR TAXPAYERS AND
PEOPLE.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK.
WE'LL HAVE MORE WITH DONALD
TRUMP AFTER THE QUICK BREAK WHEN
OUR "360" TOWN HALL COVERS FROM
RIVERSIDE THEATER IN DOWNTOWN
MILWAUKEE.
>>> AND WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE TALKING TO DONALD TRUMP.
A WEEK BEFORE THE WISCONSIN
PRIMARY, VOTERS ASKING THE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES THE
QUESTIONS THAT MATTER TO THEM
LOOKING FOR ANSWER TO HELP THEM
DECIDE.
BEFORE WE GO BACK TO THE
AUDIENCE, I WANT TO ASK YOU A
QUESTION I ASKED TO SENATOR CRUZ
AS WELL.
MORE THAN SIX MONTHS AGO YOU
PLEDGED TO SUPPORT THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE, WHOEVER THAT
MAY BE.
A LOT HAS CHANGED SINCE THEN.
IT SOUNDED WHEN I WAS PRESSING
SENATOR CRUZ ON IT, SOUNDED LIKE
HE WAS SAYING HE'D HAVE A HARD
TIME SUPPORTING SOMEBODY WHO
WENT AFTER HIS WIFE.
>> HONESTLY, HE DOESN'T HAVE TO
SUPPORT ME.
I'M NOT ASKING FOR HIS SUPPORT.
I WANT THE PEOPLE'S SUPPORT.
>> DO YOU CONTINUE TO PLEDGE
WHOEVER THE REPUBLICAN NOMINEE
IS?
>> NO.
I DON'T ANYMORE.
LOOK --
>> YOU DON'T?
>> NO.
WE'LL SEE WHO IT IS.
>> YOU WON'T PROMISE TO SUPPORT
THE REPUBLICAN NOMINEE?
>> HE WAS ESSENTIALLY SAYING THE
SAME THING.
LET ME JUST TELL YOU, HE DOESN'T
HAVE TO SUPPORT ME.
I HAVE TREMENDOUS SUPPORT RIGHT
NOW FROM THE PEOPLE.
I'M WAY OVER 2 MILLION VOTES
MORE THAN HIM.
I HAVE MANY, MANY MORE DELEGATES
THAN HIM.
LIKE MANY, MANY MORE DELEGATES.
AS I SAID BEFORE, HE WAS TALKING
ABOUT GREAT VICTORY THE NIGHT
UTAH -- WELL, I WON ARIZONA MANY
MORE DELEGATES.
MANY, MANY MORE DELEGATES.
I DON'T REALLY WANT HIM TO DO
SOMETHING HE'S NOT COMFORTABLE
WITH.
JUST LIKE I CAN'T IMAGINE JEB
BUSH.
LOOK, I BEAT THESE PEOPLE BADLY.
I BEAT JEB BUSH.
I BEAT THE GOVERNOR OF THIS
STATE.
THE GOVERNOR OF THIS STATE CAME
IN.
HE WAS FAVORED TO WIN.
HE WAS AT 22 POINTS.
THEN HE SAID SOMETHING BAD ABOUT
ME AND I HIT HIM VERY HARD AND
HE WENT BOOM AND HE LEFT THE
RACE.
HE WAS VERY EARLY.
>> JUST SO I'M CLEAR --
>> I DON'T WANT TO MAKE PEOPLE
UNCOMFORTABLE.
I DON'T NEED THEIR SUPPORT.
NOW MAYBE IT WILL BE A NEGATIVE,
MAYBE IT TWWON'T.
>> THE PLEDGE YOU TOOK IS NULL
AND VOID, SUPPORTING WHOEVER THE
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE IS, YOU SAY
YOU WILL NO LONGER GUARANTEE YOU
WILL SUPPORT THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINEE?
>> LOOK, I WON THE STATE OF
MISSOURI, RIGHT?
[ BOOING ]
NO, I HAVE.
CRUZ PEOPLE.
I'VE BEEN TREATED VERY UNFAIRLY.
>> UNFAIRLY BY WHO?
>> I THINK BY BASICALLY THE RNC.
THE REPUBLICAN PARTY.
THE ESTABLISHMENT.
YOU HAVE A GUY LIKE MITT ROMNEY
WHO LOST MISERABLY WHO DID A
TERRIBLE JOB.
HE RAN A HORRIBLE, HORRIBLE
CAMPAIGN.
THE LAST MONTH OF THAT -- I
HELPED HIM.
I RAISED HIM A MILLION --
>> DO YOU THINK THE RNC IS
PLOTTING TO TAKE THIS AWAY FROM
YOU AT THE CONVENTION?
>> I DON'T KNOW.
WE'LL SEE WHAT HAPPENS.
YOU'D HAVE UPSET PEOPLE IF THAT
HAPPENED.
JUST SO YOU UNDERSTAND, WHEN
ROMNEY CAME OUT AGAINST ANY, HE
RAN ONE OF THE WORST RACES IN
THE HISTORY OF PRESIDENTIAL
POLITICS.
HE OUGHT TO SIT BACK AND ROOT
FOR US INSTEAD OF BEING A
NEGATIVE FORCE AND WE HAVE
OTHERS ALSO.
THE BIGGEST STORY IN ALL OF
POLITICS WORLDWIDE WEIGHRIGHT N
YOU MIGHT AGREE TO THIS,S
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE ARE COMING IN
VOTING FOR ANY.
>> BEING INVOLVED IN THE
PROCESS.
>> WATCHING, ALL OF THIS.
YOUR RATINGS TONIGHT WILL BE
EXCELLENT, RIGHT?
THE DEBATE YOU HAD WHERE 23
MILLION PEOPLE, I DON'T WANT TO
SAY THIS BRAGEDLY, IF I WASN'T
IN IT --
>> IN THE OFF CHANCE YOU'RE NOT
THE REPUBLICAN NOMINEE, WHAT
WOULD YOU GO YOUR DECISION
WHETHER OR NOT YOU'D SUPPORT --
>> I'LL SEE WHO IT IS.
I'M NOT LOOKING TO HURT ANYBODY.
>> IF IT'S SENATOR TED CRUZ,
WOULD YOU SUPPORT HIM?
>> LOOK, HERE'S MY THING ON
CRUZ.
A LOT OF NASTY THINGS HAVE BEEN
SAID.
I'M A VERY HONORABLE GUY AND A
VERY HONEST GUY.
I DON'T DO -- I WOULD HAVE NEVER
DONE WHAT HE DID TO BEN CARSON,
WHO BY THE WAY, ENDORSED ME.
I WOULD HAVE NEVER GONE TO IOWA
AND SAID BEN CARSON HAS LEFT THE
RACE, HE IS GONE, 100 H%, VOTE R
ME, USHER PEOPLE INTO THE CAUCUS
AND GET THEM TO VOTE FOR TED
CRUZ.
A LOT OF PEOPLE LEFT BEN CARSON.
BEN CARSON IS AN HONORABLE GUY.
THAT'S A TERRIBLE THING TO DO.
THERE WERE OTHER TERRIBLE THINGS
TO DO, AND I HONESTLY, I WATCHED
HIM TONIGHT WITH YOU, AND I
WATCHED HOW TORMENTED HE WAS
WHEN YOU ASKED HIM THAT
QUESTION.
I DON'T WANT TO HAVE HIM
TORMENT.
I DON'T WANT TO HAVE HIM BE
TORMENTED.
LET ME JUST TELL YOU, I DON'T
WANT HIS SUPPORT.
I DON'T NEED HIS SUPPORT.
I WANT HIM TO BE COMFORTABLE.
NOW, IF HE WANTS TO SUPPORT ME,
THAT WOULD BE WONDERFUL BECAUSE
I THINK I'M GOING TO WIN.
LET ME JUST TELL YOU.
I WATCHED HIM, YOU KNOW, SKIRT
AROUND LIKE ANY POLITICIAN
WOULD.
SKIRT AROUND THE ISSUE.
I DON'T WANT TO MAKE PEOPLE LIKE
JEB BUSH, LIKE TED CRUZ, LIKE
GOVERNOR WALKER, I MEAN,
GOVERNOR WALKER, I HIT HIM VERY
HARD AFTER HE HIT ME.
I HIT HIM VERY HARD AND DROVE
HIM OUT OF THE RACE.
I DROVE JEB BUSH OUT OF THE
RACE.
I DROVE RAND PAUL OUT OF THE
I UNDERSTAND WHY THEY DON'T LIKE
ME AND I DON'T WANT PEOPLE
THAT -- I DON'T WANT PEOPLE TO
DO SOMETHING AGAINST THEIR WILL,
ANDERSON.
I COULD SEE THAT HE WAS HAVING A
HARD TIME WITH A VERY SIMPLE
QUESTION THAT YOU ASKED HIM.
WOULD YOU SUPPORT -- WELL, I
THINK I'M GOING TO WIN.
HE DOESN'T HAVE TO DO IT.
HE DOESN'T HAVE TO SUPPORT ME.
I REALLY DON'T BELIEVE I NEED
HIS SUPPORT.
I'D LOVE TO HAVE EVERYBODY'S
SUPPORT.
YOU KNOW WHAT, I'M A UNIFIER.
BELIEVE IT OR NOT, I'M A
UNIFIER.
>> IF THERE WAS A CONTESTED
CONVENTION, AND YOU DIDN'T GET
THE NOMINATION, AND SOMEONE ELSE
WAS BROUGHT IN, A PAUL RYAN, FOR
INSTANCE, WOULD YOU SUPPORT HIM?
>> LET ME EXPLAIN.
HE WAS VERY NICE.
HE CALLED ME THE OTHER DAY, LAST
WEEK AND HE WAS VERY NICE THEN I
READ REPORTS HE'S HAVING
MEETINGS WITH PEOPLE ABOUT, YOU
KNOW, SOME CLANDESTINE THINGS.
LET'S SEE WHAT HAPPENS.
BUT HE WAS VERY NICE WHEN HE
CALLED.
AND I ASSUME HE'S BEING STRAIGHT
WITH ME.
I HOPE HE'S BEING STRAIGHT WITH
ME BECAUSE WHAT HE SAID WAS VERY
APPROPRIATE.
I'M THE FRONT-RUNNER BY A LOT.
I'M BEATING TED CRUZ BY MILLIONS
OF VOTES.
MILLIONS OF VOTES.
THE REPUBLICAN PARTY IS DOING --
IT'S A PHENOMENA.
AND THIS WAS NOT GOING TO THAT
WITH THE REPUBLICAN PARTY.
PEOPLE THAT NEVER VOTED BEFORE,
DEMOCRATS AND INDEPENDENTS, ARE
POURING IN AND VOTING FOR ME.
>> IN LOUISIANA, YOU WON --
>> I WON.
>> TED CRUZ GOT --
>> SHOW YOU HOW --
>> YOU THREATENED TO SUE.
>> I WON -- WELL, I'M GOING TO
SEE.
I NEVER HEARD OF THAT BEFORE.
YOU KNOW, I'M A VERY -- I'M AN
AMERICAN.
IF YOU WIN AN ELECTION, YOU'RE
SUPPOSED TO --
>> ISN'T THAT JUST SOUR GRAPES?
DIDN'T HE HAVE -- HE OUTWORKED
YOU ON THE GROUND IN GETTING
DELEGATES?
>> LOOK, IN MISSOURI, IT WAS
JUST ANNOUNCED I WON.
I FIGURED, IN FACT, THEY
ACTUALLY FOUND AFTER A
TABULATION THAT I GOT 300 AND
SOME ODD MORE VOTES THAN I HAD
THE FIRST TIME AFTER TWO, THREE
WEEKS OF TABULATION WHICH GIVES
ME ANOTHER 12 OR 13 DELEGATES.
IT WAS ANNOUNCED A WHILE AGO
BEFORE I WENT ON THE AIR.
I WILL SAY THIS, LOUISIANA, I
WENT TO LOUISIANA.
I HAVE A GREAT RELATIONSHIP WITH
THE PEOPLE OF LOUISIANA.
THEY'RE GREAT PEOPLE.
I WON THE ELECTION.
I WAS DOWN THERE THE NIGHT
BEFORE.
WE HAD AN AIRPLANE HANGAR, YOU
WOULDN'T BELIEVE IT, PACKED WITH
PEOPLE SCREAMING.
I WON THE ELECTION.
THEN IT'S ALL ABOUT THE
DELEGATES.
SO I WON.
THEN I FOUND OUT I GOT TEN
VOTES, TEN DELEGATES LESS THAN
THE GUY WHO LOST.
I BEAT HIM.
>> THOSE ARE THE RULES.
HIS CAMPAIGN HAD A BETTER GROUND
GAME IN LOUISIANA.
>> I DON'T CALL IT A GROUND
GAME.
I CALL IT --
>> THEY'RE GOING TO GET MORE
DELEGATES.
I CALL IT BAD POLITICS.
WHEN SOMEBODY GOES IN AND WINS
THE ELECTION AND GETS LESS
DELEGATES THAN THE GUY THAT
LOST, I DON'T THINK THAT'S
RIGHT.
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET JIM, HE'S
THE CEO OF A VALVE MANUFACTURING
COMPANY THAT'S BEEN IN THE
FAMILY FOR THREE GENERATIONS.
HE SAYS HE'S UNDECIDED.
HE'S LEANING IN YOUR FAVOR.
>> THAT'S WHAT I LIKE TO HEAR.
>> HELLO, MR. TRUMP.
AS A WORLD LEADER, ANY LEADER,
YOU NEED COMPASSION AND
WILLINGNESS TO MAKE COMPROMISES.
CAN YOU GIVE ME AN EXAMPLE OF A
TIME YOU HAVE LEARNED FROM YOUR
BEHAVIOR AND CHANGED THE WAY YOU
HAVE DONE SOMETHNG GOING
FORWARD?
>> YEAH.
I AM SOMEBODY, JIM, THANK YOU.
I AM SOMEBODY THAT BELIEVES IN
FLEXIBILITY.
AND IF YOU NOTICE, TED CRUZ AND
MOSTLY HIM, HE SAYS HE WILL
CHANGE, HE WILL NEGOTIATE, HE
WILL THIS.
LOOK, YOU DON'T HAVE TO STAND ON
THE FLOOR OF THE UNITED STATES
SENATE FOR A DAY AND A HALF AND
RANT AND RAVE WHILE ALL THE
OTHER SENATORS ARE LAUGHING AT
YOU, AND BY THE WAY, NOT
ENDORSING HIM.
SENATOR JEFF SESSIONS, ONE OF
THE MOST RESPECTED MEN IN THE
SENATE ENDORSED ME, AND
FRANKLY -- HE'S A GREAT MAN.
AND BY THE WAY, JEFF SESSIONS IS
A GREAT MAN WITH GREAT, GREAT
KNOWLEDGE.
AND TED CRUZ THOUGHT HE WAS
GOING TO GET THAT ENDORSEMENT.
HE WOULD SPEAK ABOUT JEFF
SESSIONS ALL THE TIME THEN JEFF
SESSIONS CAME OUT AND ENDORSED
ME.
YOU NEED FLEXIBILITY, AND I TALK
ABOUT IT ALL THE TIME.
YOU NEED TO BE ABLE TO NEGOTIATE
GREAT DEALS.
YOU KNOWS, IT'S NOT ALL ABOUT
SIGNING EXECUTIVE ORDERS BECAUSE
THIS IS SOMETHING THAT CAME
IN -- THAT WASN'T THE WAY OUR
FOUNDERS THOUGHT THAT THIS
COUNTRY WAS GOING TO WIN.
YOU HAVE TO GET -- NOW, I'LL
MAKE GREAT DEALS.
I'LL MAKE CONSERVATIVE DEALS.
I'M GOING TO MAKE WONDERFUL
DEALS BUT YOU HAVE TO DO CAN THE
OLD-FASHIONED WAY LIKE RONALD
REAGAN DID WITH CHIP O'NEAL.
>> DO YOU HAVE A SPECIFIC,
THOUGH, FOR HIM ON -- A SPECIFIC
EXAMPLE THAT YOU CHANGED YOUR
BEHAVIOR, CHANGED THE WAY YOU'VE
DONE SOMETHING GOING FORWARD,
LEARNED FROM SOMETHING YOU'VE
DONE THAT YOU DIDN'T LIKE THE
WAY IT TURNED OUT?
>> I THINK -- YEAH, I HAVE MANY,
MANY THINGS I'VE DONE.
I HAVE MANY THINGS I'VE CHANGED
COURSE ON.
I MEAN, I'VE CHANGED COURSE ON
MANY, MANY THINGS.
TIME.
BY THE WAY, YOU KNOW WHO ELSE
EVOLVED?
RONALD REAGAN EVOLVED.
BECAUSE RONALD REAGAN SIGNED ONE
OF THE TOUGHEST ABORTION LAWS IN
FAVOR OF ABORTION IN CALIFORNIA
THAT HAD BEEN SIGNED IN MANY,
MANY YEARS.
AND YET HOOE WAS A GREAT PRESIDT
AND PRETTY CONSERVATIVE
PRESIDENT.
>> YOU SAID ON THE RADIO YOU DO
APOLOGIZE AND YOU BELIEVE IN
APOLOGIZING.
WHEN WAS THE LAST TIME YOU
ACTUALLY APOLOGIZED FOR
SOMETHING?
>> OH, WOW.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> I DON'T KNOW -- CAN I THINK?
I DO BELIEVE IN APOLOGIZING IF
YOU'RE WRONG.
WE STARTED THIS WITH COREY, MY
CAMPAIGN MANAGER.
I SAY APOLOGIZE FOR WHAT?
I SEE THE TAPE.
APOLOGIZE FOR WHAT?
APOLOGIZE, COREY.
IT WOULD BE SO MUCH EASIER.
I APOLOGIZED TO MY MOTHER YEARS
AGO FOR USING FOUL LANGUAGE.
I APOLOGIZE TO MY WIFE FOR NOT
BEING PRESIDENTIAL ON OCCASION.
SHE'S ALWAYS SAYING "DARLING, BE
MORE PRESIDENTIAL."
>> SHE TOLD ME SHE TALKED TO YOU
ABOUT THAT.
>> SHE DOES.
THE LAST DEBATE -- CRUZ TALKED
ABOUT --
>> SHE DIDN'T LIKE YOU USING A
WORD OR A DIRTY WORD OR BAD WORD
THAT SOMEBODY IN YOUR AUDIENCE
SHOUTED OUT AND YOU REPEATED.
>> REALLY IT WAS JUST A REPEAT
AND THAT DIDN'T WORK OUT TOO
WELL.
AND IT WASN'T HORRIBLE.
>> WHAT IS IT WITH YOU, REPEATS
AND RETWEETS DON'T COUNT.
>> MY BIGGEST PROBLEMS ARE
REPEATS AND RETWEETS --
>> WELL, MAYBE THAT'S ONE OF
THOSE THINGS YOU SHOULD LEARN
FROM YOUR BEHAVIOR AND NOT
RETWEET THINGS.
>> YOU'RE RIGHT.
THAT I AGREE WITH.
>> SOME FREE ADVICE.
>> I WILL SAY THIS, THOUGH, MY
WIFE AND IVANKA SAID ON THE LAST
DEBATES BECAUSE THE DEBATES HAD
BEEN PRETTY ROUGH AND I FELT I
HAD TO BE ROUGH BECAUSE IT'S
COMING AT ME FROM ALL DIFFERENT
ANGLES.
I'VE BEEN AT THE MIDDLE OF THE
PODIUM, MIDDLE OF THE STAGE
EVERY DEBATE.
>> CRUZ CHALLENGED YOU TO DEBATE
HIM.
>> GIVE ME A BREAK --
>> YOU WOULDN'T DEBATE HIM
ONE-ON-ONE?
>> HOW MANY TIMES CAN THE SAME
PEOPLE ASK THE SAME QUESTIONS?
I'VE HAD 11 OR 12 DEBATES WITH
CRUZ.
GRUDGE, THEY DO AN ONLINE POLL
RIGHT AFTER THE DEBATE, "TIME"
MAGAZINE, I THINK I'VE WON EVERY
POLL BY A LOT ON DEBATING.
>> SO NO MORE DEBATES?
>> I DON'T SEE WHERE IT'S
NECESSARY.
FRANKLY, I THINK THIS IS MUCH
BETTER THAN A DEBATE.
THE DEBATES, THEY GIVE YOU 15
SECOND, WHAT WOULD YOU DO IN
TERMS OF WAR AND PEACE, OKAY?
HONESTLY, I THINK THIS IS A MUCH
BETTER FORMAT.
>> I'M HAPPY TO KEEP HAVING
THESE CONVERSATIONS.
>> DEBATING IS EASIER BECAUSE
YOU'RE TALKING SO LITTLE.
SO I HOPE YOU CHANGE YOUR MIND
AND HOPE YOU'RE GOING TO --
SORRY, JOHN.
I WANT YOU TO MEET JOHN, HE'S A
DAIRY FARMER, HE HAS 5,000 COWS.
WE HAD ANOTHER DAIRY FARMER
ASKING A QUESTION FOR SENATOR
CRUZ EARLIER.
HE SAID HE'S LEANING IN YOUR
FAVOR.
WELCOME.
>> WELCOME TO THE CHEESE STATE.
WISCONSIN IS AN AMAZING STATE.
OUR NUMBER ONE ECONOMIC DRIVER
IS THE DAIRY AND CHEESE INDUSTRY
RIGHT BEHIND IT IS BEING
CHALLENGED BY HAVING A LABOR
FORCE DEPENDENT ON AN
IMMIGRATION POLICY.
WE HAVE OVER 10,000 FARMS IN
THIS STATE.
WITH SUCH A STRONG ECONOMIC
DRIVER, IF WE DON'T HAVE A
STRONG IMMIGRATION POLICY THAT
WILL GIVE US THE OPPORTUNITY TO
KEEP THE ONES WE HAVE AND
PROVIDE A VEHICLE TO BRING NEW
ONES IN FROM MEXICO LEGALLY --
>> LEGALLY.
YOU SAID THE WORD.
>> BUT CAN YOU DEVELOP A POLICY
THAT WILL GIVE US THAT, GIVE US
THE PEOPLE THAT WE HAVE HERE TO
STAY HERE AND DO THE JOBS AND
CREATE A POLICY THAT CAN BRING
PEOPLE IN TO FILL THE JOBS?
WE'RE DOWN TO 3.5% UNEMPLOYMENT
RATE SO WE CAN'T STEAL ANY MORE
PEOPLE FROM SOMEONE ELSE'S
INDUSTRY.
SO HOW DO WE FILL THE JOBS AND
GOOD PAYING JOBS?
>> HERE'S WHERE YOU ARE.
YOU'RE IN THE SAME POSITION AS
THE CALIFORNIA GRAPE GROWERS
BECAUSE THEY NEED PEOPLE TO COME
IN.
IT'S SEASONAL IN THAT CASE, LESS
SEASON IN YOUR CASE BUT PEOPLE
WILL BE ABLE TO COME IN LEGALLY
PLEGALLY.
YOU SAID THE WORD.
RIGHT NOW WE HAVE ILLEGALS, SOME
PEOPLE THINK IT'S 31 MILLION,
IT'S PROBABLY 12, 13, 14 -- WE
HAVE NO IDEA WHAT WE'RE DOING.
IF YOU HAVE AN INDUSTRY LIKE
CALIFORNIA GRAPES, LIKE PERHAPS
WHAT YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT IN
WISCONSIN, WE'RE GOING TO LET
PEOPLE COME IN, BUT THEY'RE
GOING TO COME IN LEGALLY.
THEY'RE GOING TO COME IN THROUGH
A VISA PROGRAM AND COME IN
LEGALLY AND IT GOING TO WORK OUT
BEAUTIFULLY.
YOU WILL NOT BE AFFECTED.
WE DON'T WANT TO AFFECT
BUSINESSES.
WE WANT TO GROW BUSINESSES.
THE OTHER PART OF YOUR QUESTION,
A THING WE REALLY HAVE TO TALK
ABOUT IT TRADE.
A LOT OF PEOPLE ARE SENDING
GOODS OVER TO OTHER COUNTRIES
AND ESPECIALLY GOODS THAT CAN
SPOIL LIKE WHAT YOU DO.
THEY SEND OVER TO OTHER
COUNTRIES AND THE OTHER
COUNTRIES REFUSE TO ACCEPT THEM
AND YET WE ACCEPT THEIR GOODS
WITHOUT TAX, WITHOUT ANYTHING.
WE ARE GOING TO STRAIGHTEN OUT
OUR TRADE POLICY SO THAT YOU'RE
GOING TO GET A LOT MORE
BUSINESS.
>> WE HAVE TIME FOR ONE MORE
QUESTION FROM THE AUDIENCE IN IS
ANDI BOWEN.
SHE SAID SHE'S LEANING IN YOUR
FAVOR FOR THE PRIMARY NEXT WEEK.
WELCOME.
>> HI, MR. TRUMP.
MY 93-YEAR-OLD FATHER IS SO
IMPRESSED WITH ALL OF YOUR KIDS,
ESPECIALLY WITH YOUR TWO SONS.
AND WHEN THEY'RE ON TELEVISION
BEING INTERVIEWED, HE WILL OFTEN
SAY "WHY CAN'T DONALD TRUMP BE
MORE HIKE HIS SONS, WHO ARE
SO --
>> I HEAR THAT.
>> "WHO ARE SO WELL SPOKEN AND
CALM."
SO MY QUESTION TO YOU, MR.
TRUMP, IS COULD YOU POSSIBLY
LOOK TO YOUR SONS AS EXAMPLES AS
HOW TO NOT TO BE QUITE SO
REACTIONARY AND CONGRATULATIONS
ON RAISING SUCH FINE YOUNG
PEOPLE.
>> I THINK I LOVE THAT QUESTION.
CAN I BE HONEST?
I HAVE SO MANY COMPLIMENTS ON MY
CHILDREN AND IVANKA IS DOING
PHENOMENALLY WELL.
MY BOYS ARE GREAT AND BARON IS A
YOUNG VERSION I THINK OF ERIC,
FRANKLY.
VERY FALL, SUCH AND SUCH.
I GET SO MANY COMPLIMENTS.
AND IVANKA, SHE'S A STAR.
THEY'RE SO SUPPORTIVE OF ME AND
WHEN I'M DOING AND THEY HAVE
GREAT ATTITUDES.
I GET SO MANY PEOPLE COME UP TO
MY OFFICE AND THEY WANT TO HAVE
THEIR CHILDREN TO COME UP AND
MEET ME BECAUSE THEY WANT THEIR
CHILDREN TO BE LIKE MINE.
>> DO YOU WISH YOU HAD MORE OF
YOUR CLARHILDREN'S CALMNESS?
>> THEY HAVE GREAT HEART.
ALL OF MY CHILDREN HAVE A
WONDERFUL, WONDERFUL FEELING FOR
PEOPLE.
THAT'S WHY THEY WANT ME DO WHAT
I'M DOING.
WE HAVE THE EXPRESSION "MAKE
AMERICA GREAT AGAIN" THEY KNOW
WE'RE NOT GOING TO BE TAKEN
ADVANTAGE OF ANYMORE.
THE WORLD IS TAKING ADVANTAGE OF
THE UNITED STATES AND IT'S
DRIVING US INTO LITERALLY BEING
A THIRD WORLD NATION.
ANDERSON, I TRAVEL ALL OVER THE
WORLD, AND I LAND AT AIRPORTS
THE LIKES OF WHICH YOU'VE NEVER
SEEN, WHETHER IT'S IN QATAR OR
DUBAI OR PLACES IN CHINA, THE
LIKES OF WHICH YOU HAVE NEVER
SEEN.
AND THEN WE COME HOME AND WE
LAND AT LAGUARDIA WITH POTHOLES
ALL OVER THE PLACE OR L.A.X. OR
KENNEDY OR NEWARK AND YOU LOOK
AT WHAT WE HAVE AND WHERE WE'VE
GONE.
IT'S TIME TO REBUILD OUR
COUNTRY.
>> YOU JUST WELCOMED --
>> AND I REALLY APPRECIATE YOUR
STATEMENT.
THANK YOU.
>> YOU JUST WELCOMED A NEW
GRANDSON.
HIS NAME IS THEODORE.
ANY CHANCE YOU'RE GOING TO CALL
HIM CRYING TED ?
>> ISN'T TED'S REAL NAME
RAPHAEL?
I THINK SO.
THAT'S ONE OF THE QUESTIONS --
>> IT IS, I'M BEING TOLD.
>> THEODORE ROOSEVELT IS
SOMEBODY JARED AND IVANKA HAVE
LONG STUDIED AND RESPECTED AND
IT'S THEODORE JAMES.
THAT'S WHAT THEY HAD IN MIND.
>> CONGRATULATIONS.
>> THANK YOU.
>> DONALD TRUMP.
BACK WITH JOHN KASICH AFTER THIS
SHORT BREAK.
>> THANK YOU.
>>> WELCOME BACK.
THERE IS HISTORY ALL AROUND US.
THE THEATER WAS LOVINGLY
RESTORED IN THE 80s.
IT IS A MAGNIFICENT THEATER.
WE'RE HERE IN THE MID OF A
HISTORY-MAKING PRESIDENTIAL
CAMPAIGN.
JOINING US IS OHIO AS GOVERNOR,
JOHN KASICH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> HOW ARE YOU?
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> HAVE A SEAT.
>> DONALD TRUMP'S CAMPAIGN
MANAGER COREY LEWANDOWSKI.
COULD YOU FIRE HIM?
>> I HAVEN'T SEEN THE VIDEO.
THEY TELL ME THE VIDEO IS REAL.
OF COURSE I WOULD.
WHEN YOU HAVE PROBLEMS LIKE
THAT, YOU HAVE TO ACT.
I'VE BEEN RUNNING THE SEVENTH
LARGEST STATE.
FROM WHAT I UNDERSTAND THE VIDEO
IS CLEAR.
OF COURSE I WOULD FIRE HIM.
>> YOU WERE PINNING YOUR HOPES
ON A CONTESTED CONVENTION.
ASSUMING THERE IS ONE, WHY WOULD
YOU BE SELECTED?
YOU'VE ONLY WON ONE STATE, YOUR
HOME STATE OF OHIO.
WHY WOULD YOU GET THE
NOMINATION?
>> IN EVERY NATIONAL POLL, I AM
THE ONLY ONE THAT BEATS HILLARY
CLINTON CONSISTENTLY.
IN THE LAST POLL I WAS UP 1
POINTS.
SECONDLY, DELEGATES WOULD LOOK
CAN YOU WIN IN THE FALL?
IT NOT JUST A NOMINATION, IT'S
ABOUT WINNING THE ELECTION.
IT WE DO NOT HAVE A STRONG
CANDIDATE WINNING THE ELECTION,
WE HAVE A POSSIBILITY OF LOSING
THE SENATE AS WELL.
PEOPLE WHO GO TO THE CONVENTION
ARE GOING TO BE CONCERNED OVER
WHO CAN RUN THE COUNTRY.
IT'S LIKE A BIG DEAL.
WHO CAN BE PRESIDENT, WHO CAN BE
COMMANDER IN CHIEF?
I HAVE MORE EXPERIENCE THAN ALL
OF THEM PUT TOGETHER EXCEPT THAN
MRS. CLINTON.
I SERVED ACE YEARS ON THE ARMED
SERVICES COMMITTEE, I WAS
INVOLVED IN WELFARE REFORM, WHEN
I WAS CHAIRMAN OF THE BUDGET
COMMITTEE, WE BALANCED THE
BUDGET, WE HAD JOB GROWTH.
I'VE BEEN THE EXECUTIVE IN OHIO.
WE'VE GROWN JOBS.
AT SOME POINT PEOPLE ARE GOING
TO LOOK AT TWO THINGS, WHO CAN
WIN IN THE FALL AND WHO CAN BE
SF
PRESIDENT.
>> TO HAVE ONLY WON ONE HOME
STATE, THE VOTERS HAVE SPOKEN.
>> ANDERSON, I THINK IT'S PRETTY
CLEAR AND MOST OF THE PEOPLE IN
HERE I THINK WOULD AGREE WITH
THIS, FOR MOST OF THE DEBATES, I
WAS COMPLETELY IGNORED.
IT'S BEEN LIKE THE LAST THREE
WEEKS TO A MONTH THAT PEOPLE
STARTED TO PAY ATTENTION TO WHO
I AM AND LISTENED TO MY MESSAGE.
I HAVEN'T GOTTEN DOWN IN THE MUD
AND HAD NASTY SOUND BITES.
BUT CONVENTIONS ARE VERY
INTERESTING.
REPUBLICANS HAVE HAD TEN
CONVENTIONS.
AND THE LEADER GOING INTO THE
CONVENTION HAS ONLY BEEN THE
NOMINEE THREE TIMES OUT OF TEN.
SEVEN TIMES OUT OF TEN THEY WERE
NOT.
SO I THINK -- AND WE'RE GOING TO
DO BETTER AS THIS CALENDAR MOVES
TO THE EAST.
I'M STARTING TO GET ON MY HOME
COURT.
LOOK, I WENT TO OHIO, I WON BY
11 POINTS, I DID VERY, VERY
WELFARE REFORM THERE, WE'RE
GOING TO GO TO PENNSYLVANIA, NEW
YORK, NEW JERSEY, CONNECTICUT.
THESE ARE ALL PLACES WHERE I DID
EXTREMELY WELL.
A CONVENTION IS NOTHING MORE
THAN A PROCESS OF WHAT WE HAVE
GOING NOW.
SOMEHOW PEOPLE THEY'RE TRUNCATED
SOMEHOW, THEY'RE DISJOINTED.
THEY'RE NOT.
YOU GO TO THE PRIMARIES, GET
DELEGATES AND DETERMINE THE
NOMINEES.
>> YOU SAID YESTERDAY ONE OF THE
OPPONENTS WANTS TO MAKE THE SAND
GLOW AND THE OTHER ONE COMPLAINS
ABOUT THE COUNTRY NOT DOING
ENOUGH.
WHY WOULD AMERICA BE SAFER UNDER
YOUR WATCH?
>> ANDERSON, FIRST OF ALL, I'VE
BEEN SAYING FOR A LONG TIME AND
LAID OUT AN EXTENSIVE PROGRAM ON
REBUILDING THE MILITARY.
I'VE BEEN ARGUING WE NEED TO GO
AFTER ISIS.
I WAS THERE IN THE GULF WAR, I
SAW IT HAPPEN AND SAW OUR
MUSLIM-ARAB FRIENDS JOIN US AND
WE PUSHED SADDAM OUT OF KUWAIT.
THAT SAME COALITION NEEDS COME
TOGETHER AND WE NEED TO DESTROY
ISIS IN THE AIR AND ON THE
GROUND D--
>> THERE ARE A LOT OF COUNTRIES,
SAUDI ARABIA THAT DON'T SEE --
>> SAUDI ARABIA, EGYPT, THEY
KNOW IT'S AN EXISTENTIAL THREAT.
THEY WILL JOIN US.
THEY JOINED US BEFORE AGAINST
SADDAM HUSSEIN.
THAT WAS NOT AS BIG OF A DEAL AS
THIS IS WHERE THEY'RE BLOWING
PEOPLE UP ALL OVER THE WORLD.
SECONDLY, OF COURSE, I THINK,
ANDERSON, THAT WE NEED REALLY
GOOD WORLD WIDE INTELLIGENCE.
THE LEMONS WE'RE SEEING CAN BE
TURNED INTO LEMONADE AND THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
CAN RALLY THE CIVIL WORLD TO
DESTROY THESE FOLKS INTENT ON
DESTROYING US.
AND WE NEED TO CHANGE NATO FROM
NOT JUST A MILITARY ORGANIZATION
BUT AN INTELLIGENCE GATHERING
AND ALSO A POLICING ORGANIZATION
THAT WORKS ACROSS BOUNDARIES.
ALL OF US TOGETHER, WORKING
TOGETHER, DESTROYS ISIS, HAVE
THE GOOD HUMAN INTELLIGENCE --
>> DONALD TRUMP SAYS NATO A'S
OBSOLETE.
IS IT?
>> OF COURSE IT'S NOT.
THAT'S ABSURD.
IT'S IMPORTANT WE GET THESE
COUNTRIES TO PITCH IN AND DO
MORE.
THEY'LL NEVER DO AS MUCH AS WE
WANT.
PART OF THE PROBLEM IS THE
GOVERNMENTS OVER THERE ARE TOO
MUCH SOCIALISM, TOO MUCH
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS.
THAT'S WHY THEY DIDN'T EVEN
CATCH THIS STUFF IN BRUSSELS.
NATO HAS AN ADDITIONAL ROLE NOW
AND THAT IS POLICING AND
INTELLIGENCE GATHERING.
WE NEED TO HAVE THE MUSLIMS
WORKING WITH US AND THE WEST --
>> THAT'S CRITICAL?
>> ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL.
LET ME TELL YOU, ANDERSON, IF WE
WANTED TO GET INFORMATION OUT OF
SOME RADICAL THAT'S IN A MOSQUE,
YOU'RE A REALLY GREAT GUY, BUT
IF YOU WERE THREE BLOCKS FROM
THE MOSQUE, DO YOU THINK YOU'D
GET ANYTHING?
>> I DON'T BLEND VERY WELL.
>> NO, YOU ARE DON'T.
THE FACT IS WE WANT THE MUSLIMS
WHO ARE -- THEY FEEL AS STRONGLY
AS WE DO ABOUT THESE MURDERERS
OUT THERE.
THESE MUSLIMS, THEY'RE THE ONES
THAT HAVE TO POLICE THEIR OWN
NEIGHBORHOODS.
AND, FRANKLY, WE NEED THE IMANS
TO COME OUT AND ISSUE STATEMENTS
ABOUT HOW THEIR RELIGION HAS
BEEN HIJACKED.
IT TAKES ALL OF US TOGETHER.
IT TAKES US TO HAVE GREAT HUMAN
INTELLIGENCE.
HERE IN THE UNITED STATES WE
HAVE COUNTERTERRORISM TASK
FORCES MADE UP OF THE FBI, MADE
UP OF HOMELAND SECURITY, STATE
AND LOCAL LAW ENFORCEMENT AND
THEIR JOB IS TO DISRUPT.
THAT'S WHY THE ISSUE OF APPLE
WAS SO IMPORTANT BECAUSE THEY
NEED THE RESOURCES TO BE ABLE TO
CARRY OUT THEIR JOB FOR ALL OF
US BUT THEY NEED ONE OTHER
THING, THEY NEED THE TOOLS.
IF THEY CAN'T HEAR, IT BECOMES A
PROBLEM.
BUT THERE'S ALSO A ROLE FOR US.
BECAUSE WHEN WE SEE SOMETHING
HAPPENING IN OUR NEIGHBORHOOD,
WE HAVE AN OBLIGATION, ANDERSON,
WE HAVE AN OBLIGATION TO ALERT
AUTHORITIES.
>> YOU TALKED ABOUT DONALD TRUMP
IN AN INTERVIEW IN HIS FOREIGN
POLICY, "I THINK THAT'S THE MOST
RIDICULOUS FOREIGN POLICY I EVER
HEARD, THERE IS SOMEBODY WHO
JUST DOESN'T UNDERSTAND FOREIGN
POLICY."
>> WHICH PART WAS I TALKING
ABOUT?
>> I DON'T REMEMBER.
>> WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A
RELIGIOUS TEST IF YOU COME IN
THE COUNTRY.
RAISE YOUR HAND IF YOU'RE A
MUSLIM.
THAT'S NOT GOING TO WORK.
WE WERE NOT GOING TO POLICE
MUSLIM NAEIGHBORHOODS.
WE CAN'T AFFORD POLARIZATION IN
CIVILIZED NATIONS ALL OVER THE
WORLD.
THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO KNOW THIS
THREAT HAS TO BE STOPPED.
WHEN PEOPLE IN PAKISTAN DIE, WE
ALL DIE A LITTLE BIT WHEN THEY
BLOW UP INNOCENT MEN, WOMEN AND
CHILDREN AT AN EASTER SERVICE.
THIS IS AN OPPORTUNITY FOR US TO
BE BROUGHT TOGETHER.
THE PRESIDENT, BY THE WAY, WENT
TO A BASEBALL GAME IN CUBA
INSTEAD OF COMING -- IF I WERE
PRESIDENT, I WOULD COME HOME, I
WOULD FIND OUR VULNERABILITIES
AND I WOULD SAY LET'S LOOK AT
WHAT OUR PROBLEMS ARE AND FIX
THEM IMMEDIATELY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THE RESPONSE OF THE WHITE
HOUSE IT THAT CRITICISM IS
OFTEN, WELL, LOOK, BY CHANGING
THE PRESIDENT'S SCHEDULE, IT
GIVES POWER TO TERRORIST GROUP
THAT THEY'RE ABLE TOER OF THE F
SCHEDULE --
>> SO YOU GO TO A BASEBALL GAME
AND YOU DON'T COME HOME?
>> THAT'S ANOTHER ISSUE.
>> HERE AS THE SITUATION.
THAT ATTACK WAS IN THE HEART OF
EUROPE.
THAT WAS AN ATTACK ON THE VERY
HEART OF OUR FRIENDS WHO LIVE IN
EUROPE.
YEAH, I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
ENOUGH TO COME HOME.
SECONDLY, I'LL GIVE YOU ANOTHER
ONE THAT I CAN'T BELIEVE.
THE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES -- THE FIRST THING HE DID
IS HE WOULDN'T MEET WITH OUR
FRIEND NETANYAHU.
THAT WAS THE FIRST MEETING HE
SNUBBED.
NOW HE SNUBBED A MEETING WITH
THE PRESIDENT OF TURKEY.
DO YOU KNOW HOW IMPORTANT IT IS
FOR TO US HAVE GOOD RELATIONS
WITH TURKEY?
THEY'RE THE GATE WEST TO THE
EAST.
HE WAS THE ONE THAT ALERTED THE
EUROPEANS ABOUT THE RADICALS
MOVING OVER TO BRUSSELS.
YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO MANAGE
THIS.
IT'S COMPLICATED, IT TAKES
SOPHISTICATION AND YOU NEED GOOD
ADVISERS.
BUT YOU NEED EXPERIENCE AND YOU
NEED A GOOD GUT.
AND I'VE BEEN INVOLVED IN THESE
THINGS FOR ALMOST ALL OF MY
ADULT LIFETIME.
I HAVE ADVISERS BUT I DON'T HAVE
MANY TEACHERS, I UNDERSTAND MOST
OF THESE THINGS.
>> WE TALKED ABOUT TRUMP'S
CAMPAIGN MANAGERS.
YOUR CAMPAIGN MANAGER TWEETED
THIS, CRUZ WITH ZERO FRIENDS,
ZERO RECORD, ZERO CHANCE DECIDES
TO LIE ABOUT@JOHN KASICH, TRUMP
RIGHT ON ONE THING,LYING TED.
IS THIS --
>> NO, SOMETIMES HE GETS A
LITTLE TWEET HAPPY AND I DON'T
LIKE IT AND I WILL HAVE A WORD
WITH HIM ABOUT IT.
THEY SAY KASICH DOESN'T HAVE ANY
STRENGTH OUT HERE.
IF YOU DON'T HAVE ANY STRETCH,
THEY DON'T SPEND MONEY ATTACKING
YOU.
ARNOLD SCHWARZENEGGER TOLD ME IN
2010 WHEN I WAS RUNNING FOR
GOVERNOR, I SAID THEY'RE REALLY
BEATING ME UP.
HE HE LOOKED AT ME AND SAID,
"JOHN, LEARN TO LOVE THE
BEATINGS."
THEY ARE HAMMERING ME, NOT
TRUMP.
THAT'S VERY INTERESTING.
I CAN TAKE IT.
>> YOUR TWO FELLOW CANDIDATES
HAVE BEEN DUKING IT OUT OVER THE
LAST WEEK OR SO --
>> THE LAST WEEK OR SO?
HOW ABOUT THE LAST FIVE MONTHS?
WHERE YOU BEEN, ANDERSON?
THAT'S WHY I'M NOT IN THE NEWS.
I DIDN'T CALL ANYBODY A ANNAME.
I'M IN THE GOING TO TAKE THE LOW
ROAD TO THE HIGHEST POSITION IN
THE LAND.
SOMETIMES IT'S AMAZING TO ME.
SOMETIMES WHEN YOU LOOK AT IT I
THINK WHAT THE HECK ARE WE DOING
HEAR?
I WAS ON THE RADIO TALK SHOW
WITH JAY SOMEBODY OR OTHER, I
DON'T REMEMBER THIS MORNING --
WHATEVER HIS NAME IS.
NICE GUY.
YESTERDAY I WAS ON A DIFFERENT
ONE AND A GUY SAYS TO ME, WELL,
YOU KNOW, MAYBE THIS IS THE NEW
POLITICS.
IF NAME CALLING, BRINGING IN
SPOUSES AND RIPPING EACH OTHER
BELOW THE BELT AND WRESTLING IN
THE MUD IS THE NEW POLITICS, WE
ALL NEED TO STAND AGAINST IT.
OUR CHILDREN ARE WATCHING.
THIS IS AMERICA.
WE NEED TO TALK ABOUT WHAT WE'RE
FOR.
AND I HAVE BEEN CONSISTENT.
NOW, WHEN THEY SAY SOMETHING ON
POLICY-WISE THAT'S BAD, OF
COURSE I'M GOING TO SAY
SOMETHING ABOUT IT, BUT I DON'T
WANT TO GO DOWN INTO -- I'M NOT
GOING TO GO DOWN THERE.
I HOPE NOT.
I COULD SCREW UP BUT I HOPE NOT.
>> JIM VOGEL IS HERE.
HE WORKS IN ADVERTISING.
HE SAID HE'S LEANING TOWARDS
SENATOR CRUZ.
>> HI, GOVERNOR.
IN OHIO YOU ACCEPTED MEDICAID
EXPANSION AND YOU TOOK ON THE
MED -- I'M SORRY, THE HEALTH
CARE EXCHANGES AND IT WAS TO
HELP THE POOR.
HERE IN WISCONSIN WE USED --
GOVERNOR WALK ER USED BADGER CAE
TO ESSENTIALLY PROVIDE THE SAME
SERVICES AT THE SAME LEVELS AND
WE CAN IT WITHOUT CREATING A NEW
EXPANSION PROGRAM AND CREATING
DEBT.
WHY DID YOU USE OBAMA CARE?
WHY DID YOU CHOOSE THE
WASHINGTON-BASED SOLUTION?
WHY CAN'T YOU EVER LOOK AT OTHER
SOLUTIONS THAN WASHINGTON.
>> IT'S NOT SO SIMPLE WHAT
GOVERNOR WALKER DID HERE.
TODAY THE "MILWAUKEE JOURNAL
SENT INEL" ENDORSED ME FOR
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
>> I BROUGHT INNOVATION TO THE
SYSTEM.
I THEN HAD A CHOICE.
NOW THAT MY PROGRAM WAS UNDER
CONTROL, I THEY HAD A CHOICE.
COULD I BRING MONEY BACK, WHICH
IS FRANKLY OUR MONEY, OHIO
MONEY, BACK TO OHIO TO SOLVE
SOME OF OUR PROBLEMS.
LET ME TELL WHAT YOU WE'VE DONE.
I DON'T BELIEVE THE MENTALLY ILL
OUGHT TO BE SLEEPING UNDER A
BRIDGE OR BE IN PRISON.
IF I CAN GET THEM MEDICATION AND
GET THEM ON THEIR FEET AND GET
THEM A JOB, THEY BECOME
TAXPAYERS.
WE SAVE MONEY.
AND I BELIEVE THE DRUG ADDICTED
IN OUR PRISONS SHOULD BE
TREATED.
THAT COSTS $22,500 A YEAR AND
WE'RE THROWING A LIFE DOWN THE
DRAIN.
BECAUSE OF OUR PROGRAM NOW IN
THE PRISONS AND WITH THE
COMMUNITY, WE HAVE AN 80%
SUCCESS RATE IN NOT HAVING
PEOPLE GO BACK IN AND OUR
RECIDIVISM RATE IS 27%.
AND, BY THE WAY, WE'RE RUNNING A
$2 BILLION SURPLUS.
WE DON'T PUT OUR BUDGET TOGETHER
WITH SCOTCH TAPE AND BAIL AND
WIRE.
WE'RE RUNNING A $2 MILLION
SURPLUS.
WE'RE IN OHIO, WE'RE TREATING
THE MENTALLY ILL, THE DRUG
ADDICTED, THE WORKING POOR,
THEY'RE IN A BETTER POSITION,
NOT IN OUR PRISONS, THEY'RE
GETTING ON THEIR FEET, BECOMING
TAXPAYERS AND OUR MEDICARE
PROGRAM IS UNDER CONTROL AND I
REJECT OBAMACARE.
I NEVER KNEW WHAT THE HECK WAS
GOING TO COME OF IT.
I HAVE A SOLID HEALTH CARE MAN
TO REPLACE OBAMACARE, WHICH
INVOLVES TRANSPARENCY,
COMPETITION, MARKET-ORIENTED
FORCES.
WE'RE ACTUALLY DOING IT IN MY
STATE AND I LIKE TO SPREAD IT
ALL ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
SO THE IDEA OF DOING THAT WAS
NOT ONLY COMPASSIONATE, BUT IT
ALSO MADE GOOD ECONOMIC SENSE
FOR OUR STATE AND IT'S WORKING
OUT QUITE WELL.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
GOVERNOR, I WANT YOU TO MEET
JE
JULIE GRACE --
>> JUST ONE OTHER THING I WANTED
TO SAY.
I SPENT TEN YEARS OF MY LIFE
FIGHTING TO BALANCE THE BUDGET.
SENATOR DOMENICI AND I WORKED
WITH THE CLINTON ADMINISTRATION.
WE GOT IT BALANCED FOUR YEARS IN
A ROW.
HAD AT ANY TIME BEEN BALANCED
SINCE MAN WALKED ON THE MOON,
HASN'T BEEN BALANCED SINCE.
WHEN I LEFT WASHINGTON, THERE
WAS A $5 TRILLION SURPLUS AND
GET WHO SPENT IT?
THE REPUBLICANS.
NOW, SIR, YOU HAVE TO STAND IN
THE BREACH WHEN YOU'RE A LEADER.
WHAT I DID IN WASHINGTON IN
GETTING THAT BUDGET UNDER CHROME
AND
-- CONTROL, AND WHAT I'VE DONE
IN OHIO, WE'VE CUT TAXES BY MORE
THAN ANY GOVERNOR IN THE
COUNTRY, INCLUDING YOUR
GOVERNOR.
>> ALL RIGHT.
I WANT YOU TO MEET JULIE GRACE,
A STUDENT AT MARQUETTE
UNIVERSITY.
SHE SAID SHE'S SUPPORTING YOU.
>> OH, YOU ARE?
>> I AM.
>> THANK YOU.
SAY SOMETHING REALLY, REALLY
GOOD.
>> I'LL TRY.
>> SO IN EUROPE MANY FAR RIGHT
CONSERVATIVE PARTIES,
ANTI-IMMIGRANT PARTIES HAVE BEEN
GAINING MOMENTUM RECENTLY,
SPECIFICALLY GERMANY, SWEDEN,
FRANCE AND BRITAIN.
DO YOU THINK A SIMILAR MOVEMENT
IS GOING ON HERE IN THE U.S. AND
IF SO, HOW CAN THE U.S. ADDRESS
THIS?
>> WE'VE GONE THROUGH PERIODS
THIS OUR DESCRIBHISTORY WHEN WE
TURNED AGAINST IMMIGRATION AND
THESE THINGS HAVE SPRUNG UP.
YOUNG LADY, WE HAVE TO PROTECT
THE BORDER.
SECONDLY, WE SHOULD HAVE A WORK
PROGRAM.
AND THIRDLY, IF THEY CAME HERE
ILLEGALLY AND THEY'VE NOT
COMMITTED A CRIME SINCE THEY'VE
BEEN HERE, THEY'LL PAY A FINE
AND THEY'LL HAVE A PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP.
THE IDEA THAT WE'RE GOING TO
WALK THROUGH MILWAUKEE AND YANK
PEOPLE OUT OF THEIR HOMES IN
FRONT OF THEIR CHILDREN, THAT'S
RIDICULOUS.
WE CAN HAVE A BORDER PROGRAM,
GET A PATH TO LEGALIZATION.
YOU HAVE TO GO BACK, NO EXCUSES.
YOU KNOW WHAT I THINK?
I THINK THAT CAN PASS THE UNITED
STATES CONGRESS AND I THINK IT
CAN PASS WITH THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE AND GET THIS ISSUE BEHIND
US AND GET THIS THING HEALED.
WE NEED A HEALING IN AMERICA.
STOP KICKING CANS DOWN THE ROAD
AND SOLVE PROBLEMS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
AND I THINK THAT'S A REASONABLE
SOLUTION TO THIS PROBLEM OF
IMMIGRATION.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THIS IS ASA WHITE, A STUDENT
ALSO, SAID HE'S LEANING TOWARDS
SUPPORTING DONALD TRUMP.
>> THANK YOU.
MY QUESTION -- THE MOST RECENT
TERROR ATTACK IN BRUSSELS HAS
HIGHLIGHTED A BIG ISSUE WE HAVE
WITH OUR ATTACK ON FOREIGN
TERRORISM.
WE HAVE NEIGHBORHOODS BEING
DEEMED AT TERRORIST HOTBEDS.
DO YOU SUPPORT SENATOR CRUZ'S
WHEN HE SAYS WE SHOULD GO INTO
MUSLIM NEIGHBORHOODS AND PATROL
THEM?
>> NO, I DON'T SUPPORT THAT AT
ALL.
I THINK IT'S RIDICULOUS.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
THE GUY WHO WAS THE BEST POLICE
GUY IN THE WHOLE COUNTRY, HE
UNDERSTANDS POLICING, IS A GUY
NAMED BILL BRATTON, NOW
CURRENTLY THE POLICE CHIEF IN
NEW YORK, HE WAS THE POLICE
CHIEF UNDER RUDY GIULIANI, HE
WAS THE HEAD OF THE METRO SYSTEM
IN BOSTON AND RAN THE LOS
ANGELES POLICE DEPARTMENT.
HE'S THE BEST.
HE SAID THAT PLAN IS RIDICULOUS.
LET ME TELL YOU, SIR, WE ALL
WANT TO CATCH THESE BAD GUYS.
I KNOW HOW IT WORKS BECAUSE I'VE
GOT JOINT TERRRERRORISM TASK FO
MEMBERS IN MY STATE AND THEY'RE
IN YOUR STATE.
LET ME ASK A QUESTION.
WE HAVE A RELIGIOUS TEST, WE'RE
GOING TO KNOW YOU AND WE'RE
GOING TO PROTECT YOU, NOW I WANT
YOU TO HELP ME WHO THE BAD GUYS
ARE.
IF WE POLARIZE THE ENTIRE
COMMUNITY, HOW ARE WE GOING TO
LEARN WHO THEY ARE?
I HAVE TO TELL YOU, THE VAST,
VAST, VAST MAJORITY OF MUSLIMS,
THEY THINK THEIR RELIGION HAS
BEEN HIJACKED, THAT WE HAVE
MURDERERS OUT THERE WHO HAVE
DISTORTED THEIR RELIGION AND
THEY WANT TO STOP HAD AS MUCH AS
WE WANT TO STOP IT.
SO THE FACT IS LET'S ISOLATE
THOSE PEOPLE WHO ARE THE KILLERS
AND LET'S WORK TOGETHER AS A
COMMUNITY OF CIVILIZED PEOPLE TO
TAKE THE BATTLE TO THEM.
DESTROY ISIS, THAT'S A GIVEN AND
THEN GREAT INTELLIGENCE TO T
THWART THESE ATTACKS.
>> THANK YOU FOR YOUR QUESTION.
THIS IS JIM WALKER, A REPUBLICAN
FROM FRANKLIN, WISCONSIN.
HE SAID HE'S LEANING TOWARDS TED
CRUZ FOR HIS EXPERIENCE BUT
LIKES YOU BECAUSE YOU RUN A BLUE
COLLAR STATE.
>> THANK YOU, ANDERSON.
WELCOME TO THE GREAT STATE OF
WISCONSIN.
I REPRESENT AN EQUIPMENT
MANUFACTURER THAT DIRECTLY
EMPLOYS MANY THOUSANDS OF
PEOPLE.
INDIRECTLY AS YOU CAN IMAGINE
WITH FARM EQUIPMENT THAT WE
SELL, WE INDIRECTLY SUPPORT MANY
THOUSANDS OF FARMERS AND WE
EXPORT ABOUT A THIRD OF OUR
PRODUCT.
IN ESSENCE, WE'RE A GLOBAL
MANUFACTURING COMPANY.
TO SPARK A TRADE BATTLE WOULD
NOT ONLY BE DETRIMENTAL TO
BUSINESS BUT TO ALL OF THOSE WE
DIRECTLY AND INDIRECT LIVE
SUPPORT.
AS PRESIDENT, HOW WOULD YOU
ENGAGE IN DIPLOMACY THAT WON'T
HURT BUSINESS?
>> WE HAVE OVER 63,000 NEW
MANUFACTURING JOBS IN MY STATE
NOW.
WE'RE PAYING ATTENTION TO ALL
THE SECTORS.
LET'S TALK ABOUT TRADE.
IT'S A TOUGH ISSUE.
ONE OUT OF FIVE AMERICANS WORK
TOWARDS SOMETHING RELATED TO
TRADE AND THAT'S 38 MILLION
AMERICANS
AMERICANS.
WE NEED TO HAVE PFREE TRADE.
I DO THESE TOWN HALLS ALL THE
TIME.
I LOVE THEM.
REMEMBER WHEN WE GOT ALL THE
JAPANESE CARS IN THE COUNTRY?
REMEMBER WHAT HAPPENED TO U.S.
CARS?
THEY GOT BETTER.
INNOVATION AND COMPETITION
REALLY WORKS.
BUT AT THE SAME TIME WHEN WE DO
TRADE AGREEMENTS AND OTHER
COUNTRIES CHEAT AND THEY DO
CHEAT, SOME MANIPULATE CURRENCY
AND WHEN WE FIND THEM, WE HAVE
TO CALL THEM ON IT.
WE HAD U.S. STEEL DEVELOP MONEY
IN OUR STATE.
THE KOREANS WERE DUMPING TUBES
INSIDE THE U.S.
THAT MEANS SELLING PRODUCT BELOW
THE COST OF WHAT IT TOOK THEM TO
MAKE THEM.
BY THE TIME YOU RESEARCH THEM
AND PROVE YOUR CASE, IT COULD BE
A YEAR OR TWO AND ALL YOUR
PEOPLE ARE OUT OF WORK.
WE NEED AN EARLY WARNING SYSTEM.
LET ME TELL YOU, WHEN THEY
CHEAT, I WILL ACT AS THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
THINK OF IT THIS WAY.
IF OHIO STATE CAME UP TO PLAY
YOUR BELOVED BADGERS AND I ASKED
FOR FIVE DOWNS TO GET A FIRST
DOWN AND YOU ONLY GOT FOUR, HOW
WOULD YOU FEEL?
YOU WOULDN'T PUT UP WITH IT,
OKAY?
WE SHOULD NOT PUT UP WITH
COUNTRIES WHEN THEY CHEAT.
THAT DOES NOT KEEP US FROM
EMBRACING THE NOTION OF OPEN AND
FREE TRADE.
ONE OTHER THING, WE NOW HAVE
THIS TRADE AGREEMENT ON THE
TABLE, THE TPP AGREEMENT.
UP
YOU KNOW, WHEN WE TRADE WE'RE
THE MOST OPEN COUNTRY AND
EVERYBODIESY ELSE HAS BARRIERS.
WE TRIED TO GET THEIR BARRIERS
DOWN TO GET OUR PRODUCT NOOSE
THEIR COUNTRY.
BUT YOU WORRY ABOUT THE CHINESE
AND THEIR GROWING STRENGTH,
PARTICULARLY IN ASIA, MAKE A
TRADE AGREEMENT, INTEGRATE
OURSELVES WITH OUR FRIENDS HAD
ASIA, WHO CAN BECOME A BULWARK
AGAINST THE CHINESE.
YOU HAVE TO HAVE AN EARLY
WARNING SYSTEM, YOU HAVE TO SHUT
IT OFF AND AGRICULTURE DEPENDS
ON EXPORTS MORE THAN ANY OTHER
IN THIS COUNTRY.
>> THAT MESSAGE DOESN'T
RESONATE.
DONALD TRUMP SAID --
>> I CAN SAY ALL KINDS OF THINGS
TO GET PEOPLE STIRRED UP BUT
LEADERS DON'T DO THAT.
THEY TELL PEOPLE THE WAY THEY
SEE IT, EVEN IF IT MEANS YOU'RE
UNPOPULAR.
YOU CAN'T BELIEVE HOW MANY
PEOPLE I MADE ANGRY IN
WASHINGTON FIGHTING TO BALANCE
THE BUDGET.
I WAS ONE OF THE MOST UNPOPULAR
GOVERNORS BUT I KNEW WHAT THE
FORMULA WAS AND NOW I'M ONE OF
THE MOST POPULAR GOVERNORS.
YOU CANNOT MAKE DECISIONS AS A
LEADER BY PUTTING YOUR FINGER IN
THE AIR OR DOING FOCUS GROUPS
AND GETTING PEOPLE INVOLVED WHEN
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY'RE SAYING IS
NOT TRUE.
I WILL NOT DO THAT.
I HAVE NEVER DONE IT IN MY
LIFETIME AND I'M NOT ABOUT TO
START.
PERIOD AND END OF STORY.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> THIS IS WILLIAM DUNNFORD.
HE'S A STUDENT AT MARQUETTE
UNIVERSITY.
HE SAYS WHO SUPPORTS TED CRUZ.
>> 70 YEARS AFTER WORLD WAR II
AND QUARTER CENTURY AFTER THE
WORLD WAR ENDED WHY DOES
SECURITY REMAIN A RESPONSIBILITY
FOR AMERICANS?
GIVEN THAT EUROPEANS ARE WEALTHY
ENOUGH TO DEPEND THEMSELVES, WHY
SHOULDN'T THEY?
>> YOUNG MAN, LOOK, I DON'T KNOW
IF YOU'RE A LEADER IN YOUR
FAMILY OR NOT, THERE ARE LEADERS
IN A FAMILY WHO DO MORE FOR YOUR
BROTHERS AND SISTERS.
AND YOUR SPOUSE SAYS WHY DO WE
HAVE DO THIS ALL THE TIME?
BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT LEADERS DO.
THEY NEED TO STRAIGHTEN OUT
THEIR ECONOMY.
I CAN TELL YOU, IT'S HARD FOR
THEM TO GET RIGHT WITH THINGS.
THEY'RE WEAK ECONOMICALLY.
THEY DOESN'T STOP THEM FROM
SHARING THEIR SHARE OF THE LOAD.
WE DON'T WANT TO HAVE THOSE
RELATIONSHIPS ELIMINATED BECAUSE
IT HURTS US, TOO.
WE NEED TO HAVE A STRONG WESTERN
EUROPE.
I JUST HEARD BRIEFLY SOMEBODY
WAS SAYING THAT WE SHOULD JUST
IGNORE UKRAINE.
ARE YOU KIDDING ME?
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA
SHOULD BE ARMING THE UKRAINIAN
WHO IS WANT TO FIGHT FOR FREEDOM
AGAINST PUTIN, WHO SHOULD BE
ARMING THEM WITH LETHAL
DEFENSIVE AID.
NOW, YOUNG MAN, WE SHOULD ALWAYS
TELL THEM YOU GOT TO DO MORE AND
WE SHOULD USE WHATEVER LEVERAGE
WE HAVE TO GET THEM TO DO MORE,
BUT I'M GOING TO TELL YOU AS
AMERICANS, AS LONG AS I'VE BEEN
ALIVE, WE ALWAYS CARRY MORE OF
THE SHARE OF THE BURDEN THAN WE
WOULD LIKE.
WE ALWAYS DO.
AND YOU KNOW THERE'S AN OLD
SCRIPTURE THAT SAYS TO WHOM MUCH
IS GIVEN MUCH IS EXPECTED.
AND AS PRESIDENT I WOULD FIGHT
TO GET THEM TO GIVE US MORE AND
I WOULD USE WHATEVER LEVERAGE I
COULD TO GET THEM TO GIVE US
MORE BUT TO BE HONEST WITH YOU,
WE'RE ALWAYS GOING TO COMPLAIN
ABOUT THIS.
BUT TO WALK AWAY FROM THAT
ALLIANCE, ARE YOU KIDDING ME?
IF WE WALK AWAY AND IT GETS WEAK
ER, HOW LONG DO YOU THINK IT
WILL TAKE THE ISLAMISTS TO COME
OVER HERE?
THERE'S NO EASY WAY OUT OF THIS.
WHEN YOU ARE A LEADER WHO HAS
SEEN THESE THINGS, THEN YOU
GREAT SOBERING APPROACH.
THAT'S WHY THE JOURNAL
CENTENNIAL HERE IN MILWAUKEE
SAID KASICH IS A PRAGMATIC
CONSERVATIVE.
YOU JUST CAN'T KNOCK ALL THE
PIECES OFF THE CHESS BOARD WHEN
YOU GET FRUSTRATED.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A QUICK
BREAK AND WE'LL HAVE MORE
QUESTIONS FOR GOVERNOR KASICH AS
THE
>>> WELCOME BACK.
WE CONTINUE THE CONVERSATION,
TAKING MORE QUESTIONS FOR OHIO
GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH.
THANKS VERY MUCH FOR JOINING US
AGAIN.
I WANT TO ASK YOU A QUESTION
WHICH I ASKED TO EACH OF THE
OTHER CANDIDATES AS WELL AND HAD
SURPRISING ANSWERS.
A PLEDGE WAS MADE EARLIER IN THE
RACE BY ALL GOP CANDIDATES
SAYING THEY WOULD PLEDGE TO
SUPPORT WHOEVER THE NOMINATION
WAS.
DOESN'T DONALD TRUMP SAID THAT
PLEDGE IS ESSENTIALLY NULL AND
VOID, HE WOULD NOT NECESSARILY
NAME NA
NOMINATE, HE'LL HAVE TO WAIT AND
SEE.
TED CRUZ WOULDN'T ANSWER IT
AND --
>> MAYBE I WON'T ANSWER IT
EITHER.
WHEN YOU'RE IN THE ARENA, YOU
DEVELOP RESPECT FOR THOSE IN THE
ARENA, BUT I'VE BEEN DISTURBED
BY SOME OF THE THINGS I'VE SEEN
AND I HAVE TO KNOW HOW MY WORD
IS PERCEIVED.
I THINK THE LITTLE ENGINE THAT
CONDITION KEEPS GOING.
I SURE HOPE THEY'LL ENDORSE ME
FOR PRESIDENT WHEN I'M THE
NOMINEE COMING OUT OF CONVENTION
IN CLEVELAND.
IS THAT A GOOD ANSWER?
I DON'T KNOW.
>> I WOULD BE REMISS NOT TO
FOLLOW UP.
ESSENTIALLY YOU'RE SAYING IT'S
IN THE BALANCE.
YOU'RE WAITING TO SEE.
>> I WOULD SAY THAT'S A GOOD WAY
TO DESCRIBE IT.
>> YOU'RE NOT IRONCLAD STANDING
BY THE INITIAL PLEDGE TO --
>> WE SHOULDN'T HAVE ANSWERED
THAT QUESTION, IT WAS THE FIRST
DEBATE AND --
>> TO BE CLEAR.
>> THAT'S AS CLEAR AS YOU'RE
GOING TO GET OUT OF ME.
I HAVE TO SEE WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN.
IF IT'S SOMEONE THAT IS GOING TO
HARM THE COUNTRY --
>> SO FAR WOULD YOU THINK THAT
IT LOOKS LIKE DONALD TRUMP WOULD
HARM THE COUNTRY?
>> THAT'S TOO BELOW THE BELT.
I'M NOT GOING TO GET INTO THAT.
>> WELCOME.
>> MY FAMILY AND I RAISE SLED
DOGS.
WE STARTED A BUSINESS AND I
FUNDED THE WHOLE THING MYSELF.
I WAS WONDERING WHAT YOUR
THOUGHT WERE ON HELPING SMALL
BUSINESSES GET GOING AND TAX
INCENTIVES.
>> I HATE TO KEEP TALKING ABOUT
MY STATE.
OUR SMALL BUSINESSES PAY
VIRTUALLY NO INCOME PKCOME TAX
BECAUSE WE WANT SMALL BUSINESSES
TO GROW.
AND THE BEST CHANCE YOU HAVE
WHEN YOU GRADUATE COLLEGE IS
WITH A SMALL BUSINESS.
I'M FOR LOWERING THE INCOME
TAXES NATIONALLY.
YOU PROBABLY ON YOUR PERSONAL
TAXES HAVE A PASS-THROUGH
CORPORATION.
WE NEED TO BRING THE TAXES DOWN
AND HELP SMALL BUSINESSES.
THE OTHER THING WE HAVE TO BE
CAREFUL OF IS WE'RE NOT SNUFFING
OUT THE SMALL LENDING
INSTITUTIONS, THE COMMUNITY
BANKS.
I WAS IN LACROSSE AND I WENT TO
THIS LITTLE BAKERY AND THIS
WOMAN PROUDLY WAS TALKING ABOUT
HOW SHE BUILT THIS BAKERY
BUSINESS, IT WAS A FANTASTIC
PLACE.
SHE SAID A GOT A $9,000 LOAN.
I SAID HOW DID YOU GET IT?
SHE SAID I WENT TO ONE LOCAL
COMMUNITY BANK AND SAID IF YOU
HAVE DON'T LOAN ME THE MONEY,
I'M GOING DOWN THE STREET.
WHAT WE'RE FACING NOW WITH SOME
OF THE BIG BANKS THAT'S TRICKLED
DOWN TO THE SMALLER BANKS IS
WE'RE BEGINNING TO SEE THE
SMALLER BANKS GO OUT OF
BUSINESS.
THOSE ARE THE ONES YOU DEPEND
UPON TO GET THE LOAN YOU NEED
BECAUSE THEY KNOW YOU.
LOWER THE TRUTH AND A PATH TO
FISCAL STABILITY, A BALANCED
BUDGET.
THOSE ARE THE THINGS THAT WILL
HELP YOU MORE THAN ANYTHING
ELSE.
AND ONE FINAL THING, WORKFORCE
DEVELOPMENT.
WE HAVE GOT TO BEGIN TO TEACH
OUR KIDS IN K THROUGH 12 TO BE
GETTING AN EDUCATION FOR A JOB
THAT EXISTS.
DON'T GET EDUCATED IN A VACUUM.
MAKE SURE YOU KNOW WHAT YOU WANT
TO DID AND LOOK FOR AN EDUCATION
THIS CAN LEAD UP TO A REAL JOB.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOOD LUCK.
GOOD LUCK.
>> LET ME FOLLOW UP ON THAT.
>> I DID A SLED DOG TRIM ONE
TIME IN NEW HAMPSHIRE MANY YEARS
AGO AND I THOUGHT I WAS GOING TO
DROWN IN THE WATER.
WHEN I COME UP, CAN YOU GIVE ME
A SAFE RIDE.
HOW'S THAT?
>> ALL RIGHT.
>> OHIO HAS ACTUALLY LAGGED
BEHIND THE NATION IN JOB GROWTH
DURING YOUR TENURE AS GOVERNOR.
IF THAT'S TRUE --
>> IT NOT TRUE.
>> THE NATIONAL PRIVATE SECTOR
JOB GROWTH RATE --
>> WE WERE 48th WHEN I BECAME
GOVERNOR, NOW WE'RE IN THE TOP
TEN.
WE'RE DOING VERY, VERY WELL.
BUT WE'RE NOT OUT OF THE WOODS
YET.
LET'S GO BACK TO WASHINGTON.
WHEN I FOUGHT FOR ALL THOSE
YEARS TO BALANCE THE BUDGET, CUT
THE CAPITAL GAINS TAX, THAT'S
THE TAX THAT GENTLEMAN USE WHEN
IS HE TAKES A RISK, JOBS WERE
FLYING OUT LIKE YOU WOULDN'T
BELIEVE.
THERE ARE THREE THINGS NEEDED TO
GROW AN ECONOMY -- COMMON SENSE
REGULATION, WE DON'T HAVE THEM
NOW, LOWER TAXES, TAXES ARE
GOING UP.
YOU GO TO THE DOCTOR, YOU SAY
I'M NOT FEELING WELL.
HE SAYS WHAT DID YOU DO?
WELL, I DIDN'T LISTEN TO
ANYTHING YOU SAID.
THIS IS A FORMULA THAT WILL
WORK.
I'M ONLY SAYING THIS BECAUSE I
WANT TO YOU HAVE JOB SECURITY
AND I WANT TO YOU BELIEVE THAT
YOUR KIDS ARE GOING TO HAVE A
BETTER LIFE THAN YOU GOT FROM
YOUR PARENTS.
THAT'S THE GREAT AMERICAN LEGACY
AND THAT'S WHEN I'M COMMITTED
TO, FOLKS, NO MATTER WHO I TICK
OFF IN THE PROCESS.
THAT'S WHAT WE GOT TO DO, OKAY?
SO --
>> THIS IS MARY BETH.
SHE'S A SALES REPRESENTATIVE FOR
HER FAMILY'S 106-YEAR-OLD
BUSINESS.
SHE SAID SHE'S UNDECIDED.
>> AS A PRACTICES ROMAN
CATHOLIC, I BELIEVE LIFE BEGINS
AT CONCEPTION AND END AT NATURAL
DEATH.
IF YOU WERE OUR PRESIDENT, WOULD
YOU SUPPORT LEGISLATION THAT
WOULD CREATE A PROTECTED CLASS
FOR UNBORN PERSONS THE SAME WAY
WE HAVE PROTECTED CLASSES FOR
MINORITY RACES AND SEXUAL
ORIENTATIONS?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I'VE BEEN PRO-LIFE ALL OF MY
CAREER.
THE ONLY EXCEPTION ARE RAPE,
INCEST AND LIFE OF THE MOTHER.
WHEN IT COMES TO A SUPREME COURT
JUSTICE, WE HAVE TO BE CAREFUL.
I WANT TO APPOINT JUDGES WHO
DON'T MAKE LAW BUT WHO INTERPRET
THE LAW.
YOU SAID LIFE BEGINS AND THEN IT
ENDS AT DEATH.
I'M GOING TO GIVE YOU ANOTHER
THOUGHT.
LIFE BEGINS AND THEN IT ENDS AT
DEATH AND THEN WE HAVE ANOTHER
LIFE YET TO COME.
DON'T LOSE SIGHT OF THAT.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> THANK YOU.
THAT'S WHAT EASTER WAS ALL
ABOUT, RIGHT?
OKAY.
>> OUR NEXT GUEST IS JOSEPH
RICE.
HE IS A BUSINESS OWNER FROM
WHITE FISH BAY.
HE SAYS HE IS SLIGHTLY LEANING
TOWARDS TED CRUZ BUT THAT HIS
HEART IS WITH YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> WELL, THEN GO WITH THE HEART,
MAN!
>> WELL, I'LL TRY TO ASK A
HEART-FELT QUESTION HERE,
GOVERNOR.
I'M CURIOUS TO KNOW HOW YOU MAY
HAVE SHOWN MORAL COURAGE IN THE
FACE OF PUBLIC OPPOSITION.
SO CAN YOU CITE AN ACTION THAT
YOU TOOK OR DECISION THAT YOU
MADE KNOWING IT WAS THE RIGHT
THING TO DO, DESPITE IT BEING
POLITICALLY UNPOPULAR?
>> LOOK, I DON'T WANT TO GET
INTO HOW COURAGEOUS I AM OR
ANYTHING, BUT LOOK, A GENTLEMAN
STOOD UP FIRST QUESTION OUT OF
HERE IS MEDICAID EXPANSION.
I KNEW IT WASN'T GOING TO BE ALL
THAT POPULAR.
OF COURSE I WASN'T THINKING
ABOUT RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
I'LL TELL YOU THE STORY.
I HAD THIS WOMAN, SHE'S
TERRIFIC.
SHE RUNS OUR MENTAL HEALTH DRUG
ADDICTION SERVICES.
SHE COMES IN MY OFFICE AND
SAYS -- I SAID DO YOU THINK I'M
GOING TO EXPAND MEDICAID?
AND SHE SAYS, WELL, I PRAY EVERY
NIGHT YOU WILL.
I SAID YOUR PRAYERS ARE
ANSWERED, I'M GOING DO IT.
SHE WALKED OUT OF MY OFFICE AND
INTO THE OTHER ROOM AND CRIED.
YOU CAN'T SIT AROUND AND WORRY
ABOUT WHO IS GOING TO LIKE YOU.
I'LL GIVE YOU ANOTHER ONE.
WHEN I WAS IN WASHINGTON, I SAID
IF WE'RE GOING TO REFORM WELFARE
FOR THE POOR PEOPLE, WE OUGHT TO
REFORM IT FOR THE RICH PEOPLE.
SO I FOUGHT FOR CORPORATE
WELFARE REFORM AND CLOSED SOME
OF THE BIG LOOPHOLES WHEN THESE
COMPANIES MOVED TO PUERTO RICO
TO GET TAX ADVANTAGES.
I WANTED AN OPPOSITION TO THE
CLINTON TAX INCREASE AND I HAD A
SPECIFIC PROGRAM TO FIGHT THAT.
WE HAD A REPUBLICAN CONFERENCE.
NEWT WAS SITTING IN THE BACK OF
THE ROOM.
WE HAD 34 SPEAKERS, AND 34
SPEAKERS SAID DON'T LET HIM
REVEAL HIS PLAN.
THE PLAN GOT OUT.
THE BATTLE WE ENGAGED IN IN '93
AND '94 BROUGHT A WHOLE ENOUGH
WAVE OF PEOPLE INTO THE
CONGRESS.
SIR, WHAT YOU HAVE TO REALIZE IN
THIS BUSINESS IS YOU'RE THERE
FOR A SHORT PERIOD OF TIME.
YOU HAVE TO DRIVE THE CAR WHEN
YOU GET YOUR HANDS ON THE WHEEL
AND YOU GOT IT HAVE PEOPLE
AROUND THAT WILL TELL YOU WHEN
YOU'RE ON THE WRONG PATH BECAUSE
SOMETIMES YOU GET ON THE WRONG
PATH.
BUT I HAVE TO ALSO TELL YOU YOU
DON'T EVER WANT TO LOOK BACK AND
SAY I PLAYED POLITICS, I TOOK
CARE OF MY PARTY AND DIDN'T
SERVE THE PEOPLE.
I'M AS BIG OF A REFORMER AS I
WAS THE DAY I GOT ELECTED.
I BELIEVE WE CAN CHANGE THE
WORLD AND MAYBE THE WORLD BETTER
FOR EVERYONE.
AND SOMETIMES YOU GET PEOPLE
UPSET.
THAT'S KIND OF GOES WITH THE
TERRITORY.
HARRY TRUMAN SAID IF YOU WANT A
FRIEND AND YOU'RE IN WASHINGTON,
YOU BETTER GO GET A DOG.
OKAY?
>> THIS IS CHARLOTTE RASMUSSEN.
SHE'S FROM THE TOWNSHIP OF
BUTLER.
SHE'S RETIRED, SAID SHE'S
UNDECIDED.
WELCOME, CHARLOTTE.
ABOUT?
HELLO.
GOVERNOR KASICH, IF YOU BECOME
THE NOMINEE OF THE PARTY, WHO
ARE YOU GOING TO PICK FOR YOUR
VICE PRESIDENT?
>> ARE YOU AVAILABLE?
YOU LOOK GREAT TONIGHT.
NO, YOU KNOW WHAT, THAT'S SO FAR
AHEAD.
THAT'S LIKE MEASURING THE
DRAPES.
BUT I PICKED A LIEUTENANT
GOVERNOR, SOMEBODY TO RUN WITH
ME, A GREAT WOMAN, SHE WAS OUR
AUDITOR AND I PICKED HER TO RUN
WITH ME BECAUSE SHE UNDERSTOOD
WHAT I WANTED TO ACCOMPLISH AND
SHE WAS WILLING TO BE A REALLY
GREAT TEAMMATE, SHE'S DONE GREAT
JOB.
SO YOU WANT TO PICK SOMEBODY WHO
YOU'RE COMFORTABLE WITH AND
SOMEBODY WHO UNDERSTANDS WHEN
YOU'RE ALL ABOUT AND SOMEBODY
WHO IS NOT AFRAID TO SPEAK UP TO
YOU.
YOU SEE, YOU CAN'T JUST SURROUND
YOURSELF WITH SYCOPHANTS, YOU
GOT TO HAVE PEOPLE THERE WHO CAN
TELL YOU, NO, I DON'T THINK
THAT'S RIGHT AND THEN YOU ARGUE
IT OUT.
AT THE END, THOUGH, ONCE YOU
DECIDE, THE WHOLE TEAM MOVES IN
THE SAME DIRECTION.
HAVE I BEEN ABLE TO BE ABLE TO
ACCOMPLISH THINGS IN POLITICS,
I'M GOING TO TELL YOU, NOT
BECAUSE I'M SO GREAT BUT I'VE
BEEN ABLE TO ATTRACT PEOPLE
THROUGHOUT THE YEARS -- I HAVE
SOME PEOPLE THAT HAVE BEEN
AROUND ME FOR 30 YEARS.
WE FORM A GREAT TEAM AND WE KEEP
OUR EYES ON THE HORIZON.
I THINK EVERYBODY WANTS TO BE
INVOLVED WITH SOMETHING THAT'S
BIGGER THAN THEMSELVES.
AND THAT'S WHAT I ALWAYS TRY TO
REPRESENT AND PRESENT IN PUBLIC
LIFE.
SO BE SOMEBODY ALONG THOSE
LINES.
OKAY?
AARON RODGERS, MAYBE IF HE HAD A
BETTER YEAR NEXT YEAR.
WE'LL SEE.
>> WE'LL TAKE A QUICK BREAK AND
HAVE MORE WITH GOVERNOR KASICH
AS WE CONTINUE FROM MILWAUKEE.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> WELCOME BACK.
WE'RE HERE WITH GOVERNOR JOHN
KASICH OF HAOHIO, HERE IN
MILWAUKEE, WISCONSIN.
YESTERDAY CNN YOUR CAMPAIGN IS
LOOKING TO WORK BEHIND THE
SCENES WITH THE CRUZ CAMPAIGN TO
WORK TOGETHER TO DENY DONALD
TRUMP DELEGATES FOR THE
NOMINATION.
>> I'M NOT IN THE MIDDLE OF THAT
AND I HAVEN'T SEEN TED SINCE THE
LAST DEE BATE.
I'M NOT INVOLVED LIKE THAT.
>> YOU SAID YOU'VE DONE A LOT OF
TOWN HALLS, ABOUT 200.
>> JUST LIKE THIS.
>> ONE OF THE THINGS THAT STUCK
IN MY MIND, YOU SAID THIS
CAMPAIGN HAS CAUSED YOU TO SLOW
DOWN.
IT WAS IN REFERENCE WITH AN
INCIDENT YOU HAD IN REFERENCE
WITH A YOUNG MAN.
IN WHAT WAY?
>> THE YOUNG MAN THAT GAVE ME A
HUG WAS JUST EMBLEMATIC OF WHAT
I'VE SEEN ALL OVER.
I THINK WHEN PEOPLE WANT TO FEEL
SAFE AND FOR SOME REASON THEY
COME TO THE TOWN HALLS I HAVE,
WHICH ARE BASICALLY TOWN HALLS
ABOUT HOW WE CAN FIX THINGS AND
BE HOPEFUL AND FOR SOME REASON
PEOPLE FEEL SAFE.
THAT'S THE GRACE OF THE LORD TO
HELP PEOPLE FEEL WHAT WAY.
I WANT TO SHIP PROGRAMS BACK TO
THE STATES.
HERE AS WHAT I WANT EVERYBODY TO
KNOW, I BELIEVE.
THE SPIRIT OF OUR COUNTRY,
ANDERSON, DOESN'T REST IN THE
PRESIDENT.
I MEAN, THE PRESIDENT'S
IMPORTANT.
BUT THE SPIRIT OF OUR COUNTRY
RESTS IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS.
IT RESTS IN THE PEOPLE WHO ARE
HERE TONIGHT.
WE'RE THE ONES THAT NEED TO
CHANGE THE WORLD, FIX EDUCATION,
DEAL WITH THE PROBLEMS OF THE
POOR.
YOU TAKE A LEADY WHO WAS MARRIE
50 YEARS, HER HUSBAND DIED,
NOBODY CALLS HER ANYMORE.
CALL HER ON A MONDAY, SHE'S
GOING TO GET HER HAIR DONE.
WHEN YOU PICK HER UP, NOT ONE
HAIR IS OUT OF PLACE AND SHE
WEARS A DRESS SHE HASN'T WORN IN
SIX MONTHS.
ARE YOU CHANGING THE WORLD?
I THINK YOU ARE.
WHEN A NURSE SITS AND SPENDS A
MINUTES WITH SOMEONE TO SEE IF
THEY'RE OKAY, THE LORD HAS GIVEN
US ALL A CERTAIN PURPOSE IN LIFE
AND WE NEED TO CARRY IT OUT AND
LIVE A LIFE BIGGER THAN
OURSELVES.
BUT WE CAN GET UP EVERY DAY AND
GIVE A LIFE TO HELP HE'AL THIS
WORLD.
WITHOUT JOBS WE SHALL DON'T HAVE
ANYTHING.
BUT WHEN WE SHIFT WELFARE,
INFRASTRUCTURE, JOB TRAINING,
MEDICAID PROGRAMS BACK TO THE
STATES, THEN WE GOT TO RUN 'EM
AND WE GOT TO RUN 'EM WHERE WE
LIVE AND STATE POWER OUGHT TO BE
SHIFT MOING MORE POWER TO THE
NEIGHBORHOODS.
THAT'S THE SPIRIT OF OUR
COUNTRY.
IT'S IN ME, IT'S IN HIM.
IT'S NOT DOWN IN SOMEBODY IN
WASHINGTON, DC.
YOU THINK?
I MEAN, I HOPE SO.
I BELIEVE THAT.
>> IS THIS IT?
>> YEAH.
WE'D LOVE TO DO ANOTHER ONE.
THAT IS ALL THE TIME WE HAVE.
I WANT TO THANK ALL THE
CANDIDATES, THANK THE VOTERS,
THANK EVERYONE WHO MADE TONIGHT
POSSIBLE, INCLUDING THE
RIVERSIDE THEATER AND TURNER
THEATER HERE MILWAUKEE.
THANK YOU.