>>> LIVE FROM THE BANK UNITED
CENTER ON THE CAMPUS OF THE
UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI, THIS IS THE
CNN REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE.
FOR OUR VIEWERS IN THE UNITED
STATES AND AROUND THE WORLD,
WELCOME TO MIAMI, FLORIDA.
I'M JAKE TAPPER.
IN JUST FIVE DAYS, VOTERS WILL
GO TO THE POLLS HERE IN THIS
STATE AS WELL AS IN OHIO,
ILLINOIS, NORTH CAROLINA AND
MISSOURI.
THE RACE FOR THE REPUBLICAN
NOMINATION FOR PRESIDENT COULD
CHANGE DRAMATICALLY.
FLORIDA AND OHIO EACH HAVE A
LARGE NUMBER OF DELEGATES AT
STAKE, AND THEY AWARD ALL OF
THEM TO THE CANDIDATE WHO WINS.
THEY ARE WINNER TAKE ALL STATES.
THAT'S THE FIRST TIME THAT WILL
HAPPEN IN THIS PRIMARY SEASON.
AND THIS IS THE LAST DEBATE
BEFORE THAT CRITICAL ROUND OF
VOTING.
WE HOPE TONIGHT THE CANDIDATES
WILL GIVE THE VOTERS SPECIFICS
ON THEIR VISIONS FOR AMERICA.
SO NOW, LET'S WELCOME THE
CANDIDATES.
OHIO GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SENATOR TED CRUZ OF TEXAS.
REAL ESTATE DEVELOPER AND
BUSINESSMAN DONALD TRUMP.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SENATOR MARCO RUBIO OF FLORIDA.
LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, THE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES FOR
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
BEFORE WE BEGIN THIS EVENING, WE
WANT TO REMEMBER FORMER FIRST
LADY NANCY REAGAN WHO PASSED
AWAY THIS WEEK.
HER FUNERAL WILL BE HELD
TOMORROW, AND WE WOULD LIKE TO
TAKE A MOMENT OF SILENCE TO
REMEMBER NANCY REAGAN.
NOW PLEASE RISE FOR OUR NATIONAL
ANTHEM PERFORMED BY THE FROST
SINGERS FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF
MIAMI.
O SAY, CAN YOU SEE
BY THE DAWN'S EARLY LIGHT
WHAT SO PROUDLY WE HAILED
AT THE TWILIGHT'S
LAST GLEAMING?
WHOSE BROAD STRIPES
AND BRIGHT STARS
THROUGH THE PERILOUS FIGHT
O'ER THE RAMPARTS
WE WATCHED
WERE SO GALLANTLY
STREAMING?
AND THE ROCKETS'
RED GLARE
THE BOMBS BURSTING
IN AIR
GAVE PROOF
THROUGH THE NIGHT
THAT OUR FLAG
WAS STILL THERE
OH, SAY, DOES THAT
STAR-SPANGLED BANNER
YET WAVE
O'ER THE LAND
OF THE FREE
AND THE HOME
OF THE BRAVE?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANKS TO THE FROST SINGERS
FROM THE UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI.
CANDIDATES YOU CAN NOW TAKE YOUR
POSITIONS BEHIND THE PODIUMS
WHILE I BRIEFLY EXPLAIN THE
RULES.
AS MODERATOR, I WILL ATTEMPT TO
GUIDE THE DISCUSSION ASKING
QUESTIONS AND FOLLOW-UPS.
JOINING ME IN THE QUESTIONING
THIS EVENING WILL BE "WASHINGTON
TIMES" REPORTER STEPHEN DINAN,
CNN CHIEF POLITICAL
CORRESPONDENT DANA BASH AND
SALEM RADIO'S HUGH HEWITT.
CANDIDATES, YOU WILL HAVE ONE
MINUTE AND 15 SECONDS TO ANSWER
EACH QUESTION AND 45 SECONDS TO
RESPOND TO FOLLOW-UPS OR
REBUTTALS IF YOUR NAME SINN
VOKED.
TIMING LIGHTS WILL BE VISIBLE.
THEY'LL WARN YOU WHEN TIME IS
UP.
AND AS YOU REQUESTED, A BELL
WILL ALSO SOUND LIKE THIS.
WE KNOW THAT EACH OF YOU WANTS
TO DEBATE THESE IMPORTANT ISSUES
BUT PLEASE WAIT UNTIL YOU ARE
CALLED UPON, AND PLEASE DO NOT
TALK OVER ONE ANOTHER.
THESE ARE THE RULES TO WHICH ALL
OF YOU AGREED.
OUR GOAL THIS EVENING IS A
SERIOUS DEBATE ON THE ISSUES.
IT'S TIME NOW FOR OPENING
STATEMENTS.
YOU'LL EACH HAVE 30 SECONDS.
GOVERNOR KASICH, WE WILL START
WITH YOU.
>> WELL, THANK YOU.
YOU KNOW, I LOOK IN THE FACES OF
PEOPLE ALL ACROSS THIS COUNTRY,
AND I KNOW THEY WANT TO BE
HOPEFUL.
AND MANY ARE HOPEFUL.
LOOK, I CAN TALK CONSERVATIVE
POLICIES TO THE WHITE HOUSE,
WASHINGTON, TO RESTORE THE
STRENGTH OF OUR ECONOMY.
BUT I ALSO WANT TO TRANSFER
POWER, MONEY AND INFLUENCE TO
WHERE YOU LIVE.
BECAUSE I BELIEVE THE STRENGTH
IN THIS COUNTRY RESTS IN THE
NEIGHBORHOODS, THE FAMILIES, THE
COMMUNITIES AND OUR STATES.
AND I BELIEVE IT'S A NEW
PARTNERSHIP.
A PARTNERSHIP THAT CAN ALLOW US
TO RESTORE THE SPIRIT OF AMERICA
AND STRENGTHEN AMERICA FOR THE
BEST CENTURY WE'VE EVER HAD.
THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> EVERY ELECTION IS IMPORTANT.
I BELIEVE THIS IS THE MOST
IMPORTANT ELECTION IN A
GENERATION.
BECAUSE WHAT'S AT STAKE IN THIS
ELECTION IS NOT SIMPLY WHAT
PARTY IS GOING TO BE IN CHARGE
OR WHICH CANDIDATE WINS.
WHAT'S AT STAKE IS OUR IDENTITY
AS A NATION AND AS A PEOPLE.
FOR OVER TWO CENTURIES, AMERICA
HAS BEEN AN EXCEPTIONAL NATION.
NOW THE TOMB HAS COME FOR THIS
GENERATION TO DO WHAT IT MUST DO
TO KEEP IT THAT WAY.
IF WE MAKE THE RIGHT CHOICE IN
THIS ELECTION, OUR CHILDREN WILL
BE THE FREEST AND MOST
PROSPEROUS AMERICANS THAT HAVE
EVER LIVED AND THE 21st CENTURY
WILL BE A NEW AMERICAN CENTURY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR CRUZ.
>> 59 YEARS AGO, FLORIDA
WELCOMED MY FATHER TO AMERICA AS
HE STEPPED OFF THE FERRYBOAT
FROM CUBA ON TO KEY WEST.
HE WAS 18.
HE WAS FILLED WITH HOPES AND
DREAMS, AND YET IN THE FREEST
LAND ON THE FACE OF THE EARTH.
THIS ELECTION, THIS DEBATE IS
NOT ABOUT INSULTS OR ATTACKS.
IT'S NOT ABOUT ANY INDIVIDUALS
ON THIS STAGE.
THIS ELECTION IS ABOUT YOU AND
YOUR CHILDREN.
IT'S ABOUT THE FREEDOM AMERICA
HAS ALWAYS HAD.
AND MAKING SURE THAT THAT
FREEDOM IS THERE FOR THE NEXT
GENERATION THAT WE STOP
WASHINGTON FROM STANDING IN THE
WAY OF THE HARD-WORKING
TAXPAYERS OF AMERICA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> ONE OF THE BIGGEST POLITICAL
EVENTS ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD IS
HAPPENING RIGHT NOW WITH THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY.
MILLIONS AND MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
ARE GOING OUT TO THE POLLS AND
THEY ARE VOTING.
THEY ARE VOTING OUT OF
ENTHUSIASM.
THEY ARE VOTING OUT OF LOVE.
SOME OF THESE PEOPLE, FRANKLY,
HAVE NEVER VOTED BEFORE.
50 YEARS OLD, 60 YEARS OLD, 70
YEARS OLD.
NEVER VOTED BEFORE.
WE'RE TAKING PEOPLE FROM THE
DEMOCRAT PARTY.
WE'RE TAKING PEOPLE AS
INDEPENDENCES.
A
INDEPENDENTS.
THEY'RE ALL COMING OUT AND THE
WHOLE WORLD IS TALKING ABOUT IT.
IT'S VERY EXCITING.
I THINK, FRANKLY, THE REPUBLICAN
ESTABLISHMENT, OR WHATEVER YOU
WANT TO CALL IT, SHOULD EMBRACE
WHAT'S HAPPENING.
WE'RE HAVING MILLIONS OF EXTRA
PEOPLE JOIN.
WE ARE GOING TO BEAT THE
DEMOCRATS.
WE ARE GOING TO BEAT HILLARY OR
WHOEVER IT MAY BE.
AND WE'RE GOING TO BEAT THEM
SOUNDLY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU.
THANK YOU.
LET'S BEGIN WITH JOBS AND THE
ECONOMY WHICH REPUBLICAN VOTERS
SAY IS THE MOST IMPORTANT ISSUE
TO THEM IN THIS ELECTION.
THERE HAVE BEEN SOME REAL
DIFFERENCES EXPRESSED ON THIS
STAGE ON WHETHER TRADE DEALS
HAVE BEEN GOOD FOR THE AMERICAN
WORKER.
MR. TRUMP'S SIGNATURE ISSUES IS
ENDING WHAT HE CALLS DISASTROUS
TRADE DEALS IN ORDER TO BRING
JOBS BACK TO AMERICA.
GOVERNOR KASICH, I'D LIKE TO
START WITH YOU.
YOU'VE BEEN A STRONG ADVOCATE
FOR THESE STRONG DEALS.
CRITICS SAY THESE DEALS ARE
KNRA
GREAT FOR CORPORATE AMERICA'S
BOTTOM LINE BUT HAVE COST THE
U.S. AT LEAST 1 MILLION JOBS.
HOW DO YOU RESPOND TO THE
CRITICISM THAT YOU'VE BEEN
CATERING TO BOARDROOMS AT THE
EXPENSE OF THE MIDDLE CLASS?
>> I GREW UP IN A BLUE COLLAR
FAMILY.
THE SIMPLE FACT OF THE MATTER
IS, OF COURSE, WE'RE SENSITIVE
ABOUT TRADE.
1 OUT OF 5 AMERICANS WORK IN A
JOB CONNECTED TO TRADE.
38 MILLION AMERICANS ARE
CONNECTED TO IT.
BUT MY POSITION HAS ALWAYS BEEN
WE WANT TO HAVE FREE TRADE, BUT
FAIR TRADE.
AND I'VE BEEN ARGUING ALL ALONG
THAT IT IS ABSOLUTELY CRITICAL
THAT WHEN OTHER COUNTRIES BREAK
THOSE AGREEMENTS, WE DON'T TURN
THE PROCESS OVER TO SOME
INTERNATIONAL BUREAUCRAT WHO
COMES BACK A COUPLE YEARS LATER
AND SAYS, OH, AMERICA WAS RIGHT
AND PEOPLE ARE OUT OF WORK.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS WE
HAVE TO HAVE AN EXPEDITED
PROCESS.
WHEN PEOPLE CHEAT, WHEN
COUNTRIES CHEAT AND THEY TAKE
ADVANTAGE OF US, WE NEED TO BLOW
THE WHISTLE.
AND AS PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, I ABSOLUTELY WILL BLOW
THE WHISTLE AND BEGIN TO STAND
UP FOR THE AMERICAN WORKER.
WE DON'T WANT TO LOCK THE DOORS
AND PULL DOWN THE BLINDS AND
LEAVE THE WORLD BECAUSE,
FRANKLY, IF WE DO THAT, PRICES
WILL GO UP.
PEOPLE WILL BUY LESS.
OTHER PEOPLE WILL BE OUT OF
WORK.
AND WE DON'T WANT TO SEE THAT
HAPPEN.
TRADE, THOUGH, HAS TO BE
BALANCED, AND WE HAVE TO MAKE
SURE THAT WHEN WE SEE A
VIOLATION LIKE SOME COUNTRY,
DUMPING THEIR PRODUCTS INTO THIS
COUNTRY, BELIEVE ME, AS
PRESIDENT, I WILL STAND UP AND I
WILL SHUT DOWN THOSE IMPORTS
BECAUSE THEY ARE A VIOLATION OF
THE AGREEMENT WE HAVE.
AND THE AMERICAN WORKER EXPECTS
US TO STAND UP AND, JAKE, MY
FAMILY WORKED IN THE STEEL
INDUSTRY, NOT WITH A WHITE
COLLAR.
I UNDERSTAND THEIR PLIGHT.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOUR CRITICS SAY
YOUR CAMPAIGN PLATFORM IS
INCONSISTENT WITH HOW YOU RUN
YOUR BUSINESSES, NOTING YOU'VE
BROUGHT IN FOREIGN WORKERS
INSTEAD OF HIRING AMERICANS AND
YOUR COMPANIES MANUFACTURE
CLOTHING IN CHINA AND MEXICO.
WHY SHOULD VOTERS TRUST THAT
YOU'LL RUN THE COUNTRY
DIFFERENTLY FROM HOW YOU RUN
YOUR BUSINESSES?
>> BECAUSE NOBODY KNOWS THE
SYSTEM BETTER THAN ME.
I KNOW THE H1B, THE H2B.
I'M A BUSINESSMAN.
THESE ARE LAWS.
THESE ARE REGULATIONS.
THESE ARE RULES.
WE'RE ALLOWED TO DO IT.
FRANKLY, BECAUSE OF THE
DEVALUATIONS THAT'S OTHER
COUNTRIES, THE MONETARY
DEVALUATIONS THAT OTHER
COUNTRIES ARE CONSTANTLY DOING
AND BRILLIANTLY DOING AGAINST
US, IT'S VERY, VERY HARD FOR OUR
COMPANIES IN THIS COUNTRY, IN
OUR COUNTRY TO COMPETE.
SO I WILL TAKE ADVANTAGE OF IT.
THEY ARE THE LAWS.
BUT I'M THE ONE THAT KNOWS HOW
TO CHANGE IT.
NOBODY ELSE ON THIS STAGE KNOWS
HOW TO CHANGE IT LIKE I DO.
BELIEVE ME.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, LAST OCTOBER
YOU SAID THAT YOU'RE QUOTE,
GENERALLY VERY MUCH IN FAVOR OF
FREE TRADE.
MORE RECENTLY YOU'VE BACKED AWAY
FROM YOUR SUPPORT OF SOME TRADE
DEALS.
IF ELECTED, WILL YOU SUPPORT
FREE TRADE DEALS, EVEN IF IT
MEANS THE INEVITABLE LOSS OF
U.S. JOBS?
>> NO, I SUPPORT FREE TRADE
DEALS THAT ARE GOOD FOR AMERICA.
WE'RE 5% OF THE WORLD'S
POPULATION.
IF ALL WE DO IS SELL THINGS DO
EACH OTHER, WE CAN ONLY SELL TO
5% OF THE PEOPLE ON EARTH.
WE HAVE TO HAVE ACCESS TO THE
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
IN THE WORLD TODAY WHO CAN
AFFORD TO BUY THINGS.
THE PROBLEM IS WE'RE A LOW
TARIFF COUNTRY.
TO IMPORT SOMETHING INTO THE
UNITED STATES IS NOT VERY
EXPENSIVE.
BUT MANY OF THESE COUNTRIES WE
CAN'T EXPORT TO BECAUSE THEIR
TARIFFS ARE TOO HIGH.
I'M IN FAVOR OF DEALS THAT ALLOW
US TO BRING DOWN THOSE TARIFFS
SO AMERICA CAN SELL THINGS TO
PEOPLE ALL AROUND THE WORLD.
THERE ARE GOOD TRADE DEALS AND
BAD ONES.
HERE IN FLORIDA WE'VE BENEFITED
FROM THE FREE TRADE DEAL WITH
COLOMBIA.
IT'S ALLOWED FLOWER EXPORTERS TO
COME INTO THE UNITED STATES BUT
CREATED JOBS FOR HUNDREDS OF
PEOPLE WHO ARE NOW DELIVERING
THOSE FLOWERS AND WORKING IN
THAT INDUSTRY.
WE HAVE A SURPLUS WITH COLOMBIA.
ON THE OTHER HAND YOU'VE SEEN
TRADE DEALS IN MEXICO LESS THAN
PROMISING IN SOME ASECTS, BETTER
IN OTHERS.
I BELIEVE THAT AMERICA, IF GIVEN
ACCESS TO FOREIGN MARKETS, OUR
WORKERS ARE THE MOST PRODUCTIVE
IN THE WORLD.
OUR PEOPLE ARE THE MOST
INNOVATIVE ON THIS PLANET.
IF IT'S A FREE AND FAIR TRADE
DEAL WE CAN C C CPETE AGAINST
ANYONE IN THE WORLD AND WE NEED
TO IN THE 21st CENTURY.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU WERE A
SUPPORTER OF THE PACIFIC TRADE
DEAL, BUT AFTER TAKING SOME HEAT
FROM CONSERVATIVES YOU CHANGED
YOUR POSITION.
WHY SHOULD THESE VOTERS WHO
DON'T LIKE THESE TRADE DEALS
TRUST THAT YOU WILL FIGHT FOR
THEM ALL THE TIME AND NOT JUST
IN ELECTION YEARS?
>> ACTUALLY THAT'S INCORRECT.
THERE ARE TWO DIFFERENT
AGREEMENTS.
THERE'S TPA AND TPP.
I OPPOSED TPP AND HAVE ALWAYS
OPPOSED TPP.
WHEN IT COMES TO TRADE, LOOK,
FREE TRADE, WHEN WE OPEN UP
FOREIGN MARKETS, HELPS
AMERICANS.
BUT WE'RE GETTING KILLS IN
INTERNATIONAL TRADE RIGHT NOW.
AND WE'RE GETTING KILLED BECAUSE
WE HAVE AN ADMINISTRATION THAT'S
DOESN'T LOOK OUT FOR AMERICAN
WORKERS AND JOBS ARE GOING
OVERSEAS.
WE'RE DRIVING JOBS OVERSEAS.
AND THE PEOPLE WHO ARE LOSING
OUT ARE MANUFACTURING JOBS, OR
THE STEEL INDUSTRY OR AUTO
INDUSTRY.
BUT I'LL TELL YOU WHO ELSE IS
GOING TO BE LOSING OUT, WHICH IS
THE SERVICE INDUSTRY.
THIS OBAMA ADMINISTRATION IS
NEGOTIATING THE TRADE OF
SERVICES AGREEMENT WHICH IS
ANOTHER TREATY TO ALLOW SERVICES
TO COME IN AND TAKE JOBS FROM
AMERICANS AS WELL.
AND YOU HAVE TO UNDERSTAND.
TRADE AND IMMIGRATION ARE
INTERWOVEN, AND THEY ARE HURTING
THE WORKING MEN AND WOMEN OF
THIS COUNTRY.
SO THE QUESTION IS, WHAT'S THE
SOLUTION?
IT'S EASY TO TALK ABOUT THE
PROBLEMS.
BUT DO YOU HAVE A SOLUTION TO
FIX IT?
I THINK THE SOLUTION IS SEVERAL
THINGS.
NUMBER ONE, WE NEED TO NEGOTIATE
TRADE DEALS PROTECTING AMERICAN
WORKERS FIRST, NOT THE CORPORATE
BOARD ROOM.
NUMBER TWO, WE NEED TO LIFT THE
REGULATIONS ON AMERICAN
BUSINESSES HERE SO WE SEE JOBS
COMING BACK.
AND NUMBER THREE, WE NEED A TAX
PLAN LIKE THE TAX PLAN I'VE
INTRODUCED THAT WILL NOT TAX
EXPORTS AND WILL TAX IMPORTS AND
THAT WILL BRING MILLIONS OF
HIGH-PAYING JOBS BACK TO
AMERICA.
>> LET'S TALK MORE ABOUT HOW
AMERICAN JOBS ARE IMPACTED BY
FOREIGN WORKERS.
LET'S GO TO STEPHEN DINAN OF THE
"WASHINGTON TIMES."
>> SENATOR RUBIO IN LATE 2014,
DISNEY LAID OFF 250 TECH WORKERS
IN ORLANDO REPLACING MANY WITH
FOREIGN WORKERS.
SOME OF THE AMERICANS EVEN HAD
TO TRAIN THEIR OWN REPLACEMENTS.
YOU SUPPORT INCREASING THE H1B
VISA PROGRAM THAT MADE IT
POSSIBLE TO BRING IN THESE
FOREIGN WORKERS.
DOESN'T THIS PROGRAM TAKE JOBS
AWAY FROM AMERICANS?
>> IF IT'S BEING ABUSED THE WAY
DISNEY DID.
UNDERSTAND THAT PROGRAM, IT IS
ILLEGAL NOW UNDER THAT PROGRAM
TO TUS TO REPLACE AMERICAN
WORKERS.
YOU HAVE TO PROVE YOU'RE NOT
REPLACING AMERICANS BUT YOU'VE
TRIED TO HIRE AMERICANS.
IF A COMPANY IS CAUGHT ABUSING
THAT PROCESS THEY SHOULD NEVER
BE ALLOWED TO USE IT AGAIN.
THE SECOND PROBLEM WITH THE
CURRENT STRUCTURE OF THE PROGRAM
THAT PEOPLE PERHAPS DON'T
UNDERSTAND IS A LOT OF THESE
COMPANIES ARE NOT DIRECTLY
HIRING EMPLOYEES FROM ABROAD.
THEY ARE HIRING A CONSULTING
COMPANY OUT OF INDIA.
THAT COMPANY HOARDS UP ALL OF
THESE VISAS.
THEY HIRE WORKERS.
YOU HIRE DISNEY OR SOME OTHER
COMPANY HOURS A THIS COMPANY.
WHAT THEY ARE DOING IS
INSOURCING AND OUTSOURCING.
THEY ARE BRINGING IN WORKERS
FROM ABROAD THAT ARE NOT DIRECT
EMPLOYEES OF DISNEY OR SOMEONE
ELSE.
THEY ARE EMPLOYEES OF THIS
CONSULTING BUSINESS.
WHAT I ARGUE IS THAT NO
CONSULTING BUSINESS SUCH AS THAT
SHOULD BE ALLOWED TO HOARD UP
ALL OF THESE VISAS.
THE VISAS SHOULD ONLY BE
AVAILABLE FOR COMPANIES TO USE
TO DIRECTLY HIRE WORKERS AND WE
SHOULD BE STRICTER IN HOW HE
ENFORCE IT.
IT'S ILLEGAL NOW.
IT IS A VIOLATION OF THE LAW NOW
TO USE THAT PROGRAM TO REPLACE
AMERICANS.
AND IF A COMPANY IS CAUGHT DOING
THAT, WHETHER IT BE DISNEY OR
ANYONE ELSE, THEY SHOULD BE
BARRED FROM USING THE PROGRAM IN
THE FUTURE.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, REAL QUICK
FOLLOW-UP ON THIS.
A IN THE CONTEXT OF ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION YOU'VE CALLED FOR
BASICALLY PUTTING OFF ANY
LEGALIZATION PROCESS UNTIL WE
GET THE BORDER SECURED.
WHY NOT CALL FOR A PAUSE ON H1Bs
UNTIL THOSE ABUSES ARE SOLVED.
>> I'D BE OPEN TO IT IF IT TAKES
A PAUSE.
I DON'T THINK IT TAKES A PAUSE
TO ENFORCE THE LAW.
IF THEY ARE USING THAT PROGRAM
TO REPLACE AN AMERICAN, IF
THERE'S AN AMERICAN WORKING AT
DISNEY AND THEY BRING SOMEONE
FROM ANOTHER COUNTRY USING H1B
TO REPLACE THEIR DIRECT JOB,
THAT'S IN VIOLATION OF THE LAW.
WHAT I'M EXPLAINING TO YOU IS
WHAT THEY ARE DOING NOW IS THEY
ARE NOT -- WHAT THEY ARE DOING
IS ELIMINATING THE JOB,
OUTSOURCING THE ENTIRE TECH
DIVISION TO A CONSULTING
COMPANY.
MAKING THE ARGUMENT WE DIDN'T
REPLACE YOU.
WE REPLACED THE WHOLE UNIT BY
HIRING A COMPANY TO DO IT
INSTEAD.
AND THAT COMPANY THEY ARE HIRING
IS BRINGING THEIR WORKERS FROM
ABROAD.
IT'S A LOOPHOLE THEY'VE FIGURED
OUT THAT WE NEED TO CLOSE SO
THEY CAN NO LONGER DO IT THAT
WAY.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, MR. TRUMP
SAYS THAT LEGAL IMMIGRATION IS
PRODUCING, QUOTE, LOWER WAGES
AND HIGHER UNEMPLOYMENT FOR U.S.
WORKERS.
HE'S CALLING FOR A PAUSE ON
GREEN CARDS ISSUED TO FOREIGN
WORKERS.
WOULDN'T THAT HELP WORKERS IN
THE U.S.?
>> LOOK, I BELIEVE IN
IMMIGRATION, BUT IT HAS TO BE
CONTROLLED.
THE SIMPLE FACT OF THE MATTER IS
I WOULDN'T BE STANDING HERE.
I'D BE MAYBE RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT OF CROATIA IF WE
DIDN'T HAVE IMMIGRATION.
IMMIGRATION IS SOMETHING THAT
BRINGS YOUTHS AND VIBRANCE AND
ENERGY TO OUR COUNTRY.
WE CLEARLY HAVE TO CONTROL OUR
BORDERS.
WE CAN'T HAVE PEOPLE JUST
WALKING IN.
WE LOCK OUR DOORS AT HOME AT
NIGHT.
THE COUNTRY HAS TO BE ABLE TO
LOCK ITS DOORS AS WELL.
SO I HAVE A COMPREHENSIVE PLAN
TO DEAL WITH THIS PROBLEM OF
IMMIGRATION.
I WOULD SAY WE HAVE TO
ABSOLUTELY FINISH THE WALL AND
GUARD THE BORDER.
AND IF ANYBODY WERE TO COME IN
AFTER THAT, THEY ARE GOING TO
HAVE TO GO BACK.
NO EXCUSES BECAUSE WE CAN'T
CONTINUE THIS PROBLEM.
WE OUGHT TO HAVE A GUEST WORKER
PROGRAM WHERE PEOPLE COME IN,
WORK AND GO HOME.
AND I THINK AT THE SAME TIME FOR
THE 11.5 MILLION WHO ARE HERE,
THEN IN MY VIEW IF THEY HAVE NOT
COMMITTED A CRIME, SINCE THEY'VE
BEEN HERE, THEY GET A PATH TO
LEGALIZATION.
NOT TO CITIZENSHIP.
I BELIEVE THAT THAT PROGRAM CAN
PASS THE CONGRESS IN THE FIRST
100 DAYS.
BUT LET'S NOT LOSE SIGHT OF THE
FACT THAT THE WHOLE KEY TO THE
FUTURE OF AMERICA IS STRONG
ECONOMIC GROWTH WITH COMMON
SENSE REGULATION, LOWER TAXES
AND A BALANCED BUDGET.
WE CAN HAVE A RISING TIDE THAT
LIFTS ALL THE WORKERS IN
AMERICA, ALL THE PEOPLE WHO ARE
CITIZENS OF AMERICA IF WE'LL
JUST FOLLOW THE FORMULA THAT
WORKS THAT I USED IN WASHINGTON
AND, GUESS WHAT, I'VE USED IN
OHIO TO GROW OVER 400 PRIVATE
SECTOR JOBS SINCE I'VE BEEN
GOVERNOR.
>> MR. TRUMP, I DO WANT TO COME
TO YOU.
WILL YOU ALSO IN YOUR ANSWER
ADDRESS HOW LONG YOU THINK THAT
PAUSE WOULD BE AND WHAT THAT
PAUSE WOULD LOOK LIKE.
>> FIRST OF ALL, I KNOW THE H1B
VERY WELL.
IT'S SOMETHING THAT I FRANKLY
USE AND SHOULDN'T BE ALLOWED TO
USE.
WE SHOULDN'T HAVE IT.
VERY, VERY BAD FOR WORKERS.
AND SECOND OF ALL, IT'S VERY
IMPORTANT TO SAY, WELL, I'M A
BUSINESSMAN AND I HAVE TO DO
WHAT I HAVE TO DO.
WHEN IT'S SITTING THERE WAITING
FOR YOU, BUT IT'S VERY BAD.
IT'S VERY BAD FOR BUSINESS.
AND IT'S BAD FOR OUR WORKERS AND
UNFAIR FOR OUR WORKERS.
VERY IMPORTANT, THE DISNEY
WORKERS ENDORSED ME, AS YOU
PROBABLY READ.
I GOT A FULL ENDORSEMENT BECAUSE
THEY ARE THE ONES THAT SAID, AND
THEY HAD A NEWS CONFERENCE AND
SAID HE'S THE ONLY ONE THAT'S
GOING TO BE ABLE TO FIX IT,
BECAUSE IT IS A MESS.
FOR A PERIOD OF A YEAR TO TWO
YEARS WE HAVE TO LOOK BACK AND
SEE, JUST ANSWER THE SECOND PART
OF YOUR QUESTION, WHERE WE ARE,
WHERE WE STAND, WHAT'S GOING ON.
WE HAVE TO SORT OF TAKE A
STRONG, GOOD HARD LOOK AND COME
UP WITH PLANS THAT WORK.
AND WE'RE RUSHING INTO THINGS,
AND WE'RE JUST -- WE'RE LEADING
WITH THE CHIN.
WE'RE LEADING WITH PEOPLE THAT
DON'T KNOW WHAT THEY ARE DOING
IN TERMS OF OUR LEADERSHIP.
I'D SAY A MINIMUM OF ONE YEAR,
MAYBE TWO YEARS.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, I WANT TO BRING
YOU IN VERY QUICKLY ON THIS.
THE UNITED STATES AVERAGES ABOUT
A MILLION NEW PERMINENT LEGAL
IMMIGRANTS A YEAR AND HUNDREDS
OF THOUSANDS MORE GUEST WORKERS.
WHAT SHOULD THE RIGHT LEVEL BE?
>> WE NEED TO REDEFINE OUR LEGAL
IMMIGRATION SYSTEM SO THAT IT
MEETS THE NEEDS OF THE AMERICAN
ECONOMY.
RIGHT NOW WE'RE BRINGING IN FAR
TOO MANY LOW SKILLED WORKERS.
WHAT THAT IS DOING IS DRIVING
DOWN THE WAGES OF HARD-WORKING
AMERICANS.
OUR SYSTEM ISN'T WORKING.
THEN ON TOP OF THAT, WE HAVE A
SYSTEM THAT'S ALLOWING IN
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE TO BE HERE
ILLEGALLY AND THE ANSWER TO
THAT, I'VE LAID OUT A VERY
DETAILED IMMIGRATION PLAN ON MY
WEBSITE.
WE'RE GOING TO BUILD A WALL,
TRIPLE THE BORDER PATROL.
WE'RE GOING TO END SANCTUARY
CITIES.
WE'RE GOING TO CUT OFF FEDERAL
TAXPAYER FUNDS TO ANY CITY THAT
DEFIES FEDERAL IMMIGRATION LAWS.
WE'RE GOING TO END WELFARE
BENEFITS FOR ANYONE WHO IS HERE
ILLEGALLY.
AND THE THING TO UNDERSTAND,
STEPHEN, WE CAN SOLVE THESE
PROBLEMS.
IT'S NOT THAT WE DON'T KNOW HOW
TO DO IT.
IT'S THAT WE'RE LACKING THE
POLITICAL WILL.
NEITHER OF THE PARTIES IN
WASHINGTON WANTS TO DO THIS.
THE DEMOCRATS SUPPORT ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION BECAUSE THEY VIEW
THOSE ILLEGAL IMP GRANTS AS
POTENTIAL VOTERS AND FAR TOO
MANY OF THE REPUBLICANS ARE
DOING THE BIDDING OF WALL STREET
AND THE SPECIAL INTEREST AND
THEY VIEW TIT AS CHEAP LABOR.
WE NEED LEADERSHIP THAT WORKS
FOR THE MEN AND WOMEN OF THIS
SYSTEM AND A SYSTEM THAT TAKES
CARE OF THE JOBS OF THE WORKING
MEN AND WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY.
>> DO YOU WANT TO WEIGH IN?
>> I WOULD ADD WHEN YOU TALK
ABOUT THE MILLIONS OF GREEN
CARDS COMING IN, THOSE AREN'T
WORKERS AT ALL.
THEY ARE JUST COMING IN
PRIMARILY BASEOD FAMILY
CONNECTION.
MY PARENTS CAME IN 1956.
I ACKNOWLEDGE THAT MY PARENTS
CAME TO THE U.S. ON A
FAMILY-BASED SYSTEM.
THE PROBLEM IS NOTHING LOOKS
LIKE IT DID 60 YEARS AGO.
THE 21st CENTURY ECONOMY IS NOT
CREATING ENOUGH JOBS FOR PEOPLE
THAT DON'T HAVE SKILLS.
WHEN MY PARENTS CAME, THEY HAD A
VERY LIMITED EDUCATION.
MY FATHER STOPPED GOING TO
SCHOOL WHEN HE WAS 9 YEARS OLD
BECAUSE HIS MOTHER DIED AND HE
HAD TO WORK.
HE'D WORK THE NEXT 70 YEARS OF
HIS LIFE AND NEVER GO BACK TO
SCHOOL.
I'M GRATEFUL EVERY DAY THAT
AMERICA WELCOMED THEM.
BUT TODAY IN THE 21st CENTURY,
60 YEARS LATER, FINDING JOBS
WHEN YOU DON'T HAVE SKILLS IS
VERY IMPORTANT.
WE NEED TO MOVE TO A MERIT BASED
SYSTEM OF IMMIGRATION.
PARTICULARLY ON GREEN CARDS.
THE PRIMARY CRITERIA FOR
BRINGING SOMEONE FROM ABROAD
SHOULD BE, WHAT SKILLS DO YOU
HAVE?
WHAT BUSINESS ARE YOU GOING TO
OPEN?
WHAT INVESTMENT ARE YOU GOING TO
MAKE?
WHAT JOB ARE YOU GOING TO BE
ABLE TO DO WHEN YOU ARRIVE IN
THE UNITED STATES?
>> EDUCATION, OBVIOUSLY, PLAYS A
LARGE ROLE WHEN IT COMES TO JOBS
AND THE ECONOMY.
THE UNITED STATES HAS LONG BEEN
FALLING BEHIND OTHERS IN THE
INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD.
AMERICAN STUDENTS RANK 27th OUT
OF 34 COUNTRIES IN MATH AND 17th
IN READING.
MR. TRUMP, YOU'VE CALLED THE
EDUCATION STANDARDS KNOWN AS
COMMON CORE A DISASTER.
WHAT ARE YOUR SPECIFIC
OBJECTIONS TO COMMON CORE?
>> EDUCATION THROUGH WASHINGTON,
D.C.
I DON'T WANT THAT.
I WANT LOCAL EDUCATION.
I WANT THE PARENTS, AND I WANT
ALL OF THE TEACHERS AND I WANT
EVERYBODY TO GET TOGETHER AROUND
A SCHOOL AND TO MAKE EDUCATION
GREAT.
AND IT WAS VERY INTERESTING.
I WAS WITH DR. BEN CARSON TODAY,
WHO IS ENDORSING ME, BY THE WAY,
TOMORROW MORNING, AND HE IS --
WE WERE TALKING.
WE SPOKE FOR OVER AN HOUR ON
EDUCATION.
HE HAS SUCH A GREAT HANDLE ON
IT.
HE WANTS COMPETSATIVE SCHOOLS
AND A LOT OF DIFFERENT THUINGS
THAT ARE TERRIFIC, INCLUDING
CHARTER SCHOOLS THAT THE UNIONS
ARE FIGHTING LIKE CRAZY.
BUT CHARTER SCHOOLS WORK AND
WORK VERY WELL.
THERE ARE A LOT OF THINGS.
I'M GOING TO HAVE BEEN VERY
INVOLVED WITH EDUCATION,
SOMETHING THAT'S AN EXPERTISE OF
HIM.
>> TO CLARIFY, THE COMMON CORE
STANDARDS WERE DEVELOPED BY THE
STATES.
STATES AND LOCALITIES
VOLUNTARILY ADOPT THEM AND THEY
COMING UP WITH THEIR OWN
CURRICULA TO MEET THOSE
STANDARDS.
WHEN YOU SAY EDUCATION BY
WASHINGTON, D.C., WHAT DO YOU
MEAN.
>> BUT IT'S BEEN TAKEN OVER BY
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
IT WAS ORIGINALLY SUPPOSED TO BE
THAT WAY AND CERTAINLY SOUNDS
BETTER THAT WAY DUIT'S ALL BEEN
TAKEN OVER BY THE BUREAUCRATS IN
WASHINGTON AND THEY ARE NOT
INTERESTED IN WHAT'S HAPPENING
IN MIAMI OR FLORIDA IN MANY
CASES.
IN SOME CASES THEY WOULD BE.
THEY ARE MORE INTERESTED IN
THEIR PAYCHECK AND THE BIG
BUREAUCRACY THAN TAKING CARE OF
THE CHILDREN.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, YOU'VE
CALLED OPPOSITION TO COMMON CORE
HYSTERIA.
WHAT'S YOUR RESPONSE TO
GRASSROOTS CONSERVATIVES WHO DO
NOT AGREE WITH YOU?
>> ALL I'M IN FAVOR OF IN OHIO
IS HIGH STANDARDS.
FIRST OF ALL, I WOULD TAKE 125
FEDERAL EDUCATION PROGRAMS, PUT
THEM IN FOUR BUCKETS AND SEND
THEM BACK TO THE STATES.
I'VE BEEN WORKING ON THIS FOR
MANY, MANY YEARS.
SECONDLY, JAKE, IN OUR STATE,
THE STATE SCHOOL BOARD SETS THE
STANDARDS.
AND WE WANT HIGH STANDARDS
BECAUSE WE HAVE NOT ALWAYS HAD
HIGH STANDARDS, UNFORTUNATELY.
THEY SET THE STANDARDS AND THE
LOCAL SCHOOL BOARDS DEVELOP THE
CURRICULUM.
NOT ONLY DID WE HAVE THAT IN THE
LAW.
WE REASSERTED IT IN THE LAW.
AND WE ALSO WANT PARENTAL
ADVISERS IN THE LOCAL SCHOOL
DISTRICT SO THAT IN FACT, YOU
KNOW, FRANKLY, EDUCATION HAS TO
BE RUN AT THE SCHOOL BOARD LEVEL
WITH A LITTLE GUIDANCE FROM THE
STATE.
NOW ON TOP OF THAT, YOU WANT TO
TALK ABOUT THE 21st CENTURY,
WHAT WE NEED TO DO WITH OUR
KIDS?
WE NEED TO START CONNECTING THEM
TO THE REAL WORLD.
WE NEED TO BE TRAINING THEM FOR
THE JOBS OF THE 21st CENTURY,
NOT THE JOBS OF 20 YEARS AGO.
WE NEED VOCATIONAL EDUCATION
STARTING IN THE SEVENTH GRADE
WHERE KIDS CAN GET THAT KIND OF
EDUCATION THAT CAN TAKE THEM TO
COLLEGE BUT ALL THE WAY THROUGH
THEIR K THROUGH 12 THEY OUGHT TO
BE CONNECTED WITH THE REAL --
WITH REAL-WORLD JOBS.
FRANKLY WHAT OUGHT TO HAPPEN IS
WE OUGHT TO GET THEM TO PURSUE
THEIR GOD-GIVEN TALENTS AND
CONNECT THEM WITH THE THINGS
THAT GIVE THEM PASSION.
AND THAT'S EXACTLY WHAT'S WE'RE
DOING IN OHIO.
COMBINED WITH MENTORING PROGRAMS
TO TALK TO KIDS ABOUT WHAT THEIR
FUTURE CAN BE.
SO LET ME BE CLEAR -- LOCAL
CONTROL, OBVIOUSLY, HIGH STATE
STANDARDS.
THAT'S WHAT IT IS IN THE STATE
OF OHIO.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU OBJECT TO
COMMON CORE.
GOVERNOR KASICH SAYS LOCAL
SCHOOL BOARDS DEVELOPING LOCAL
CURRICULUM TO MEET HIGHER
STANDARDS.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH THAT?
>> COMMON CORE IS A DISASTER.
AND IF I AM ELECTED PRESIDENT IN
THE FIRST DAYS AS PRESIDENT, I
WILL DIRECT THE DEPARTMENT OF
EDUCATION THAT COMMON CORE ENDS
THAT DAY.
NOW LET ME TELL YOU WHY YOU CAN
DO THAT.
IT'S EASY TO TALK ABOUT THE
PROBLEM BUT YOU HAVE TO
UNDERSTAND THE SOLUTIONS.
THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION HAS
ABUSED EXECUTIVE POWER ENFORCING
COMMON CORE ON THE STATES.
IT IS USED RACED TO THE TOP
FUNDS TO EFFECTIVELY BLACKMAIL
AND FORCE THE STATES TO ADOPT
COMMON CORE.
THE ONE SILVER LINING OF OBAMA
ABUSING EXECUTIVE POWER IS THAT
EVERYTHING DONE WITH EXECUTIVE
POWER CAN BE UNDONE WITH
EXECUTIVE POWER.
AND I INTEND TO DO THAT.
BEYOND THAT, THOUGH, JAKE, I
INTEND TO WORK TO ABOLISH THE
FEDERAL DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION
AND SEND EDUCATION BACK TO THE
STATES AND BACK TO THE LOCAL
GOVERNMENTS.
AND LET ME SAY FINALLY, THE MOST
IMPORTANT REFORM WE CAN DO IN
EDUCATION AFTER GETTING THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT OUT OF IT IS
EXPAND SCHOOL CHOICE.
EXPAND CHARTER SCHOOLS AND HOME
SCHOOLS AND PRIVATE SCHOOLS AND
VOUCHERS AND SCHOLARSHIPS AND
GIVE EVERY CHILD,
AFRICAN-AMERICAN, HISPANIC,
EVERY CHILD IN NEED AN
OPPORTUNITY TO ACCESS TO A
QUALITY EDUCATION.
>> LET'S MOVE ON TO ANOTHER
TOPIC OF PARTICULAR INTEREST
HERE IN FLORIDA.
FLORIDA HAS THE HIGHEST
PERCENTAGE OF SENIORS IN THE
COUNTRY.
THERE ARE 3.1 MILLION SENIOR
CITIZENS HERE WHO RECEIVE SOCIAL
SECURITY BENEFITS, AND THEY ARE
VERY INTERESTED IN HEARING WHAT
YOU CANDIDATES INTEND TO DO TO
KEEP SOCIAL SECURITY GOING FOR
FUTURE GENERATIONS.
LET ME TURN TO DANA BASH.
>> SENIORITY RUBIO, YOU ARGUE
AMERICANS YOUR AGE MUST HAVE AN
HONEST CONVERSATION ABOUT MAKING
SOCIAL SECURITY SUSTAINABLE.
FOR PEOPLE UNDER 55, YOU WANT TO
RAISE THE RETIREMENT AGE AND
ALSO REDUCE BENEFITS FOR
WEALTHIER AMERICANS.
SO WHAT SHOULD THE NEW
RETIREMENT AGE BE, AND HOW MUCH
WILL THOSE BENEFITS BE CUT?
>> LET ME SAY THAT YOU ARE
RIGHT.
THERE ARE ABOUT 3 MILLION
SENIORS IN FLORIDA, WITH SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICARE.
ONE OF THEM IS MY MOTHER WHO
HAPPENS TO BE HERE TODAY.
I'M AGAINST ANY CHANGES TO
SOCIAL SECURITY THAT ARE BAD FOR
MY MOTHER.
AND WE DON'T HAVE TO MAKE ANY
CHANGES FOR THEM.
BUT ANYONE WHO TELLS YOU THAT
SOCIAL SECURITY SCAN STAY THE
WAY IT IS, IS LYING.
ANY POLITICIAN THAT GOES AROUND
SAYING WE DON'T HAVE TO DO
ANYTHING.
ALL WE HAVE TO DO IS RAISE A FEW
TAXES OR LEAVE IT THE WAY IT IS
THEY AREN'T BEING HONEST.
SOCIAL SECURITY WILL GO BANKRUPT
AND BANKRUPT THE COUNTRY WITH
IT.
IT REQUIRES PEOPLE YOUNGER, LIKE
MYSELF, PEOPLE 30 YEARS AWAY
FROM RETIREMENT, TO ACCEPT THAT
OUR SOCIAL SECURITY IS GOING TO
WORK DIFFERENTLY THAN IT DID FOR
MY PARENTS.
FOR EXAMPLE, INSTEAD OF RETIRING
AT 67, THE WAY I'M SUPPOSED TO
RETIRE, I'D HAVE TO RETIRE AT
68.
IF I WERE STILL IN THE SENATE,
I'D BE ONE OF THE YOUNGEST
PEOPLE THERE.
IF I MADE A LOT OF MONEY, MY
SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFIT WILL NOT
GROW AS FAST AS SOMEONE WHO MADE
LESS MONEY.
MEDS CARE COULD BECOME THE
OPTION OF USING MY MEDS CARE
BENEFIT TO BUY A PRIVATE PLAN I
LIKE.
MEDICARE ADVANTAGE DOES THAT
NOW.
THESE ARE NOT UNREASONABLE
THINGS TO ASK FOR SOMEONE WHO IS
30 YEARS AWAY FROM RETIREMENT IF
IT MEANS LEAVING THE PROGRAM
UNDISTURBED FOR THOSE ON IT NOW
OR ABOUT TO BE ON IT AND MAKING
SURE WE DO NOT BANKRUPT OUR
COUNTRY AND THAT THIS SYSTEM
STILL EXISTS WHEN I RETIRE OR
WHEN MY CHILDREN RETIRE.
>> THE QUESTION WAS SPECIFICS,
THE THOUGH.
MADE YOUR PLAN VERY CLEARLY
ABOUT GENERALLY WHAT YOU WANT TO
DO.
HOW HIGH WOULD THE RETIREMENT
AGE GO AND HOW MUCH WOULD YOU
CUT --
>> SOMEONE MY AGE WOULD RETIRE
AT 68.
WE'D ALLOW THE RETIREMENT AGE TO
INCREASE UNTIL IT HITS 70.
SO MY CHILDREN WOULD RETIRE AT
70.
I'D RETIRE AT 68.
A GRADUATING SCALE OVER A PERIOD
OF TIME.
I'M TALKING ABOUT PEOPLE LIKE
MYSELF AND TED WHO ARE 45 YEARS
OLD, YEARS AWAY FROM RETIREMENT.
PEOPLE ON IT NOW, WE DON'T HAVE
TO CHANGE IT AT ALL.
IF WE DON'T DO ANYTHING, WE'LL
HAVE A DEBT CRISIS.
IT'S NOT A QUESTION OF IF.
IT'S A QUESTION OF WHEN.
IN LESS THAN FIVE YEARS, ONLY
17% OF OUR BUDGET WILL REMAIN
DISCRETIONARY.
83% OF THE BUDGET IN LESS THAN
FIVE YEARS WILL BE SPENT ON
MEDICARE, MEDICAID, THE INTEREST
ON THE DEBT.
ALL OF IT WILL BE EATEN UP BY
THAT.
THAT'S A DEBT CRISIS.
AND IT WILL BE DEBILITATING TO
OUR ECONOMY AND OUR CHILDREN
DESERVE BETTER THAN TO INHERIT A
DEBT CRISIS.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU DON'T WANT TO
RAISE THE RETIREMENT AGE OR CUT
BENEFITS.
UNLESS ADJUSTMENTS ARE MADE,
SOCIAL SECURITY IS PROJECTED TO
RUN OUT OF MONEY WITHIN 20
YEARS.
SO SPECIFICALLY, WHAT WOULD YOU
DO TO STOP THAT FROM HAPPENING?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I WANT YOU TO
UNDERSTAND THE DEMOCRATS, AND
I'VE WATCHED THEM VERY
INTENSELY, EVEN THOUGH IT'S A
VERY, VERY BORING THING TO
WATCH, THAT THE DEMOCRATS ARE
DOING NOTHING WITH SOCIAL
SECURITY.
THEY ARE LEAVING IT THE WAY IT
IS.
THEY WANT TO INCREASE IT.
THEY WANT TO ACTUALLY GIVE MORE.
AND THAT'S WHAT WE'RE UP
AGAINST.
WHETHER WE LIKE IT OR NOT,
THAT'S WHAT WE'RE UP AGAINST.
I'LL DO EVERYTHING WITHIN MY
POWER NOT TO TOUCH SOCIAL
SECURITY, TO LEAVE IT THE WAY IT
IS, TO MAKE THIS COUNTRY RICH
AGONE, BRING BACK OUR JOBS, GET
RID OF DEFICITS, GET RID OF
WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE WHICH IS
RAMPANT IN THIS COUNTRY.
R
RAMPANT.
TOTALLY RAMPANT.
AND IT'S MY ABSOLUTE INTENTION
TO LEAVE SOCIAL SECURITY THE WAY
IT IS.
NOT INCREASE THE AGE AND TO
LEAVE IT AS IS.
YOU HAVE 22 YEARS, YOU HAVE A
LONG TIME TO GO.
IT'S NOT LONG IN TERMS OF WHAT
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT, BUT IT'S
STILL A LONG TIME TO GO.
AND I WANT TO LEAVE SOCIAL
SECURITY AS IS.
I WANT TO MAKE OUR COUNTRY RICH
AGAIN SO WE CAN AFFORD IT.
I WANT TO BRING BACK OUR JOBS.
I WANT TO DO THINGS THAT WILL
MAKE US -- THAT WILL BRING BACK
GDP.
AS AN EXAMPLE, GDP WAS 0
ESSENTIALLY FOR THE LAST TWO
QUARTERSES.
IF THAT EVER HAPPENED IN CHINA
YOU WOULD HAVE HAD A DEPRESSION
LIKE NOBODY HAS EVER SEEN.
THEY GO DOWN TO 7%, 8% AND IT'S
A NATIONAL TRAGEDY.
WE'RE AT ZERO.
WE'VE LOST OUR JOBS.
WE'VE LOST EVERYTHING.
WE'RE LOSING EVERYTHING.
OUR JOBS ARE GONE.
OUR BUSINESSES ARE BEING TAKEN
OUT OF THE COUNTRY.
I WANT TO MAKE AMERICA GREAT
AGAIN AND LEAVE SOCIAL SECURITY
AS IS.
WE'RE GOING TO GET RID OF WASTE,
FRAUD ABUSE AND BRING BACK
BUSINESS.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU WANT TO
GET IN.
I WANT TO FOLLOW UP WITH MR.
TRUMP.
YOU ARE TALKING ABOUT WASTE,
FRAUD AND ABUSE.
AN INDEPENDENT BIPARTISAN
ORGANIZATION, THE COMMITTEE FOR
A RESPONSIBLE FEDERAL BUDGET,
SAYS IMPROPER PAYMENTS LIKE YOU
ARE TALKING ABOUT, THAT WOULD
ONLY SAVE ABOUT $3 BILLION.
BUT IT WOULD TAKE $150 BILLION
TO MAKE SOCIAL SECURITY SOLVENT.
HOW WOULD YOU FIND ANOTHER $147
MILLION?
>> WE'RE THE POLICEMEN OF THE
WORLD.
WE TAKE CARE OF THE ENTIRE
WE'LL HAVE A STRONGER MILITARY,
MUCH STRONGER.
OUR MILITARY IS DEPLETING.
WE TAKE CARE OF GERMANY.
WE TAKE CARE OF SAUDI ARABIA.
WE TAKE CARE OF JAPAN.
WE TAKE CARE OF SOUTH KOREA.
EVERY TIME THIS MANIAC FROM
NORTH KOREA DOES ANYTHING, WE
IMMEDIATELY SEND OUR SHIPS.
WE GET VIRT YUALLY NOTHING.
WE HAVE 28,000 SOLDIERS ON THE
LINE BETWEEN NORTH KOREA AND
SOUTH KOREA.
WE HAVE SO MANY PLACES.
SAUDI ARABIA WAS MAKING A
BILLION DOLLARS A DAY, AND WE
WERE GETTING VIRTUALLY NOTHING
TO PROTECT THEM.
WE ARE GOING TO BE IN A
DIFFERENT WORLD.
WE'RE GOING TO NEGOTIATE REAL
DEALS NOW.
AND WE'RE GOING TO BRING THE
WEALTH BACK TO OUR COUNTRY.
WE OWE $19 TRILLION.
WE'RE GOING TO BRING WEALTH BACK
TO OUR COUNTRY.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, WILL THAT BE
ENOUGH TO SAVE SOCIAL SECURITY?
>> NO.
YOU'VE OUTLINED WHY.
THE NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP.
WHEN I RAN FOR SENATE I CAME OUT
AND SAID WE'D HAVE TO MAKE
CHA
CHANGES TO SOCIAL SECURITY.
PEOPLE KNOW IT'S THE TRUTH HERE
IN FLORIDA.
FRAUD IS NOT ENOUGH.
CERTAINLY LET'S WIPE OUT THE
FRAUD.
AS YOU SAID, IT WON'T ADD UP.
YOU ALREADY GAVE THOSE NUMBERS.
ON FOREIGN AID I HEAR THAT ALL
THE TIME AS WELL.
I'M AGAINST ANY SORT OF WASTING
MONEY ON FOREIGN AID.
IT'S LESS THAN 1% OF OUR FEDERAL
BUDGET.
THE NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP.
WE CAN'T TIP TOE AROUND THIS.
FRAUD AND ABUSE.
LET'S GET RID OF FRAUD AND ABUSE
AND BE MORE CAREFUL ABOUT HOW WE
SPEND FOREIGN AID.
YOU STILL HAVE HUNDREDS OF
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS OF DEFICIT
YOU'LL HAVE TO MAKE UP.
IF WE DO NOT DO IT, WE WILL HAVE
A DEBT CRISIS.
NOT TO MENTION A CRISIS OF
SOCIAL SECURITY AND MEDICARE.
BOTH PARTIES HAVE TAKEN FAR TOO
LONG TO DEAL WITH IT.
IT'S ONE OF THE MAJOR ISSUES
CONFRONTING AMERICA.
IT'S BARELY BEEN ASKED IN ANY OF
THESE DEBATES.
WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH IT OR WE'LL
HAVE TO EXPLAIN TO OUR CHILDREN
WHY THEY INHERITED THIS
DISASTER.
>> SENATOR RUBIO SAYS YOUR
NUMBERS DON'T ADD UP.
WHAT'S YOUR RESPONSE?
SENATOR RUBIO SAYS YOUR NUMBERS
DON'T ADD UP.
WHAT'S YOUR RESPONSE, MR. TRUMP?
>> I'M JUST SAYING VERY SIMPLY
WE HAVE A COUNTRY THAT I'VE
NEVER SEEN ANYTHING LIKE IT.
I'VE BEEN GOING OVER BUDGETS AND
LOOKING AT BUDGETS.
WE DON'T BID THINGS OT.
WE DON'T BID OUT THE DRUG
INDUSTRY, PHARMACEUTICAL
INDUSTRY.
THEY DON'T GO OUT TO BID.
THEY JUST PAY ALMOST AS IF YOU
WALK INTO A DRUG STORE.
THAT'S WHAT THEY ARE PAYING.
THE REASON IS THEY HAVE A
FANTASTIC LOBBY.
THEY TAKE CARE OF ALL THE
SENATORS, THE CONGRESSMEN.
THEY HAVE GREAT POWER AND DON'T
BID OUT.
THE MILITARY IS NEVER PROPERLY
BID.
WE GO OUT TO MILITARY BIDS, IT'S
NOT PROPERLY BID.
AND THE PEOPLE THAT SELL US THE
PRODUCT ARE OFTENTIMES THE
PRESIDENT WE DON'T WANT ONLY
BECAUSE THAT PARTICULAR COMPANY
HAS POLITICAL JUICE, OKAY?
I'M SELF-FUNDING MY CAMPAIGN.
NOBODY IS GOING TO BE TAKING
CARE OF ME.
I DON'T WANT ANYBODY'S MONEY.
I WILL TELL YEOH SOOU SOMETHING.
WE'LL GO OUT TO BID IN EVERY
FACET OF OUR GOVERNMENT.
WE'RE GOING TO SAVE A FORTUNE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU ADVOCATE
ALLOWING YOUNGER WORKERS TO PUT
SOME OF THEIR SOCIAL SECURITY
TAXES INTO PERSONAL ACCOUNTS.
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO CRITICS WHO
SAY THAT MARKET VOLATILITY MEANS
THAT THIS IS A DISASTEROUS
PROPOSAL?
>> NUMBER ONE, WE NEED TO SEE
RESPONSIBILITY.
SOCIAL SECURITY RIGHT NOW IS
CAREENING TOWARDS INSOLVENCY,
AND IT'S IRRESPONSIBLE.
AND ANY POLITICIAN THAT DOESN'T
STEP FORWARD AND ADDRESS IT IS
NOT BEING A REAL LEADER.
WE NEED TO SEE POLITICAL COURAGE
TO TAKE THIS ON AND SAVE AND
STRENGTHEN SOCIAL SECURITY.
AND AS PRESIDENT, WHAT I WILL DO
FOR SENIORS, FOR ANYONE AT OR
NEAR RETIREMENT, THERE WILL BE
NO CHANGES WHATSOEVER.
EVERY BENEFIT WILL BE PROTECTED
TO THE LETTER.
BUT FOR YOUNGER WORKERS, WE NEED
TO GRADUALLY RAISE THE
RETIREMENT AGE.
FOR YOUNGER WORKERS, CHAUCHBLG
CHANGE THE RATE OF GROWTH OF
BENEFITS.
AND WE NEED TO HAVE FOR YOUNGER
WORKERS THAT A PORTION OF YOUR
TAX PAYMENTS ARE IN PERSONAL
ACCOUNTS LIKE A 401(k) THAT YOU
OWN THAT YOU CONTROL THAT YOU
CAN PASS ON TO YOUR KIDS AND
GRANDKIDS.
AND ONE OF THE THINGS THAT IS
CRITICALLY IMPORTANT.
WE'VE GOT LOTS OF CHALLENGES IN
THE WORLD.
BUT THE ANSWER CAN'T JUST BE
WAVE A MAGIC WAND AND SAY
PROBLEM GO AWAY.
YOU HAVE TO UNDERSTAND THE
PROBLEMS.
YOU HAVE TO HAVE REAL SOLUTIONS.
IT'S LIKE GOVERNMENT SPENDING.
IT IS VERY EASY.
HILLARY CLINTON SAYS SHE'LL CUT
WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE.
IF ONLY WE HAD SMARTER PEOPLE IN
WASHINGTON, THAT WOULD FIX THE
PROBLEM.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
THAT IS THE STATEMENT OF A
LIBERAL WHO DOESN'T UNDERSTAND
GOVERNMENT IS THE PROBLEM.
HERE'S MY PHILOSOPHY.
THE LESS GOVERNMENT, THE MORE
FREEDOM.
THE FEWER BUREAUCRATS, THE MORE
PROSPERITY.
AND THERE ARE BUREAUCRATS IN
WASHINGTON RIGHT NOW WHO ARE
KILLING JOBS AND I'LL TELL YOU,
I KNOW WHO THEY ARE.
I WILL FIND THEM AND I WILL FIRE
THEM.
>> DID YOU JUSTICE JUST COMPARE
DONALD TRUMP TO HILLARY CLINTON
ON THIS ISSUE?
>> I WILL LET DONALD SPEAK FOR
HIMSELF.
BUT THERE'S A REASON, IN MY
CAMPAIGN I'VE SET OUT A SPECIFIC
SPENDING CUT PLAN.
$500 BILLION.
I'VE SPECIFIED FIVE MAJOR
AGENCIES I'D ELIMINATE, 25
PROGRAMS.
AND DANA, YOU KNOW WHY POLITICAL
CANDIDATES DON'T DO THAT?
BECAUSE WHEN YOU DO THAT, THE
LOBBYISTS ATTACK YOU.
WHEN YOU SPECIFY THE PROGRAMS
YOU WOULD ELIMINATE, THEN YOU
GET ATTACKED.
LET'S TALK FOR EXAMPLE BACK IN
IOWA THE FIRST PRIMARY.
WHEN I WENT TO IOWA AND
CAMPAIGNED AGAINST ETHANOL
MANDATES, EVERYONE SAID THAT WAS
POLITICAL SUICIDE.
YOU CAN'T TAKE ON ETHANOL IN
IOWA.
AND MY OPPONENTS ON THIS STAGE
NOT ONLY DIDN'T DO THE SAME.
THEY ATTACKED ME AND EVEN
PROMISED TO EXPAND CORPORATE
WELFARE.
IF WE'RE GOING TO STOP
BANKRUPTING OUR KIDS AND
GRANDKIDS, YOU HAVE TO BE
WILLING TO TAKE ON THE LOBBYIST
WHICH MEANS NOT JUST SOME
FANCIFUL WASTE, FRAUD AND ABUSE
BUT SPECIFYING THESE ARE THE
PROGRAMS I'LL ELIMINATE.
>> MR. TRUMP, WOULD YOU LIKE TO
RESPOND?
>> IF YOU LOOK BACK TO IOWA, TED
DID CHANGE HIS VIEW AND HIS
STANCE ON ETHANOL QUITE A BIT AT
THE END.
NOT FULL ON, BUT HE DID CHANGE
HIS VIEW IN THE OPENS OF MAYBE
DOING WELL.
AND YOU KNOW, I THINK EVERYBODY
KNOWS THAT.
IT WAS A FRONT PAGE STORY ALL
OVER THE PLACE, AND HE DID MAKE
A CHANGE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> LISTEN, IF YOU ARE FED UP
WITH WASHINGTON, THE QUESTION
YOU OUGHT TO BE ASKING IS WHO IS
WILLING TO TAKE ON WASHINGTON?
IT'S EASY TO HAVE LANGUAGE, I'M
FED UP WITH THE CORRUPTION IN
WASHINGTON.
BUT IF YOU HAVE A CANDIDATE WHO
HAS BEEN FUNDING LIBERAL
DEMOCRATS AND FUNDING THE
WASHINGTON ESTABLISHMENT, IT'S
VERY HARD TO IMAGINE HOW
SUDDENLY THIS CANDIDATE IS GOING
TO TAKE ON WASHINGTON.
WHEN I STOOD UP AND LED THE
FIGHT AGAINST OBAMACARE,
WASHINGTON WAS FURIOUS AND
ATTACKED ME, BUT I DID IT
BECAUSE I WAS HONORING MY
COMMITMENT TO THE HARD-WORKING
MEN AND WOMEN OF THIS COUNTRY
WHO ARE LOSING THEIR JOBS
BECAUSE OF OBAMACARE.
WHEN I LED THE FIGHT AGAINST
AMNESTY, IT'S BECAUSE I WAS
STANDING WITH THE PEOPLE AGAINST
WASHINGTON.
AND IF YOU WANT TO TELL PEOPLE
YOU'RE GOING TO STAND AGAINST
WASHINGTON, THE QUESTION WE
SHOULD ASK IS, WHEN HAVE YOU
EVER STOOD UP TO THE LOBBYISTS
IN WASHINGTON?
>> MR. TRUMP, I'LL LET YOU
RESPOND BECAUSE HE MENTIONED
YOU.
>> FIRST OF ALL, TED WAS IN
FAVOR OF AMNESTY.
NO QUESTION ABOUT THAT.
AND SHERIFF JOE ARPAIO RECENTLY
ENDORSED ME AND THERE'S NOBODY
TOUGHER ON THE BORDERS THAN
SHERIFF JOE.
AND SENATOR JEFF SESSIONS, AN
INCREDIBLE MAN, ALSO ENDORSED
ME.
THERE'S NOBODY THAT KNOWS MORE
ABOUT THE BORDERS THAN SENATOR
JEFF SESSIONS.
I WOULD SAY THIS.
WE'RE ALL IN THIS TOGETHER.
WE'RE GOING TO COME UP WITH
SOLUTIONS.
WE'RE GOING TO FIND THE ANSWERS
TO THINGS.
AND SO FAR I CANNOT BELIEVE HOW
CIVIL IT'S BEEN UP HERE.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, LET'S GET
BACK TO SOCIAL SECURITY.
YOU TOLD THE VOTER IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE TO, QUOTE, GET OVER
CUTS TO SOCIAL SECURITY BENEFITS
BECAUSE YOU HAVE A REFORM PLAN
AND THAT IS JUST THE REALITY YOU
SAY THAT IS OUT THERE.
WHY IS CUTTING SOCIAL SECURITY
PAYMENTS THE SOLUTION?
>> FIRST OF ALL, WE HEAR ABOUT
TAKING ON WASHINGTON.
I TOOK ON WASHINGTON AND I WON.
I ACTUALLY GOT THE BUDGET
BALANCED WHEN I WAS A MEMBER OF
THE CONGRESS, THE CHAIRMAN OF
THE BUDGET COMMITTEE.
WE PAID DOWN A HALF A TRILLION
DOLLARS OF THE NATIONAL DEBT.
WE ALSO BALANCED THE BUDGET FOUR
YEARS IN A ROW, AND WE WERE JUST
GROWING JOBS LIKE CRAZY, AND THE
WAGE ISSUE WAS NOT EVEN AN ISSUE
THEN.
I ALSO HAD A PLAN IN 1999 TO
SAVE SOCIAL SECURITY AND TAKE
THE $5 TRILLION PROJECTED
SURPLUS AND NOT ONLY HAVE SOCIAL
SECURITY FOR OUR YOUNG PEOPLE
BUT ALSO TO GIVE THEM PRIVATE
ACCOUNTS.
THERE ARE MORE 18-YEAR-OLDS WHO
BELIEVE THEY HAVE A BETTER
CHANCE OF SEEING A UFO THAN A
SOCIAL SECURITY CHECK AND A LOT
OF SENIORS WHO ARE VERY NERVOUS.
I HAVE A PLAN THAT DOESN'T
REQUIRE RAISING THE RETIREMENT
AGE.
IF YOU'VE HAD WEALTH THROUGHOUT
YOUR LIFETIME, WHEN THE TIME
COMES TO BE ON SOCIAL SECURITY,
YOU'LL STILL GET IT.
IT WILL SIMPLY BE LESS.
AND FOR THOSE THAT DEPOEND ON
THAT SOCIAL SECURITY, THEY'LL
GET THEIR FULL BENEFIT.
WE DON'T HAVE TO MONKEY AROUND
WITH THE RETIREMENT AGE.
I'VE DONE ALL THIS BEFORE.
THIS IS NOT A THEORY.
DO YOU HAVE TO TAKE ON
ENTITLEMENT PROGRAMS TO BALANCE
A BUDGET?
YES.
DOESN'T MEAN YOU HAVE TO CUT
THEM.
IT MEANS YOU NEED TO INNOVATE
THEM, THE WAY WE DO IN THE 21st
CENTURY.
NOT ONLY DID WE HAVE A BALANCED
BUDGET IN WASHINGTON, BUT WHEN I
WENT TO OHIO, WE WERE $8 BILLION
IN THE HOLE AND NOW $2 BILLION
IN THE BLACK.
WE'RE UP 400,000 JOBS AND I WANT
TO GO BACK WITH THE SAME FORMULA
TO BEAT THE WASHINGTON INSIDERS
AGAIN.
AND I WILL GET IT DONE, AND THIS
COUNTRY WILL BE MUCH STRONGER
ECONOMICALLY AS A RESULT.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> LET'S TAKE A BROADER LOOK AT
THE REPUBLICAN PARAR NOW.
MR. TRUMP, ONE OF THE CONCERNS
YOUR OPPONENTS HAVE EXPRESSED
THROUGHOUT THE COURSE OF THIS
CAMPAIGN IS THE NOTION THAT IN
THEIR ESTIMATION YOU HOLD VIEWS
THAT ARE AT DIRECT ODDS WITH
REPUBLICAN PARTY TRADITION.
HOW ARE YOU LOOKING TO
FUNDAMENTALLY CHANGE THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY AS ITS
POTENTIAL LEADER?
WHAT SHOULD THE REPUBLICAN PARTY
STAND FOR IN 2016?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I DON'T
REALLY THINK THAT.
I THINK I HOLD VIEWS THAT ARE
SIMILAR TO MANY OF THE PEOPLE.
WE ARE MORE INCLUSIVE.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE POLLS AND THE
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE THAT HAVE
BEEN POURING INTO THE POLLS,
IT'S THE BIGGEST STORY.
YOU LOOK AT ALL THESE PEOPLE
COMING IN.
SOMETHING IS HAPPENING.
I AM DIFFERENT IN ONE PRIMARY
RESPECT.
AND THAT'S TRADE.
I FEEL THAT WE HAVE HAD HORRIBLE
NEGOTIATORS.
HORRIBLE TRADE DEALS.
THE JOBS IN THIS COUNTRY ARE
DISAPPEARING.
AND ESPECIALLY THE GOOD JOBS.
YOU LOOK AT THE RECENT JOBS
REPORTS, WHICH ARE REALLY DONE
SO THAT PRESIDENTS AND
POLITICIANS LOOK GOOD.
ALL OF THESE PEOPLE LOOKING FOR
JOBS, WHEN THEY GIVE UP, THEY GO
HOME, THEY GIVE UP AND THEY ARE
CONSIDERED STATISTICALLY
EMPLOYED.
SO THAT'S THAT.
BUT I WILL SAY, TRADE DEALS ARE
ABSOLUTELY KILLING OUR COUNTRY.
THE DEVALUATIONS OF THEIR
CURRENCIES BY CHINA AND JAPAN
AND MANY, MANY OTHER COUNTRIES,
AND WE DON'T DO IT BECAUSE WE
DON'T PLAY THE GAME.
AND THE ONLY WAY WE'LL BE ABLE
TO DO IT IS WE'LL HAVE TO DO
TAXES UNLESS THEY BEHAVE.
IF YOU DON'T TAX CERTAIN
PRODUCTS COMING INTO THIS
COUNTRY FROM CERTAIN COUNTRIES
THAT ARE TAKING ADVANTAGE OF THE
UNITED STATES AND LAUGHING AT
OUR STUPIDITY, WE'RE GOING TO
CONTINUE TO LOSE BUSINESSES AND
WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE TO LOSE
JOBS.
AND IF YOU LOOK AT THE AVERAGE
WORKER OVER THE LAST 12 YEARS,
THEIR SALARY AND PAY HAVE GONE
DOWN, NOT UP.
IT'S GONE DOWN.
AND I THINK THAT'S WHY THERE'S
BEEN SUCH AN OUTPOURING OF LOVE
TO WHAT I'M SAYING.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, DONALD TRUMP
HAS SO FAR WON 35% OF THE VOTE.
THOSE PEOPLE ARE SIGNING UP TO
HIS VISION OF THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY.
WHAT DO YOU THINK IS WRONG WITH
THAT VISION?
>> WELL, DONALD IS RIGHT, FOR
EXAMPLE.
HE WAS JUST TALKING ABOUT
INTERNATIONAL TRADE.
HE'S RIGHT ABOUT THE PROBLEMS.
BUT HIS SOLUTIONS DON'T WORK.
FOR EXAMPLE, HIS SOLUTION ON
INTERNATIONAL TRADE, HE PROPOSED
EARLIER A 45% TARIFF ON FOREIGN
GOODS.
HE BACKED AWAY FROM THAT
IMMEDIATELY AND MAY COME BACK
WITH A DIFFERENT NUMBER TONIGHT.
I DON'T KNOW WHERE HE'LL BE
TONIGHT.
BUT I'LL TELL YOU WHAT HAPPENS.
WE'VE SEEN PRIOR PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES WHO PROPOSE TARIFFS.
AND THE EFFECT OF A 45% TARIFF
WOULD BE WHEN YOU GO TO THE
STORE, TO WALMART, WHEN YOU ARE
SHOPPING FOR YOUR KIDS, THE
PRICES YOU PAY GO UP 45%.
BUT NOT ONLY THAT.
WHEN YOU PUT THOSE IN PLACE
BECAUSE A TARIFF IS A TAX ON
YOU, THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, BUT
THE RESPONSE IS THAT THE
COUNTRIES WE TRADE WITH PUT IN
THEIR OWN TARIFFS.
A MUCH BETTER SOLUTION THAT
WORKS IS THE TAX PLAN I'VE LAID
OUT WHICH WOULD ENABLE OUR
EXPORTS TO BE TAX-FREE WOULD TAX
OUR IMPORTS, WOULD NOT RAISE
PRICES FOR AMERICANS AND WOULD
NOT RESULT IN RECIPROCAL
TARIFFS.
FIX THE PROBLEM AND THAT'S
WHAT'S MISSING FROM WHAT DONALD
SAYS.
>> MR. TRUMP, WE'LL LET YOU
RESPOND.
>> THE 45% TAX IS A THREAT.
IT WAS NOT A TAX, IT WAS A
THREAT.
IT WILL BE A TAX IF THEY DON'T
BEHAVE.
TAKE CHINA AS AN EXAMPLE.
I HAVE MANY FRIENDS, GREAT
MANUFACTURERS THAT WANT TO GO
INTO CHINA.
THEY CAN'T.
CHINA WON'T LET THEM.
WE TALK ABOUT FREE TRADE.
IT'S NOT TREEFREE TRADE.
IT'S STUPID TRADE.
CHINA DUMPS EVERYTHING THEY HAVE
OVER HERE.
WE CAN'T GET INTO CHINA.
I HAVE THE BEST PEOPLE,
MANUFACTURERS, THEY CAN'T GET
IN.
WHEN THEY GET IN, THEY HAVE TO
PAY A TREMENDOUS TAX.
THE 45% IS A THREAT THAT IF THEY
DON'T BEHAVE IF THEY DON'T
FOLLOW THE RULES AND REGULATIONS
SO THAT WE CAN HAVE IT EQUAL ON
BOTH SIDES, WE WILL TAX YOU.
DOESN'T HAVE TO BE 45%.
COULD BE LESS.
BUT IT HAS TO BE SOMETHING
BECAUSE OUR COUNTRY AND TRADE
AND DEALS AND MOST IMPORTANTLY
OUR JOBS ARE GOING TO HELL.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> JAKE, LET ME BE CLEAR WHAT
DONALD TRUMP SAID.
HE SAID THAT 45% TAX IS A
THREAT.
AND MIND YOU, YOU ARE PAYING THE
TAX.
IT'S NOT CHINA THAT PAYS THE
IT'S YOU THE WORKING MEN AND
WOMEN.
SO ASK YOURSELF AT HOME, HOW IS
THIS HELPING YOU?
IF YOUR WAGES HAVE BEEN STAGNANT
FOR 20 YEARS, IF YOU CAN'T PAY
THE BILLS, HOW DOES IT HELP YOU
TO HAVE A PRESIDENT COME AND
SAY, I'M GOING TO PUT A 45% TAX
ON DIAPERS WHEN YOU BUY DIAPERS,
ON AUTOMOBILES, ON CLOTHING WHEN
YOU BUY CLOTHING.
THAT HURTS YOU.
IT'S WHY WE'VE GOT TO GET BEYOND
RHETORIC OF CHINA BAD AND
ACTUALLY GET TO HOW DO YOU SOLVE
THE PROBLEM BECAUSE THIS
SOLUTION WOULD HURT JOBS AND
HURT HARD-WORKING TAXPAYERS IN
AMERICA.
>> OKAY --
>> JAKE, I HAVE TO SAY,
HONESTLY, IT'S JUST THE
OPPOSITE.
WHAT WILL HAPPEN IF THEY DON'T
BEHAVE, WE WILL PUT ON A TAX OF
SOME AMOUNT, AND IT COULD BE A
LARGE AMOUNT, AND WE WILL START
BUILDING THOSE FACTORIES OR
THOSE PLANTS.
INSTEAD OF IN CHINA, WE'LL BUILD
THEM HERE AND PEOPLE WILL BUY
PRODUCT FROM HERE RATHER THAN
BUYING IT THROUGH CHINA WHERE
WE'RE BEING RIPPED OFF.
AND WE HAVE A $505 BILLION TRADE
DEFICIT RIGHT NOW.
SO WE'LL BUILD OUR FACTORIES
HERE, AND WE'LL MAKE OUR OWN
PRODUCTS.
AND THAT'S THE WAY IT SHOULD BE
DONE.
AND THE WAY WE'VE BEEN DOING IT
FOR THE LAST LONG PERIOD OF TIME
IS OUR COUNTRY -- OUR COUNTRY IS
IN SERIOUS, SERIOUS TROUBLE.
IT'S A BUBBLE.
AND IT'S GOING TO EXPLODE.
BELIEVE ME.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TAKE A VERY
QUICK BREAK.
WHEN WE COME BACK, WE'LL HAVE
MUCH MORE OF THIS REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE FROM THE
UNIVERSITY OF MIAMI RIGHT AFTER
THIS.
STAY WITH US.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
IN MIAMI, FLORIDA.
MR. TRUMP, LET ME START WITH
YOU.
LAST NIGHT YOU TOLD CNN, QUOTE,
ISLAM HATES US.
DID YOU MEAN ALL 1.6 BILLION
MUSLIMS?
>> I MEAN A LOT OF THEM.
I MEAN A LOT OF THEM.
>> DO YOU WANT TO CLARIFY THE
COMMENT AT ALL?
>> I'VE BEEN WATCHING THE DEBATE
TODAY.
THEY'RE TALKING ABOUT RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM OR RADICAL
ISLAM.
I WILL TELL YOU THERE'S
SOMETHING GOING ON THAT MAYBE
YOU DON'T KNOW ABOUT, MAYBE A
LOT OF OTHER PEOPLE DON'T KNOW
ABOUT, BUT THERE'S TREMENDOUS
HATRED.
AND I WILL STICK WITH EXACTLY
WHAT I SAID TO ANDERSON COOPER.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOUR
SUPPORTER, REPUBLICAN SENATOR
JEFF SESSIONS, SAID IN RESPONSE
TO MR. TRUMP'S COMMENT LAST
NIGHT, I'M SORRY -- SENATOR JEFF
FLAKE, YOUR SUPPORTER, SAID IN
RESPONSE TO THAT COMMENT,
REPUBLICANS ARE BETTER THAN
THIS.
DO YOU AGREE?
>> LET ME SAY, I KNOW THAT'S A
LOT OF PEOPLE FIND APPEAL IN THE
THINGS DONALD SAYS.
THE PROBLEM IS PRESIDENTS CAN'T
JUST SAY ANYTHING THEY WANT.
IT HAS CONSEQUENCES HERE AND
AROUND THE WORLD.
AND SO LET ME GIVE YOU ONE.
TWO DAYS AGO, I MET THIS
EXTRAORDINARY COUPLE WHO ARE ON
FURLOUGH BECAUSE THEY ARE
MISSIONARIES IN BANGLADESH.
IT'S A VERY TOUGH PLACE TO BE A
MISSIONARY.
IT'S MUSLIM.
THEIR SAFETY AND SECURITY RELIES
UPON FRIENDLY MUSLIMS THAT LIVE
ALONGSIDE THEM THAT MAY NOT
CONVERT BUT PROTECT THEM AND
LOOK OUT FOR THEM.
AND THEIR MISSION FIELD REALLY
ARE MUSLIMS LOOKING TO CONVERT
TO CHRISTIANITY.
THEY TELL ME TODAY THEY HAVE A
HOSTILE ENVIRONMENT BECAUSE THE
NEWS IS COMING OUT THAT IN
AMERICA LEADING POLITICAL
FIGURES ARE SAYING THAT AMERICA
DOESN'T LIKE MUSLIMS.
THIS IS A REAL IMPACT.
THERE'S NO DOUBT THAT RADICAL
ISLAM IS A DANGER IN THE WORLD.
I CAN ALSO TELL YOU IF YOU GO TO
ANY NATIONAL CEMETERY,
ESPECIALLY ARLINGTON, YOU'LL SEE
CRESCENT MOONS THERE.
IF YOU GO ANYWHERE IN THE WORLD
YOU'LL SEE AMERICAN MEN AND
WOMEN SERVING US IN UNIFORM THAT
ARE MUSLIMS.
AND THEY LOVE AMERICA.
AND AS FAR AS I KNOW, NO ONE ON
THIS STAGE HAS SERVED IN UNIFORM
IN THE UNITED STATES MILITARY.
ANYONE OUT THERE THAT HAS THE
UNIFORM OF THE UNITED STATES ON
AND IS WILLING TO DIE FOR THIS
COUNTRY IS SOMEONE THAT LOVES
AMERICA.
NO MATTER WHAT THEIR RELIGIOUS
BACKGROUND MAY BE.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> MARCO TALKS ABOUT
CONSEQUENCES.
WELL, WE'VE HAD A LOT OF
CONSEQUENCES, INCLUDING
AIRPLANES FLYING INTO THE WORLD
TRADE CENTER, THE PENTAGON AND
COULD HAVE BEEN THE WHITE HOUSE.
THERE HAVE BEEN A LOT OF
PROBLEMS.
NOW YOU CAN SAY WHAT YOU WANT,
AND YOU CAN BE POLITICALLY
CORRECT IF YOU WANT.
I DON'T WANT TO BE SO
POLITICALLY CORRECT.
I LIKE TO SOLVE PROBLEMS.
WE HAVE A SERIOUS, SERIOUS
PROBLEM OF HATE.
THERE IS TREMENDOUS HATE.
WE'RE LARGE PORTIONS OF A GROUP
OF PEOPLE, ISLAM, LARGE PORTIONS
WANT TO USE VERY, VERY HARSH
MEANS.
LET ME GO A STEP FURTHER.
WOMEN ARE TREATED HORRIBLY.
YOU KNOW THAT.
YOU DO KNOW THAT.
WOMEN ARE TREATED HORRIBLY, AND
OTHER THINGS ARE HAPPENING THAT
ARE VERY, VERY BAD.
NOW I WILL SAY THIS, THERE IS
TREMENDOUS HATRED.
THE QUESTION WAS ASKED, WHAT DO
YOU THINK?
I SAID THERE IS HATRED.
IT WOULD BE VERY EASY TO SAY
SOMETHING DIFFERENTLY.
AND EVERYBODY WOULD SAY, OH,
ISN'T THAT WONDERFUL.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
>> WE BETTER SOLVE THE PROBLEM
BEFORE IT'S TOO LATE.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> I'M NOT INTERESTED IN BEING
POLITICALLY CORRECT.
I'M NOT INTERESTED IN BEING
I'M INTERESTED IN BEING CORRECT.
AND IN ORDER TO BE CORRECT ON
THIS ISSUE, HERE'S THE BOTTOM
LINE.
WE DO WORK.
THERE IS ISLAM HAS A MAJOR
PROBLEM ON ITS HANDS.
IT HAS A SIGNIFICANT PERCENTAGE
IN THE SUNNI FAITH BUT ALSO IN
THE SHIA WHO HAVE BEEN
RADICALIZED AND ARE WILLING TO
FLY PLANES INTO A BUILDING AND
KILL INNOCENT PEOPLE.
THERE IS NO DOUBT ABOUT THAT.
IT IS ALSO TRUE IF YOU LOOK
AROUND THE WORLD AT THE
CHALLENGES WE FACE, WE ARE GOING
TO HAVE TO WORK TOGETHER WITH
OTHER -- WITH MUSLIMS WHO DO
NOT -- WHO ARE NOT RADICALS.
WE'LL HAVE TO WORK WITH THE
JORDANIAN KINGDOM, THE SAUDIS,
THE GULF KINGDOMS.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO WORK WITH
THE
THE EGYPTIANS TO DEFEAT ISIS.
I THINK YOU CAN BE CORRECT
WITHOUT BEING POLITICALLY
CORRECT.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO WORK WITH
THE ISLAM FAITH.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, DO YOU THINK
ISLAM HATES US?
>> NO, I DON'T.
I THINK THERE IS A SECT OF THIS
RADICAL ISLAM THAT IS REALLY,
REALLY SERIOUS AND POSES THE
GREATEST THREAT TO US TODAY.
THERE ISN'T ANY QUESTION.
THAT'S WHY THE WHOLE WORLD HAS
TO WORK TOGETHER TO MAKE SURE WE
DON'T HAVE PROLIFERATION OF
THESE WEAPONS OF MASS
DESTRUCTION.
I WAS THERE AND SAW WHEN THE
EGYPTIAN AMBASSADOR WAS IN THE
ROSE GARDEN BRINGING THE MUSLIM
WORLD TO WORK WITH US TO DEFEAT
SADDAM HUSSEIN.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO HAVE IN
SOME WAY OR ANOTHER A
REPROACHMENT WITH TURKEY AND I
THINK THEY WENT IN THE WRONG
DIRECTION WHEN THEY REJECTED
TURKEY FROM JOINING INTO THE
ECONOMIC SPHERE OF EUROPE.
THE SIMPLE FACT OF THE MATTER IS
A LOT OF THESE MUSLIMS COUNTRIES
CAN'T BELIEVE THE STUFF THEY SEE
OUT OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE DISTORTED
THEIR FAITH.
THE PEOPLE WHO REPRESENT RADICAL
ISLAM, THEY WANT TO DESTROY
EVERYTHING THAT WE'RE ABOUT AND
OTHER MUSLIMS WHO DON'T SHARE
THEIR VIEW, BUT AT THE END OF
THE DAY, WE GOT TO BRING THE
WORLD TOGETHER, THE CIVILIZED
WORLD, AND WE ALL BRING WITH ONE
VOICE THAT THE PEOPLE WHO SIT ON
THE FENCE UNDERSTAND WHAT
CIVILIZATION IS AND WE REPRESENT
IT AND EQUALITY AND HOPE FOR
EVERYBODY.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR KASICH.
MR. TRUMP, YOU SAID THE U.S. HAS
TO, QUOTE, TAKE OUT THE FAMILIES
OF TERRORISTS.
WHEN IT WAS REPORTED IT WAS
AGAINST THE GENEVA CONVENTION,
YOU SAID "SO THEY CAN KILL US
BUT WE CAN'T KILL THEM?"
HOW WILL YOU ORDER THE MILITARY
TO DEAL WITH FAMILIES OF
SUSPECTED TERRORISTS WHILE
ABIDING BY THE LAW.
>> ALL ACROSS THE MIDDLE EAST
YOU HAVE PEOPLE CHANTING DEATH
TO THE USA.
THAT DOES NOT SOUND LIKE A
FRIENDLY ACT TO ME.
WE HAVE A LAW, THIS ALL STARTED
WITH YOUR QUESTION ON
WATERBOARDING.
WE HAVE A LAW THAT DOESN'T ALLOW
RIGHT NOW WATERBOARDING.
THEY HAVE NO LAWS, NO RULES, NO
REGULATIONS.
THEY CHOP OFF HEADS, THEY DROWN
40, 50, 60 PEOPLE AT A TIME IN
BIG STEEL CAGES, PULL THEM UP AN
HOUR LATER, EVERYONE DEAD, AND
WE'RE WORKING ON A DIFFERENT SET
OF PARAMETERS.
NOW, WE HAVE TO OBEY THE LAWS,
OKAY, BUT WE HAVE TO EXPAND
THOSE LAWS BECAUSE WE HAVE TO BE
ABLE TO FIGHT ON AT LEAST
SOMEWHAT OF AN EQUAL FOOTING OR
WE WILL NEVER, EVER KNOCK OUT
ISIS AND ALL OF THE OTHERS THAT
ARE SO BAD.
WE BETTER EXPAND OUR LAWS OR
WE'RE BEING A BUNCH OF SUCKERS
AND THEY ARE LAUGHING AT US.
THEY ARE LAUGHING AT US.
BELIEVE ME.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, WOULD YOU AS
PRESIDENT PURSUE A POLICIES OF
TARGETING THE FAMILIES OF
SUSPECTED TERRORISTS?
>> NO, OF COURSE NOT AND WE
DON'T HAVE TO IN ORDER TO DEFEAT
TERRORISTS.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, THE PRESIDENT
INTELLIGENCE AGENCIES OF THE
WORLD THAT ARE HAM STRUNG RIGHT
NOW ARE GOING TO BE EXPANDED,
AND THE BEST MILITARY IN THE
WORLD WHICH NEEDS TO BE REBUILT,
BARACK OBAMA WILL LEAVE US WITH
THE SMALLEST ARMY, SMALLEST NAVY
AND IF WE CAPTURE ANY OF THESE
TERRORISTS ALIVE, THEY'RE NOT
GOING TO HAVE THE RIGHT TO
REMAIN SILENT AND THEY'RE NOT
GOING TO GO TO A COURTROOM IN
MANHATTAN, THEY'RE GOING TO GO
TO GUANTANAMO BAY, CUBA AND FIND
OUT EVERYTHING WE KNOW AND DO SO
LEGALLY.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU TALKED
ABOUT CHANGING THE RULES OF
ENGAGEMENT OF BATTLE AGAINST
ISIS.
WOULD THAT INCLUDE TARGETING THE
FAMILIES OF SUSPECTED
TERRORISTS?
>> NO, OF COURSE NOT, WE'VE
NEVER TARGETED INNOCENT
CIVILIANS AND WE'RE NOT GOING TO
START NOW.
I UNDERSTAND PEOPLE ARE SCARED.
PRESIDENT OBAMA LECTURES PEOPLE
ON ISLAMOPHOBIA.
THAT IS MADDENING.
THE ANSWER IS NOT TO YELL CHINA
BAD, MUSLIM BAD.
YOU HAVE TO UNDERSTAND THE
NATURE OF THE THREATS WE'RE F
FACING AND HOW YOU DEAL WITH
THEM.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT COMMANDER IN
CHIEF FOCUSED ON FIGHTING THEM.
FRANKLY ONE CONCERN I HAVE WITH
DONALD IS ALTHOUGH HIS LANGUAGE
IS QUITE INCENDIARY, WHEN YOU
LOOK AT HIS SUBSTANTIVE POLICIES
ON IRAN, HE HAS SAID HE WOULD
NOT RIP UP THIS IRANIAN NUCLEAR
DEAL.
THE AYATOLLAH KHOMEINI WANTS
NUCLEAR WEAPONS TO MURDER US.
ANOTHER EXAMPLE, DEALING WITH
ISLAMIC RADICAL TERRORISM.
DONALD SAID HE WANTS TO BE
NEUTRAL BETWEEN ISRAEL AND THE
PALESTINIANS.
AS PRESIDENT I WILL NOT BE
NEUTRAL.
A TEXAN, TAYLOR FORCE, HE WAS
MURDERED BY A PALESTINIAN
TERRORIST THIS WEEK IN ISRAEL,
AND I DON'T THINK WE NEED A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF WHO IS
NEUTRAL BETWEEN THE PALESTINIAN
TERRORISTS AND ONE OF OUR
STRONGEST ALLIES IN THE WORLD,
THE NATION OF ISRAEL.
>> I WANT TO GO TO HUGH HEWITT
WHO HAS QUESTIONS ON THIS
SUBJECT.
>> YOU SAID YOU WOULD WANT TO
BE, QUOTE, SORT OF A NEUTRAL
GUY.
HE DID MENTION TAYLOR FORCE, HE
WAS A WEST POINT GRADUATE, A WAR
HERO, A VANDERBILT GRADUATE
STUDIO, KILLED IN A PALESTINIAN
TERROR ATTACK NEAR TEL AVIV,
MANY OTHERS WERE KILLED.
THE ISRAELI GOVERNMENT SAYS THE
PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY IS
INCITING THIS.
DO YOU STILL WANT TO STAY
NEUTRAL WHEN THE PALESTINIAN
AUTHORITY IS INCITING THESE
ATTACKS.
>> FIRST OF ALL, THERE'S NOBODY
ON THIS STAGE THAT'S MORE PRO
ISRAEL THAN I AM.
THERE'S NOBODY.
I AM PRO ISRAEL.
I WAS THE GRAND MARSHALL, NOT SO
LONG AGO, OF THE ISRAELI DAY
PARADE DOWN 5th AVENUE.
I'VE MADE MASSIVE CONTRIBUTIONS
TO ISRAEL.
I HAVE A LOT OF -- I HAVE
TREMENDOUS LOVE FOR ISRAEL.
I HAPPEN TO HAVE A SON-IN-LAW
AND A DAUGHTER THAT ARE JEWISH,
OKAY, AND TWO GRANDCHILDREN THAT
ARE JEWISH.
BUT I WILL TELL YOU, I THINK IF
WE'RE GOING TO EVER NEGOTIATE A
PEACE SETTLEMENT, WHICH EVERY
ISRAELI WANTS, AND I'VE SPOKEN
TO THE TOUGHEST AND THE
SHARPEST, THEY ALL WANT PEACE, I
THINK IT WOULD BE MUCH MORE
HELPFUL, I'M A NEGOTIATOR.
IF I GO IN, I'LL SAY I'M PRO
ISRAEL AND I'VE TOLD THAT TO
EVERYBODY AND ANYBODY THAT WOULD
LISTEN.
BUT I WOULD LIKE TO AT LEAST
HAVE THE OTHER SIDE THINK I'M
SOMEWHAT NEUTRAL AS TO THEM SO
THAT WE CAN MAYBE GET A DEAL
DONE.
MAYBE WE CAN GET A DEAL.
I THINK IT'S PROBABLY THE
TOUGHEST NEGOTIATION OF ALL
TIME.
BUT MAYBE WE CAN GET A DEAL
DONE.
AND, BY THE WAY, JUST SO YOU
UNDERSTAND, AS FAR AS IRAN, I
WOULD HAVE NEVER MADE THAT DEAL.
I THINK IT'S MAYBE THE WORLD
DEAL I'VE EVER SEEN NEGOTIATED.
I WILL BE SO TOUGH ON THEM AND
ULTIMATELY THAT DEAL WILL BE
BROKEN UNLESS THEY BEHAVE BETTER
THAN THEY'VE EVER BEHAVED IN
THEIR LIVES, WHICH IS PROBABLY
UNLIKELY.
THAT DEAL WILL BE BROKEN.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> WE NEED A PRESIDENT THAT
UNDERSTANDS THE NATIONAL
SECURITY DEMANDS OF THIS
COUNTRY.
ISRAEL IS A LIBERAL DEMOCRATIC
COUNTRY THAT SHARE OUR VALUES,
THEY'RE OUR STRONGEST ALLY IN
THE REGION.
WE GET BILLIONS AND INTELLIGENCE
RESOURCES AND HILLARY CLINTON
AND BARACK OBAMA WANT TO TREAT
NEUTRAL ISRAEL.
THEY PAY THE FAMILIES OF THE
TERRORISTS WHO MURDER PEOPLE.
THIS IS THE MORAL RELEVANCE THAT
BARACK OBAMA HAS.
WE OUGHT TO BE STANDING WITH
PRESIDENT ASSISI IN EGYPT.
>> YOU'VE SEEN THE SPEECHES OF
THE PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY
PRESIDENT TALKING ABOUT HOW
GLORIOUS THIS IS THAT THEY'RE
DOING THESE SORTS OF THINGS.
LET ME GO BACK FOR A MOMENT.
THE POLICY DONALD HAS OUTLINED,
I DON'T KNOW IF HE REALIZES IS
AN ANTI-ISRAELI POLICY.
MAYBE THAT'S NOT YOUR INTENT BUT
HERE'S WHY IT IS AN ANTI-ISRAELI
POLICY.
THERE IS NO PEACE DEAL POSSIBLE
WITH THE PALESTINIANS AT THIS
MOMENT.
THERE JUST ISN'T.
BECAUSE THERE'S NO ONE TO
NEGOTIATE WITH.
THE PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY IS NOT
INTERESTED IN A SERIOUS DEAL AND
THEY ARE NOW IN UNION WITH
HAMAS, AN ORGANIZATION WHOSE
SPECIFIC PURPOSE IS THE
DESTRUCTION OF THE JEWISH STATE.
EVERY TIME THAT ISRAEL HAS
TURNED OVER TERRITORY OF ANY
KIND, BE IS GAZA, IT IS USED AS
A LAUNCHING PAD TO ATTACK
ISRAEL.
THAT'S WHAT WILL HAPPEN AGAIN.
THESE GROUPS ARE NOT INTERESTED
IN A DEAL WITH ISRAEL.
WHAT THEY ARE INTERESTED IN IS
ULTIMATELY REMOVING THE JEWISH
STATE AND OCCUPYING ITS ENTIRE
TERRITORY.
SO MAYBE 30 YEARS THE CONDITIONS
WILL EXIST, BUT THEY DO NOT
EXIST NOW.
TO HAVE A PRESIDENT FORCING THE
ISRAELIS TO THE TABLE IS HARMFUL
TO THE ISRAELI AND TO ITS
ENEMIES.
>> IF I BECOME PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, ONE OF THE THINGS
THAT WILL BE AN ABSOLUTE
PRIORITY IS NUMBER ONE,
PROTECTION OF ISRAEL BUT ALSO
SEEING IF A DEAL CAN BE MADE,
THE TOUGH ET EST DEAL, AT THE T
NEGOTIATION, BUT I WOULD LIKE TO
GIVE IT A SHOT.
I HAVE FRIEND, ISRAELIS,
NON-ISRAELIS, HAPPEN TO BE
JEWISH AND LOVE ISRAEL, EVERY
SINGLE ONE OF THEM WANTS TO EVER
SEE IF WE COULD EVER HAVE PEACE
IN ISRAEL.
SOME BELIEVE IT POSSIBLE.
IT MAY NOT BE, IN WHICH CASE
WE'LL FIND OUT BUT IT WOULD BE A
PRIORITY IF I BECOME PRESIDENT
TO SEE.
>> DO YOU AGREE THAT THE
PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY IS
INCITING THIS VIOLENCE?
>> NO QUESTION.
THEY WERE SAYING THEY I TEND TO
GO TO THE DOME OF IRAQ.
THANK GOODNESS WE WORKED WITH
ISRAELI TO GIVE THEM THE IRON
DOME WHERE THEY CAN PROTECT
THEMSELVES AGAINST ALL THE
MISSILES THAT WERE FLYING IN.
CAN YOU IMAGINE LIVING IN MIAMI
HERE AND HAVING PEOPLE SHOOTING
MISSILES IN?
SECONDLY, THERE WAS JUST AN
ARTICLE WHERE ISRAELI WERE
LEARNING TO RAIN UNDERGROUND IN
COMBAT BECAUSE HAMAS IS DIGGING
TUNNELS TRYING TO COME IN UNDER
ISRAEL.
THEY'RE COMING AT THIS MANY FROM
ABOVE, TRYING TO COME AT THEM
UNDER THE GROUND.
I DON'T BELIEVE THERE IS ANY
LONG-TERM PERMANENT PEACE
SOLUTION.
THINK PURSUING THAT IS A WRONG
THING TO DO.
I THINK EVERYBODY DAY SUPPORTING
THEM WITH OUR 100% BACKING IS
THE WAY TO PROCEED IN THE MIDDLE
EAST WITH REGARD TO ISRAEL.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, I WANT TO STAY
IN THE REGION.
JUST THIS WEEK THERE WAS A
CENTRAL COMMAND GENERAL LLOYD
AUSTIN ESSENTIALLY SAID IT'S
GOING TO TAKE A LOT MORE TROOPS
ON THE GROUND TO FIX -- TO END
THE ISIS THREAT IN SYRIA AND
IRAQ.
FROM THE BEGINNING OF THIS
CAMPAIGN, YOU HAVE SAID YOU WILL
FOLLOW THE JUDGMENT OF MILITARY
COMMANDERS AND THE PENTAGON.
HERE'S THE COMMANDER SAYING A
LOT MORE TROOPS ARE NEEDED ON
THE GROUND.
WILL YOU FOLLOW THAT ADVICE AND
INJECT AMERICANS AGAIN INTO WHAT
IS IN ESSENCE IS METASTASIZING
SHI'A/SUNNI WAR.
>> WE NEED TO DO WHATEVER WE
NEED TO DO TO DEFEAT ISIS.
RIGHT NOW WE'RE NOT USING A
FRACTION OF THE TOOLS WE HAVE,
NOT USING OUR AIR POWER, NOT
ARMING THE KURDS.
WE NEED TO PUT WHATEVER GROUND
POWER.
A QUESTION THAT JAKE ASKED, WE
HAVE OUR TROOPS ENGAGED IN
COMBAT BUT PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS
RULES OF ENGAGEMENT THAT ARE SO
STRICT THAT THEIR ARMS ARE TIED
BEHIND THEIR BACK, THEY'RE NOT
ABLE TO FIGHT, NOT ABLE TO
DEFEND THEMSELVES OR KILL THE
ENEMY.
I HAVE TO TELL YOU, HUGH, I
THINK THAT IS WRONG, IT IS
IMMORAL.
I GIVE MY WORD TO EVERY SOLDIER,
SAILOR, AIRMAN AND MARINE, EVERY
WIFE, HUSBAND, SON AND DAUGHTER,
EVERY MOTHER AND FATHER THAT
WILL END IN JANUARY 2017.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, IF IT TAKES
20,000 OR 30,000, IF THE
PENTAGON SAYS THAT'S WHAT NEEDS
TO BE DONE, WILL YOU FOLLOW
THEIR ADVICE?
>> HUGH, I SAID ALL ALONG AND
LAID OUT MY FOREIGN POLICY, I'M
GOING TO REMIND EVERYBODY THAT
55% OF THE FOREIGN POLICY
EXPERTS IN THIS COUNTRY SAID I
WAS THE BEST TO BE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF.
WE ABSOLUTELY HAVE TO WIN THIS
WITH A COALITION.
ARABS HAVE TO BE WITH US, THE
EUROPEANS HAVE TO UNDERSTAND
THAT THIS THREAT IS CLOSER TO
THEM -- IS AS CLOSE AS IT IS TO
US.
IN ADDITION TO THAT, YOU HAVE TO
BE IN THE AIR AND YOU HAVE TO BE
ON THE GROUND.
AND YOU BRING ALL THE FORCE YOU
NEED.
IT GOT TO BE SHOCK AND AWE IN
THE MILITARY SPEAK.
THEN ONCE IT GETS DONE, AND WE
WILL WIPE THEM OUT, ONCE IT GETS
DONE, IT SETTLES DOWN, WE COME
HOME AND LET THE REGIONAL POWERS
REDRAW THE MAP IF THAT'S WHAT IT
TAKES.
>> MR. TRUMP, MORE TROOPS?
>> WE REALLY IS NO CHOICE.
WE HAVE TO KNOCK OUT ISIS.
WE HAVE TO KNOCK THE HELL OUT OF
THEM, GET RID OF IT AND THEN
COME BACK AND REBUILD OUR
COUNTRY, WHICH IS FALLING APART.
I WOULD LISTEN TO THE GENERALS
BUT I'M HEARING 20,000 TO
30,000.
WE HAVE TO KNOCK THEM OUT FAST.
WE'RE NOT ALLOWED TO FIGHT.
WE CAN'T FIGHT.
WE'RE NOT KNOCKING OUT THE OIL
BECAUSE THEY DON'T WANT TO
CREATE ENVIRONMENTAL POLLUTION
UP IN THE AIR.
THESE ARE THINGS THAT NOBODY
EVEN BELIEVES.
THEY THINK WE'RE KIDDING.
THEY DIDN'T WANT TO KNOCK OUT
THE OIL BECAUSE OF WHAT IT GOING
TO DO TO THE CARBON FOOTPRINT.
WE DON'T FIGHT LIKE WE USED TO
FIGHT.
WE USED TO FIGHT TO WIN.
NOW WE FIGHT FOR NO REASON
WHATSOEVER.
WE DON'T EVEN KNOW WHAT WE'RE
DOING.
SO THE ANSWER IS WE HAVE TO
KNOCK THEM OUT, WE HAVE TO KNOCK
THEM OUT FAST AND GET BACK HOME
AND WE HAVE TO REBUILD OUR
COUNTRY, WHICH IS FALLING APART.
>> THANK YOU, MR. TRUMP.
LET TURN FROM CURRENT CONFLICTS
TO THOSE WHO HAVE SERVED HAD
CONFLICTS.
SENATOR RUBIO, ACCORDING TO A
V.A. STUDY OF 22 VETERANS WHO
COMMIT SUICIDE EVERY DAY, THEY
HAVE NO CONNECTION TO THE V.A.?
WHAT WOULD YOU DO TO ENSURE THE
VETERANS GET WHAT THEY NEED?
>> MY BROTHER IS A VETERAN.
HE'S STRUGGLING WITH THE V.A.
WE HEARD A HORRIBLE STORY, A
HEADLINE IN THE "USA TODAY" AND
IT SAYS CALLS TO THE V.A.
SUICIDE HOTLINE WENT TO VOICE
MAIL.
ABOUT A FEW DAYS AGO WE FOUND
OUT ONE OF THE VETERANS WHO LEFT
A VOICE MAIL COMMITTED SUICIDE
AND THEY HAPPENED TO CALL HIM
BACK THE DAY AFTER HE DIED.
PEOPLE NEED TO BE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE FOR THIS.
ONE OF THE THINGS I'M PROUDEST
OF IS IN MY TIME IN THE U.S.
SENATE WORKING WITH JEFF MILLER
HERE FROM FLORIDA IN A
BIPARTISAN WAY, AND BERNIE
SANDERS WAS A PART OF THIS, WE
PASSED A V.A. ACCOUNTABILITY
BILL.
IT GIVES THE V.A. SECRETARY THE
POWER TO FIRE PEOPLE THAT AREN'T
DOING A GOOD JOB.
SENIOR EXECUTIVES SHOULD BE HELD
ACCOUNTABLE IF THE V.A. OUTREACH
ISN'T WORKING.
NO ONE BEING HELD ACCOUNTABLE.
EVEN THOUGH WE PASSED THAT LAW,
NO ONE HAS BEEN FIRED FOR
OUTREACHED, FOR THAT CALL GOING
TO VOICE MAIL.
WHEN I AM PRESIDENT, IF YOU WORK
AT THE V.A. AND YOU ARE NOT
DOING YOUR JOB, YOU WILL BE
FIRED FROM THE V.A.
>> AS PART OF A AN ATTEMPT TO
CUT COSTS, THE REPUBLICANS VOTED
TO TRY TO REDUCE SPENDING IN THE
POST 9/111 ERA TO REDUCE BENEFIS
TO THE G.I. BILL.
>> THE VETERAN ADMINISTRATION
NEEDS TO BE RESTRUCTURED,
DOWNSIZED AND SPREAD OUT.
IT NEEDS TO BE SO RESPONSIVE TO
THE NEED OF THE VETERANS.
SECONDLY, THE PENTAGON NEED TO
SHARE INFORMATION WITH RETURNING
VETERANS, WITH THE OPERATIONS IN
THE STATES AND WITH THE JOB
PEOPLE IN THE STATES SO THAT
WHEN A VETERAN COMES HOME, THEY
CAN BE LINKED WITH A JOB.
AND WHEN THAT HAPPENS, THAT
MEANS THAT EVERY VETERAN WILL
GET WORK BECAUSE THEY'RE OUR
GOLDEN EMPLOYEES.
NO VETERAN OUT TO BE WITHOUT
HEALTH CARE, NO VETERAN OUGHT TO
BE HOMELESS OR UNEMPLOYED IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
>> LET TURN TO ANOTHER ISSUE.
JUST OVER A WEEK FROM NOW
PRESIDENT OBAMA WILL VISIT CUBA,
THE FIRST TIME IN 88 YEARS A
SITTING U.S. PRESIDENT WILL SET
FOOT IN CUBA.
TWO OF YOU ON IT STAGE HAVE
PARENTS THAT WERE BORN IN CUBA
AND MOVED TO THE UNITED STATES.
LET'S GO TO DANA BASH.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, DONALD TRUMP
BELIEVES WITH PRESIDENT OBAMA IN
HIS DECISION TO REENGAGE
DIPLOMATICALLY IN CUBA.
THE MAJORITY OF AMERICANS SEEM
TO DEAL WITH THAT AS WELL.
WHY ARE THEY WRONG?
>> I WOULD LOVE A RELATIONSHIP
BETWEEN CUBA AND THE UNITED
STATES TO CHANGE.
BUT IT WOULD REQUIRE CUBA TO
CHANGE, AT LEAST ITS GOVERNMENT.
TODAY IT HAS NOT.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS AFTER
THESE CHANGES WERE MADE, THERE
ARE NOW MILLIONS AND HUNDREDS OF
MILLIONS OF DOLLARS THAT WILL
FLOW TO THE CASTRO REGIME.
IT WILL ALLOW THEM TO SET
PERMANENT AND IN STONE, CARRY
OUT A TRANSITION WHERE THE
MILITARY CONTINUES TO RUN THE
COUNTRY, THEY'LL PUT A PUPPET
FIGURE FORWARD TO RUN THE
COUNTRY, THERE AS NOT BEEN A
SINGLE CHANGE ON THE ISLAND IN
HUMAN RIGHT.
THE ONLY THING THAT HAS CHANGED
IS NOW THE CUBAN GOVERNMENT HAS
MORE SOURCES OF MONEY FROM WHICH
TO BUILD OUT THEIR OPPRESSIVE
APPARATUS AND WE ASKED NOTHINGIN
RETURN.
COMPARE THAT TO THE CHANGES
REQUIRED IN BURMA.
THEY WERE REQUIRED TO MAKE SOME
DEMOCRAT BEING OPENINGS.
WHEN THERE WAS A DIPLOMACY BEING
O
-- DIPLOMATIC OPENING, IT
REQUIRED A DEMOCRATIC OPENING.
IT'S HARBORING FUGITIVES OF
AMERICAN JUSTICE, INCLUDING
PEOPLE STEALING OUR MEDICARE
MONEY AND MOVING BACK TO CUBA,
ALL IN EXCHANGE FOR NOTHING.
>> MR. TRUMP, YOU SAID THE
CONCEPT OF OPENING CUBA IS FINE.
YOU SAID THE CONCEPT OF OPENING
CUBA IS FINE.
>> WHAT I WANT IS I WANT A MUCH
BETTER DEAL TO BE MADE.
RIGHT NOW CUBA IS MAKING -- AS
USUAL WITH OUR COUNTRY, WE DON'T
HAVE PEOPLE MAKING GOOD DEALS,
WE DON'T HAVE A CLUE.
I HEARD THE THREAT WAS MADE THAT
THEY WANT REPARATIONS FOR YEARS
OF ABUSE BY THE UNITED STATES
AND NOBODY'S TALKING ABOUT IT
AND THEY'LL END UP SIGNING A
DEAL AND THEN WE'LL GET SUED FOR
$400 BILLION OR $1 TRILLION.
ALL OF THAT STUFF HAS TO BE
AGREED TO NOW.
WE DON'T WANT TO GET SUED AFTER
THE DEAL IS MADE.
I DON'T AGREE WITH PRESIDENT
OBAMA.
I DO AGREE SOMETHING SHOULD TAKE
PLACE.
AFTER 50 YEARS, IT ENOUGH TIME,
FOLKS.
BUT WE HAVE TO MAKE A GOOD DEAL
AND GET RID OF ALL THE
LITIGATION THAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN.
THIS WAS JUST A LITTLE STORY BUT
IT WAS A BIG STORY TO ME BECAUSE
I SAID HERE WE GO, WE MAKE A
DEAL AND THEN GET SUED FOR A
TREMENDOUS AMOUNT OF MONEY FOR
REPARATIONS I WANT TO DO
SOMETHING BUT IT'S GOT TO BE
DONE INTELLIGENTLY.
WE HAVE TO MAKE A GOOD DEAL.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, I KNOW YOU
WANT TO GET IN.
MR. TRUMP, ARE YOU SAYING YOU
WOULD CONTINUE DIPLOMATIC
RELATIONS OR REVERSE THEM?
>> I WOULD WANT TO MAKE A GOOD
DEAL, A STRONG, SOLID, GOOD
DEAL.
RIGHT NOW EVERYTHING IS IN
CUBA'S FAVOR.
EVERY SINGLE ASPECT OF THIS DEAL
IS IN CUBA'S FAVOR.
IT THE SAME AS THE IRAN DEAL.
ALL WE DO IS KEEP GIVING.
WE GIVE AND GIVE AND GIVE.
>> MR. TRUMP, THERE IS AN
EMBASSY.
YOU WOULD HAVE TO DECIDE WHETHER
TO HAVE IT OPEN OR CLOSE IT.
WHICH WOULD IT BE?
>> I WOULD PROBABLY HAVE THE
EMBASSY CLOSED UNTIL A REALLY
GOOD DEAL WAS MADE AND STRUCK BY
THE UNITED STATES.
>> FIRST OF ALL, THE EMBASSY,
THE THE FORMER CAONSULATE, IT'S
THE SAME BUILDING.
WE CAN JUST GO BACK TO CALLING
IT THE CONSULATE.
SECONDLY I DON'T KNOW WHERE
THEY'RE GOING TO SUE US.
CUBA HAS FREE ELECTIONS, CUBA
STOPS PUTTING PEOPLE IN JAIL FOR
SPEAKING OUT, IT KICKS OUT THE
CHINESE LISTENING STATION, IT
STOPS HELPING NORTH KOREA EVADE
U.N. SANCTIONS, AND THEY TAKE
THE FUGITIVES FROM JUSTICE,
INCLUDING THE COP KILLER AND
SEND HER BACK TO THE UNITED
STATES, THAT'S A GOOD DEAL.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, IF YOU BECOME
PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU REVERSE
COURSE AND ONCE AGAIN BREAK
DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH CUBA?
>> YES, I WOULD.
I THINK THIS HIGHLIGHTS A CHOICE
FOR REPUBLICAN PRIMARY VOTERS.
WHEN IT COMES TO FOREIGN POLICY,
DO YOU WANT TO CONTINUE ON THE
SAME BASIC TRAJECTORY AS THE
LAST SEVEN YEARS AS THE OBAMA
FOREIGN POLICY?
WHEN IT COMES TO THESE DEALS,
CUBA AND IRAN, THEY WERE
NEGOTIATED BY HILLARY CLINTON
AND JOHN KERRY.
THERE'S A REALLY DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN US.
DONALD SUPPORTED HILLARY CLINTON
AND JOHN KERRY.
AND WHAT HE SAID RIGHT NOW IS
THAT HE AGREES IN PRINCIPLE WITH
WHAT THEY'RE DOING.
THE ONLY THING HE THINKS IS AT
THAT THEY SHOULD NEGOTIATE A
LITTLE BIT BETTER DEALS, THEY
SHOULD BE MORE EFFECTIVE.
I HAVE A FUNDAMENTAL
DISAGREEMENT AND I THINK MOST
REPUBLICANS AND MOST AMERICANS
DO, THAT WE SHOULDN'T BE
ALLOWING BILLIONS OF DOLLARS TO
GO TO NATIONS THAT HATE US TO GO
TO CUBA, TO GO TO IRAN AND TO
LET THEM USE THOSE BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS TO TRY TO MURDER US.
>> WELL, IF TED WAS LISTENING,
HE WOULD HAVE HEARD ME SAY
SOMETHING VERY SIMILAR.
I SAID WE WOULD NOT DO THE DEAL
UNLESS IT WAS GOING TO BE A VERY
GOOD DEAL FOR US.
I SAID IT LOUD AND I THINK
CLEAR.
I HAVE MANY FRIEND AND OWN MANY
PROPERTIES IN MIAMI, MANY, MANY,
AND I HAVE MANY PEOPLE THAT KNOW
AND THEY FEEL EXACTLY THE WAY I
DO, MAKE A DEAL BUT IT'S GOT TO
BE A GREAT DEAL FOR THE UNITED
STATES, NOT A BAD DEAL FOR THE
UNITED STATES.
AS FAR AS IRAN IS CONCERNED, I
WOULD HAVE NEVER MADE THAT DEAL.
IT'S ONE OF THE WORST DEALS EVER
MADE BY THIS COUNTRY.
FOR TED TO SAY I AGREE WITH THIS
DEAL, IT A STAPLE IN MY SPEECHES
THAT MAY BE THE WORST SINGLE
DEAL I'VE EVER SEEN NEGOTIATED.
SO DON'T TRY TO PUT IT ON ME
LIKE I LOVE IT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, A RESPONSE?
>> IT A MATTER OF PUBLIC RECORD
THAT DONALD SUPPORTED JOHN KERRY
IN 2004 OVER GEORGE W. BUSH, HE
SUPPORTED HILLARY CLINTON, GAVE
HER TWO CHECKS IN 2008, AND ONCE
SHE WAS SECRETARY OF STATE, HE
DESCRIBED HER AS ONE OF THE
GREATEST SECRETARIES OF STATE IN
INDUSTRY.
HIS ANSWER IS ONLY IF SOMEONE
SMARTER WAS IN GOVERNMENT,
THINGS WOULD BE BETTER.
NO.
WE NEED LEADERS WHO WOULD
PROTECT AMERICAN INTERESTS.
WHEN IT COMES TO IRAN, GIVING
THE AYATOLLAH KHOMEINI OVER $100
BILLION, THAT REFLECTS YOU DO
NOT UNDERSTAND THE RADICAL ISLAM
BEING TERRORIST THAT IS THE
AYATOLLAH THAT WANTS TO MURDER
US.
WE NEED A COMMANDER IN CHIEF
THAT UNDERSTANDS OUR ENEMIES AND
DOESN'T GIVE THEM BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS TO THREATEN OUR SAFETY
AND SECURITY.
>> I WAS AGAINST THE GIVING OF
THE MONEY AT ALL COST.
I SAID DON'T NEGOTIATE AT ALL
UNTIL YOU GET THE PRISONER BACK.
IF THE PRISONERS DON'T COME BACK
EARLY THREE YEARS AGO, ONE OF
THE LONGEST NEGOTIATIONS I'VE
EVER SEEN, BY THE WAY, IF THEY
DON'T COME BACK EARLY, I WAS
SAYING DON'T NEGOTIATE.
THEY COME BACK EARLY.
WHAT YOU DO IS YOU TAKE IT BACK
AND YOU SAY EITHER GIVE US THE
PRISONER OR WE DOUBLE UP THE
SANCTIONS.
WHAT WE SHOULD HAVE DONE IS
DOUBLED UP THE SANCTIONS AND
MADE A MUCH BETTER DEAL.
THAT DEAL IS A DISASTER.
TED, THE MONEY IS LARGELY GONE
BECAUSE OF INCOMPETENT AND VERY,
VERY POOR NEGOTIATORS, BUT THAT
MONEY, THE $150 BILLION, IS
LARGELY GONE AND ALREADY SPENT
EVERYWHERE BUT THE UNITED
STATES.
>> LET'S REFOCUS THIS BACK ON
CUBA.
GOVERNOR KASICH, A PAIR OF
ENTREPRENEURS FROM ALABAMA AND
NORTH CAROLINA HAVE RECEIVED
APPROVAL TO BUILD THE FIRST U.S.
FACTORY IN CUBA MAKING TRACTOR
FOR SMALL FARMS.
THIS IS A DIRECT RESULT OF
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S POLICY IN
CUBA.
IF YOU WERE ELECTED WOULD YOU
ENCOURAGE MORE U.S. COMPANIES
LIKE THAT TO DO BUSINESS IN
CUBA?
>> NO, I WOULDN'T.
IF YOU TALK TO OUR FRIENDS
AROUND THE WORLD, THEY SAY WHAT
IS AMERICA DOING?
YOU DON'T SUPPORT US, WE CAN'T
FIGURE OUT WHERE YOU ARE, YOU
WON'T ARM THE FREEDOM FIGHTERS
IN UKRAINE, WE LET THE RUSSIANS
TRUMP UP SOME EXCUSE IN THE
BUSINESS OF RUSSIAN-SPEAKING
PEOPLE.
YOU HAD A RED LINE IN SYRIA.
YOU WALKED AWAY FROM IT.
YOU REFUSED TO FUND THE SYRIAN
REBELS, YOU UNDERCUT EGYPT AND
WOO
WE ENDED UP WITH THE MUSLIM
BROTHERHOOD FOR WHILE AND WE
TURN OUR BACK ON NETANYAHU WHEN
HE COMES TO CONGRESS TO TALK
ABOUT THE IRANIAN DEAL.
I KNOW IN HUMAN NATURE THAT
SOMETIMES THERE'S A SENSE THAT
YOU MAKE BETTER WITH YOUR
ENEMIES THAN YOU DO WITH YOUR
FRIENDS.
YOU KNOW WHAT HAPPENS WHEN YOU
DO THAT?
YOU MAKE A TERRIBLE MISTAKE.
YOU NEED TO SUPPORT YOUR
FRIENDS, HOLD YOUR ENEMIES OUT
HERE AND NEGOTIATE TOUGH DEALS.
THE FACT IS THEY NEED TO
UNDERSTAND WHO WE ARE.
THE CHINESE UNDERSTAND.
THEY DON'T OWN THE SOUTH CHINA
SEA.
THEY HAVE TO STOP HACKING
EVERYTHING WE HAVE IN THIS
COUNTRY OR WE'LL TAKE OUT THEIR
SYSTEMS.
WE WILL ARM THE UKRAINIANS SO
THEY HAVE LETHAL DEFENSIVE SAID.
WE WILL DESTROY ISIS AND MR.
PUTIN, YOU BETTER UNDERSTAND
YOU'RE EITHER WITH US OR AGAINST
US.
WE'RE NOT RATTLING A SWORD,
YOU'RE NOT OUR ENMEMY BUT WE'RE
NOT GOING TO PUT UP WITH THIS
ANY LONGER.
WHERE HAS AMERICA GONE IS WHAT
MANY OF OUR ALLIES SAY AROUND
THE WORLD?
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, THEY'LL KNOW
EXACTLY WHERE WE ARE BECAUSE
WE'RE COMING BACK.
>> WHILE WE'RE DISCUSSING ISSUES
OF IMPORTANCE TO FLORIDIANS, I
REACHED OUT TO THE REPUBLICAN
MAYOR OF MIAMI TO FIND OUT WHAT
HE WANTED TO HEAR FROM YOU THIS
MORNING.
HE TOLD ME, QUOTE, CLIMATE
CHANGE MEANS RISING OCEAN
LEVELS, WHICH IN SOUTH FLORIDA
MEANS FLOODING DOWNTOWN AND OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS.
IT'S AN EVERY DAY PROBLEM IN OUR
AS PRESIDENT, WILL YOU PLEDGE TO
DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT?
SENATOR RUBIO, THE MIAMI MAYOR
HAS ENDORSED YOU.
WILL YOU HONOR HIS REQUEST FOR A
PLEDGE AND ACKNOWLEDGE THE
REALITY OF THE SCIENTIFIC
CONSENSUS OF CLIMATE CHANGE AND
PLEDGE TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT IT?
>> SURE THE CLIMATE IS CHANGING
AND ONE OF THE REASONS IS
BECAUSE THE CLIMATE HAS ALWAYS
BEEN CHANGING.
I THINK THE FUNDAMENTAL QUESTION
FOR A POLICY MAKING IS IS THE
CLIMATE CHANGING BECAUSE OF
CERTAINLY WE ARE DOING AND IF
SO, IS THERE A LAW YOU CAN PASS
TO FIX IT?
SOUTH FLORIDA WAS BIT ON LAND
THAT WAS LARGELY A SWAMP.
I HAVE LONG SUPPORTED MITIGATION
EFFORTS.
BUT AS FAR AS A LAW THAT WE CAN
PASS IN WASHINGTON TO CHANGE THE
WEATHER, THERE'S NO SUCH THING.
ON THE CONTRARY, THERE IS LAWS
THEY WANT US TO PASS, THERE ARE
LAWS THEY WANT TO US PASS THAT
WOULD BE DEVASTATING FOR OUR
ECONOMY OR THESE PROGRAMS LIKE
THE PRESIDENT PUT IN WITH THE
CLEAN POWER ACT OR ALL THESE
THINGS HE'S FORCING DOWN OUR
THROAT ON THE WAR ON COAL.
AMERICANS ARE GOING TO PAY THE
PRICE OF THAT.
THE COST OF DOING THAT IS GOING
TO BE RAMMED DOWN THE THROAT OF
THE AMERICAN CONSUMER, THE
SINGLE PARENT, THE WORKING
FAMILY WHO ARE GOING TO SEE
INCREASES IN THE COST OF LIVING,
THE BUSINESSES THAT ARE GOING TO
LEAVE AMERICA.
YOU KNOW WHAT IMPACT IT WOULD
HAVE ON THE ENVIRONMENT?
ZERO.
BECAUSE CHINA AND INDIA WILL
STILL BE POLLUTING AT HISTORIC
LEVELS.
I WANT TO BE A SAFE AND CLEAN
PLACE BUT THESE LAWS THEY'RE
ASKING TO PASS WILL DO NOTHING
FOR THE ENVIRONMENT AND WILL
HURT AND DEVASTATE OUR ECONOMY.
>> JUST TO CLARIFY, WHEN THE
REPUBLICAN MAYOR OF MIAMI, HE'S
SAYING THE SCIENTIFIC CONSENSUS
IS THAT MAN DOES CONTRIBUTE TO
CLIMATE CHANGE.
WHEN YOU TALK TO HIM BECAUSE
HE'S THE MAYOR OF MIAMI AND HE
ENDORSED YOU, YOU SAY HE'S
WRONG?
>> I WOULD SAY THERE'S NO LAW WE
COULD PASS THAT WOULD HAVE AN
IMPACT ON THAT.
IF YOU TOOK THE GIFT LIST OF
EVERY ONE ASKING US TO PASS
THESE LAWS, THERE WOULD BE NO
CHANGE.
IT WOULD CONTINUE TO GO ON.
MR
AMERICA IS NOT A PLANET.
IT'S A COUNTRY.
HERE'S WHAT HE WILL
IMMEDIATELY -- HE'S A GREAT
MAYOR AND A GOOD FRIEND BUT
HERE'S WHAT HE'S IMMEDIATELY
GOING TO START HEARING FROM.
HE'LL START HEARING FROM
FAMILIES IN SOUTH FLORIDA WHO
ARE BARELY MAKING IT BY AND NOW
THEIR ELECTRIC BILL WENT UP $20
OR $30 A MONTH BECAUSE WE MADE
IT MORE EXPENSIVE TO GENERATE
POWER.
THAT COST WILL BE PASSED ON TO
WORKING FAMILIES.
I AM NOT GOING TO DESTROY THE
U.S. ECONOMY FOR A LAW THAT WILL
DO NOTHING FOR OUR ECONOMY.
>> I DON'T THINK IT HAS TO BE
EITHER YOU'RE FOR ENVIRONMENTAL
RULES OR U YOU'RE NOT GOING TO
HAVE ANY JOBS.
IN OUR STATE, WE REDUCED
EMISSIONS BY 30%.
WE WANT TO DIG COAL BUT CLEAN IT
WHEN WE BURN IT.
WE BELIEVE IN NATURAL, IN
NUCLEAR POWER, I BELIEVE IN
SOLAR ENERGY, WIND ENERGY,
EFFICIENCY, RENEWABLES MATTER.
NOW, IT DOESN'T MEAN BECAUSE YOU
PURSUE A POLICY OF BEING
SENSITIVE TO THE ENVIRONMENT
BECAUSE WE DON'T KNOW HOW MUCH
HUMANS ACTUALLY CONTRIBUTE, BUT
IT IMPORTANT WE DEVELOP
RENEWABLES, A BATTERY TECHNOLOGY
CAN UNLEASH AN ENTIRELY
DIFFERENT WORLD.
THE FACT IS YOU CAN HAVE A
STRONG ENVIRONMENTAL POLICY AT
THE SAME TIME THAT YOU HAVE
STRONG ECONOMIC GROWTH.
THEY ARE NOT INCONSISTENT WITH
ONE ANOTHER.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, I WANT TO TALK
A LITTLE BIT RIGHT NOW ABOUT HOW
YOU GENTLEMEN SEE THE WORLD.
SENATOR CRUZ, COLIN POWELL THIS
WEEK SAID THE NASTY TONE OF THIS
PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION IS HURTING
IMAGE OF THE U.S. ABROAD, HE
SAID FOREIGNERS OF THE WORLD
LOOKING AT THIS ARE DISTRESSED.
DOES IT MATTER TO YOU WHAT THE
REST OF THE WORLD THINKS OF THE
UNITED STATES?
>> OF COURSE IT DOES.
AND WE'VE SEEN FOR SEVEN YEARS A
PRESIDENT THAT HAS MADE THE
PRESIDENCY AND HAS MADE SADLY
HIS ADMINISTRATION A LAUGHING
STOCK IN THE WORLD.
THIS ADMINISTRATION STARTED WITH
PRESIDENT OBAMA SENDING BACK THE
BUST OF WINSTON CHURCHILL TO THE
UNITED KINGDOM WITHIN THE
OPENING WEEKS.
THEN HE DECIDED TO GO ON A
WORLDWIDE APOLOGY TOUR,
APOLOGIZING FOR THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA.
OUR FRIENDS AND ALLIES LEARNED
AMERICA COULD NOT BE COUNTED ON.
WHEN I MEET WITH HEADS OF STATES
AND DEFENSE MINISTER AND FOREIGN
MINISTERS, THEY SAY IT HARD TO
BE FRIENDS WITH AMERICA, AMERICA
DOESN'T STAND WITH US.
BUT THE GOOD NEWS IS WE'VE SEEN
THIS BEFORE.
WE HAVE SEEN A WEAK DEMOCRAT
BEING PRESIDENT UNDERMINE THE
MILITARY, WEAKEN OUR READINESS,
WEAKEN OUR RESPECT WITH JIMMY
CARTER.
THAT CAN CHANGE OVERNIGHT.
IT WORTH REMEMBERING.
IRAN RELEASED OUR HOSTAGES THE
DAY RONALD REAGAN WAS SWORN INTO
OFFICE.
AND AMERICA NEEDS A PRESIDENT
WHO STANDS WITH OUR FRIEND AND
ALLIES AS I WILL DO AND WHO
STANDS UP AND DEMONSTRATES
STRENGTH TO OUR ENEMIES.
THAT'S WHY ON DAY ONE I WILL RIP
TO SHREDS THIS CAT TRAFFIC I
IRANIAN NUCLEAR DEAL BECAUSE THE
AYATOLLAH KHOMEINI CAN NEVER BE
ALLOWED TO GET NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
>> YOU HAVE SAID POSITIVE THINGS
ABOUT PUTIN AS A LEADER AND
ABOUT CHINA'S MASSACRE OF
PRO-DEMOCRACY PROTESTERS AT
TIANANMEN SQUARE.
YOU SAID WHEN THE STUDENTS
POURED INTO TIANANMEN SCARE,
THEY ALMOST BLEW IT, THEY WERE
VICIOUS AND THEN THEY PUT IT
DOWN WITH STRENGTH.
>> THAT DOESN'T MEAN I WAS
ENDORSING IT.
I SAID IT WAS A STRONG, POWERFUL
GOVERNMENT THAT PUT IT DOWN WITH
STRENGTH.
IT DOESN'T MEAN AT ALL I WAS
ENDORSING.
AS FAR AS PUTIN IS CONCERNED, I
THINK PUTIN HAS BEEN A STRONG
LEADER FOR RUSSIA.
HE'S BEEN A LOT STRONGER THAN
OUR LEADER AND THAT DOESN'T MEAN
I'M ENDORSING PUTIN.
>> MANY HAVE LOOKED AT WHAT THE
CHINESE HAVE DONE AND WHAT PUTIN
IS DOING IS ATROCITIES.
>> I USED TO THINK MERKEL WAS A
GOOD LEADER AND WHAT SHE'S DOING
IS AN ATROCITY.
I CAN NAME MANY STRONG LEADERS,
I COULD NAME MANY WEAK LEADERS.
I DON'T SAY THAT AS A GOOD WAY
OR BAD WAY.
I SAY IT AS A FACT.
>> GOVERNOR, YOU WERE OUTSPOKEN
ABOUT THE TIANANMEN SQUARE
MASSACRE.
WHAT DO YOU THINK?
>> I THINK THAT THE CHINESE
GOVERNMENT BUTCHERED THOSE KIDS
AND WHEN THAT GUY STOOD IN FRONT
OF -- THAT YOUNG MAN STOOD IN
FRONT OF THAT TANK, WE OUGHT TO
BUILD A STATUE OF HIM OVER HERE
WHEN HE FACED DOWN THE CHINESE
GOVERNMENT.
NOW, I WILL TELL YOU I DON'T
BELIEVE THAT WE NEED TO MAKE
CHINA AN ENEMY.
THEY'RE A COMPETITOR.
BUT I WANT TO GO BACK TO THREE
THINGS THEY SHOULD DO.
WE SHOULD HAVE THE HEAT ON THEM
TO WORK IN NORTH KOREA TO GET
RID OF THAT GUY AND THE THINGS
THAT HE'S DOING, NUMBER ONE.
NUMBER TWO, THEY NEED TO REALIZE
THEY DON'T OWN THE SOUTH CHINA
SEA.
I WILL COMPLIMENT THE
ADMINISTRATION FOR SENDING A --
CARRIER BATTLE GROUP INTO THE
SOUTH CHINA SEA.
AND, THIRDLY, WHEN IT COMES TO
THE ISSUE OF CYBER ATTACKS,
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE TO BEEF UP
THE CYBER COMMAND.
THEY NEED TO UNDERSTAND IF YOU
ATTACK US, WE WILL DEFEND OUR
S
-- OURSELVES, INCLUDING OUR
GRID.
THE PRESIDENT HAS NOT GIVEN THE
CYBER COMMAND THAT AUTHORITY AND
I WILL.
WHEN IT COMES TO TRADE, THEY
CAN'T MANIPULATE THEIR CURRENCY.
THAT WOULD NOT BE ANYTHING I
WOULD ALLOW THEM TO GET AWAY
WITH.
IF I SAW THEM DOING IT, I WOULD
TAKE IMMEDIATE ACTION AND MAKE
SURE THE AMERICAN WORKER IS
PROTECTED.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR KASICH.
WHEN WE COME
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
IN MIAMI, FLORIDA.
MR. TRUMP, I WANT TO START WITH
YOU IN IN BLOCK.
EARLIER TODAY A MAN WAS ARRESTED
AND CHARGED WITH ASSAULT AFTER
SUCKER PUNCHING A PROTESTER AT
YOUR RALLY.
TODAY HILLARY CLINTON, YOUR
POTENTIAL GENERAL ELECTION
OPPONENT CLEARLY INDICATED SEE
SEES THIS AS AN ISSUE FOR THE
CAMPAIGN.
SHE SAID "THIS KIND OF BEHAVIOR
IS REPUGNANT, WE SET THE TONES
FOR OUR CAMPAIGNS, WE SHOULD
ENCOURAGE RESPECT, NOT
VIOLENCE."
DO YOU BELIEVE YOU'VE DONE
ANYTHING TO ENCOURAGE THIS KIND
OF VIOLENCE?
>> I HOPE NOT.
I HOPE NOT.
WE HAVE 25,000, 30,000 PEOPLE,
THEY COME WITH TREMENDOUS LOVE
AND PASSION FOR THE COUNTRY.
YOU'RE MENTIONING ONE CASE, I
HAVEN'T SEEN, I HEARD ABOUT IT,
WHICH I DON'T LIKE.
WHEN THEY SEE WHAT'S GOING ON IN
THIS COUNTRY, THEY HAVE ANGER
THAT'S UNBELIEVABLE.
THEY LOVE THIS COUNTRY.
THEY DON'T LIKE SEEING BAD TRADE
DEALS, HIGHER TAXES, THEY DON'T
LIKE SEEING A LOSS OF THEIR JOBS
WHERE OUR JOBS HAVE JUST BEEN
DEVASTATED.
AND I KNOW -- I MEAN, I SEE IT.
THERE IS SOME ANGER.
THERE'S ALSO GREAT LOVE FOR THE
COUNTRY.
IT'S A BEAUTIFUL THING IN MANY
RESPECTS.
BUT I CERTAINLY DO NOT CONDONE
THAT AT ALL, JAKE.
>> SOME OF YOUR CRITICS POINT TO
POINTS YOU'VE MADE AT THESE
RALLIES INCLUDING FEBRUARY 23rd,
I'D LIKE TO PUNCH HIM IN THE
FACE REFERRING TO A PROTESTERS.
FEBRUARY 27th, IN THE GOOD OL'
DAYS, THEY'D HAVE KNOCKED HIM
OUT OF SEAT SO FAST.
>> KNOCK THE CRAP OUT OF THEM.
KNOCK THE HELL.
I PROMISE YOU I WILL PAY FOR THE
LEGAL FEES, I PROMISE, I
PROMISE.
>> WE HAVE SOME PROTESTERS WHO
ARE BAD DUDES, THEY HAVE DONE
BAD THINGS.
THEY ARE SWINGING, THEY ARE
REALLY DANGEROUS AND THEY GET IN
THERE AND START HITTING PEOPLE.
WE HAD A COUPLE BIG, STRONG,
POWERFUL GUYS DOING SERIOUS
DAMAGE.
IF THEY'RE GOING TO BE TAKEN
OUT, TO BE HONEST, WE HAVE TO
RUN SOMETHING.
AND IT'S NOT ME.
IT'S USUALLY THE MUNICIPAL
GOVERNMENT, THE POLICE BECAUSE I
DON'T HAVE GUARDS ALL OVER THESE
STADIUMS.
WE FILL UP STADIUMS.
IT'S USUALLY THE POLICE AND, BY
THE WAY, SPEAKING OF THE POLICE,
WE SHOULD PAY OUR RESPECTS TO
THE POLICE BECAUSE THEY ARE
TAKING TREMENDOUS ABUSE IN THIS
COUNTRY AND THEY DO A PHENOMENAL
JOB.
SO WE SHOULD TRULY GIVE OUR
POLICE, THEY'RE INCREDIBLE
PEOPLE, WE SHOULD GIVE THEM A
GREAT DEAL MORE RESPECT THAN
THEY RECEIVE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, ARE YOU
CONCERNED AT ALL THAT THESE KIND
OF SCENES POTENTIALLY HURT THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY FOR THE GENERAL
ELECTION?
>> LISTEN, I THINK FOR EVERY ONE
OF US, WE NEED TO SHOW RESPECT
TO THE PEOPLE.
WE NEED TO REMEMBER WHO IT IS
WE'RE WORKING FOR.
YOU KNOW, WE'VE SEEN FOR SEVEN
YEARS A PRESIDENT WHO BELIEVES
HE'S ABOVE THE LAW, WHO BAEHAVE
AS AN EMPEROR, AND HE FORGOT
HE'S WORKING FOR THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
TURN THE CAMERA AROUND HERE.
HOW MANY OF Y'ALL FEEL
DISRESPECTED BY WASHINGTON?
WASHINGTON ISN'T LISTENING TO
THE PEOPLE.
THAT'S THE FRUSTRATION THAT IS
BOILING OVER.
AND WE NEED TO NOMINATE AND
ELECT A PRESIDENT WHO REMEMBERS
HE WORKS FOR THE PEOPLE.
YOU KNOW, AT DONALD'S RALLIES
RECENTLY, HE'S TAKEN TO ASKING
PEOPLE IN THE CROWD TO RAISE
THEIR HAND AND PLEDGE THEIR
SUPPORT TO HIM.
I GOT TO SAY TO ME I THINK
THAT'S EXACTLY BACKWARDS.
THIS IS A JOB INTERVIEW.
WE ARE HERE PLEDGING OUR SUPPORT
TO YOU, NOT THE OTHER WAY
AROUND.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
THE ONLY HAND RAISING I'M
INTERESTED IN DOING IS ON
JANUARY 20, 2017 RAISING MY HAND
WITH THE LEFT HAND ON THE BIBLE,
PLEDGING TO PRESERVE, PROTECT
AND DEFEND THE CONSTITUTION OF
UNITED STATES.
>> IF YOU'D LIKE TO RESPOND.
>> IT SHOWS THE TOTAL DISHONESTY
OF THE PRESS.
WE WERE HAVING ON A FEW
OCCASIONS MASSIVE CROWDS.
I'M SAYING WHO IS GOING TO VOTON
TUESDAY?
THE PLACE GOES CRAZY.
THEN I SAY, HEY, DO ME A FAVOR.
DO YOU SWEAR YOU'RE GOING TO
VOTE FOR A DEMOCRAT?
EVERYONE'S LAUGHING, WE'RE ALL
HAVING A GOOD TIME.
THAT'S WHY I HAVE MUCH BIGGER
CROWDS THAN TED, BECAUSE WE HAVE
A GOOD TIME AT MINE.
BUT WE'RE ALL HAVING A GOOD TIME
AND THE NEXT DAY ON THE "TODAY"
SHOW AND A COUPLE OF OTHER
PLACE, NOT TOO MANY, THEY HAD
STILL PICTURES OF PEOPLE AND
THEY TRIED TO EQUATE IT TO NAZI,
GERMANY.
IT IS A DISGRACE.
IT WAS A TOTAL DISGRACE.
AND I'VE HAD REPORTERS, PEOPLE
THAT YOU KNOW, COME UP TO ME AND
SAID THAT -- WHAT THEY DID ON
THE "TODAY" SHOW WAS A DISGRACE.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, DO YOU WORRY
ABOUT THE SCENES OF VIOLENCE AT
SOME OF THESE RALLIES AFFECTING
THE REPUBLICAN PARTY'S CHANCES
IN NOVEMBER?
>> I WORRY ABOUT RALLY VIOLENCE
PERIOD.
ELECTIONS ARE IMPORTANT BUT THE
UNITY OF THIS COUNTRY REALLY
MATTERS.
JAKE, HERE'S WHAT I THINK IS
HAPPENING.
THERE ARE PEOPLE OUT THERE WHO
ARE WORRIED ABOUT THEIR JOBS.
THEY'RE WORRIED SOMEBODY IS
GOING TO COME IN AND TELL THIS
MANY THEY'RE OUT OF WORK AND
THEY'RE 54 YEARS OLD AND THEY
DON'T KNOW WHERE THEY'RE GOING
TO GET ANOTHER JOB, A MAN AND A
WOMAN.
MAYBE THEY'RE WORRIED ABOUT A
TRADE DEAL, WORRIED THAT THEIR
WAGES HAVEN'T GONE UP.
THEY'RE WORRIED THAT THEIR KIDS
WENT TO COLLEGE, YOU GO TO
COLLEGE, GET A JOB, THINGS WILL
BE GREAT, THEY WENT TO COLLEGE,
RANG UP DEBT AND STILL LIVING IN
THEIR PARENTS' BASEMENT, SENIORS
ARE WORRIED ABOUT LOSING THEIR
SOCIAL SECURITY.
YOU CAN EITHER PREY ON THAT AND
BE NEGATIVE ABOUT IT OR YOU TELL
PEOPLE THAT THESE THINGS CAN BE
FIXED.
IF WE'RE AMERICANS RATHER THAN
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS, WE
GET TOGETHER, WE CAN SOLVE ALL
OF THESE PROBLEMS.
WE CAN PROVIDE FINANCIAL
SECURITY, WE CAN DRIVE WAGES UP,
GET KIDS JOBS WITH A MORE ROBUST
ECONOMY.
THEY WANT TO HELP SOLVE THESE
PROBABLY LESS RIGHT WHERE THEY
LIVE AND I'LL GIVE THEM THE
POWER TO DO IT.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> I'M CONCERNED ABOUT VIOLENCE
IN GENERAL.
THE FIRST PEOPLE FACING THAT
VIOLENCE ARE OUR LAW ENFORCEMENT
OFFICERS AND THEY DESERVE OUR
RESPECT AND OUR THANKS FOR
EVERYTHING THEY DO FOR US.
ON THE ISSUE OF ANGER, YES,
PEOPLE ARE ANGRY.
OF COURSE THEY'RE ANGRY.
EVERY INSTITUTION IN AMERICA
HAVE BEEN FAILING US FOR THE
BETTER PART OF 20 OR 30 YEARS.
LEADERSHIP IS ABOUT USING THE
ANGER TO MOTIVATE US, NOT TO
DEFINE US, BUT TO MOTIVATE US TO
TAKE ACTION.
BEING HERE IN MIAMI IS SPECIAL.
MY GRANDFATHER LIVED WITH US
MOST OF HIS LIFE.
MY GRANDFATHER WAS BORN IN 1899
BEFORE THERE WERE AIRPLANES IN
THE SKY.
ONE NIGHT IN THE SUMMER OF 1969,
HE WATCHED A MAN SET FOOT ON THE
MOON.
YOU KNOW WHAT HE SAID WHEN HE
SAW THAT?
HE SAID "AMERICANS CAN DO
ANYTHING."
AMERICANS CAN DO ANYTHING.
THERE IS NO PROBLEM WE CANNOT
SOLVE IF WE EMBRACE ALL OF THE
PRINCIPLES THAT MADE US GREAT.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
THE MATH SUGGESTS THAT IT
POSSIBLE THAT NOT ONE OF YOU
WILL REACH THE MAGIC NUMBER OF
1,237 DELEGATES BEFORE THE
REPUBLICAN CONVENTION, WHICH
WOULD MEAN A CONTESTED
CONVENTION.
LET'S GO BACK TO HUGH HEWITT.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, THE MATH ON
THE MAPS SAY YOU CAN ONLY BECOME
THE NOMINEE IF IN FACT THERE IS
A CONTESTED VECONVENTION.
WHY SHOULDN'T THE PERSON WITH
THE MOST DELEGATES, EVEN IF IT'S
NOT A MAJORITY OF DELEGATES BE
THE NOMINEE IS.
>> MATH DOESN'T TELL THE WHOLE
STORY IN POLITICS.
THE GREAT THING ABOUT POLITICS,
THE REASON WHY WE WATCH IT IS
BECAUSE WHAT'S TRUE TODAY IS NOT
NECESSARILY TRUE TOMORROW SO
LET'S NOT GET AHEAD OF
OURSELVES.
SECONDLY, LOOK, WHEN YOU WENT TO
SCHOOL UP THERE IN SALEM, OHIO,
OKAY, IF YOU GOT AN 86, YOU GOT
A B.
BECAUSE EVERYBODY ELSE HAD AN 84
DIDN'T MEAN YOU GOT AN A.
SO YOU JUST HAVE TO WIN ENOUGH
DELEGATES TO BE THE NOMINEE.
AND, FRANKLY, I DON'T KNOW IF
WE'RE GOING TO GET A CONVENTION
LIKE THAT BUT IF WE DO, I WAS AT
ONE IN 1976 AS A WEE LAD AND
SUPPORTED RONALD REAGAN AND
WORKED HIM.
HE LOST, GERALD FORD SERVED THE
COUNTRY BY PARDONING RICHARD
NIXON, BUT HE HEALED THE
COUNTRY.
WE DON'T KNOW WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN.
WE STILL HAVE ABOUT HALF THE
DELEGATES TO BE SELECTED.
THAT'S WHAT'S GOING TO BE A VERY
INTERESTING THING TO SEE HOW IT
ALL TURNS OUT AS WE MOVE FORWARD
OVER THE NEXT COUPLE WEEKS.
>> MR. TRUMP, IF YOU ARRIVE IN
CLEVELAND WITH A PLURALITY AND
THE MOST BUT NOT A MAJORITY, IS
IT LEGITIMATE FROM SOMEONE ELSE
TO EMERGES FROM THAT CONVENTION?
>> I THINK THAT WHOEVER -- FIRST
OF ALL, I THINK I'M GOING TO
HAVE THE DELEGATES, OKAY?
I THINK.
LET'S SEE WHAT HAPPENS.
BUT IF SOMEBODY DOESN'T HAVE THE
DELEGATES, AND I GUESS THERE'S
TWO OF US UP HERE THAT CAN AND
THERE ARE TWO OF US THAT CANNOT
AT THIS MOMENT -- NO, THAT'S
JUST -- BY THE WAY, THAT IS NOT
MEANT TO BE A CRITICISM, THAT'S
JUST A MATHEMATICAL FACT, OKAY?
IF TWO OF US GET UP THERE, I
WOULD SAY THIS -- IF MARCO, IF
THE GOVERNOR, IF TED HAD MORE
VOTES THAN ME IN THE FORM OF
DELEGATES, I THINK WHOEVER GETS
TO THAT TOP POSITION AS OPPOSED
TO SOLVING THAT ARTIFICIAL
NUMBER THAT WAS SET BY SOMEBODY,
WHICH IS A VERY RANDOM NUMBER, I
THINK THAT WHOEVER GETS THE MOST
DELEGATES SHOULD WIN.
THAT'S WHAT I THINK.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, IF YOU OVERTAKE
DONALD TRUMP AT THE CONVENTION,
WHAT WOULD YOU DO TO TAKE HIS
PASSIONATE SUPPORTERS AND KEEP
THEM FROM BOLTING THE CONVENTION
AND SABOTAGING THE FALL
ELECTION?
>> THERE'S SOME --
>> MAKE ME PRESIDENT.
>> DONALD, YOU ARE WELCOME TO BE
PRESIDENT OF THE SMITHSONIAN.
YOU KNOW, THERE ARE SOME IN
WASHINGTON WHO ARE HAVING
FEVERED DREAMS OF A BROKEN
CONVENTION.
THEY'RE UNHAPPY WITH HOW THE
PEOPLE ARE VOTING AND THEY WANT
TO PARACHUTE IN THEIR FAVORITE
WASHINGTON CANDIDATE TO BE THE
NOMINEE.
I THINK THAT WOULD BE AN
ABSOLUTE DISASTER.
WE NEED TO RESPECT THE WILL OF
THE VOTERS.
IT'S ONE OF THE REASONS WHY IN
THE COURSE OF THIS ELECTION --
LISTEN, EVERYONE UP HERE HAS
WORKED VERY, VERY HARD BUT
DODG
DONALD IS RIGHT.
THERE ARE ONLY TWO OF US THAT
HAVE A PATH TO WINNING THE
NOMINATION, DONALD AND MYSELF.
AT THIS POINT I HAVE YOU ROUGHLY
360 DELEGATES, HE HAS ABOUT 100
MORE THAN I HAVE.
WE HAVE BEATEN DONALD IN EIGHT
SEPARATE STATES ALL OVER THE
COUNTRY, GEOGRAPHICALLY FROM
MAINE TO ALASKA, SO FOR THE
PEOPLE AT HOME, IF YOU'RE ONE OF
THE 65% OF REPUBLICANS WHO
RECOGNIZES WE NOMINATE DONALD
TRUMP, HILLARY WINS.
THAT'S WHY THE MEDIA WANTS HIM
TO BE THE NOMINEE SO MUCH.
IF YOU RECOGNIZE THAT, THEN I
WANT TO INVITE YOU, IF YOU'VE
SUPPORTED OTHER CANDIDATES ARE
COME AND JOIN US.
WE ARE SEEING CANDIDATES COMING
TO THE AND UNITING.
IT'S WHY CARLY FIORINA ENDORSED
ME YESTERDAY, WHY MIKE LEE
ENDORSED ME TODAY.
I ASK EVERYONE TO COME TOGETHER
AND STAND TOGETHER AND BEAT
HILLARY CLINTON IN NOVEMBER.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> I LISTEN AND I WATCH TED ON
TELEVISION WHEN HE SPEAKS.
HE'S ALWAYS SAYING I'M THE ONLY
ONE WHAT BEAT DONALD?
SIX CONTESTS AND I BEAT HIM.
BUT I BEAT HIM IN 13 CONTESTS.
HE NEVER MENTIONS THAT.
AND ANOTHER LITTLE MINOR FACT.
I HAVE ABOUT 1,600,000 VOTES
DURING THIS PRIMARY SEASON, MORE
VOTES THAN TED.
THE OTHER THING IS I BEAT
HILLARY AND I WILL GIVE YOU THE
LIST, I BEAT HILLARY IN MANY OF
THE POLLS THAT HAVE BEEN TAKEN
AND EACH WEEK I GET BETTER AND
BETTER.
AND BELIEVE ME, I HAVEN'T EVEN
STARTED ON HER YET.
>> SENATOR RUBIO.
>> LET ME TELL YOU WHAT THIS
ELECTION IS ABOUT FOR ME AND I
GET ALL THE DELEGATE MATH AND
DEBATE.
ON TUESDAY NIGHT I DIDN'T DO AS
WELL OBVIOUSLY AS I WANTED TO
AND I WAS A LITTLE BIT
DISAPPOINTED WHEN I GOT HOME.
AND MY WIFE TOLD ME A STORY THAT
NIGHT, WHICH IS THE REASON WHY I
CAN GET UP THE NEXT DAY AND KEEP
FIGHTING.
THERE'S A GENTLEMAN HERE IN
SOUTH FLORIDA WHO JUST GOT OUT
OF SURGERY.
HIS DOCTORS TOLD HIM HE NEEDS TO
BE HOME RESTING.
EVERY DAY HE SITS OUTSIDE OF A
POLLING CENTERS AND HOLDS A SIGN
THAT SAYS "MARCO RUBIO."
FOR HIM I REPRESENT ALL THE
SACRIFICES HIS GENERATION MADE
SO THEY CAN HAVE A BETTER LIVES.
HE HAS NOT GIVEN UP ON ME AND I
AM NOT GOING TO GIVE UP ON HIM.
I BELIEVE THAT AT THE END OF
THIS PROCESS THIS NATION WILL
MAKE THE RIGHT CHOICE BECAUSE
I'VE ALWAYS BELIEVED THAT GOD
HAS BLESSED AMERICA, THAT GOD'S
HAND IS UPON THIS COUNTRY AND
THAT ITS GREATEST DAYS ARE YET
TO COME.
>> LET'S GO BACK TO STEVEN DINAN
OF "THE WASHINGTON POST."
>> YOU ARE LARGELY SELF-FUNDING
YOUR CAMPAIGN.
WILL YOU MAINTAIN YOUR PLEDGE
NOT TO TAKE OUTSIDE
CONTRIBUTIONS THROUGHOUT THE
GENERAL ELECTION?
>> I HAVE NOT MADE THAT DECISION
YET.
I WILL MAKE A DECISION ON THAT.
MY DECISION IS I WOULD GO
THROUGH THE ENTIRE PRIMARY
SEASON AND I HAVE TURNED DOWN
PROBABLY $275 MILLION WORTH.
I HAVE MANY, MANY FRIENDS THAT
COME UP ALL DAY LONG, $5
MILLION, $10 MILLION, I'M
TURNING DOWN MONEY.
I FEEL KIND OF FOOLISH TO BE
HONEST.
I DON'T KNOW IF I GET ANY CREDIT
FOR IT BUT I'M SELF-FUNDING MY
CAMPAIGN.
OTHER THAN VERY SMALL DONATIONS
WHERE PEOPLE ARE SENDING IN
$200, $20, IT NOT A LARGE
AMOUNT.
I'M SELF-FUNDING MY CAMPAIGN.
I'VE BEEN IN THIS BUSINESS A
LONG TIME AND I WAS ON THE OTHER
SIDE UNTIL EIGHT MONTHS AGO I
WAS ON THE OR SIDE.
I MADE MASSIVE CONTRIBUTIONS,
LARGE CONTRIBUTIONS TO
POLITICIANS, BOTH DEMOCRATS AND
REPUBLICANS.
I WAS LIKED BY EVERYBODY, WHICH
IS AN IMPORTANT THING.
I WILL SAY THIS -- PEOPLE
CONTROL SPECIAL INTERESTS,
LOBBYISTS, DONORS, THEY MAKE
LARGE CONTRIBUTIONS TO
POLITICIANS AND THEY HAVE TOTAL
CONTROL OVER THOSE POLITICIANS.
I DON'T WANT ANYBODY TO CONTROL
ME BUT THE PEOPLE RIGHT OUT
THERE.
AND I'M GOING TO DO THE RIGHT
THING.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, THE VAST
MAJORITY OF REPUBLICANS AND
VOTERS AGREE WITH MR. TRUMP.
DO YOU DENY THOSE BIG DONORS DO
HAVE INFLUENCE?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
IT'S WHAT I'VE CALLED THE
WASHINGTON CARTEL.
IT'S CAREER POLITICIANS IN BOTH
PARTIES THAT GET IN BED WITH THE
LOBBYISTS AND SPECIAL INTERESTS.
DONALD TOLD YOU FOR 40 YEARS
HE'S BEEN SITTING AT THAT TABLE
USING HIS MONEY TO BUY
INFLUENCE, SUPPORTING LIBERAL
DEMOCRATS LIKE HILLARY CLINTON
AND JOHN KERRY, BUT ALSO
SUPPORTING THE REPUBLICAN
ESTABLISHMENT AND FUNDING THEIR
EFFORT TO CRUSH THE TEA PARTY.
AND NOW HIS ARGUMENT IS AFTER
FOUR DECADES OF BEING PART OF
THAT INFLUENCE BUYING, THAT
SUDDENLY HE WILL CHANGE.
BUT THE INTERESTING POINT IS
TONIGHT HE HASN'T POINTED TO A
SINGLE SPECIAL INTEREST HE'S
WILLING TO TAKE ON.
HE DIDN'T TAKE ON WALL STREET
WHEN HE SUPPORTED THE T.A.R.P.
BAILOUT AND MY CAMPAIGN WAS
FUNDED BY 1.1 MILLION
CONTRIBUTIONS ALL ACROSS THE
COUNTRY.
$62 TO TEDCRUZ.ORG.
>> THESE SUPER PACS ARE A
DISASTER, VERY CORRUPT.
IT'S GOING TO LEAD TO LOTS OF
DISASTERS.
TED HAS SUPER PACS AND YOU HAVE
TO LOOK AT THE PEOPLE GIVING TO
THOSE SUPER PACS.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT TO DO THAT.
W
THERE IS TOTAL CONTROL OF THE
CANDIDATES, I KNOW IT BETTER
THAN PROBABLY ANYBODY WHO HAS
EVER LIVED.
I WILL TELL YOU THIS, I KNOW THE
SYSTEM FAR BETTER THAN ANYBODY
ELSE AND I KNOW THE SYSTEM IS
BROKEN.
AND I'M THE ONE BECAUSE I KNOW
IT SO WELL BECAUSE I WAS ON BOTH
SIDES OF IT, I WAS ON THE OTHER
SIDE ALL MY LIFE AND MADE LARGE
CONTRIBUTIONS.
FRANKLY, I KNOW THE SYSTEM
BETTER THAN ANYONE ELSE AND I'M
THE ONLY ONE UP HERE THAT'S
GOING TO BE ABLE TO FIX THAT
SYSTEM BECAUSE THAT SYSTEM IS
WRONG.
>> THANK YOU.
AT THE LAST DEBATE MR. RUBIO,
YOU MOCKED MR. TRUMP FOR BEING
FLEXIBILITY.
HOW CAN YOU EXPECT TO LEAD THE
COUNTRY AND GET THINGS DONE IF
YOU'RE NOT WILLING TO SHOW
FLEXIBILITY.
>> YOU CAN BE FLEXIBILITY ABOUT
IDEAS BUT YOU SHOULDN'T BE F
FLEXIBLE ABOUT YOUR PRINCIPLES.
I OWED OVER $100 IN -- $100,000
IN STUDENT LOAN DEBT.
THE ACT THAT DEALS WITH HUMAN
TRAFF
TRAFFICKING, I DID THAT ON A
BIPARTISAN ISSUE OVER.
WHEN IT COMES TO REPEALING AND
REPLACES OBAMA CARE, THAT'S NOT
GOING TO BE BIPARTISAN.
WHEN IT COMES TO SHRINKING THE
SIZE OF THE FEDERAL BUREAUCRACY,
THAT'S PROBABLY NOT GOING TO BE
BIPARTISAN.
THERE ARE ISSUES WE CAN WORK
TOGETHER ON AND WE SHOULD, BUT
THERE ARE FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES
ABOUT THE PROPER ROLE OF
GOVERNMENT AND ON THOSE ISSUES,
I WILL FIGHT ANYONE WHO WANTS TO
EXPAND GOVERNMENT, RAISE TAXES
OR WEAKEN OUR MILITARY.
>> MR. TRUMP, I WANT TO GIVE YOU
A CHANCE TO RESPOND BUT
SPECIFICALLY YOU TALK ABOUT
FLEXIBILITY AND ONE OF THE
EXAMPLES YOU GAVE IS THE HEIGHT
OF THE BORDER FENCE.
WHAT ARE THE OTHER ISSUES ON
WHICH YOU'RE WILLING TO SHOW
FLEXIBILITY?
>> IT DEPENDS ON WHAT COME UP.
WE HAVE A GREAT PRESIDENT,
RONALD REAGAN.
WE HAD SPEAKER TIP O'NEILL.
THEY GOT ALONG, HAD
RELATIONSHIPS AND NOBODY IS
COMPLAINING ABOUT THE DEALS THAT
RONALD REAGAN MADE AND HE MADE
IT WITH TIP O'NEILL.
WE NEED TO HAVE PEOPLE GET
TOGETHER AND WORK GOOD DEALS OUT
FROM OUR STANDPOINT.
AND I'LL TELL YOU THIS, IT CAN
BE DONE.
WE DON'T WANT TO CONTINUE TO
WATCH PEOPLE SIGNING EXECUTIVE
ORDERS BECAUSE THAT'S NOT WHAT
THE CONSTITUTION AND BRILLIANT
DESIGNERS OF THIS INCREDIBLE
DOCUMENT HAD IN MIND.
WE NEED PEOPLE THAT CAN MAKE
DEALS AND CAN WORK.
RIGHT NOW IN WASHINGTON THERE'S
TOTAL, ABSOLUTE GRIDLOCK.
>> I WANT TO GO TO GOVERNOR
KASICH ON THIS ISSUES OF
FLEXIBILITY, SIR.
>> MY RECORD SPEAKS FOR ITSELF.
WHEN I TALK ABOUT TONIGHT IS NOT
THEORY.
THESE ARE THINGS THAT I'VE DONE.
I WAS THERE WHEN WE REFORMED THE
PENTAGON ON A BIPARTISAN BASIS
TO GIVE CONTROL TO THE
COMMANDERS IN THE FIELD AND
FORCE THE SERVICES TO WORK
TOGETHER.
I WAS THE CHIEF ARCHITECT ALONG
WITH SENATOR DOMENICI THE LAST
TIME WE BALANCED THE BUDGET AND
FIRST TIME WE WALKED ON THE
MOON.
I WAS THERE FOR WELFARE REFORM
IN WARM AND ELIMINATED
ENTITLEMENT ON WELFARE, I WORKED
IN OHIO -- MY PROBLEM IS PEOPLE
DON'T KNOW THIS.
THEY SAY DOES THAT MEAN YOU'RE
TOO EASY?
WHEN WE DID THE BALANCED BUDGET,
WE CUT THE CAPITAL GAINS TAX,
PROVIDED A TAX CREDIT AND SHRUNK
THE GOVERNMENT.
THE STATE OF OHIO HAS THE
SMALLEST GOVERNMENT IN THE STATE
OF OHIO IN 30 YEARS.
IN REGARDS TO SOCIAL SECURITY,
WE WILL NOT GET THAT DONE ALONE.
WE WILL HAVE TO HAVE SOME
RESPONSIBLE DEMOCRATS WHO WILL
COME IN TO FIX THE PROBLEM WITH
SOCIAL SECURITY.
I KNOW HOW TO DO IT BECAUSE I'VE
DONE IT AND I'LL DO IT AGAIN.
>> WE HAVE TIME FOR ONE LAST
BREAK.
WE'LL BE BACK AFTER THIS.
>>> AND WE'RE BACK WITH THE
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE,
JUST FIVE DAYS BEFORE THE NEXT
PRIMARY ELECTIONS, IT IS TIME
NOW FOR CLOSING STATEMENTS.
CANDIDATES, YOU WILL EACH HAVE
ONE MINUTE.
AND WE'LL START WITH GOVERNOR
KASICH.
>> I'D LIKE TO SAY TO ALL OF
YOU, THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, I HAVE
RUN AN UNWAVERING POSITIVE
CAMPAIGN FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
I HAVE TRIED TO BE POSITIVE IN
SUCH A WAY AS TO SHOW MY RECORD,
MY ACCOMPLISHMENTS, MY VISION.
AND I WANTED TO RAISE THE BAR IN
PRESIDENTIAL POLITICS SO OUR
KIDS CAN TAKE A LOOK AT THE WAY
YOU CAN RUN FOR PRESIDENT AND
YOU WILL SOMEDAY MAYBE BE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
SOMETIMES BEING POSITIVE ISN'T
ALL THAT INTERESTING BUT IT'S
VERY INTERESTING TO MY FAMILY,
CHILDREN AND MY SUPPORTERS THAT
I MEET ALL ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
I WILL CONTINUE TO RUN A
POSITIVE CAMPAIGN.
I CAN FIX THE PROBLEMS IN
WASHINGTON, I'VE DONE IT BEFORE.
AND, IN FACT, I WANT TO TURN
POWER, MONEY AND INFLUENCE BACK
TO YOU, THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, SO
THAT YOU CAN BE IN THE SCHOOLS
AND ON THE STREETS FIGHTING
DRUGS AND DEALING WITH THE
ISSUES OF POVERTY.
WE CAN DO THIS TOGETHER.
ALLOW ME TO TAKE CARE OF THE
FEDERAL ISSUES WHEN I SEND THE
POWER BACK AND THE MONEY AND THE
INFLUENCE TO YOU AND YOU CAN
STRENGTHEN OUR NATION AND OUR
NEIGHBORHOODS AND FAMILIES.
T
THAT'S WHERE THE SPIRIT AND
STRENGTH OF AMERICA IS.
ASK MY FRIENDS IN ILLINOIS AND
MY BELOVED BUCKEYES TO CONSIDER
ME ON TUESDAY AND, PLEASE, LET
ME HAVE YOUR VOTE.
GOD BLESS.
>> NSENATOR RUBIO.
>> IT'S GREAT TO BE BACK IN
MIAMI.
MY FATHER WAS