>>> WELCOME TO A SPECIAL EDITION
OF SPECIAL REPORT, I'M BRET
BAIER COMING TO YOU FROM THE GEM
THEATER IN DOWNTOWN DETROIT.
IN JUST A MOMENT, THE FIRST OF
TWO DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES WILL
TAKE THE STAGE AT THIS TOWN
HALL.
WE'LL CHECK THE STORIES MAKING
HEADLINES TODAY.
>> BLOOMBERG WILL NOT RUN FOR
PRESIDENT.
HE CANNOT TAKE THE RISK THAT HIS
CANDIDACY COULD LEAD TO THE
ELECTION OF DONALD TRUMP OR TED
CRUZ.
HE CALLS TRUMP DIVISIVE AND CRUZ
EXTREME.
FLAGS ARE FLYING AT HALF STAFF
TODAY AROUND THE COUNTRY IN
MEMORY OF NANCY REAGAN.
THE FORMER FIRST LADY DIED
SUNDAY OF CONGESTIVE HEART
FAILURE AT HER HOME IN LAS
VEGAS.
HER 52 YEAR MARRIAGE TO RONALD
REAGAN ENDED WITH HIS DEATH IN
2004 AFTER A LONG BATTLE WITH
ALASKA HIGHLIGHTER'S DISEASE.
SHE BECAME A LEADING ADVOCATE,
EVEN BREAKING FROM MANY
REPUBLICANS IN THE USE OF STEM
CELL RESEARCH.
SHE WILL BE BURIED NEXT TO HER
HUSBAND IN SIMI VALLEY,
CALIFORNIA.
>>> NORTH KOREA IS THREATENING
WHAT IT CALLS A PREEMPTIVE
NUCLEAR STRIKE OF JUSTICE ON
WASHINGTON AND SEOUL SOUTH
KOREA.
IT'S THE START OF WAR GAMES.
LAST WEEK, THE NUCLEAR ARSENAL
WAS ON ALERT FOLLOWING NEW
SANCTIONS FROM THE U.N. OVER ITS
NUCLEAR PROGRAM.
NOW, LET'S WELCOME OUR FIRST
CANDIDATE ON STAGE.
VERMONT SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
>> THANK YOU, THANK YOU.
>> I DON'T KNOW, THEY'RE FEELING
THE BURN HERE I THINK.
>> THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE.
I WANT TO GET YOUR REACTION TO
THE NEWS THAT MICHAEL BLOOMBERG
DECIDED NOT TO RUN AS AN
INDEPENDENT AN HOUR AGO.
>> THAT'S HIS DECISION.
WHAT DOES CONCERN ME ON A
BROADER SCALE IS MR. BLOOMBERG
IS A BILLIONAIRE.
I THINK IT'S A BAD IDEA FOR
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY THAT THE ONLY
PEOPLE WHO FEEL IN MANY WAYS
THAT THEY CAN RUN FOR PRESIDENT
ARE PEOPLE WHO HAVE SO MUCH
MONEY ONE OF THE THINGS WE
BELIEVE IN IS TO OVERTURN THE
DISASTROUS SUPREME COURT
DECISIONS SO ALL PEOPLE CAN RUN
FOR OFFICE, NOT JUST PEOPLE WHO
HAVE A WHOLE LOT OF MONEY.
WHAT THE POLITICAL RAMIFICATIONS
OF IT ARE, I DON'T KNOW.
>> YOU SAID SOMETHING THAT
CAUSED A BIT OF A STIR ON SOCIAL
MEDIA, AND AMONG THE POLITICAL
ANALYSTS WHO COVER THIS RACE.
YOU SAID, WHEN YOU ARE WHITE,
YOU DON'T KNOW WHAT IT'S LIKE TO
BE POOR.
DIFFERENT COMMUNITIES
INTERPRETED THAT DIFFERENT WAYS,
WHAT DID YOU MEAN BY THAT?
>> THERE IS NO CANDIDATE IN THIS
RACE WHO HAS TALKED MORE ABOUT
POVERTY THAN I HAVE.
ONE OF THE THINGS THAT'S
DISTURBING, THE MEDIA DOESN'T
COVER THAT, WE HAVE 47 MILLION
PEOPLE IN THIS COUNTRY LIVING IN
POVERTY.
THAT'S A HIGH RATE IN THIS
COUNTRY.
WE HAVE THE HIGHEST RATE OF
CHILDHOOD POVERTY.
I TALK ABOUT POVERTY ALL OF THE
TIME.
WHAT I MEANT BY THAT IS IN
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITIES YOU
HAVE PEOPLE LIVING IN
DESPERATION, OFTEN BEING ABUSED
BY WHITE POLICE OFFICERS, THAT
IS A BAD THING.
THAT HAS GOT TO CHANGE, THAT'S
WHY I'M FIGHTING TO REFORM A
BROKEN CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM.
I KNOW ABOUT WHITE POVERTY, IT
EXISTS IN MY STATE, ALL OVER
THIS COUNTRY.
IN THE RICHEST COUNTRY IN THE
HISTORY OF THE WORLD, WE HAVE
MORE INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY THAN ANY OTHER MAJOR
COUNTRY.
WE HAVE TOO MANY PEOPLE LIVING
IN POVERTY, WE HAVE TO CHANGE
OUR NATIONAL PRIORITIES.
WE HAVE GOT TO DEAL WITH THAT
ISSUE.
>> YOU ALSO SEEMED TAKEN ABACK A
BIT BY SECOND CLINTON'S AUTO
BAILOUT LONE.
IS THIS PART OF THE PROBLEM
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT FROM THE
U.S. SENATE TRYING TO EXPLAIN
CLOTURE VOTES.
>> THAT'S A GOOD POINT, AS YOU
KNOW, VOTES ARE COMPLICATED
SOMETIMES WITHIN LARGE PIECES OF
LEGISLATION ARE GOOD THINGS, BAD
THINGS.
IN THIS CASE, THERE WAS ONE VOTE
TO SUPPORT THE AUTOMOTIVE
INDUSTRY.
I BELIEVE -- AND, OF COURSE, I
KNEW AT THE TIME, IF THAT
INDUSTRY WENT DOWN, MILLIONS OF
JOBS, NOT ONLY IN MICHIGAN AND
OHIO, ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY
WOULD BE IMPACTED.
OF COURSE I VOTED IN THE ONE
SENATE VOTE I HAVE THE
OPPORTUNITY TO VOTE TO SUPPORT
THE AUTOMOBILE INDUSTRY.
WHAT I DID NOT VOTE FOR WAS THE
BAILOUT OF WALL STREET.
AND THAT IS ESSENTIALLY WHAT
SENATOR CLINTON WAS TALKING
ABOUT.
WHAT I PROPOSED AND I LOST BY
WHAT THEY CALL A VOTE, IS TO ASK
THE WEALTHIEST PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY TO PAY A SUR TAX.
THEY ARE THE PEOPLE BY AND LARGE
WHO BENEFITED FROM THE ILLEGAL
BEHAVIOR OF WALL STREET.
AND I THOUGHT THAT RATHER THAN
HAVE THE MIDDLE CLASS AND
WORKING FAMILIES OF THIS COUNTRY
BAILOUT WALL STREET I WANTED THE
1% TO BAIL OUT WALL STREET.
>> SENATOR, THERE IS WIDESPREAD
BIPARTISAN AGREEMENT THAT
PROGRAMS LIKE MEDICARE, SOCIAL
SECURITY AND MEDICAID ARE THE
MAIN DRIVERS OF OUR RAPIDLY
INCREASING NATIONAL DEBT.
NOW APPROACHING $20 TRILLION.
WITHOUT REFORMS OF THESE
PROGRAMS, THEY SAY WE'RE HEADING
FOR A DEBT CRISIS.
YOU HAVE THE CONGRESSIONAL
BUDGET OFFICE AMONG OTHERS,
SPENDING ON THESE PROGRAMS COULD
CONSUME ALL REVENUE BY 2031.
WE WOULDN'T HAVE MONEY FOR
NATIONAL DEFENSE AND POVERTY
BRAHAMS.
YOU HAVE A BIG TAX INCREASE
PLANNED.
BUT YOU ALSO PLAN TO SPEND SOME
$18 TRILLION ON PROGRAMS.
HOW DO YOU PREVENT A DEBT
CRISIS?
>> OF THAT 18 TRILLION, MUCH OF
IT IS BEING SPENT TO HAVE THE
UNITED STATES JOIN THE REST OF
THE INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD.
IN GUARANTEEING HEALTH CARE TO
ALL PEOPLE.
AND WHAT THAT MEANS IS THAT IN
FACT THE AVERAGE MIDDLE CLASS
FAMILY.
THAT 18 TRILLION DOES NOT
INCLUDE THE FACT THAT THAT
MIDDLE CLASS FAMILY IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE ECONOMY WOULD SAVE
ABOUT $5,000 A YEAR ON THEIR
HEALTH CARE COSTS.
I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE, I KNOW NOT
EVERYONE AGREES WITH ME, I
BELIEVE THAT HEALTH CARE IS A
RIGHT OF ALL PEOPLE.
I BELIEVE THERE'S SOMETHING
WRONG WHEN WE ARE SPENDING --
>> WHERE DOES THAT RIGHT COME
FROM?
>> BEING A HUMAN BEING.
>> AND I BELIEVE THAT SHE IS
POOR AND YOU ARE RICH, SHE IS
EARN TITLED TO THE SAME QUALITY
HEALTH CARE YOU HAVE, BECAUSE
SHE'S A HUMAN BEING.
BUT IN ANY CASE, WHEN WE TALK
ABOUT OUR HEALTH CARE SYSTEM,
IT'S IMPORTANT TO KNOW.
IT'S NOT JUST THAT WE HAVE 29
MILLION PEOPLE WITHOUT HEALTH
INSURANCE, WE HAVE MANY MORE WHO
ARE UNDERINSURED AND WE ARE
GETTING RIPPED OFF BIG TIME BY
THE PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY.
WE END UP SPENDING AND YOU CAN
EXPLAIN IT TO PEOPLE.
WHY DO WE SPEND THREE TIMES MORE
THAN THE BRITISH DO PER PERSON
FOR HEALTH CARE OPINION AND WHY
DO WE PAY THE HIGHEST PRICES IN
THE WORLD FOR DRUGS.
>> CURRENTLY WE'RE AT 19 BNT 1
TRILLION GROSS FEDERAL DEAD
PROJECTED TO RISE BY 10 TRILLION
2026.
>> I RAISE THE ISSUE, BECAUSE OF
THAT 19 YOU WERE TALKING ABOUT,
15 WAS HEALTH CARE.
YOU EXCLUDE THAT.
AND LET'S TALK ABOUT THE OTHERS.
I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE THAT IN THE
YEAR 2016, WHEN WE TALK ABOUT
PUBLIC EDUCATION, IT MEANS TO ME
THAT A COLLEGE DEGREE TODAY IN
MANY RESPECTS IS WHAT A HIGH
SCHOOL DEGREE WAS 50 YEARS AGO.
I BELIEVE THAT WE'VE GOT TO MAKE
PUBLIC COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION FREE.
I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE TO
SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER STUDENT DEBT
BECAUSE YOUNG PEOPLE SHOULD NOT
BE FORCED TO PAY OFF THEIR DEBTS
FOR 50 YEARS.
HOW DO YOU PAY FOR THAT?
THAT'S YOUR QUESTION.
WHEN THE ILLEGAL BEHAVIOR IN
THIS COUNTRY CAUSED THE
DOWNTURN, THE UNITED STATES
CONGRESS AGAINST MY VOTE,
HILLARY CLINTON AND I DISAGREE,
SHE VOTED FOR IT, I VOTEDED
AGAINST IT.
CONGRESS PASSED A BAILOUT.
I THINK WE SHOULD IMPOSE A TAX
ON WALL STREET SPECULATION, I
THINK IT'S WALL STREET'S TURN TO
HELP THE MIDDLE CLASS OF THIS
COUNTRY PAY FOR IT.
>> MY POINT,WE PAY FOR THAT.
>> ONE OF THE MOST INTERESTING
TRENDS TO EMERGE FROM THE
ENTRANCE AND EXIT POLLS SO FAR,
IS WHICH OF YOU IS HONEST AND
TRUSTWORTHY.
IN STATE AFTER STATE, THE TOP
PRIORITY, THERE'S A MASSIVE GULF
BETWEEN YOU AND SENATOR CLINTON.
NEVADA, 82-12.
IOWA, 83-10.
IN FIVE OF THE SUPER TUESDAY
STATES YOU HAD AN ADVANTAGE ON
THIS QUESTION.
DO YOU SHARE THE CONCERNS OF
YOUR SUPPORTERS THAT SECRETARY
CLINTON IS NOT TRUSTWORTHY?
>> I WILL LET THE PEOPLE OF THE
UNITED STATES MAKE THAT
DECISION, THIS IS WHAT I WILL
SAY, WHICH MAKES ME VERY, VERY
PROUD.
AS YOU KNOW ON SUPER TUESDAY, MY
OWN STATE OF VERMONT VOTED.
ESSENTIALLY.
THE PEOPLE WHO KNOW YOU THE BEST
ARE YOUR OWN NEIGHBORS.
I REPRESENTED VERMONT IN
CONGRESS FOR 25 YEARS.
I AM PROUD THAT I RECEIVED 86%
OF THE VOTE IN MY HOME STATE
MANY.
>> CLARK?
>> THANK YOU.
>> MY QUESTION HAS TO DO WITH --
I'M AN AMERICAN, I WATCH WHAT
HAPPENS IN THE MIDDLE EAST, I'M
PERSONALLY HORRIFIED BECAUSE
THAT'S WHERE MY FATHER IS FROM.
LEFT UNCHECKED, ISIS IS GOING TO
PERPETUATE AGAIN SIDE ON A
NUMBER OF RELIGIOUS MINORITIES
IN THAT AREA.
I'M WONDERING HOW YOU WILL
ADDRESS THAT CRISIS.
>> ALL OF US CAN AGREE THAT ISIS
IS A BARBARIC ORGANIZATION THAT
HAS TO BE DESTROYED.
THE QUESTION IS, HOW DO WE DO IT
MIDDLE EAST EFFECTIVELY.
ONE OF THE DIFFERENCES BETWEEN
SECRETARY CLINTON AND MYSELF, I
VOTED AGAINST THE WAR IN IRAQ.
SHE VOTED FOR THE WAR IN IRAQ.
IN A LOT OF WAYS, THE TURMOIL
WE'RE SEEING NOW RESULTED FROM
THAT DISASTROUS DECISION.
THE LESSON I HAVE LEARNED FROM
THE WAR IN IRAQ, IS THAT THE
UNITED STATES CANNOT AND SHOULD
NOT DO IT ALONE, WE HAVE TO WORK
IN COALITION.
>> KING ABDULLAH OF JORDAN MADE
A PROFOUND STATEMENT.
WHAT'S GOING ON THERE RIGHT NOW.
IS A WAR FOR THE SOUL OF ISLAM.
AND THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE GOT THE
MOST EFFECTIVELY DEAL WITH THAT
ISSUE ARE THE MUSLIM NATIONS
THEMSELVES.
THEY ARE THE ONES ON THE GROUND
WHO ARE GOING TO HAVE TO DESTROY
ISIS.
AND I AGREE WITH THAT I WILL DO
EVERYTHING CAN I TO KEEP
AMERICAN TROOPS OUT OF PERPETUAL
WARFARE.
I BELIEVE ALONG WITH A COALITION
OF THE MAJOR COUNTRIES ON EARTH.
I BELIEVE WE SHOULD SUPPORT THE
MUSLIM TROOPS ON THE GROUND WITH
AIR ATTACKS, WITH MILITARY
EQUIPMENT, AND WITH ALL OF THE
HELP THAT WE CAN PROVIDE.
BUT IT SHOULD NOT BE OUR TROOPS.
ON THE GROUND FOR MANY REASONS.
>> DO YOU THINK WHAT'S HAPPENING
TO CHRISTIANS IN THE MIDDLE EAST
SHOULD BE CLASSIFIED AS AGAIN
GENOCIDE?
>> WHAT'S HAPPENING TO
CHRISTIANS IN THE MIDDLE EAST IN
THAT AREA IS HORRIFIC.
WHAT IS HAPPENING TO MUSLIMS IS
HORRIFIC.
I DON'T KNOW THAT WE HAVE TO PUT
A WORD ON IT, BUT WHEN YOU HAVE
A GROUP -- I MEAN, WHAT CAN WE
SAY ABOUT THESE PEOPLE?
THEY ARE KILLING CHILDREN
BECAUSE THEY ARE GOING TO
SCHOOL.
GIRLS WHO ARE GOING TO SCHOOL,
THEY'RE PUTTING GIRLS IN SEXUAL
SLAVERY.
THIS IS BARBARISM AND WE HAVE TO
DESTROY ISIS.
>> SENATOR GEORGE JACKSON IS
SELF-EMPLOYED.
>> I'LL SPEAK FOR THE AMERICAN
PUBLIC YOU'RE MUCH MORE HONEST
THAN HILLARY.
MY QUESTION TO YOU IS, YOU TALK
ABOUT THE RICH, AND BY TAXING
THE RICH TO HELP OUR ECONOMY.
WOULDN'T THAT HURT THOSE RICH
BUSINESS OWNERS THAT HELP CREATE
JOBS?
>> GOOD QUESTION, I DISAGREE
WITH YOU IN THIS SENSE.
WE HAVE TO PUT INTO CONTEXT,
WHAT'S HAPPENED IN THE LAST 30
YEARS.
>> WHAT'S HAPPENED IN THE LAST
30 YEARS, THERE HAS BEEN A
MASSIVE TRANSFER OF WEALTH FROM
THE WORKING CLASS AND THE MIDDLE
CLASS, WE HAVE SEEN A DOUBLING
OF WEALTH OWNED BY THE TOP 1/10
OF 1%.
YOU TALK ABOUT CORPORATIONS AND
JOB CREATION.
ALL OF THE MAJOR CORPORATIONS IN
THE COUNTRY.
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY'VE BEEN DOING
IN THE LAST 30 YEARS?
YOU THINK THEY'VE BEEN CREATING
JOBS IN AMERICA?
NO, THEY'VE BEEN CREATING JOBS
IN CHINA AND MEXICO.
I'VE HELPED LEAD THE OPPOSITION
AGAINST EVERY ONE OF THESE
TERRIBLE TRADE PROGRAMS.
NAFTA AND PERMANENT NORMAL TRADE
RELATIONS WITH CHINA.
I DON'T BELIEVE AMERICAN WORKERS
SHOULD BE FORCED TO COMPETE
AGAINST DESPERATE PEOPLE AROUND
THE WORLD WHO ARE MAKING PENNIES
AN HOUR.
IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, I'M GOING
TO CHANGE THOSE TRADE POLICIES,
CORPORATIONS ARE GOING TO INVEST
IN AMERICA NOT IN CHINA.
I DO NOT BELIEVE IN TRICKLE DOWN
ECONOMICS.
I DO BELIEVE IF YOU GIVE TAX
BREAKS TO THE RICH AND LARGE
CORPORATIONS, SUDDENLY IT'S
GOING TO COME DOWN AND HELP
WORKING FAMILIES.
WHAT I DO BELIEVE IN, WE HAVE TO
PUT MORE MONEY INTO THE HANDS OF
WORKING FAMILIES.
HOW DO YOU DO THAT?
YOU RAISE THE MINIMUM WAGE TO A
LIVING WAGE.
I WAS IN FLINT MICHIGAN LAST
NIGHT, OUR INFRASTRUCTURE, IT'S
NOT JUST FLINT, WHERE KIDS ARE
DRINKING POISONED WATER.
IT'S ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY OUR
ROADS AND BRIDGES AND AIRPORTS.
WHY IS IT THAT THE HEALTHIEST
COUNTRY IN THE HISTORY OF THE
WORLD, WE'RE SUFFERING.
I DON'T THINK IT'S APPROPRIATE
THAT YOU HAVE MAJOR CORPORATIONS
MAKING BILLIONS OF DOLLARS A
YEAR, STASHING THEIR PROFITS IN
THE CAYMAN ISLANDS AND BERMUDA.
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY END UP PAYING
IN A GIVEN YEAR?
THEY DON'T PAY A NICKEL IN
TAXES.
I THINK WE SHOULD CREATE 15
MILLION JOBS OVER THE NEXT TEN
YEARS.
I THINK YOU AND I HAVE A
DIFFERENCE.
>> NEXT QUESTIONER IS A
PHYSICIAN -- DOCTOR.
>> I WANTED TO ASK YOU TO
ARTICULATE THE BENEFITS OF YOUR
HEALTH CARE PLAN OF THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE.
>> I HAVE BELIEVED MY ENTIRE
ADULT LIFE THAT HEALTH CARE IS A
RIGHT OF ALL PEOPLE.
I KNOW SECRETARY CLINTON IS
SUGGESTING THAT IF WE GO FROM
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT WHERE WE
ARE TODAY, CHILDREN WILL LOSE
THE CHIP PROGRAM.
ELDERLY PEOPLE LOSE MEDICARE.
THIS IS WHAT I BELIEVE, EVERY
OTHER COUNTRY ON EARTH AS YOU
MAY KNOW.
HAS A NATIONAL HEALTH PROGRAM OF
ONE KIND OR ANOTHER.
RIGHT NOW IN AMERICA, WE HAVE 29
MILLION PEOPLE WHO HAVE NO
HEALTH INSURANCE AT ALL.
WE HAVE MEDICARE, WHICH NEEDS
IMPROVEMENT.
WHAT I BELIEVE SIMPLY STATED IS
THAT PROGRAM SHOULD BE EXPANDED
TO ALL AMERICANS.
WHEN WE DO THAT, WE MAKE OUR
HEALTH CARE SYSTEM MUCH MORE
COST EFFECTIVE, WE END A WHOLE
LOT OF ADMINISTRATION.
IF YOU ARE A PHYSICIAN, YOU
SPEND HALF YOUR LIFE ARGUING
WITH THE INSURANCE COMPANIES.
AND YOU HAVE PEOPLE FILLING OUT
FORMS.
THE REASON THAT WE ARE SO MUCH
MORE EXPENSIVE THAN OTHER
COUNTRIES IS THAT WE HAVE HUGE
BUREAUCRACY IN THE HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM, AND WE PAY MUCH MUCH TOO
MUCH FOR PRESCRIPTION DRUGS.
TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, I
BELIEVE THAT WE MOVE IN A
MEDICARE -- TO A MEDICARE FOR
ALL HEALTH CARE SYSTEM.
MORE COST EFFECTIVE, COVERS
EVERYBODY.
>> ARE YOU WORRIED?
ARE YOU WORRIED ABOUT THE
TRANSITION, IS THAT THE GENESIS
OF YOUR QUESTION?
>> WHAT WOULD BE YOUR CONCERN?
>> WELL, I'VE HEARD A NUMBER OF
OTHER CANDIDATES SAY, WE'RE
GOING TO REPEAL OBAMA CARE,
WE'RE GOING TO DO THIS.
WE HAVE A CURRENT SYSTEM.
I DON'T SEE HOW YOU MAKE THE
LEAP FROM WHERE WE ARE TO WHERE
SOMEBODY ELSE WANTS TO.
SOMEBODY WHO HAS SPENT MY ENTIRE
LIFE FIGHTING FOR UNIVERSAL
HEALTH CARE, I ASSURE YOU THAT
WE'RE NOT GOING TO LEAVE ANYBODY
OUT.
THE POINT IS TO COVER MORE
PEOPLE.
ONE OF THE PROBLEMS, AND YOU CAN
DISAGREE WITH ME OR NOT.
WE TALK ABOUT 90% OF AMERICANS
HAVING INSURANCE.
THAT'S A GOOD THING.
WE MADE PROGRESS ON THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT.
BUT AS YOU WELL KNOW, WE GOT
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY WHO MAY HAVE HEALTH
INSURANCE, BUT THEY ARE UNDER
INSURED WITH HIGH DEDUCTIBLES
AND PAYMENTS.
LET ME MAKE A GUESS, THERE ARE
PEOPLE WHO WALK INTO YOUR OFFICE
WHO ARE MUCH SICKER THAN THEY
SHOULD HAVE BEEN, BECAUSE THEY
DIDN'T GO INTO YOUR OFFICE.
THAT'S PRETTY CRAZY STUFF, I
WANT EVERY AMERICAN TO BE ABLE
TO WALK INTO THE DOCTOR'S OFFICE
WHEN THEY SHOULD.
I DON'T WANT TO SEE ONE OUT OF
FIVE AMERICANS NOT BEING ABLE TO
AFFORD THE PRESCRIPTION DRUGS
THEIR DOCTORS PRESCRIBE.
I DON'T WANT TO SEE ELDERLY
PEOPLE CUT THEIR PILLS IN HALF,
AND I DON'T WANT TO SEE AT THE
SAME TIME, THE THREE MAJOR DRUG
COMPANIES IN THIS COUNTRY MAKE
$45 BILLION IN PROFITS, WHILE SO
MANY PEOPLE CANNOT AFFORD THEIR
MEDICINE.
>> ANOTHER HEALTH CARE TYPE
QUESTION.
CAN YOU NAME A SINGLE
CIRCUMSTANCE AT ANY POINT IN A
PREGNANCY AT WHICH POINT YOU
WOULD BE OKAY WITH ABORTION
BEING ILLEGAL.
>> I HAPPEN TO BELIEVE, AND LET
ME BE CLEAR -- I HAPPEN TO
BELIEVE THAT IT IS WRONG FOR THE
GOVERNMENT TO BE TELLING A WOMAN
WHAT TO DO WITH HER OWN BODY.
I BELIEVE, AND I UNDERSTAND
THERE ARE HONEST PEOPLE.
VERY A LOT OF FRIENDS.
THEY HOLD A DIFFERENT POINT OF
VIEW, AND I RESPECT THAT.
THAT IS MY POINT OF VIEW, I'LL
TELL YOU SOMETHING WHICH I DON'T
LIKE IN THIS DEBATE.
THERE ARE A WHOLE LOT OF PEOPLE
OUT THERE, WHO TELL ME THE
GOVERNMENT IS TERRIBLE,
GOVERNMENT IS AWFUL.
MY REPUBLICAN FRIENDS WANT TO
CUT SOCIAL SECURITY, MEDICAID.
SOMEHOW ON THIS ISSUE, THEY WANT
TO TELL EVERY WOMAN IN AMERICA
WHAT SHE SHOULD DO WITH HER
BODY.
THERE ARE SOME DEMOCRATS WHO SAY
AFTER FIVE MONTHS, WITH THE
EXCEPTION OF THE LIFE OF THE
MOTHER OR THE HEALTH OF THE BABY
THAT PERHAPS THAT'S SOMETHING TO
LOOK AT.
>> I'M VERY STRONGLY PROCHOICE,
THAT IS A DECISION TO BE MADE BY
THE WOMAN HER PHYSICIAN AND HER
FAMILY.
>> THE NEXT QUESTIONER IS
DANIEL, A COLLEGE STUDENT.
>> HOW DO YOU PLAN ON ENACTING
ALL OF THE LEGISLATIVE GOALS YOU
PROPOSE WITHOUT IMMENSE
CONGRESSIONAL INVOLVEMENT AND
SUPPORT.
IN OTHER WORDS, ARE YOU SOLELY
RELYING ON EXECUTIVE ACTIONS TO
PUSH YOUR LEGISLATION EVERYONE
AGENDA?
>> NO, I COULDN'T BE DOING THAT,
I MEAN, THAT'S UNCONSTITUTIONAL.
I BELIEVE THAT I WANT TO SEE
PUBLIC COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION FREE.
I WANT TO GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE
TO ALL PEOPLE.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE WOMEN HAVE
PAY EQUITY ON THE JOB.
AND I WANT TO DO A LOT OF OTHER
THINGS, I WILL ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION IN TWO WAYS.
I HAVE WORKED WITH REPUBLICANS
WHERE THERE HAS BEEN COMMON
GROUND FOR MANY YEARS.
A COUPLE YEARS AGO, I WAS THE
CHAIRMAN OF THE SENATE COMMITTEE
ON VETERANS AFFAIRS.
WORKS WITH JOHN McCAIN.
WE PUT TOGETHER THE MOST
COMPREHENSIVE VETERANS HEALTH
CARE BILL IN THE MODERN HISTORY
OF AMERICA, OKAY?
>> NUMBER ONE, I CAN WORK WITH
REPUBLICANS, HERE IS THE SECOND
POINT.
I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE WHO WILL
TELL YOU THIS.
AT THE END OF THE DAY, YOU HAVE
A CONGRESS TODAY WHERE TOO MANY
MEMBERS ARE WORRIED ABOUT
SECURING LARGE CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS FROM VERY, VERY
WEALTHY PEOPLE.
IN FACT ONE OF THE DIFFERENCES
BETWEEN SECRETARY CLINTON
COLLECTED A WHOLE LOT OF MONEY
FROM WALL STREET, I HAVE 5
MILLION INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS
AVERAGING $27 A PIECE.
I SAY THAT, NOT TO BRAG.
WELL, I'M BRAGGING.
THAT WHAT GOES ON IN WASHINGTON
NOW IS CONGRESS IS NOT LISTENING
TO YOU, AND THE NEEDS OF
ORDINARY PEOPLE.
CONGRESS IS LISTENING TO WALL
STREET, MULTINATIONAL
CORPORATIONS.
WHAT I HAVE SAID THROUGHOUT THIS
CAMPAIGN AND I REPEAT TONIGHT,
NO PRESIDENT, NOT BERNIE SANDERS
OR ANYBODY ELSE CAN DO IT ALONE.
TO FUNDAMENTALLY ANSWER YOUR
QUESTION, WHAT WE NEED ARE
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE, MANY OF WHOM
HAVE GIVEN UP ON THE POLITICAL
PROCESS IN DISGUST, MANY YOUNG
PEOPLE HAVE NOT BEEN INVOLVED IN
THE I POLITICAL PROCESS, WE NEED
THEM TO COME TOGETHER AND DEMAND
THAT WE HAVE A GOVERNMENT IN
THIS COUNTRY THAT REPRESENTS ALL
OF US.
>> THE FOLLOW-UP ON DANIEL, I
MEAN, YOU HAVE SOME BOLD
PRESCRIPTIONS FOR THE COUNTRY.
>> YES.
AND YOU'RE DEALING WITH A
REPUBLICAN CONGRESS.
SO HOW DO YOU CONVINCE THAT
REPUBLICAN CONGRESS TO DO
EXACTLY OPPOSITE OF WHAT THEY
BELIEVE?
>> IN TWO WAYS, IF I BECOME
PRESIDENT IT WILL MEAN THAT
THERE WILL BE A MASSIVE VOTER
TURNOUT.
THAT'S WHAT WE'RE SEEING IN
MAINE.
IN KANSAS, THEY BROKE THEIR
CAUCUS RECORD.
IT WILL MEAN THAT YOUNG PEOPLE
AND WORKING CLASS PEOPLE WILL
COME OUT IN LARGE NUMBERS.
NAIL HAVE A LOT LESS SEATS IN
THE HOUSE.
HERE IS THE POINT.
IF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE BEGIN TO
STAND UP AND FIGHT FOR THEIR
RIGHTS.
THERE'S OVERWHELMING SUPPORT IN
THIS COUNTRY TO RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE.
IF REPUBLICANS LOOK OUT AND
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE ARE ENGAGED,
YOU ARE GOING TO RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE OR YOU'LL LEARN
WHAT UNEMPLOYMENT IS, YOU KNOW
WHAT WILL HAPPEN?
MINIMUM WAGE WILL GO UP.
IF WOMEN BECOME MOBILIZED AND
SAY, SORRY, WE'RE TIRED OF
WORKING FOR $79 ON THE DOLLAR
THAN THE 1 DOLLAR FOR MEN.
WHETHER IT'S THE CIVIL RIGHTS
MOVEMENT, THE GAY MOVEMENT,
ALWAYS COMES FROM THE BOTTOM ON
UP.
THAT'S WHAT THIS CAMPAIGN IS
ABOUT.
MOBILIZING MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
MANY.
>> WHO'S YOUR FAVORITE
REPUBLICAN?
>>.
>> I'LL TELL YOU SOMETHING
FUNNY, I HAVE FAVORITE
REPUBLICANS, PEOPLE I WORK WITH.
IF I TELL YOU, IT WILL BE A
DISSERVICE TO THAT PERSON.
>> I WANT TO KEEP THIS ANSWER A
LITTLE TIGHT.
WE'RE RUNNING UP AGAINST TIME.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, WELCOME TO
DETROIT.
>> THANK YOU.
>> I WONDER IF YOU CAN ELABORATE
FOR US, THE POLICIES YOU SUPPORT
TO HELP TO REBUILD AND IMPROVE
THE INFRASTRUCTURES IN CITIES
LIKE DETROIT AND FLINT?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
LOOK IN THE WEALTHIEST COUNTRY
IN THE HISTORY OF THE WORLD, WE
SHOULD NOT BE HAVING A FLINT
MICHIGAN.
THAT IS BEYOND DISGRACEFUL.
IN MY STATE OF VERMONT, WE HAVE
BRIDGES WHICH ARE IN DESPERATE
NEED OF REPAIR.
ROADS ALL OVER THIS COUNTRY ARE
FALLING APART WE HAVE A RAIL
SYSTEM WHICH AT ONE POINT USED
TO BE THE BEST IN THE WORLD, NO
LONGER IS.
WE HAVE GOT TO TRANSFORM OUR
ENERGY SYSTEM AWAY FROM FOSSIL
FUEL SO WE CAN EFFECTIVELY
COMBAT CLIMATE COMPLAINING.
WHAT I HAVE PROPOSED IS TO
EXPEND A TRILLION DOLLARS OVER A
FIVE-YEAR PERIOD TO MAKE SURE
THAT STATES AND CITIES
THROUGHOUT THIS COUNTRY HAVE THE
RESOURCES THEY NEED TO REBUILD
OUR CRUMBLING INFRASTRUCTURE.
THE AMERICAN SOCIETY OF CIVIL
ENGINEERS TELLS US WE NEED EVEN
MORE.
YOU KNOW WHAT HAPPENS WHEN WE
INVEST A TRILLION DOLLARS IN
ROADS AND BRIDGES AND WATER
SYSTEMS?
AND OUR EDUCATIONAL SYSTEMS?
WE'RE GOING TO CREATE 13 MILLION
JOBS OVER A FIVE-YEAR PERIOD.
>> VERY QUICKLY, YOUR SENIOR
AIDE SAID YOU MAY BE OFFERED IF
YOU WEREN'T THE NOMINEE, THE VP
SLOT, WOULD YOU TAKE IT?
>> WE'RE TALKING ABOUT RUNNING
THIS CAMPAIGN TO WIN TO BECOME
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
NOT TALKING ABOUT --
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU
VERY MUCH.
>> SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
>> WHEN WE COME BACK, SECRETARY
OF STATE HILLARY CLINTON JOINS
US HERE AS OUR SPECIAL EDITION
OF SPECIAL REPORT CONTINUES LIVE
FROM DETROIT.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THIS SPECIAL
EDITION OF SPECIAL REPORT, A
DEMOCRATIC TOWN HALL LIVE FROM
DETROIT.
PLEASE JOIN ME IN WELCOMING
FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE
HILLARY CLINTON.
>> HOW ARE YOU?
>> GOOD TO SEE YOU.
>> GREAT TO SEE YOU.
>>.
>> HI, MAYOR.
>> HI, DEBBIE.
>> THANK YOU FOR JOINING US.
>> THANK YOU FOR HAVING US AND.
>> I WANT TO START OUT WITH THE
BREAKING NEWS, MICHAEL BLOOMBERG
DECIDING NOT TO MAKE AN
INDEPENDENT RUN THIS YEAR.
YOUR THOUGHTS ON THAT.
>> I HAVE THE GREATEST RESPECT
FOR MIKE BLOOMBERG WE WORKED
TOGETHER DURING THE EIGHT YEARS
I WAS IN THE SENATE.
HE HAS TO MAKE HIS OWN
DECISIONS.
I LOOK FORWARD TO CONTINUING TO
WORK WITH HIM, FINDING WAYS HE
CAN SHOW LEADERSHIP.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU QUESTIONS
THAT HAVEN'T COME UP, ONE OF
THEM IS ABOUT LIBYA, YOU WERE
THE LEADING VOICE IN THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION FOR THE
INTERVENTION.
AN INTERVENTION THAT TOPPLED
KHADAFI'S DICTATORSHIP.
AND IT'S IMPORTANT TO POINT OUT
THERE WERE NO U.S. CASUALTIES,
MINIMAL RESOURCES EXPENDED.
LIBYA NOW IS IN TOTAL CHAOS.
THE U.N. REPRESENTATIVE SAID
THIS, ISIS HAD QUOTE TAKEN
ADVANTAGE OF THE POLITICAL AND
SECURITY VACUUM AND IS EXPANDING
TO THE WEST, EAST, AND SOUTH,
WHILE LIBYA'S FINANCIAL
RESOURCES ARE DWINDLING.
THE NETWORKS ARE BOOMING.
IF THE INTERVENTION OF LIBYA WAS
ONE OF YOUR GREAT FOREIGN POLICY
SUCCESSES.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT IT IN
CONTEXT, AND LET'S REMEMBER WHAT
WAS GOING ON AT THE TIME.
IT WAS DURING THE SO CALLED ARAB
SPRING, PEOPLE IN LIBYA WHO HAD
BEEN LIVING UNDER THE
DICTATORSHIP OF GADHAFI FOR 42
YEARS WERE RISING UP.
AND HE, AS WE ALL CAN REMEMBER,
WAS A RUTHLESS DICTATOR WITH
AMERICAN BLOOD ON HIS HANDS.
RONALD REAGAN TRIED TO TAKE HIM
OUT BECAUSE OF THE DANGER HE
POSED 37 AND ONCE IT BECAME
CLEAR TO HIM THAT THE PEOPLE OF
LIBYA WERE TRYING TO GET MORE
FREEDOM AND HOPEFULLY A BETTER
FUTURE, HE BASICALLY SAID HE WAS
GOING TO HUNT THEM DOWN LIKE
COCKROACHES.
THE EUROPEANS WHO HAD A LOT MORE
OF A CONNECTION WITH LIBYA,
GOING BACK MR. DECADES WERE
ABSOLUTELY INTENT UPON WORKING
WITH US WITH NATO.
FOR THE FIRST TIME, ARAB
COUNTRIES STEPPED UP AND SAID WE
WILL WORK WITH NATO, THIS MAN
HAS PAID FOR EFFORTS TO
UNDERMINUS, ASSASSINATE OUR
LEADERS, ALL AROUND BADS
CHARACTER.
WE DID JOIN WITH OUR EUROPEAN
AND ARAB PARTNERS.
HE WAS OVERTHROWN.
LET'S REMEMBER THAT THE LIBYAN
PEOPLE HAVE VOTED TWICE IN FREE
AND FAIR ELECTIONS FOR MODERATE
LEADERS TRYING TO GET THEMSELVES
TO A BETTER FUTURE.
WHAT HAS HAPPENED IS DEEPLY
REGRETTABLE.
THERE HAVE BEEN FORCES COMING
FROM THE OUTSIDE, INTERNAL
SQUABBLES THAT HAVE LED TO THE
INSTABILITY THAT HAS GIVEN
TERRORIST GROUPS INCLUDING ISIS
A FOOT HOLD IN SOME PARTS OF
LIBYA.
I THINK IT'S FAIR TO SAY HOWEVER
IF THERE HAD NOT BEEN THAT
INTERVENTION TO GO AFTER
GADHAFI, WE WOULD BE LOOKING AT
SOMETHING MUCH MORE RESEMBLING
SYRIA NOW, THAN WHAT WE FACED IN
LIBYA.
>> THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO SAY
LIBYA IS A FAILED STATE AND
THEY'RE CONCERNED ABOUT ISIS
GETTING POWER.
WOULD YOU PUT U.S. TROOPS ON THE
GROUND IN LIBYA?
>> NO.
>> TO PREVENT ISIS FROM GAIN A
FOOTHOLD?
>> NOT U.S. COMBAT TROOPS.
WE ARE USING SPECIAL FORCES,
USING AIR STRIKES TO GO AFTER
ISIS LEADERS.
I WAB THE TO STRESS THE POINT I
WAS MAKING.
LEAVING A DICTATOR IN PLACE,
LIKE THE IRANIANS AND RUSSIANS
HAVE DONE WITH ASSAD.
WHERE WE HAVE AT LEAST 250,000
PEOPLE KILLED, LIBYA, THE
NUMBERS ARE MEN SCHOOL IN
COMPARISON ABOUT 1500 LAST YEAR.
THERE IS A KWON CERTIFICATED
EFFORT, THE U.N. AND OTHERS ARE
REALLY WORKING HARD TO TRY TO
UNIFY THE DIFFERENT ELEMENTS
WITHIN THE COUNTRY.
SO IT'S BEEN A COUPLE YEARS,
THEY HAVEN'T BEEN AS SUCCESSFUL
AS THEIR NEIGHBOR TUNISIA, THEY
ARE ATTEMPTING TO MOVE FORWARD.
WE OUGHT TO BE SUPPORTING THEM,
NOT ONLY WITH SPECIAL FORCES AND
AIR STRIKES AGAINST TERRORISTS,
BUT HELPING THEM SECURE THEIR
BORDERS AND DEAL WITH SOME OF
THE INTERNAL CHALLENGES THEY
FACE.
>> I WANT TO ASK YOU ABOUT A
QUESTION I ASKED SENATOR
SANDERS.
>> DO YOU THINK A CHILD SHOULD
HAVE ANY LEGAL RIGHTS OR
PROTECTIONS BEFORE ITS BORN.
DO YOU THINK THERE SHOULD NOT BE
ANY RESTRICTIONS ON ANY
ABORTIONS ON ANY STAGE IN A
PREGNANCY.
>> LET ME PUT THIS IN CONTEXT.
IT'S AN IMPORTANT QUESTION.
RIGHT NOW THE SUPREME COURT IS
CONSIDERING A DECISION THAT
WOULD SHUT DOWN A LOT OF THE
OPTIONS FOR WOMEN IN TEXAS, AND
THERE HAVE BEEN OTHER
LEGISLATURES THAT HAVE TAKEN
SIMILAR STEPS TO TRY TO RESTRICT
A WOMAN'S RIGHT TO OBTAIN AN
ABORTION.
UNDER ROE VERSUS WADE, WOMEN
HAVE THIS RIGHT TO MAKE THIS
HIGHLY PERSONAL DECISION WITH
THEIR FAMILY IN ACCORDANCE WITH
THEIR FAITH, WITH THEIR DOCTOR.
IT'S NOT MUCH OF A RIGHT IF IT
IS TOTALLY LIMITED AND
CONSTRAINED.
I THINK WE HAVE TO CONTINUE TO
STAND UP FOR A WOMAN'S RIGHT TO
MAKE THESE DECISIONS AND TO
DEFEND PLANNED PARENTHOOD, WHICH
DOES AN ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF
FOOTWORK ACROSS OUR COUNTRY.
>> JUST TO BE CLEAR.
NO EXCEPTIONS?
>> I HAVE BEEN ON RECORD IN
FAVOR OF A LATE PREGNANCY
REGULATION THAT WOULD HAVE
EXCEPTIONS FOR THE LIFE AND
HEALTH OF THE MOTHER.
I OBJECT TO THE RECENT EFFORT IN
CONGRESS TO PASS A LAW SAYING
AFTER 20 WEEKS, YOU KNOW, NO
SUCH EXCEPTIONS, BECAUSE
ALTHOUGH THESE ARE RARE, THEY
SOMETIMES ARISE IN THE MOST
COMPLEX DIFFICULT MEDICAL
SITUATION.
>> FETAL MALFORMITIES?
>> AND THREATS TO THE WOMAN'S
HEALTH.
>> SURE.
>> SO I THINK IT IS UNDER ROE
VERSUS WADE.
IT IS APPROPRIATE TO SAY IN
THESE CIRCUMSTANCES, SO LONG AS
THERE'S AN EXCEPTION FOR THE
LIFE AND HEALTH OF THE MOTHER.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I KNOW YOU
HAVE SAID YOU'RE NOT WORRIED AT
ALL ABOUT WHAT YOU CALL THE
SECURITY REVIEW OF YOUR PRIVATE
SERVER AND THE PERSONAL E-MAILS
DURING YOUR TIME AS SECRETARY.
THE FBI INVESTIGATION IS HANGING
OVER YOUR CAMPAIGN.
THERE ARE DEMOCRATS WHO ARE
WORRIED ABOUT ANOTHER SHOE
DROPPING, POTENTIALLY WITH THE
WORD THAT THERE'S IMMUNITITY FOR
BRIAN PAGLIANO.
YOU WERE ASKED A QUESTION ABOUT
THE DEBATE WLFT NIGHT.
I'D LIKE TO ASK YOU A FEW QUICK
QUESTIONS ON THIS, I'VE HEARD
OTHERS SAY THAT NEITHER YOU NOR
YOUR LAWYERS HAVE BEEN APPRISED
THAT YOU ARE A TARGET OF THE
INVESTIGATION.
IS THAT TRUE?
>> ABSOLUTELY TRUE.
HAVE YOU OR YOUR LAWYERS BEEN
APPRISED THAT ANY MEMBERS OF
YOUR FORMER OR CURRENT STAFF ARE
DARG ETS OF THE INVESTIGATION?
>> ABSOLUTELY NOT.
>> AT THE TIME YOU AND YOUR
STAFF DELETED 32,000 E-MAILS,
WERE YOU AWARE THAT THE SERVER
WAS GOING TO BE SOUGHT AS
EVIDENCE BY FEDERAL AUTHORITIES?
>> NO, LET ME COLLAR PHI THIS,
THERE'S MISINFORMATION GOING ON
AROUND HERE.
LET ME START WITH THE BASIC
FACTS.
I HAVE SAID, IT WASN'T THE BEST
CHOICE TO USE A PERSONAL E-MAIL.
IT WAS A MISTAKE, HOWEVER, I AM
NOT ALONE IN THAT.
MANY PEOPLE IN THE GOVERNMENT
PAST AND CURRENT HAVE ON
OCCASION OR AS A PRACTICE DOES
THE SAME.
NOTHING I SENT WAS MARKED
CLASSIFIED OR THAT I RECEIVED
WAS MARKED CLASSIFIED.
AND SPECIFICALLY, WITH RESPECT
TO YOUR QUESTION, EVERY
GOVERNMENT OFFICIAL AND THIS IS
A LEGAL THEORY, NOT JUST A
THEORY, THAT'S A LEG RULE, GETS
TO CHOOSE WHAT IS PERSONAL AND
WHAT IS IT OFFICIAL.
WHAT WE TURNED OVER WERE MORE
THAN 30,000 E-MAILS THAT I
ASSUMED WERE ALREADY IN THE
GOVERNMENT SYSTEM, BRET.
BECAUSE THEY WERE SENT TO
STATE.GOV ADDRESSES.
>> SURE, BUT THERE WERE SOME
THAT WERE JUST RECENTLY
DISCOVERED AND TURNED OVER --
>> NO, THAT WAS IN THE STATE
DEPARTMENT, NOT ME.
>> THE STATE DEPARTMENT HAS
REDACTED AND DECLARED 2101 OF
YOUR WORK E-MAILS CLASSIFIED.
44 CLASSIFIED AS SECRET, 22
CLASSIFIED AS TON SECRET.
I DID NOT E-MAIL ANY CLASSIFIED
MATERIAL TO ANYONE ON MY E-MAIL.
THERE IS NO CLASSIFIED MATERIAL.
SO CAN WE SAY DEFINITIVELY THAT
THAT STATEMENT'S NOT ACCURATE?
>> NO, YOU CAN'T.
HERE'S WHAT HAPPENS, THE STATE
DEPARTMENT HAS A PROCESS FOR
DETERMINING WHAT IS OR ISN'T
CLASSIFIED, IF THEY DETERMINE IT
IS, THEY MARK IT AS CLASSIFIED.
>> WHO DECIDES --
>> THE STATE DEPARTMENT DECIDES.
>> WHAT ABOUT YOU WHEN YOU'RE
TYPING AN E-MAIL.
>> NO, THE STATE DEPARTMENT
DECIDES WHAT IS --
>> AND LET ME GO A STEP FURTHER
HERE, I WILL REITERATE, IT'S A
FACT, NOTHING I SENT OR RECEIVED
WAS MARKED CLASSIFIED.
NOW, WHAT HAPPENS WHEN YOU ASKED
OR WHEN YOU ARE ASKED TO MAKE
INFORMATION PUBLIC, IS THAT IT'S
REVIEWED AND DIFFERENT AGENCIES
COME IN WITH THEIR OPINIONS?
AS YOU KNOW, JUST RECENTLY,
COLIN POWELL'S E-MAILS WERE
RETROACTIVELY CLASSIFIED FOR
MORE THAN 10 YEARS AGO.
AS HE SAID, THAT WAS AN
ABSURDITY.
I CANNOT AGREE MORE.
>> IT CONTAINED INFORMATION THAT
SHOULD BE CLASSIFIED AT ANY
TIME.
IT SHOULDN'T BE NOW OAR THEN.
IT'S NOT -- IT SHOULDN'T HAVE
BEEN CLASSIFIED?
>> WHAT I'M SAYING IS, IT WASN'T
AT THE TIME, IF YOU -- LET'S
TAKE MARY SMITH WHO HAS SOME
INFORMATION IN THE GOVERNMENT,
AND SHE IS FOIA, FREEDOM OF
INFORMATION ACT.
GIVE US YOUR INFORMATION, YOUR
E-MAILS, MEMOS, WHATEVER IT
MIGHT HAVE BEEN.
THAT GOES THROUGH A PROCESS,
EVEN THOUGH THE AGENCY SHE WORKS
IN, HAS SAID NONE OF THIS IS
CLASSIFIED, OTHERS START TO HAVE
A CHANCE TO WEIGH-IN.
SO OTHERS MIGHT SAY, YOU KNOW,
THAT WASN'T AT THE TIME, BUT NOW
WITH CIRCUMSTANCES, WE DON'T
WANT TO RELEASE IT, SO,
THEREFORE, WE HAVE TO CLASSIFY
IT, I'VE ASKED, AND I ECHO COLIN
POWELL IN THIS, RELEASE IT, AND
ONCE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE SEE IT,
THEY WILL KNOW HOW ABSURD THIS
IS.
COLIN POWELL AND I ARE EXACTLY
ON THE SAME PAGE.
>> WE WANT TO GET TO AUDIENCE
QUESTIONS, WE HAVE A COUPLE MORE
THINGS THERE.
LET'S GO TO A QUESTION FROM A
DONOR OF THE UNITED WAY.
>> I LOVE THE UNITED WAY.
>> WELCOME TO DETROIT, REALLY
GLAD YOU'RE HERE OPINION.
>> HOW DO YOU ANTICIPATE GETTING
ANYTHING DONE IN WASHINGTON,
WHEN COMPROMISE IS A BAD WORD?
>> YOU KNOW, THIS IS ONE OF THE
MOST QUESTIONS FOR ANYONE IN
WASHINGTON.
I WILL TELL YOU WHAT I HAVE DONE
AND WHAT I INTEND TO DO.
WHEN I WAS FIRST LADY, SENATOR,
SECRETARY OF STATE I WORKED
CLOSELY WITH THE REPUBLICANS.
AFTER WE FAILED TO GET HEALTH
CARE DONE, I TURNED AROUND AND
WORKED WITH DEMOCRATS AND
REPUBLICANS AND WORKED ON THE
CHIP PROGRAM.
I ALSO WORKED WITH FOSTER CARE
AND ADOPTION, WITH ONE OF THE
MOST PARTISAN REPUBLICANS THEN
IN THE CONGRESS, TOM DeLAY, HE
CARED ABOUT FOSTER KIDS, I KNEW
THAT, I CALLED HIM UP.
I SAID, CONGRESSMAN WOULD YOU
WORK WITH ME TO REFORM THE
ADOPTION AND FOSTER CARE SYSTEM?
I SAID, WHAT DO YOU WANT TO DO?
COME TO THE WHITE HOUSE, LET'S
HAVE A MEETING, WE WERE ABLE TO
FIND COMMON GROUND ON THE ISSUE.
I GOT TO THE SENATE, I STARTED
WORKING WITH PEOPLE WHO HAD BEEN
SOME OF THE BIGGEST CRITICS AND
OPPONENTS OF MY HUSBAND'S
PRESIDENCY.
WE FOUND COMMON GROUND.
AND WHEN I BECAME SECRETARY OF
STATE, I DID THE SAME.
NOW, I'M NOT SAYING THIS IS
EASY, BUT AS MY GOOD FRIEND
DEBBIE DINGELL KNOWS, YOU HAVE
TO WORK AT IT EVERY SINGLE DAY,
YOU HAVE TO GET UP, TRY TO FIND
RELATIONSHIPS, YOU HAVE TO BUILD
ON IT, FIND COMMON GROUND.
AND THAT IS WHAT I WILL DO, NOW,
THE OTHER THING I WILL SAY,
WHICH IS A LITTLE BIT FUNNY, IS
WHEN I'M NOT RUNNING FOR
SOMETHING, THE REPUBLICANS SAY
REALLY NICE THINGS ABOUT ME.
AND I HAVE LIKE A WHOLE ARCHIVE
OF THOSE COMMENTS.
BECAUSE I DID WORK WITH THEM,
AND I WILL WORK WITH THEM 37 I
WILL STAND MY GROUND, I WILL
DISAGREE WITH SOME OF THE THINGS
THEY WANT TO DO.
I THINK YOUR POINT IS SO
IMPORTANT.
OUR FOUNDERS CREATED A SYSTEM
WHERE THEY MADE CLEAR NO HUMAN
BEING HAS ALL THE ANSWERS, YOU
HAVE TO WORK TOGETHER.
THEY HAD SOME REALLY INTENSE
DISAGREEMENTS, BUT THEY KEPT
WORKING UNTIL THEY COULD COME TO
SOME COMPROMISE.
COMPROMISE IS NOT A DIRTY WORD.
IT'S THE WAY DEMOCRACY HAS TO
WORK, THAT'S WHAT I WILL DO.
>> THANK YOU, DOUGLAS FOR THE
QUESTION.
I ASKED THIS OF SENATOR SANDERS,
WHO IS YOUR FAVORITE REPUBLICAN.
>> I WORKED WITH SO MANY OF
THEM, THE WOMEN IN THE SENATE
BECAME GOOD FRIENDS, BOTH
DEMOCRATS AND REPUBLICANS, AND
WE WORKED ON A LOT OF ISSUES.
SUSAN COLLINS FROM MAINE, FOR
EXAMPLE.
BUT I ALSO WORKED WITH JOHN
McCAIN, HE AND I JOINED TOGETHER
TO RAISE MONEY FOR THE
REHABILITATION HOSPITAL IN SAN
ANTONIO FOR RETURNING VETERANS.
AND WE ALSO JOINED WITH OTHERS
TO WORK ON SOME IMPORTANT
ISSUES.
SO I HAVE GOOD RELATIONS WITH A
LOT OF REPUBLICANS.
I HESITATE TO MENTION ANY MORE
NAMES, IT WILL PROBABLY HURT
THEM, AND I DO WANT TO WORK WITH
THEM.
>> THAT'S WHAT SENATOR SANDERS
SAID.
LET'S GO TO ANOTHER QUESTION.
>> BEING AN EDUCATION POLICY
Ph.D. CANDIDATE, I WORRY ABOUT
THE CONFLUENCE OF POVERTY AND
WHAT THAT CAN YIELD.
I KNOW IN 1994 YOU SUPPORTED THE
CRIME BILL, I WOULD LIKE TO KNOW
YOUR REASONS FOR SUPPORTING IT,
AND IF THAT BILL WERE ON THE
TABLE TODAY, WOULD YOU STILL BE
IN SUPPORT.
>> I THINK THAT'S -- AS WE SAID
LAST NIGHT, BOTH SENATOR SANDERS
AND I SUPPORTED IT.
I DID HAVE A VOTE, HE SUPPORTED
IT.
WHY DID WE DO THAT?
BECAUSE THERE WAS A VERY SERIOUS
CRIME CHALLENGE.
EVEN AN EPIDEMIC IN A LOT OF
COMMUNITIES IN OUR COUNTRY AT
THAT TIME.
SO THERE WERE SOME POSITIVE
THINGS THAT WERE IN THE CRIME
BILL TO TRY TO DEAL WITH THE
THREAT OF CRIME THAT REALLY HAD
SO MANY SERIOUS CONSEQUENCES FOR
PEOPLE ACROSS OUR COUNTRY.
BUT AS MY HUSBAND SAID, LAST
SUMMER, AT THE NAACP, THERE WERE
PROBLEMS THAT WERE SOLVED, BUT
THERE WERE MISTAKES MADE IN THAT
BILL.
AND ONE OF THEM WAS, ALTHOUGH
IT'S JUST ABOUT THE FEDERAL
SYSTEM, IT SET OFF A CHAIN
REACTION WHERE MORE AND MORE
PEOPLE ENDED UP BEING
INCARCERATED WHO IN MY OPINION
SHOULD NOT HAVE BEEN.
LOW LEVEL OFFENDERS, NONVIOLENT
OFFENDERS.
WE HAVE TO RIP AWAY THE SCHOOL
TO PRISON PIPELINE AND REPLACE
IT WITH A CRADLE TO COLLEGE
PIPELINE.
AND IN ORDER TO DO THAT, WE NEED
A COMPREHENSIVE APPROACH.
SO, YES, WE HAVE TO IMPROVE THE
CRIMINAL JUSTICE SYSTEM, WE HAVE
TO DIVERT PEOPLE FROM JAIL AND
PRISON.
BUT WE ALSO HAVE TO PROVIDE
EDUCATIONAL OPPORTUNITIES,
PARTICULARLY FOR DISADVANTAGED
KIDS FROM THE EARLIEST AGES,
WHICH IS WHY I SUPPORT QUALITY
EARLY CHILDHOOD EDUCATION,
UNIVERSAL PREKINDERGARTEN
EDUCATION.
WE HAVE TO WORK TO REVERSE
TERRIBLE SITUATIONS LIKE WHAT
YOU HAVE RIGHT NOW IN THE
DETROIT PUBLIC SCHOOLS.
I KNOW THIS IS SOMETHING THE
MAYOR CARES DEEPLY ABOUT.
HAVE YOU LITTLE CHILDREN IN
CLASSROOMS INFESTED WITH MOLD
AND RODENTS, THAT IS
UNACCEPTABLE, INDEFENSIBLE.
I'M CALLING ON THE GOVERNOR TO
RETURN CONTROL OF THE DETROIT
PUBLIC SCHOOLS TO THE PEOPLE OF
DETROIT.
AND --
>> THANK YOU. YOU, ALTON.
>> AND I WANT TO FINISH WITH
JUST ONE ADDITIONAL COMMENT
BECAUSE YOU ALLUDED TO IT.
IT IS ABSOLUTELY IMPERATIVE
THAT WE MAKE COLLEGE
AFFORDABLE.
I HAVE A PLAN TO DO THAT,
DEBT-FREE TUITION.
MORE HELP FOR NON-TUITION
COSTS SO MORE YOUNG PEOPLE
CAN ACTUALLY START COLLEGE
AND COMPLETE COLLEGE.
[[INAUDIBLE] SHOUTING]
>> I WOULD BE GLAD TO TELL
YOU, ABSOLUTELY.
IT'S DIFFERENT FROM SENATOR
SANDERS.
IF I HAVE GOT TIME.
DO I HAVE TIME?
>> YOU HAVE TIME.
>> OKAY.
THIS IS EXCITING.
GOOD.
ALL RIGHT.
HERE'S WHAT IT IS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I CALL IT THE NEW COLLEGE
COMPACT BECAUSE EVERYBODY IS
GOING TO HAVE TO DO THEIR
PART.
I WANT DEBT-FREE TUITION.
YOU WILL NEVER HAVE TO
BORROW MONEY TO ATTEND A
PUBLIC COLLEGE OR
UNIVERSITY.
THE MONEY THAT YOU WILL NEED
WILL BE PROVIDED IF YOU
CANNOT AFFORD TO GO TO
COLLEGE.
AND, RIGHT NOW, GIVEN THE
COSTS, THAT COVERS MOST
PEOPLE, EXCEPT WEALTHY
PEOPLE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SO, WHAT I AM SAYING IS THAT
WE WILL FUND DEBT-FREE
TUITION.
YOU WON'T HAVE TO BORROW
MONEY.
IT'S DIFFERENT FROM SENATOR
SANDERS IN THIS REGARD.
I THINK THE COSTS ARE TOO
HIGH IN COLLEGE AND
UNIVERSITY.
TUITION HAS GONE UP 42% OVER
THE LAST 10 YEARS.
I DON'T UNDERSTAND HOW THAT
CAN BE JUSTIFIED.
SO, WHEN SENATOR SANDERS
SAYS "FREE COLLEGE" WITH NO
PRESSURE ON THE UNIVERSITIES
AND COLLEGES TO LOWER THEIR
COSTS.
I THINK THAT WILL ONLY MAKE
IT MORE EXPENSIVE.
SO I'M REQUIRING THE
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TAKE A HARD LOOK AT WHAT
THEY ARE CHARGING.
AND IF IT'S NOT RELATE TO DO
A YOUNG PERSON GETTING A
DEGREE, THAT WILL LEAD TO A
JOB, DON'T CHARGE THE
STUDENT.
YOU WILL NOT BE ABLE TO DO
THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SECONDLY, I EXPECT STATES TO
START REINVESTING IN HIGHER
EDUCATION.
WE HAVE ENOUGH PRISONS.
THEY DON'T NEED TO BE
BUILDING MORE PRISONS.
THEY NEED TO BE INVESTING IN
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES,
SO THEY WILL DO THEIR PART.
AND I HAVE THE FUNDING
WORKED OUT SO THAT WE'RE
ABLE TO DO THIS.
SENATOR SANDERS RELIES, IN
ORDER TO GET WHAT HE CALLED
FREE EDUCATION ON REPUBLICAN
AS WELL AS DEMOCRATIC
GOVERNORS PUTTING IN
$23 BILLION A YEAR.
FRANKLY, I'M SKEPTICAL OF
THAT.
SO I THINK WE CAN GET TO
WHERE WE NEED TO GET TO,
PLUS REDUCE STUDENT DEBT.
NOT ONLY YOU HAVE REFINANCED
YOUR STUDENT DEBT, BUT ALSO
MAKE IT POSSIBLE FOR YOU TO
PAY IT BACK AS A PERCENTAGE
OF YOUR INCOME, WHICH IS
WHAT I GOT TO DO BECAUSE I
BORROWED MONEY TO GO TO LAW
SCHOOL AND I WASN'T STUCK
WITH THE HIGH INTEREST RATES
THAT TOO MANY ARE TODAY.
>> THANK YOU, SECRETARY.
WE DO WANT TO TAKE SOME
OTHER QUESTIONS HERE.
BUT, BY THE WAY, THE
QUESTION I ASKED SENATOR
SANDERS WAS, YOU KNOW U THE
CONCERN ABOUT THE NATIONAL
DEBT AND HOW YOU PAY FOR
EVERYTHING.
>> MY NUMBERED A UP, AND MY
NUMBERS ARE CONNECTED TO
SOURCES OF FUNDING THAT WE
CAN COUNT ON AND PEOPLE HAVE
LOOKED AT MY PLANS AND
SENATOR SANDERS.
MINE COST ABOUT $100 BILLION
A YEAR.
AND THAT IS ALL PAID FOR,
BECAUSE I THINK IT WOULD BE
A MISTAKE TO RUN UP THE
NATIONAL DEBT, TO RUN UP THE
SIZE OF GOVERNMENT BY 30%,
40%, 50% WITHOUT KNOWING HOW
WE ARE GOING TO PAY FOR IT.
>> LET ME BRING IN
AUTOMOTIVE LAB TECHNICIAN
FRANK ROTH.
>> I HAVE A 29-YEAR-OLD SON
WHO PURCHASED HEALTH
INSURANCE THROUGH THE
HEALTHCARE.GOV WEBSITE.
HIS POLICY COST $240 A MONTH
WHEN HE FILED FEDERAL TAXES
THIS YEAR HE OWED THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT $241
BECAUSE THE TAX BREAK HE GOT
FROM THE WEBSITE WAS
OVERESTIMATED.
WHAT WILL YOU DO TO MAKE
HEALTH INSURANCE MORE
AFFORDABLE FOR SOMEONE LIKE
HIM?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, WE
HAVE TO GO AT THE MISTAKES
THAT YOU JUST REFERENCED
THAT YOUR SON HAS
EXPERIENCED.
I HAVE HEARD ABOUT THOSE.
I'M A BIG SUPPORTER AND
DEFENDER OF THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT BECAUSE I THINK IT
HAS GIVEN US THE CHANCE TO
DO WHAT I HAVE WORKED FOR,
WHAT SENATOR SANDERS
BELIEVES IN TO GET TO
UNIVERSAL COVERAGE.
WE ARE AT 90%'
WE HAVE 10% TO GO.
I'M GOING TO GET THE COSTS
DOWN.
WE ARE GETTING TO GET
OUT-OF-POCKET COSTS DOWN.
WE ARE GOING TO GET
DEDUCTIBLES DOWN.
WE ARE GOING TO REQUIRE MORE
FREE SERVICES WITHIN THE
BENEFIT PACKAGE.
AND WE ARE GOING TO GO RIGHT
AFTER PRESCRIPTION DRUG
COSTS.
ALL OF THAT SHOULD HELP
SON AND EVERYBODY ELSE.
HERE'S SOMETHING ELSE I WANT
TO DO.
WE NEED MORE COMPETITION IN
THE HEALTHCARE MARKETPLACE.
ONE OF THE IDEAS UNDER THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT WAS TO
ENCOURAGE NONPROFITS TO GET
IN TO PROVIDING HEALTH
INSURANCE.
YOU KNOW, BLUE SHIELD, BLUE
CROSS USED TO BE NONPROFITS
AND THEY MADE A PERFECTLY
GOOD -- DON'T CALL THAT
PROFIT BECAUSE THEY WERE
NONPROFIT BUT THEY MADE
ENOUGH MONEY TO KEEP GOING
AND IT TO PAY THEIR
EXECUTIVES AND EVERYBODY
ELSE WHO WORKED THERE THEN
THEY ALL BECAME FOR PROFIT.
WE NEED TO GET MORE
COMPANIES MORE NONPROFITS TO
FILL THIS SPACE.
THE ONES THAT KNEW WHAT THEY
WERE DOING PROVIDED GOOD
SERVICES.
A LOT OF THEM HAVE FAILED
BECAUSE THEY DIDN'T HAVE THE
RIGHT SUPPORT.
I WANT MORE COMPETITION AND
I WANT COMPETITION FROM
NONPROFITS SO THAT WE CAN
REALLY GIVE THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES A LOT OF PRESSURE
TO GET THE COSTS DOWN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> OKAY.
SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU ARE
NOT WINNINGtD z IN THESE STATES
WITH MILLENNIALS AND SOME
ALSO WITH YOUNG WOMEN.
WHY IS SENATOR SANDERS DOING
BETTER?
>> WELL, LOOK, I THINK IT'S
GREAT THAT BOTH OF US ARE
BRINGING A LOT OF PEOPLE
INTO THE PROCESS.
AND I APPLAUD SENATOR
SANDERS FOR REALLY GETTING A
VERY BIG TURNOUT AMONG YOUNG
PEOPLE.
I LOVE TO SEE THAT.
AND I'M GOING TO CONTINUE TO
ATTRACT YOUNG PEOPLE.
I'M PROUD OF THOSE WHO ARE
SUPPORTING ME.
AND I TELL YOUNG PEOPLE ALL
THE TIME, YOU MAY NOT BE FOR
ME NOW, BUT I AM FOR YOU
REGARDLESS AND I'M GOING TO
KEEP WORKING TO TRY TO HELP
YOUNG PEOPLE.
BECAUSE, AFTER ALL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THIS ELECTION IS ABOUT THEIR
FUTURE.
THE FINAL THING I WOULD SAY
ABOUT IN THIS IS I THINK A
LOT OF PEOPLE -- WE HEARD AN
ALLUSION THE FATHER TALKING
ABOUT HIS SON, YOU KNOW, A
LOT OF YOUNG PEOPLE ARE
SAYING WHAT IS GOING ON?
YOU KNOW, THEY GET OUT OF
GREAT RECESSION AND INTO THE
JOB MARKET AND THERE ARE NO
JOBS.
THEY ARE BURDENED WITH
STUDENT DEBT THE ONES THAT
HAVE GOTTEN STUDENT DEBT.
THE ECONOMY DOESN'T WORK FOR
THEM, THE GOVERNMENT DOESN'T
WORK FOR THEM.
I DON'T BLAME THEM FOR BEING
REALLY DISTURBED BY WHAT'S
GOING ON IN OUR COUNTRY.
THAT'S WHY I'M NOT
OVERPROMISING.
I'M TELLING YOU WHAT I THINK
CAN I DO AND HOW CAN I
DELIVER RESULTS BECAUSE I
WANT TO REBUILD PEOPLE'S
CONFIDENCE IN OUR COUNTRY
AND WHERE WE ARE HEADED IN
THE FUTURE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, HERE
IS OUR YOUNGEST QUESTIONER,
SAMUEL IS 13 YEARS OLD AND
IS HE IN MIDDLE SCHOOL.
>> SAMUEL?
>> IS HE COVERING AND
FOLLOWING.
>> SAMUEL.
>> THANK YOU.
SECRETARY CLINTON, WHEN YOU
THINK OF SENATOR SANDERS, DO
YOU CONSIDER HIM AN ENEMY OR
ALLY.
>> OH, AN ALLY FOR SURE.
AND HERE'S HOW I THINK ABOUT
IT, SAMUEL.
WE HAVE DIFFERENCES.
AND WE ARE PASSIONATE ABOUT
OUR POSITIONS AND OUR
DIFFERENCES.
AND, YOU KNOW, LIKE WE SAW
IN THE DEBATE LAST NIGHT, WE
AIR THOSE DIFFERENCES ABOUT
ISSUES COMPARE THAT TO THE
REPUBLICANS AND HOW THEY
BEHAVE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU KNOW, I AM VERY PROUD OF
THE CAMPAIGN THAT SENATOR
SANDERS AND I ARE RUNNING.
AND I HAVE SAID PUBLICLY I
WILL REPEAT THAT TONIGHT, I
HOPE TO WIN THE NOMINATION.
IF I AM SO FORTUNATE, I HOPE
TO WORK WITH HIM BECAUSE THE
ISSUES HE HAS RAISED, THE
PASSION HE HAS DEMONSTRATED,
THE PEOPLE HE HAS ATTRACTED
ARE GOING TO BE VERY
IMPORTANT IN THE GENERAL
ELECTION BUT EQUALLY
FOLLOWING THE ELECTION TO
TRY TO GET THINGS DONE.
SO, I CERTAINLY CONSIDER HIM
AN ALLY.
>> WOULD YOU TAP HIM TO BE
YOUR V.P. CHOICE?
>> LET'S NOT GET AHEAD OF
OUR.
[ LAUGHTER ]
MY GOSH, YOU KNOW, I DON'T
WANT TO THINK ANY FURTHER
AHEAD THAN TOMORROW AND THE
MICHIGAN PRIMARY.
I CAN'T DO THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I WANT TO TELL SAMUEL AN
EXPERIENCE THAT KIND OF ITS
WHAT I'M TALKING ABOUT.
THEN SENATOR OBAMA AND I RAN
A REALLY TOUGH CAMPAIGN
AGAINST EACH OTHER TO THE
VERY END.
HE WON.
I LOST.
SO WHEN I DROPPED OUT, I0TiU(R"D
I BEGAN TO DO THAT.
I NOMINATED HIM AT THE
CONVENTION IN DENVER.
I WORKED REALLY HARD TO GET
HIM ELECTED.
AND IT WASN'T EASY TO
CONVINCE A LOT OF MY
SUPPORTERS TO IMMEDIATELY
MOVE TO SUPPORTING THEN
SENATOR OBAMA.
BUT I MADE THE CASE.
I MADE THE CASE IN PUBLIC.
I MADE THE CASE IN PRIVATE.
AND THE VAST MAJORITY DID
WHAT I THOUGHT WAS THE RIGHT
THING TO SUPPORT HIM TO BE
PRESIDENT.
SO, WHEN YOU GET THROUGH A
PRIMARY, DESPITE THE
EMOTIONS THAT ARE ARE
ENGENDERED IN YOUR
SUPPORTERS, YOU HAVE TO TAKE
STOCK OF WHERE YOU ARE AND
WHO<H
SIDE.
AND WHAT THAT PERSON
REPRESENTS.
AND I THINK IF ANY OF THE
REMAINING CANDIDATES ON THE
REPUBLICAN SIDE IS
NOMINATED, THEN I THINK MY
SUPPORTERS, SENATOR SANDERS'
SUPPORTERS, WE ARE GOING TO
FIND A LOT OF COMMON CAUSE
TO PREVENT THAT PERSON
EVER BEING PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THANK
YOU FOR YOUR TIME.
>> OH MY GOSH, IT WENT BY SO
FAST, BRET.
>> IT DID GO BY FAST.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR BEING
HERE.
WE LOOK FORWARD TO HAVING
YOU BACK
>> THANK YOU SO MUCH.
THANK YOU, ALL.
>> THAT WRAPS UP OUR SPECIAL
EDITION OF "SPECIAL REPORT."
WE WILL HAVE ALL THE
COVERAGE TOMORROW FROM THE
MICHIGAN PRIMARY IN NEW YORK
GOOD NIGHT FROM DETROIT.