>>> I'M A PROGRESSIVE WHO LIKES
TO GET THINGS DONE.
>> WE FIGHT FOR PAY EQUITY FOR
WOMEN WORKERS.
>> LET US STAND TOGETHER AND SAY
THAT THE ENDURING SYMBOL OF OUR
NATION IS NOT THE BARBED WIRE
FENCE.
IT IS THE STATUE OF LIBERTY.
>> I'VE BEEN TOLD TO STOP
SHOUTING ABOUT ENDING GUN
VIOLENCE.
WELL, I HAVEN'T BEEN SHOUTING,
BUT WHEN A WOMAN SPEAKS OUT SOME
PEOPLE THINK IT'S SHOUTING.
>> I WILL HAVE THE INDEPENDENCE
AND I WILL HAVE THE BACKBONE TO
FIGHT FOR YOU.
>> AN ECONOMY THAT WORKS FOR ALL
AMERICANS, NOT JUST THE
WEALTHIEST PEOPLE IN THIS
COUNTRY.
>> THE FIRST IN THE SOUTH
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATES FORUM LIVE
FROM WINTHROP UNIVERSITY IN
SOUTH CAROLINA.
HERE NOW, RACHEL MADDOW.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>>> WELCOME.
WELCOME.
IT'S GREAT TO HAVE YOU HERE.
I WANT TO SAY A BIG THANK YOU TO
EVERYBODY AT HOME WATCHING.
THANK YOU TO EVERYBODY IN THE
ROOM.
WE ARE AT BEAUTIFUL WINTHROP
UNIVERSITY IN ROCK HILL, SOUTH
CAROLINA.
THEY TELL ME THERE ARE 3,000
PEOPLE IN THIS ROOM, WHICH I'M
GOING TO TRY NOT TO THINK ABOUT.
BUT LET ME JUST SAY A COUPLE OF
THINGS ABOUT WHAT WE'RE ABOUT TO
DO TONIGHT WITH THESE THREE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES.
NUMBER ONE IS THAT FOR THOSE OF
YOU HERE IN THE ROOM I'M NOT
GOING TO ASK ALL OF YOU HERE IN
THE ROOM TO REMAIN ABSOLUTELY
SILENT.
I RECOGNIZE THAT YOU ARE HUMAN
BEINGS, AND I DO NOT EXPECT YOU
TO STICK A CORK IN IT FOR TWO
SOLID HOURS.
THAT SAID, KEEP IN MIND, IF YOU
MAKE TOO MUCH NOISE OR IF YOU
MAKE ANY SUSTAINED NOISE, YOU'RE
ONLY GOING TO BE TAKING AWAY
FROM THE TIME OF THE CANDIDATE
WHO YOU ARE REACTING TO.
SO JUST KEEP THAT IN MIND.
TRY NOT TO LET ANY REACTION YOU
HAVE ACTUALLY INTERRUPT WHAT
THEY'RE SAYING.
SO THAT'S ONE.
SECOND THING IS THAT THIS IS A
FORUM AND NOT A DEBATE.
BUT IT IS ALSO NOT JUST A SERIES
OF INTERVIEWS.
AT LEAST I HOPE NOT.
ONE OF THE THINGS I TRY TO BE
CAREFUL ABOUT, IF YOU'VE EVER
SEEN MY SHOW, IS THAT I TRY TO
BE CONSCIENTIOUS WHEN I'M
INTERVIEWING SOMEBODY THAT I
DON'T INTERRUPT THEM.
WHEN I HAVE PEOPLE AS A GUEST ON
MY SHOW, THEY ARE THERE AS MY
GUEST, AND I WANT THEM TO BE
ABLE TO FINISH A THOUGHT SO I
DON'T INTERJECT TOO MUCH.
AS A RULE.
IT IS NOT NECESSARILY GOING TO
BE LIKE THAT TONIGHT.
I NEED TO GET INFORMATION FROM
THESE FOLKS.
WE'VE ONLY GOT A SPECIFIC AMOUNT
OF TIME TO GET IT FROM THEM.
AND I DON'T WANT YOU TO DISLIKE
ME OR THINK THAT I AM BEING
RUDE.
I DON'T MEAN IT IN A RUDE WAY.
BUT WITH ALL RESPECT, I WILL
PROBABLY INTERJECT A LITTLE MORE
THAN YOU MIGHT HAVE EXPECTED OR
THAN YOU HAVE SEEN BEFORE.
SO DON'T HATE ME.
THAT'S YOUR FAIR WARNING.
AND A VERY QUICK THIRD THING,
YOU SHOULD KNOW THAT THE
QUESTIONS I'M GOING TO ASK
TONIGHT ARE MY OWN.
I'VE COME UP WITH THESE WITH MY
OWN STAFF.
WE DID ASK THE PUBLIC TO SUBMIT
QUESTIONS ONLINE, AND WHEN WE
USE THOSE QUESTIONS I WILL LET
YOU KNOW THAT'S WHAT WE'RE
DOING.
BUT JUST BECAUSE THIS IS
SPONSORED BY THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY OF SOUTH CAROLINA AND
CO-SPONSORED BY ALL THE OTHER
SOUTHERN DEMOCRATIC PARTIES I
DON'T WANT YOU TO THINK THAT THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY HAS GIVEN ME
ANY QUESTIONS TO ASK.
AND SURPRISINGLY ENOUGH, NEITHER
HAS THE REPUBLICAN PARTY.
NEITHER HAS ANY OTHER GROUP.
SO I'M GOING TO BE ASKING WHAT I
WANT.
THIS IS THE REAL DEAL.
SO OKAY.
WE'RE GOING TO BE TALKING WITH
MARTIN O'MALLEY FIRST AND THEN
BERNIE SANDERS SECOND AND THEN
HILLARY CLINTON THIRD.
AND THIS IS GOING TO BE A LOT OF
FUN.
SO LET'S GET STARTED.
THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
¶ SING OUT LOUD WITH YOUR
VOICE ¶
COME ON, YOU CAN DO BETTER THAN
THAT!
BL
¶¶
>> BELIEVE IT OR NOT, THIS IS
THE BULGING BICEPS OF PART ROCK
STAR PART MAYOR, ALSO
BALTIMORE'S NEW MAYOR.
>> I MARTIN O'MALLEY.
>> MARYLAND HAS BECOME THE
EIGHTH STATE TO LEGALIZE GAY
MARRIAGE.
>> THE WAY FORWARD IS ALWAYS
FOUND THROUGH GREATER RESPECT
FOR THE EQUAL RIGHTS OF ALL.
>> A BILL REPEALING CAPITAL
PUNISHMENT DREW THE LARGEST
CROWD.
MARYLAND'S NEW GUN LAW BANS THE
SALE OF SEMI-AUTOMATIC WEAPONS.
>> I DECLARE THAT I AM A
CANDIDATE FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
>> WELCOME TO THE STAGE TONIGHT
FORMER GOVERNOR OF MARYLAND
MARTIN O'MALLEY.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
GREAT TO HAVE YOU HERE.
>> THANK YOU TOO.
THANK YOU.
THANKS A LOT.
.
>> YOU'RE SURROUNDED.
>> I AM.
>> IN A GOOD WAY.
FIRST OF ALL, THANK YOU FOR
DOING THIS.
I KNOW YOU HAVE A CHOICE AS TO
WHAT TO DO AND I APPRECIATE YOU
BEING HERE.
>> THANK YOU.
I WOULDN'T BE ANY PLACE ELSE.
I LOVE SOUTH CAROLINA.
IT REMINDS ME OF MARYLAND.
>> YOU SHOULD.
AS THE FORMER GOVERNOR OF
MARYLAND YOU ARE THE CLOSEST
THING WE ARE GOING TO HAVE TO A
SOUTHERNER ON STAGE TONIGHT.
SOUTH CAROLINA HAS NOT VOTED FOR
A DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE FOR
PRESIDENT SINCE JIMMY CARTER IN
1976.
SOUTH CAROLINA HAS NOT HAD A
DEMOCRATIC GOVERNOR IN OVER A
DECADE.
NO DEMOCRATS HOLD STATEWIDE
OFFICE.
BOTH HOUSES OF THE LEGISLATURE
ARE REPUBLICAN.
YOUR PARTY, THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY, MUST BE DOING SOMETHING
WRONG IN THIS STATE.
WHAT IS IT?
>> I BELIEVE THAT WHEN OUR PARTY
IS OUR BEST WE ARE OUR BEST WHEN
WE TALK ABOUT WHERE OUR
COUNTRY'S GOING AND NOT WHERE
OUR COUNTRY'S BEEN.
AND I BELIEVE THAT WE ARE AT OUR
BEST WHEN WE PUT FORWARD THE
IDEAS THAT ACTUALLY ACKNOWLEDGE
THAT OUR ECONOMY ISN'T MONEY,
IT'S PEOPLE.
IT'S ALL OF OUR PEOPLE.
AND A STRONGER MIDDLE CLASS IS
THE CAUSE OF ECONOMIC GROWTH.
AND WHEN WE VEER AWAY FROM THAT,
PEOPLE LOSE SIGHT OF US.
WE'RE BEST WHEN WE TALK ABOUT
THINGS LIKE RAISING THE MINIMUM
WAGE, PAYING OVERTIME PAY FOR
OVERTIME WORK, MAKING IT EASIER
FOR WOMEN TO PARTICIPATE FULLY
IN OUR WORKFORCE, MAKING IT
EASIER FOR PEOPLE TO BARGAIN
COLLECTIVELY FOR BETTER WAGES.
I BELIEVE THAT THE SOURCE OF OUR
COUNTRY'S STRENGTH, RACHEL, IS
ACTUALLY AN ECONOMY THAT
RECOGNIZES THAT WE'RE ALL IN
THIS TOGETHER, THAT WHEREVER
PEOPLE START THEY SHOULD BE ABLE
TO GET AHEAD.
AND IF WE HONE TO THAT MESSAGE
AND SPEAK TO WHERE OUR COUNTRY'S
GOING AND THE GOODNESS WITHIN
OUR NATION, I THINK WE'RE GOING
TO BE VERY SUCCESSFUL.
NOT ONLY IN THE NEXT
PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION BUT IN THE
SOUTH AS WELL.
>> IN THE SOUTH RIGHT NOW
DEMOCRATS ARE REALLY, REALLY,
REALLY NOT SUCCESSFUL.
AND THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY IN
TERMS OF STATEWIDE ELECTED
OFFICE HOLDERS HAS BEEN REALLY
HOLLOWED OUT.
THERE'S A COUPLE OF EXCEPTIONS.
YOU CAN COUNT THE GOVERNOR OF
VIRGINIA.
YOU CAN COUNT A FEW STATEWIDE
OFFICE HOLDERS IN KENTUCKY.
THERE'S AN ATTORNEY GENERAL IN
MISSISSIPPI WHO'S A DEMOCRAT.
BUT OTHER THAN THAT THERE REALLY
ARE NOT A LOT OF ELECTED
DEMOCRATS IN THE SOUTH.
ARE YOU SAYING THAT THAT'S
BECAUSE THE DEMOCRATS AREN'T
EFFECTIVELY BUILDING AN ECONOMIC
MESSAGE FOR THE SOUTH
SPECIFICALLY?
WHY DOES IT NOT WORK HERE WHEN
IT WORKS EVERYWHERE ELSE?
>> WHAT I'M SAYING IS THAT AS A
PARTY I THINK WE NEED TO START
ACTING LIKE A PARTY AGAIN.
WHAT DO I MEAN?
I MEAN THAT, LOOK, DEMOCRATIC
GOVERNORS ARE IMPORTANT.
STATE HOUSES ARE IMPORTANT.
AND WE NEED TO MAKE SURE WE'RE
VOONSING THE IDEAS THAT ACTUALLY
PEOPLE CAN LISTEN TO AROUND
THEIR KITCHEN TABLES AND SAY YOU
KNOW, WHAT THE DEMOCRATS ARE
ACTUALLY ON MY SIDE, I'VE BEEN
WORKING HARDER, I'M NOT GETTING
FURTHER AHEAD, BUT THOSE
DEMOCRATS ARE ACTUALLY OFFERING
THE THINGS THAT SERVE AND THAT
ACTUALLY MOVE US FORWARD.
I ALSO THINK THAT WE NEED TO DO
A LOT BETTER JOB AS A PARTY
NATIONALLY IN FRAMING THIS AND
STICKING TO THE MESSAGE THAT OUR
PARTY IS THE PARTY FOR
OPPORTUNITY FOR ALL, THAT OUR
PARTY IS THE PARTY UNDERSTAND
THATS THAT WE'RE ALL IN THIS
TOGETHER AND THAT IN FACT WE
NEED TO RESTORE COMMON SENSE
WAGE AND LABOR POLICIES TO OUR
EQUATION, WE NEED TO INVEST IN
OUR OWN COUNTRY, WE NEED TO
SQUARE OUR SHOULDERS TO THE
GREAT CHALLENGES OF OUR TIMES
LIKE CLIMATE CHANGE AND CREATE
THE JOBS THAT PROPEL US INTO THE
FUTURE.
CAN I SAY -- ADD ONE OTHER
THING?
AND THAT IS THAT WE NEED TO
SPEAK TO THE ZEITGEIST, IF YOU
WILL, THAT SPIRIT IN THE YOUNG
PEOPLE OF OUR COUNTRY, BECAUSE
WHEN I TALK TO YOUNG PEOPLE I
RARELY EVER FIND YOUNG PEOPLE
THAT DENY THAT CLIMATE CHANGE IS
REAL OR THAT WANT TO BASH NEW
AMERICAN IMMIGRANTS OR DENY
RIGHTS TO GAY COUPLES AND THEIR
CHILDREN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND THAT TELLS ME -- THAT TELLS
ME THAT WE ARE MOVING TO A MUCH
MORE CONNECTED AND GENEROUS
PLACE.
BUT SOMETIMES AS DEMOCRATS WE
ARE RELUCTANT TO TALK ABOUT
THINGS LIKE THAT, THOSE VALUES
THAT UNITE US.
AND I THINK WE MAKE A BIG
MISTAKE WHEN WE DO THIS BECAUSE
PUBLIC POLICY IS NOT ONLY ABOUT
THE LITANY OF BETTER IDEAS AND
BETTER RESULTS.
IT'S ALSO ABOUT OUR VALUES AS A
PEOPLE.
>> IN TERMS OF COMMUNICATING
VALUES ON POLICY ISSUES LIKE YOU
JUST MENTIONED, PRESIDENT OBAMA
TODAY ANNOUNCED HE HAS REJECTED
THE APPLICATION TO BUILD THE
KEYSTONE PIPELINE.
>> HO-HO!
HEY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> EVERY DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE --
THAT'S YOUR ANSWER.
YOU AND EVERY DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATE OPPOSE THE PIPELINE.
>> BUT SECRETARY CLINTON GOT
THERE JUST LAST WEEK.
AND I WAS THERE A YEAR AGO.
>> WHY IS THAT IMPORTANT?
YOU'RE ON THE SAME PAGE NOW.
>> I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
BECAUSE LEADERSHIP ISN'T ABOUT
FOLLOWING POLLS.
I THINK LEADERSHIP'S ABOUT BEING
CLEAR ABOUT YOUR PRINCIPLES --
>> TO THAT POINT, THOUGH, ON THE
POLLS SHE'S NOT ACTUALLY
FOLLOWING THE POLLS.
THE POLLING THIS YEAR ON
KEYSTONE AS RECENTLY AS THIS
YEAR SHOWED THAT PUBLIC SUPPORT
FOR BUILDING KEYSTONE IS STILL
AT 60% NATIONWIDE.
PREVIOUS POLLS HAVE SHOWED THAT
85% OF AMERICANS THOUGHT
BUILDING KEYSTONE WOULD CREATE A
SIGNIFICANT NUMBER OF JOBS,
WHICH IT WOULD NOT, BUT A VAST
MAJORITY OF THE AMERICAN PUBLIC
THINKS THAT.
SO THE POLLING ACTUALLY ISN'T
NECESSARILY WITH THE PRESIDENT
AND WITH YOU AND NOW WITH
SECRETARY CLINTON ON THIS ISSUE.
AND THAT'S PART OF THE POLITICAL
FAILURE HERE.
WHY HAVE DEMOCRATS FAILED TO WIN
THE ARGUMENT ON THIS?
WHY HAVE THEY FAILED TO PERSUADE
THE PUBLIC EVEN THOUGH THEY'VE
NOW GOT THE POLICY WHERE THEY
WANT IT?
>> I THINK WE'VE MADE A BIG
MISTAKE AS A PARTY WHEN WE TALK
ABOUT CLIMATE CHANGE.
BECAUSE WE'RE THE PARTY THAT
ACTUALLY BELIEVES IN SCIENCE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
WE RUSH TO CONNECT THE DOTS BUT
IT DRAWS US ALL IN A STRAIGHT
LINE TO HELL.
AND THE GREAT AMERICAN MYSTIC
THOMAS MERITON ONCE SAID THAT
ANY APPEAL THAT BEGINS FROM A
STANDPOINT OF DESPAIR IS DOOMS
TO FAIL.
SO WE NEED TO WRAP THE CHALLENGE
OF CLIMATE CHANGE IN THE
OPPORTUNITY OF MORE JOBS.
WHAT AM I TALKING ABOUT?
IN IOWA.
IN THE STATE OF IOWA 15 YEARS
AGO YOU'D HARDLY FIND A
WINDMILL.
TODAY 30% OF THEIR ENERGY COMES
FROM CLEAN IOWA WIND.
IT EMPLOYS 4,000 PEOPLE.
IT'S ABOUT MORE PROSPERITY AND
MORE JOBS, NOT ABOUT SOMEHOW
HAVING LESSER LIVES OR THE
INCONVENIENT TRUTH.
IT'S ABOUT THE FACT THAT AS
AMERICANS EVERY GENERATION, WE
SQUARE OUR SHOULDERS TO THE
GREAT CHALLENGES AND WE MAKE
THEM OUR OPPORTUNITY.
AND THAT'S HOW WE NEED TO WRAP
THIS IN ORDER TO WITH WIN THIS
NEXT GENERAL ELECTION.
>> THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO ARE
GOING TO LOSE THEIR JOBS,
THOUGH, IF -- AND THERE ARE
WHOLE STATES WHO ARE GOING TO
HAVE THEIR ECONOMIES IF NOT HURT
THEN AT LEAST DRAMATICALLY
CHANGED IF WE MAKE A REALLY
RADICAL SWITCH TOWARD RENEWABLE
FUELS.
YOU'RE RIGHT THAT THERE IS
OPPORTUNITY IN GREEN ENERGY.
BUT, I MEAN, YOU WANT 100%
RENEWABLE ENERGY BY 2050.
HOW DOES A STATE LIKE, YOU KNOW,
LOUISIANA WITH ITS OFFSHORE
DRILLING OR NORTH DAKOTA WITH
ITS FRACKING, A LOT OF STATES
HAVE THEIR ECONOMIES AND A LOT
OF GOOD WORKING-CLASS
BLUE-COLLAR JOBS TIED UP IN THE
ECONOMY.
HOW DO YOU EPIHELP THEM THROUGH
THE TRANSITION?
>> YEAH, WE HAVE TO MAKE THE
CHANGE INTENTIONALLY.
AND WHAT I'M TALKING ABOUT IS
THIS.
LOOK, IN THE GREAT STATE OF
SOUTH CAROLINA ABOUT 1 OUT OF 5
PEOPLE ACTUALLY LIVE IN POVERTY.
AND THE TRUTH OF THE MATTER IS
THAT FOR ALL OF THE GREAT WORK
THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS DONE,
OUR COUNTRY'S NOW CREATING JOBS
AGAIN.
THE LATEST MONTHLY FIGURES CAME
OUT SHOWING A REALLY ROBUST
MONTH OF JOB GROWTH.
OUR COUNTRY'S DOING BETTER.
BUT IN A LOT OF OUR CITIES,
WHETHER IT'S COLUMBIA OR
CHARLESTON OR BALTIMORE OR
PHILADELPHIA, THERE ARE POCKETS
OF PEOPLE WHO ARE UNEMPLOYED.
IT IS STRUCTURAL UNEMPLOYMENT.
AND THIS SORT OF GROWING
INJUSTICE ISN'T GOING TO FIX
ITSELF.
BUT THE CITIES ARE ALSO THE
PLACE WHERE THE GREATEST AMOUNT
OF ENERGY IS USED, WHERE THE
RETROFITZ COULD HAPPEN, WHERE
AFFORDABLE AND WORKHORSE HOUSING
WE NEED NOIFT IN AGAIN AND SEE
THE WHOLE NEW GENERATION OF
GREEN BUILDINGS AND LIVING
BUILDINGS, AND THESE ARE THE
THINGS A GREAT NATION DOES IN
ORDER NOT TO LEAVE PEOPLE
BEHIND.
>> DOES THE REST OF THE COUNTRY
HAVE TO FILL IN AND HELP NORTH
DAKOTA INTO A POST-FRACKING AGE?
>> IT'S INTERESTING --
>> IT'S GOING TO BE TROUBLE.
>> YOU MENTION NORTH DAKOTA.
WHAT MOST OF THE PEOPLE IN NORTH
DAKOTA WOULD TELL YOU IS A LOT
OF THEIR TROUBLES COME FROM THE
AMOUNT OF GROWTH AND AMOUNT OF
PEOPLE THAT HAVE COME IN BECAUSE
OF THE FRACKING THING.
IT EBBS AND FLOWS BOTH WAYS.
BUT LOOK, I THINK IT WAS
ACTUALLY A LEADER OF A MIDDLE
EASTERN NATION WHO SAID WE
DIDN'T MOVE OUT OF THE STONE AGE
BECAUSE WE RAN OUT OF STONES.
YOU KNOW?
CLIMATE CHANGE IS REAL AND IT'S
A VERY BIG SECURITY THREAT BUT
IT'S ALSO A HUGE OPPORTUNITY FOR
US.
AND IT'S A HUGE OPPORTUNITY FOR
AMERICA'S CITIES, THE VERY
PLACES WHERE POVERTY IS MOST
ENTRENCHED AND WHERE WE CAN MAKE
THE INVESTMENTS IN A CLEAN
ENERGY JOBS CORPS, WHERE WE CAN
SEE THE WHOLE NEW GENERATION OF
CLEAN BUILDINGS AND AFFORDABLE
AND WORKFORCE HOUSING.
AND THE DISTRIBUTED GRID THAT
WE'RE MOVING TO IS VERY WELL
SUITED FOR CITIES.
SO I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE IN
THIS RACHEL -- IN THIS RACE,
RACHEL, WHO HAS PUT OUT A PLAN
TO MOVE US TO 100% CLEAN ENERGY
GRID BY 2050.
I BELIEVE THE GOAL -- THE
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN A GOAL AND A
DREAM IS A DEADLINE.
WE DID NOT LAND A MAN ON THE
MOON WITH AN ALL OF THE ABOVE
STRATEGY.
IT WAS AN INTENTIONAL
ENGINEERING CHALLENGE.
AND WE BROUGHT THE GREAT
DIVERSITY OF OUR NATION TO THAT
CHALLENGE, AND WE MADE IT OUR
STRENGTH.
AND THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO ON
THIS.
>> IN TERMS OF POLITICAL
REALITIES AND GETTING THINGS
DONE, I'M GOING TO TALK FOR A
LITTLE BIT ABOUT --
>> GETTING THINGS DONE.
THE GREAT RESONANT PHRASE.
GETTING THINGS DONE.
>> MOVING PEOPLE.
I MEAN, WHEN YOU WERE GOVERNOR
OF MARYLAND, THERE WAS A
NATIONAL POLITICAL SHOCK WAVE
AFTER YOU LEFT BECAUSE THE MAN
YOU ENDORSED TO SUCCEED YOU,
YOUR LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR, HE
LOST TO REPUBLICAN LARRY HOGAN
WHO'S NOW THE GOVERNOR AND
REPUBLICANS MADE BIG GAINS IN
THE LEGISLATURE AFTER YOU LEFT.
AND THAT WAS BLUE STATE
MARYLAND.
WHEN YOU WERE GOVERNOR, YOU
SIGNED MARRIAGE EQUALITY, YOU
SIGNED A HIGHER MINIMUM WAGE,
YOU SIGNED NEW RESTRICTIONS ON
GUNS, YOU SIGNED AN END TO THE
DEATH PENALTY.
BUT THEN WHEN YOU LEFT, MARYLAND
WENT A LOT REDDER THAN IT HAD
BEEN.
DID YOUR PROGRESSIVE AGENDA GO
TOO FAST TOO FAR?
DID YOU NOT BRING YOUR STATE
ALONG WITH YOU WHEN YOU MADE ALL
THOSE AGGRESSIVE CHANGES?
>> MOST OF THE TOUGH DECISIONS
AND THE MOST POLITICALLY
UNPOPULAR DECISIONS THAT I MADE
I MADE IN MY FIRST TERM.
AND THEN I RAN FOR RE-ELECTION
AGAINST THE INCUMBENT REPUBLICAN
GOVERNOR THAT I BEAT BY SEVEN
POINTS.
AND IN THAT SECOND RACE IN 2010,
WHICH WASN'T A GREAT YEAR FOR
DEMOCRATS, I BEAT MY REPUBLICAN
OPPONENT, WELL FINANCED AS HE
WAS, BY TWICE THE MARGIN, BY 14
POINTS.
AND THE WAY I DID THAT I THINK
IS INSTRUCTIVE FOR OUR PARTY
NATIONALLY --
>> I WANT TO KNOW ABOUT THE
LEGACY YOU THAT LEFT IN YOUR
STATE WHEN YOU WENT.
I MEAN, ONE OF THE BIG
CHALLENGES, ONE OF THE REASONS
THAT WE'RE FIRST IN THE SOUTH
HERE AND WE'RE TALKING ABOUT
PARTICULARLY THE CHALLENGES OF
SOUTHERN DEMOCRATIC PARTIES IS
THAT IT'S NOT ENOUGH TO HAVE
BARACK OBAMA WIN THE PRESIDENCY
IF WE SEE THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY
LOSE 13 GOVERNORSHIPS AND 900
STATE LEGISLATIVE SEATS AND ALL
THESE LEGISLATIVE SEATS ACROSS
THE HOUSE -- ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
IF YOU DON'T BRING THE PARTY
WITH YOU, IF YOU DON'T BUILD
BEHIND YOU, IF YOU LEAVE IT A
MORE REPUBLICAN STATE THAN WHEN
YOU LEFT, WHAT DOES THAT SAY?
>> WELL, LOOK, I UNDERSTOOD --
SOMETHING I LEARNED, AND I'M THE
ONLY CANDIDATE IN THIS RACE WITH
15 YEARS OF EXECUTIVIVE
EXPERIENCE.
IS YOU THAT ALWAYS HAVE TO MAKE
YOUR PARTY STRONGER.
AND THE TRUTH IS IN OUR STATE WE
RETAINED ALL OF OUR STATEWIDE
RACES AS DEMOCRATIC AND WE ALSO
KEPT OUR HOUSE DEMOCRATIC.
WE KEPT OUR SENATE DEMOCRATIC.
YOU WANT TO TALK ABOUT LEGACY?
HERE'S A LEGACY.
FOR FIVE YEARS IN A ROW WE MADE
OUR PUBLIC SCHOOLS THE BEST IN
AMERICA.
FOR FIVE YEARS IN A ROW.
WE WENT FOUR YEARS IN A ROW
WITHOUT A PENNY'S INCREASE TO
COLLEGE TUITION.
BECAUSE WE DROVE BOTH
INCARCERATION RATES DOWN TO
20-YEAR LOWS AND OUR VIOLENT
CRIME RATE DOWN TO 30-YEAR LOWS.
WE SAVED THOUSANDS OF LIVES.
WE REDUCED INFANT MORTALITY.
WE TOOK GREAT STRIDES TO
ERADICATE CHILDHOOD HUNGER.
EVERY ELECTION IS DIFFERENT,
EVERY CANDIDATE IS DIFFERENT,
BUT IN OUR STATE WE HAD A THEME
OF ONE MARYLAND, THAT WE MOVE
FORWARD TOGETHER AND THAT'S WHAT
WE DID.
AND WE DEFENDED NOT ONLY A AAA
BOND RATING ALL THE WAY THROUGH
THE RECESSION BUT MORE
IMPORTANTLY THE HIGHEST MEDIAN
INCOME AND THE SECOND HIGHEST
INCOME IN THE NATION FOR
AFRICAN-AMERICAN FAMILIES.
WE DROVE AN INCLUSIVE ECONOMIC
AGENDA.
AND THAT'S THE LEGACY.
>> ON THE ISSUE OF
AFRICAN-AMERICAN ACTIVISM AND
HEAVILY AFRICAN-AMERICAN
ELECTORATE HERE IN SOUTH
CAROLINA, ACTIVISTS FROM THE
BLACK LIVES MATTER MOVEMENT AND
OTHER YOUTH-DRIVEN MOVEMENTS
THAT WE'RE SEEING AROUND THE
COUNTRY RIGHT NOW, THEY HAVE PUT
FORWARD A BUNCH OF PRETTY
SPECIFIC POLICY PRIORITIES,
EVERYTHING FROM SCRAPPING BROKEN
WINDOWS-STYLE POLICING, ENDING
FOR-PROFIT PRISONS, A NUMBER OF
OTHER THINGS, MANY IF NOT MOST
OF WHICH YOU SAY YOU AGREE WITH.
FROM WHAT YOU KNOW OF THIS
ACTIVIST MOVEMENT AND WHAT YOU
SEE OF THEIR ENERGY, WHAT DO YOU
THINK IS THE LOWEST HANGING
FRUIT IN TERMS OF WHAT THEY'RE
ASKING FOR?
WHAT DO YOU THINK COULD ACTUALLY
GET DONE THAT'S ON THEIR AGENDA
IN THE POLITICAL WORLD THAT
WE'VE GOT RIGHT NOW?
>> I THINK THAT THERE ARE -- I
THINK THAT ALMOST ALL OF THEIR
AGENDA CAN GET DONE.
I MEAN, IF YOU --
[ APPLAUSE ]
LOOK, NONE OF US HAS A CRYSTAL
BALL.
NONE OF US KNOWS THE PACE OF
CHANGE AND REFORM AND PROGRESS.
BUT I PUT FORWARD A CRIMINAL
JUSTICE REFORM AGENDA AT THE
URBAN LEAGUE ABOUT THREE MONTHS
AGO THAT CALLED FOR MANY OF
THESE THINGS.
I THINK IT'S APPALLING, THE --
THIS MOVE TO FOR-PROFIT PRISONS
IN OUR COUNTRY.
I THINK IT'S IMMORAL.
I THINK IT'S WRONG.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I MEAN, AND THE SECTORS THAT WE
NOW HAVE ON THE BORDER OF WOMEN
AND CHILDREN BEING DETAINED FOR
MONTHS AND MONTHS ON END.
LOOK, CONTRARY TO DONALD TRUMP'S
ASSERTION, THE ENDURING SYMBOL
OF OUR COUNTRY IS NOT THE BARBED
WIRE FENCE.
IT IS THE STATUE OF LIBERTY.
SO I BELIEVE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- IN MY OWN SERVICE FOR 15
YEARS -- LOOK, WHEN I RAN FOR
MAYOR OF BALTIMORE IN 1999, IT
WAS NOT BECAUSE OUR CITY WAS
DOING WELL.
WE HAD BECOME THE MOST VIOLENT,
ADDICTED, AND ABANDONED CITY IN
AMERICA.
WE HAD OPEN AIR DRUG MARKETS
THAT HAD TAKEN OVER WHOLE
SECTIONS OF OUR CITY WHERE THE
POOREST NEIGHBORS OF OURS
COULDN'T GO OUTSIDE IN PEACE ANY
DAY OF THE WEEK.
BUT OVER THOSE 15 YEARS I'VE
BEEN ON A CONSTANT SEARCH FOR
THE THINGS THAT ACTUALLY WORK TO
SAVE AND REDEEM LIVES.
WE REPEALED THE DEATH PENALTY.
WE REDUCED OUR INCARCERATION
RATE TO 20-YEAR LOWS.
WE REDUCED OUR RECIDIVISM RATE
TO 15-YEAR LOWS.
I RESTORED VOTING RIGHTS TO
52,000 PEOPLE.
I DECRIMINALIZED THE POSSESSION
OF SMALL AMOUNTS OF MARIJUANA.
AND WE ALSO PUT OUR CITY ON THE
PATH FOR BETTER DAYS.
I WASN'T ABLE TO MAKE HER IMMUNE
TO SETBACKS, AS WE SAW IN THE
AFTERMATH OF FREDDIE GRAY'S
DEATH, BUT WE WERE ABLE TO SAVE
A LOT OF LIVES.
AND GIVEN THE LEGACY OF RACISM
AND SLAVERY AND THE WAY THAT IT
IS INTERTWINED WITH PUBLIC
SAFETY, WITH LAW ENFORCEMENT AND
PARTICULARLY WITH DRUG POLICIES
IN OUR COUNTRY, ALL OF US HAVE A
RESPONSIBILITY TO BE ON A
CONSTANT SEARCH FOR THE POLICIES
THAT FEEL WORK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR, WE'RE GOING TO TAKE
A VERY QUICK BREAK.
WE'RE GOING TO COME BACK, AND
I'M GOING TO TALK WITH YOU ABOUT
FOREIGN POLICY AND A FEW OTHER
THINGS.
BUT FIRST HERE'S THE FRONT.
I PROMISE IT WON'T HURT.
PICK ONE.
THERE'S FOUR HERE.
GO AHEAD.
I WON'T HURT YOU.
>> JOHNNY CARSON AND THE SWAMI
THING.
>> THERE YOU GO.
THESE ARE NOT POLICY QUESTIONS.
THEY'RE ALSO NOT QUESTIONS THAT
WILL MAKE YOU LOOK OR FEEL DUMB.
I PROMISE I WILL DO IT TO THE
OTHER CANDIDATES AS WELL.
READY?
>> SURE.
>> IF YOU HAD TO CAPTURE YOUR
OWN FOOD TO SURVIVE, WOULD YOU
HUNT OR WOULD YOU FISH?
>> I WOULD FISH.
>> HIGH-SPEED RAIL COAST TO
COAST OR MANNED MISSION TO MARS?
>> I REJECT THE PREMISE OF YOUR
QUESTION.
I BELIEVE WE CAN DO BOTH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WAS THERE EVER A TIME IN YOUR
LIFE WHEN YOU WERE A SMOKER?
>> NO.
>> NEVER EVER?
>> EVER.
>> WHAT IS -- THE LAST ONE.
WHAT IS THE MOST IMPRACTICAL
ITEM OF CLOTHING THAT YOU OWN?
I'M SO GLAD THIS QUESTION IS FOR
A MAN.
>> A KILT.
AND IT WAS GIVEN TO ME.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> FAIR ENOUGH.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK WITH
MARYLAND GOVERNOR MARTIN
O'MALLEY.
THE Q
>>> WE ARE HERE WITH FORMER
MARYLAND GOVERNOR MARTIN
O'MALLEY.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU.
>> AND FOR INDULGING ME ON MY
QUICK QUESTIONS.
>> SURE.
>> THIS NEXT QUESTION WE ASKED
VIEWERS TO SEND US QUESTIONS TO
ASK EITHER BY FACEBOOK OR
TWITTER.
THIS ONE CAME IN BY FACEBOOK
FROM MICHAEL HERM.
THE QUESTION?
.
WITH WAR IN THE MIDDLE EAST
RAMPING UP, ONE, SHOULD THE
DRAFT BE REINSTATED SO THAT LESS
THAN 1% OF THE POPULATION IS NO
LONGER FIGHTING FOR THE REST OF
US?
AND NUMBER TWO, SHOULD THERE BE
A WAR TAX TO HELP PAY FOR IT?
MICHAEL SAYS "IT HAS BECOME TOO
EASY TO WAGE WAR SINCE SUCH A
SMALL PERCENTAGE OF AMERICANS
HAVE SKIN IN THE GAME."
>> GREAT -- INTERESTING IDEAS.
I WOULD -- I WOULD DISAGREE WITH
MICHAEL ON THE FIRST ONE BUT I
WOULD AGREE WITH HIM ON THE
SECOND ONE.
>> SO NO DRAFT?
>> LOOK, I THINK THAT NONE OF US
FULLY APPRECIATE THE DEGREE TO
WHICH OUR -- I SHOULDN'T SAY
THAT.
NOT ENOUGH OF US APPRECIATE THE
DEGREE TO WHICH WE HAVE PUT THE
BURDEN OF THESE LAST 15 YEARS OF
CONFLICT ON THE BACK OF SUCH A
SMALL NUMBER OF OUR PEOPLE.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> BUT I DO BELIEVE THAT
PROBABLY ONE OF THE GREATEST
BLUNDERS IN MODERN AMERICAN
HISTORY WAS THE WAY THAT GEORGE
W. BUSH UNDER FALSE PRETENSES
LED OUR ARMY INTO WAR IN IRAQ.
AND HE DIDN'T EVEN --
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND HE DIDN'T EVEN HAVE THE
NERVE TO ASK US TO PAY FOR IT.
AND NOW I HEAR ALL OF THESE
REPUBLICANS SQUAWKING ABOUT THE
DEBT, THE DEBT, THE DEBT.
WELL, YOU KNOW WHAT?
THE REASON WE HAVE THE DEBT IS
BECAUSE GEORGE BUSH FALSELY LED
US INTO WAR AND DIDN'T EVEN ASK
US TO PAY FOR IT ALONG THE WAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE A BIG DEBT.
SO I DO THINK THERE NEEDS TO BE
SOME MORE TRUTH IN WHAT IT MEANS
TO BE AN AMERICAN CITIZEN.
LOOK, THE MOST WEIGHTY DECISION
ANY PRESIDENT EVER HAS IS TO
SEND TROOPS INTO COMBAT.
AND RACHEL, MY LIEUTENANT
GOVERNOR ANTHONY BROWN AND I
MADE IT A POINT TO GO TO EVERY
FUNERAL IN MARYLAND OF FAMILIES
THAT WERE ASKED TO PAY A LOT
MORE THAN A FEW CENTS, YOU KNOW,
IN THEIR TAXES.
>> YOU DON'T BELIEVE THERE
SHOULD BE A DRAFT?
>> I DON'T BELIEVE THERE SHOULD
BE A DRAFT BUT I DO BELIEVE WE
NEED TO DO A MUCH BETTER JOB OF
TELLING PEOPLE WHAT THE COST OF
THE QUICK AND ALMOST REFLEXIVE
DEFAULT REACH FOR THE MILITARY
OPTION EVERY TIME.
THAT DOES OUR SOLDIERS A
DISSERVICE.
IF WE'RE NOT SMART ENOUGH TO
IDENTIFY THREATS BEFORE THEY
ARISE AND TAKE ACTIONS TO REDUCE
THEM, SHAME ON US.
AND WE SHOULDN'T SEND THEM INTO
WARS WE'RE NOT WILLING TO PAY
FOR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT A
FINANCIAL SECURITY ISSUE THAT
LOOKS LIKE IT MAY BE A LEGACY
ISSUE FOR THE NEXT PRESIDENT.
IF PRESIDENT OBAMA CANNOT CLOSE
GUANTANAMO BY THE TIME HE LEAVES
OFFICE, DO YOU HAVE A PLAN FOR
HOW YOU COULD DO IT AS THE NEXT
PRESIDENT EVEN THOUGH HE HAS NOT
BEEN ABLE TO GET IT DONE SO FAR?
>> I BELIEVE THAT IN TALKING TO
A LOT OF MILITARY LEADERS THEY
TELL ME THE TWO BIGGEST
RECRUITMENT TOOLS FOR AL QAEDA
OR NOW ISIL ARE AMERICAN BOOTS
ON THE GROUND IN THE MIDDLE EAST
AND OUR CONTINUED OPERATION OF
GUANTANAMO.
THE PRESIDENT UNDERSTANDS THIS.
THE PRESIDENT HAS TAKEN GREAT
STRIDES TO REDUCE THE POPULATION
THERE.
>> BUT CONGRESS HAS BLOCKED HIM.
>> WELL, CONGRESS HAS BLOCKED
HIM.
AND WE NEED TO CALL IT OUT IN
THE COURSE OF THIS ELECTION.
AND I THINK THAT WE NEED TO DO A
BETTER JOB AS A PARTY FRANKLY OF
PUTTING OUR MILITARY VOICES
FORWARD TO SAY THAT THIS IS
WRONG.
IT'S NOT GOOD FOR OUR TROOPS
THAT WE CONTINUE TO OPERATE
GUANTANAMO.
WE ARE A NATION OF LAWS.
FOR US TO MAINTAIN INTERNMENT
CAMPS AND TO KEEP PEOPLE
INTERNED INDEFINITELY IS
CONTRARY TO OUR PRINCIPLES AS A
PEOPLE.
AND WE'RE BEST IN THE WORLD WHEN
WE OPERATE ACCORDING TO OUR
PRINCIPLES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I'M GOING TO ASK YOU A DOWN
AND DIRTY POLITICS QUESTION.
SO FORGIVE ME IN ADVANCE.
HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA --
>> USUALLY PEOPLE SAY MY EDITOR
WANTED ME TO ASK YOU THIS
QUESTION.
>> NOBODY TO BLAME BUT MYSELF.
THE LATEST WINTHROP UNIVERSITY
POLL IN SOUTH CAROLINA HAS YOU
AT 2%.
THAT IS 13 POINTS BEHIND SENATOR
SANDERS.
THAT IS 69 POINTS BEHIND
SECRETARY CLINTON.
AND I ASK YOU THIS NOT BECAUSE I
WANT YOU TO EXPLAIN THAT NUMBER
BUT BECAUSE VOTERS LOOKING AT
YOU AS A POTENTIAL CANDIDATE ARE
GOING TO HAVE CONCERNS ABOUT
YOUR VIABILITY.
YOU'RE IN LOW SINGLE DIGITS
EVERYWHERE.
AND THAT'S AFTER MONTHS OF
CAMPAIGNING.
DOES YOUR CAMPAIGN NEED TO BE
SHAKEN UP?
WHAT ARE YOU CHANGING ABOUT YOUR
CAMPAIGN TO TRY TO CHANGE THE
TRAJECTORY THAT YOU'RE ON?
BECAUSE IT'S LESS THAN 90 DAYS
TO IOWA AND YOUR TRAJECTORY DOES
NOT LOOK GOOD.
>> RACHEL, WHEN I RAN FOR MAYOR
OF BALTIMORE, I ONLY HAD 88 DAYS
TO GO AND I WAS THE WHOPPING
FIRST CHOICE OF 7% OF MY
NEIGHBORS.
SO I KIND OF LIKE A TOUGH FIGHT.
AND I BELIEVE THAT WE'RE
ACTUALLY ON COURSE AND IN FACT
THIS RACE IS NOW NARROWED TO
THREE PEOPLE AND ONLY ONE OF US
ACTUALLY HAS 15 YEARS OF
EXECUTIVE EXPERIENCE NOT JUST
TALKING ABOUT PROGRESSIVE THINGS
BUT ACTUALLY GETTING PROGRESSIVE
THINGS DONE.
THE DREAM ACT, MARRIAGE
EQUALITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
COMPREHENSIVE GUN SAFETY
LEGISLATION.
WE PASSED THAT IN MARYLAND.
WE PUT TOGETHER THE VOTES TO DO
THAT.
AND THE BIGGEST QUESTION AS I
TRAVEL AROUND THE COUNTRY, ALL
OF US ARE DISSATISFIED WITH OUR
GRIDLOCK POLITICS IN WASHINGTON.
WE ARE DISSATISFIED WITH AN
ECONOMY WHERE 70% OF US ARE
WORKING HARDER AND FALLING
FURTHER BEHIND.
AND IF THAT IS THE OPINION OF
THE VAST MAJORITY OF AMERICANS
BASED ON THE REALITY THAT WE SEE
AND THAT WE EXPERIENCE, IT DOES
NOT HOLD THAT A RETURN TO THE
OLD IDEOLOGIES OF THE PAST OR
DEBATING THE PROS AND CONS OF
SOCIALISM IS GOING TO SOLVE OUR
PROBLEMS, NOR WILL DECLARING ALL
REPUBLICANS AS OUR ENEMIES HELP
US BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER.
LOOK --
>> DO YOU THINK SENATOR
SANDERS'S CAMPAIGN HAS BEEN
ABOUT DEBATING THE PROS AND CONS
OF SOCIALISM?
DO YOU THINK THAT'S WHAT HE'S
RUNNING FOR?
>> I WANT YOU TO IMAGINE WITH ME
WHAT THE NEXT FOUR YEARS WOULD
BE LIKE.
AND LOOK, ONE OF THE BEAUTIFUL
THINGS ABOUT THIS STATE FOR ALL
OF THE TRAGEDY THAT THEY HAVE --
THAT THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA HAVE EXPERIENCED, WHEN
I FILED WITH THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA, WHEN SENATOR PINKNEY
WAS LYING IN STATE HERE IN
COLUMBIA, NOBODY WAS ASKING
THEMSELVES ARE YOU A DEMOCRAT OR
ARE YOU A REPUBLICAN?
WHEN PEOPLE GOT WIPED OUT BY
FLOODS IN LOWER RICHLAND NOBODY
WENT TO HELP A NEIGHBOR AND SAID
BEFORE I HELP YOU WITH YOUR
FLOODED OUT HOUSE YOU NEED TO
TELL ME ARE YOU A DEMOCRAT OR A
REPUBLICAN.
OUR COUNTRY NEEDS NEW LEADERSHIP
IN ORDER TO MOVE OUT OF THESE
DIVIDE TIMES.
I HAVE THE INDEPENDENCE TO DO
THAT.
AND I'M PRETTY EXCITED ABOUT
WHAT THE NEXT 90 DAYS HOLDS.
>> LET ME PRESS YOU ON THAT
POINT YOU JUST DIDN'T ANSWER ME
ON, THOUGH.
[ LAUGHTER ]
YOU KEEP SAYING THIS ABOUT
SENATOR SANDERS THAT HIS
CAMPAIGN -- YOU NEVER SAY IT
DIRECTLY.
BUT WHAT YOU'RE SAYING IS HIS
CAMPAIGN IS ABOUT DEBATING THE
PROS AND CONS OF SOCIALISM.
DO YOU THINK THAT HIM BEING A
DEMOCRATIC SOCIALIST IS
DISQUALIFYING, HE SHOULDN'T BE
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT, THAT'S
TOO BIG A DISTRACTION, HIM IN
THE RACE MEANS THAT'S WHAT
PEOPLE TALK ABOUT AND THAT'S
UNHELPFUL?
IT SEEMS LIKE THAT'S THE CASE
YOU'RE MAKING.
>> I THINK THAT WHEN PRESIDENT
OBAMA WAS RUNNING FOR
RE-ELECTION I WAS GLAD TO STEP
UP AND WORK VERY HARD FOR HIM
WHILE SENATOR SANDERS WAS TRYING
TO FIND SOMEONE TO PRIMARY HIM.
I AM A DEMOCRAT.
I'M A LIFELONG DEMOCRAT.
I'M NOT A FORMER INDEPENDENT.
I'M NOT A FORMER REPUBLICAN.
I BELIEVE IN THE PARTY OF
FRANKLIN ROOSEVELT, THE PARTY OF
JOHN F. KENNEDY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I BELIEVE THAT WE'RE ALL IN THIS
TOGETHER AND WE CAN MAKE A
BETTER FUTURE.
THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING FOR OUR
PARTY'S NOMINATION.
AND I'VE NEVER ONCE REJECTED THE
NOMINATION OF THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY, NOR WILL I THIS TIME.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I WANT YOU TO MEET SOMEBODY
BEFORE WE GO.
DO WE HAVE SOMEBODY -- YES.
SEE THAT GUY ON THE LEFT?
>> I DO.
>> YOU CAN'T SEE HOW FILTHY HIS
SNEAKERS ARE BUT HE'S WEARING A
VERY WELL-WORN PAIR OF CHUCK
TAYLORS THERE.
THAT'S YOU ON THE FAR LEFT,
PLAID SHIRT.
I THINK YOU'RE ABOUT 22 YEARS
OLD THERE.
YOU WERE WORKING FOR GARY HART'S
PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN.
AS YOU SAY, LIFELONG DEMOCRAT.
WHAT IS YOUNG MARTIN O'MALLEY
THINKING THERE, AND WHAT REMAINS
OF HIM IN THE EXPERIENCED
POLITICIAN THAT WE SEE TODAY?
>> THIS IS A DEEP
METAPHYSICAL QUESTION.
>> YOU'RE WELCOME.
>> I THINK WHAT I'M THINKING
THERE IS THAT POLITICS IS
ACTUALLY A NOBLE CALLING AND THE
ONLY THING WRONG WITH POLITICS
IS NOT ENOUGH GOOD PEOPLE TRY,
AND THAT I BELIEVE THAT THE BEST
LEADERSHIP IS THE LEADERSHIP OF
PRINCIPLE, THE LEADERSHIP THAT
SAYS THAT IN FACT THERE'S A LOT
MORE THAT UNITES US THAN DIVIDES
US AND TOGETHER WE CAN GIVE OUR
KIDS A FUTURE WITH MORE
OPPORTUNITY RATHER THAN LESS.
LEADERSHIP MATTERS.
AND THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING.
THAT'S WHY I WORKED THEN.
AND THAT'S WHY I'M RUNNING NOW.
>> GOVERNOR MARTIN O'MALLEY,
THANK YOU, SIR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
PLEASURE HAVING YOU.
>> THANKS A LOT.
>> THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO BE RIGHT BACK
WITH SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS AND
WITH HILLARY CLINTON WHEN WE
COME BACK.
THANK YOU, SIR.
¶¶
>>> MY PARENTS, MY BROTHER, AND
I LIVED TOGETHER IN A SMALL
RENT-CONTROLLED APARTMENT IN
BROOKLYN, NEW YORK.
>> THEY LAUGHED AT BERNIE
SANDERS WHEN HE RAN FOR MAYOR
BECAUSE HE WAS AN AVOWED
SOCIALIST.
>> A WAR IN THE PERSIAN GULF
NOW, AN ABSOLUTELY UNNECESSARY
WAR, WOULD BE A TERRIBLE
MISTAKE.
>> I'M OPPOSED TO GIVING THE
PRESIDENT A BLANK CHECK TO
LAUNCH A UNILATERAL INVASION AND
OCCUPATION OF IRAQ.
>> THIS IS NOT A GOOD DEAL.
WE CAN DO BETTER.
>> VERY SERIOUS ALLEGATIONS HAVE
BEEN MADE ABOUT VA PERSONNEL.
>> I AM PROUD TO ANNOUNCE MY
CANDIDACY FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> VERMONT SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
GREAT TO SEE YOU.
THANK YOU FOR BEING HERE.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
YOU HAVE A LOT OF FANS HERE.
IT'S GREAT TO SEE YOU, SENATOR.
THANK YOU FOR COMING.
>> GREAT TO SEE YOU TOO, RACHEL.
>> REMEMBER WHAT WE SAID?
REMEMBER?
THANK YOU.
ALL RIGHT.
SO YOUR CAREER TOOK ROOT IN A
VERY PARTICULAR CULTURE.
VERMONT IS MORE COMPLICATED THAN
PEOPLE THINK IT IS.
BUT VERMONT IS VERY FRIENDLY
TERRITORY FOR EVERYTHING FROM
SINGLE PAYER HEALTH CARE TO
SAME-SEX MARRIAGE TO RECYCLING
TO SOLAR POWER.
VERMONT IS ALSO 95% WHITE.
HOW CAN YOU EXPECT TO SELL YOUR
IDEAS AND YOUR LEADERSHIP IN A
HEAVILY CHRISTIAN, GENERALLY
CONSERVATIVE, HIGHLY TRADITIONAL
REGION LIKE THE SOUTH?
WHAT'S BERNIE SANDERS GOT TO DO
WITH THE CAROLINA PIEDMONT OR
WITH THE MISSISSIPPI DELTA?
>> BECAUSE THE ISSUES THAT
IMPACT THE PEOPLE OF SOUTH
CAROLINA, THE
THEIR COLLEGE.
AND GUESS WHAT, RACHEL?
ALMOST ALL OF THE NEW INCOME
BEING CREATED, ALMOST ALL OF THE
NEW WEALTH BEING CREATED IS
GOING TO THE PEOPLE ON TOP.
THE TOP 1%.
THAT'S TRUE ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY, AND PEOPLE ARE SAYING
ENOUGH IS ENOUGH.
THEY WANT A GOVERNMENT WHICH
REPRESENTS ALL OF US AND NOT
JUST A HANDFUL OF BILLIONAIRES.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> SINCE THINKING ABOUT THE
CHALLENGES OF YOUR CAMPAIGN AS
YOU HAVE DONE, DEFIED ALL THE
PUNDITS' EXPECTATIONS,
PARTICULARLY IN NEW HAMPSHIRE,
ALSO IN IOWA, ALSO IN TERMS OF
THE SUCCESS YOU'VE HAD AROUND
THE COUNTRY.
BUT SINCE I'VE BEEN HERE IN
SOUTH CAROLINA THE LAST COUPLE
OF DAYS, PEOPLE KEEP TELLING ME
THAT AFRICAN-AMERICAN VOTERS IN
SOUTH CAROLINA JUST DON'T KNOW
YOU WELL ENOUGH TO CONSIDER
SUPPORTING YOU.
IN THE LAST POLL IN SOUTH
CAROLINA, WINTHROP UNIVERSITY
POLL, YOU ONLY GET 8% SUPPORT
AMONG BLACK DEMOCRATS HERE.
DO YOU HAVE ENOUGH REAL-WORLD
EXPERIENCE WITH THE ISSUES THAT
RACIAL MINORITIES FACE TO BE
ABLE TO CONVINCE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN VOTERS IN THE
SOUTH SPECIFICALLY THAT -- THE
WAY THE STATE DEMOCRATIC PARTY
CHAIRMAN PUT IT TO ME IS CAN YOU
CONVINCE THEM YOU'RE THE BEST
PERSON TO CARRY THE FLAG FOR
THEM ON THE ISSUES THEY'RE
CONCERNED WITH?
>> I BELIEVE I CAN FOR A FEW
REASONS.
NUMBER ONE, IN TERMS OF MY
HISTORY.
IF YOU CHECK OUT MY RECORD,
YOU'LL FIND THAT THERE ARE VERY
FEW MEMBERS OF THE CONGRESS WHO
HAVE A STRONGER RECORD ON CIVIL
RIGHTS THAN BERNIE SANDERS HAS.
WAY BACK WHEN, WHEN I WAS A
LITTLE BIT YOUNGER, I WAS
INVOLVED IN CIVIL RIGHTS
DEMONSTRATIONS, AND I WAS THERE
WITH MARTIN LUTHER KING JR., DR.
KING, IN THE MARCH ON
WASHINGTON.
SO I HAVE A LONG HISTORY.
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY, I THINK I
HAVE THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL
JUSTICE AGENDA NOW THAT ONCE WE
GET THE WORD OUT WILL IN FACT
RESONATE WITH THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT RAISING THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO 15 BUCKS AN
HOUR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND WHAT THAT MEANS, OVER HALF
OF THE BLACK WORKERS IN THIS
COUNTRY EARN LESS.
WE'RE TALKING ABOUT TAKING ON
THE GOVERNOR OF SOUTH CAROLINA
WHO'S DENYING MEDICAID TO
200,000 PEOPLE.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
AND PASSING A MED CARE FOR ALL
SINGLE PAYER SYSTEM.
THAT'S IMPORTANT TO
AFRICAN-AMERICANS.
WE ARE TALKING ABOUT TELLING
WALL STREET THEY'RE GOING TO
HAVE TO PAY A TAX ON SPECULATION
AND WE'RE GOING TO MAKE PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION-FREE.
THAT'S IMPORTANT TO THE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
AND RACHEL, ONE OTHER POINT.
ONE OTHER POINT THAT DOESN'T GET
TALKED ABOUT ENOUGH, AND I
TALKED ABOUT IT ALL THE TIME,
AND I WANT EVERYBODY TO HEAR IT.
WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT UNEMPLOYMENT
IN AMERICA, I WANT EVERYBODY TO
KNOW THAT REAL UNEMPLOYMENT AND
UNDEREMPLOYMENT FOR
AFRICAN-AMERICAN KIDS 17 TO 20
WHO ARE HIGH SCHOOL GRADUATES IS
51%.
AND I'VE WORKED WITH CONGRESSMAN
JOHN CONYERS AND OTHERS TO SAY
WE ARE GOING TO INVEST IN
EDUCATION AND JOBS FOR THE KIDS
OF THIS COUNTRY RATHER THAN
JAILS AND INCARCERATION.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU HAVE ARTICULATED EXACTLY
THAT MESSAGE FROM THE VERY START
OF YOUR CAMPAIGN, YOU'VE SAID
THAT IT IS WHY YOU ARE RUNNING.
VICE PRESIDENT BIDEN DECIDED
THAT HE WOULD NOT RUN FOR
PRESIDENT THIS YEAR.
HE SAYS THAT THE REASON HE
WANTED TO AND HE HAS REGRET I
THINK ABOUT NOT RUNNING IS
BECAUSE HE WANTS THE NEXT
DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE TO CHAMPION
THE RECORD OF THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION AND DOUBLE DOWN
ON THEIR EFFORTS SPECIFICALLY TO
TRY TO GIVE THE MIDDLE CLASS A
BETTER DEAL THAN THEY ARE
GETTING RIGHT NOW.
AND THERE'S A SPECIFIC PART OF
THAT THAT I WANT TO ASK YOU
ABOUT BECAUSE I KNOW IT'S
IMPORTANT TO YOU.
HOW WOULD YOU MOVE AMERICAN
BUSINESS?
HOW WOULD YOU GET AMERICAN
COMPANIES AT THE CORPORATE LEVEL
TO INVEST MORE IN EMPLOYEE PAY,
TO INVEST MORE IN EMPLOYEE
TRAINING, EXPANSION OF THEIR
BUSINESSES INSTEAD OF PUTTING SO
MUCH OF THEIR PROFITS IN THE
POCKETS OF THEIR CEOs AND THEIR
WALL STREET INVESTORS?
>> EXCELLENT QUESTION.
AND THE ANSWER IS, AND SOUTH
CAROLINIANS UNDERSTAND THIS,
AMONG OTHER THINGS WE HAVE TO
END OUR DISASTROUS TRADE
POLICIES AND CREATE JOBS IN
SOUTH CAROLINA, IN VERMONT
RATHER THAN JUST IN CHINA.
TEXTILE INDUSTRIES HERE ARE VERY
SIGNIFICANTLY IMPACTED BY BAD
TRADE AGREEMENTS.
SO WHAT WE'RE GOING TO TELL
CORPORATE AMERICA, YOU KNOW
WHAT, INSTEAD OF MOVING ABROAD,
HOW ABOUT INVESTING IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA?
AND WE'RE NOT GOING TO GIVE HUGE
TAX BREAKS ANYMORE TO LARGE
CORPORATIONS WHO ARE PUTTING
THEIR PROFITS IN THE CAYMAN
ISLANDS AND IN BERMUDA AND NOT
PAYING A NICKEL IN FEDERAL
TAXES.
WE'RE GOING TO USE THAT TAX
MONEY TO REBUILD OUR CRUMBLING
INFRASTRUCTURE AND CREATE UP TO
13 MILLION GOOD PAYING JOBS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ON THE SUBJECT OF
INFRASTRUCTURE PRESIDENT OBAMA
TODAY SAID KEYSTONE IS NOT GOING
TO GET BUILT.
HE SAID -- I GOT YOUR ANSWER ON
THAT.
HE SAID ONE OF THE MYTHS ABOUT
KEYSTONE, HE SAID THERE'S TWO
MYTHS ABOUT IT, ONE THAT IT
WOULD BE DEVASTATING IN TERMS OF
CLIMATE CHANGE, AND THE OTHER
MYTH IS THAT IT WOULD BE A
CREATIVE OF A HUGE AMOUNT OF
AMERICAN JOBS, IF YOU WANT TO
GREAT A LOT OF AMERICAN JOBS YOU
NEED A STRUCTURE BILL.
>> EXACTLY.
>> ON BOTH SIDES OF THAT, HAVE
YOU OVERSTATED THE IMPACT OF
KEYSTONE --
>> NO.
>> -- ON CLIMATE CHANGE?
THE PRESIDENT SAYS IT'S
OVERSTATED BUT IT WOULDN'T BE --
>> EVERY NOW AND THEN -- BARACK
OBAMA'S A GOOD FRIEND AND I LOVE
HIM BUT NOW AND THEN WE
DISAGREE.
HERE'S THE STORY.
AND THIS I BELIEVE.
I'VE GOT FOUR KIDS, SEVEN
BEAUTIFUL GRANDCHILDREN.
AND WHAT I BELIEVE FROM THE
BOTTOM OF MY HEART, IF WE ARE
NOT EXTREMELY AGGRESSIVE IN
TRANSFORMING OUR ENERGY SYSTEM
AWAY FROM FOSSIL FUEL TO ENERGY
EFFICIENCY AND SUSTAINABLE
ENERGY, THE PLANET WE'RE GOING
TO BE LEAVING THE KIDS AND
GRANDCHILDREN OF THIS COUNTRY
MAY NOT BE HABITABLE.
SO I BELIEVE WE HAVE GOT TO BE
EXTREMELY AGGRESSIVE.
NOW, FOR ME AS OPPOSED TO MAYBE
SOME OTHER UNNAMED CANDIDATES,
THE ISSUE OF KEYSTONE WAS KIND
OF A NO-BRAINER.
IT NEVER MADE SENSE TO ME FROM
DAY ONE AS TO WHY YOU WOULD
EXTRACT AND TRANSPORT SOME OF
THE DIRTIEST FUEL ON THIS
PLANET.
SO I SAID NO TO THE KEYSTONE ON
DAY ONE.
I SAID YES TO ATTACKS ON CARBON.
JUST THE OTHER DAY WITH SOME
OTHER SENATORS WE ARE PUSHING
LEGISLATION THAT WOULD STOP THE
EXTRACTION OF FOSSIL FUELS FROM
FEDERALLY OWNED LANDS.
WE ARE FIGHTING FOR THE FUTURE
OF THIS PLANET.
AND WE'VE GOT TO BE BOLD.
WE'VE GOT TO WORK WITH CHINA.
WE'VE GOT TO WORK WITH INDIA.
WE'VE GOT TO WORK WITH RUSSIA.
I AM A MEMBER OF THE ENERGY
COMMITTEE AND THE ENVIRONMENTAL
COMMITTEE.
AND IT IS BEYOND MY
COMPREHENSION HOW WE HAVE A
BUNCH OF REPUBLICANS OUT THERE
WHO ARE REJECTING SCIENCE, ARE
MUCH MORE INTERESTED IN GETTING
THEIR CAMPAIGN CONTRIBUTIONS
FROM THE KOCH BROTHERS AND
EXXONMOBIL.
THAT'S ALL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ON A NATIONAL SECURITY ISSUE
OF A DIFFERENT KIND, THIS WEEK
IT APPEARS THAT ISIS MAY HAVE
USED A BOMB TO BRING DOWN A
RUSSIAN AIRLINER OVER EGYPT.
IF THAT TURNS OUT TO BE TRUE --
IT'S NOT KNOWN YET, BUT IF THAT
TURNS OUT TO BE THE CASE, THAT
WOULD MEAN THAT ISIS HAS CROSSED
A NEW THRESHOLD IN TERMS OF
THEIR ABILITY TO WREAK
INTERNATIONAL HAVOC AND MURDER
CIVILIANS.
REPUBLICANS ACCUSE PRESIDENT
OBAMA OF NOT DOING ENOUGH
AGAINST ISIS.
THAT SAID, THOUSANDS OF AIR
STRIKES AGAINST ISIS IN SYRIA
AND IRAQ IS NOT NOTHING.
GROUND TROOPS IN IRAQ AND SYRIA
IS NOT NOTHING.
PARTICULARLY WITH THIS BOMB
POSSIBILITY SHOULD MORE BE DONE
AGAINST ISIS?
SHOULD THE FIGHT BE RAMPED UP?
WHAT SHOULD BE DONE THAT'S NOT
BEING DONE NOW?
>> YOU'RE LOOKING AT A FORMER
MEMBER OF CONGRESS WHO LISTENED
TO WHAT BUSH AND CHENEY HAD TO
SAY ABOUT GOING TO WAR IN IRAQ,
I LISTENED CAREFULLY, I DIDN'T
BELIEVE THEM, AND I VOTED
AGAINST THAT WAR, WHICH TURNS
OUT TO BE ONE OF THE WORST
FOREIGN POLICY DISASTERS IN THE
HISTORY OF THIS COUNTRY.
NOW, WHAT I BELIEVE IN TERMS OF
HOW YOU DEAL WITH ISIS, I KNOW
THAT SAUDI ARABIA AND ALL THESE
COUNTRIES, THEY WANT AMERICAN
GROUND TROOPS TO BE IN COMBAT
RIGHT NOW.
I DISAGREE.
I THINK WHAT THIS WAR AGAINST
THE BARBARIC ISIS ORGANIZATION
IS ABOUT IS FOR THE SOUL OF
ISLAM.
AND I THINK YOU'VE GOT A LOT OF
MUSLIM COUNTRIES THERE WHO ARE
GOING TO HAVE TO ROLL UP THEIR
SLEEVES AND GET THEIR TROOPS ON
THE GROUND AND START TAKING ON
ISIS IN A WAY THEY HAVE NOT YET
DONE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I THINK -- I THINK ALSO, AND
I FEEL VERY STRONGLY ABOUT THIS,
THE UNITED STATES HAS GOT TO BE
SUPPORTIVE.
SO DOES THE UNITED KINGDOM.
SO DOES FRANCE.
SO DOES GERMANY.
SO DO COUNTRIES ALL OVER THE
WORLD WHO ARE FACING THREATS
FROM ISIS.
WHAT HAS GONE ON IN RECENT
YEARS, WHENEVER THERE IS A
MILITARY ISSUE THE WORLD IS
SAYING HEY, NO PROBLEM, AMERICAN
TROOPS, AMERICAN TAXPAYERS,
THEY'LL DO IT, WE DON'T HAVE TO
DO ANYTHING.
WRONG.
THE WHOLE WORLD IS GOING TO HAVE
TO GET INVOLVED IN COALITION TO
TAKE ON ISIS, NOT JUST THE
UNITED STATES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND IF THE WORLD WILL NOT DO
IT?
DOES THAT MEAN THERE SHOULDN'T
BE GROUND TROOPS?
SPECIFICALLY SPEAKING, DO YOU
SUPPORT THE DEPLOYMENT OF GROUND
FORCES, SMALL NUMBER OF SPECIAL
OPERATIONS TROOPS TO SYRIA THAT
WAS ANNOUNCED BY THE WHITE HOUSE
LAST WEEK?
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID THERE
WOULDN'T BE BOOTS ON THE GROUND.
THERE ARE NOW.
DO YOU SUPPORT THAT?
>> NO.
I DO NOT WANT TO SEE US GET
IN -- SUCKED INTO A QUAGMIRE OF
WHICH THERE MAY BE NO END.
>> YOU SUPPORTED THE WAR IN
AFGHANISTAN.
>> YES.
>> YOU FAMOUSLY VOTED AGAINST
THE IRAQ WAR, BUT YOU SUPPORTED
THE WAR IN AFGHANISTAN.
THAT WAR HAS NOW GONE ON FOR
MORE THAN 14 YEARS.
NO END IN SIGHT.
THE TALIBAN JUST LAST MONTH
BRIEFLY TOOK OVER THE LARGEST
CITY THEY HAVE CONTROLLED SINCE
2001.
DO YOU REGRET SUPPORTING THE
AFGHAN WAR?
>> NO.
IN THE SENSE THAT ON 9/11 WE
EXPERIENCED A TERRIBLE, TERRIBLE
TRAGEDY.
THAT ATTACK WAS LED BY OSAMA BIN
LADEN.
THE TALIBAN AT THAT POINT
REFUSED TO BRING HIM TO JUSTICE.
AND I THOUGHT WE HAVE TO GO IN
AND GET HIM.
BUT WHAT I DO BELIEVE, AT THE
END OF THE DAY-S THAT THERE HAS
GOT TO BE AN INTERNATIONAL
COALITION DEALING WITH TERRORISM
AND IT CANNOT ONLY BE THE UNITED
STATES.
>> YOU TOLD "THE BOSTON GLOBE"
EDITORIAL BOARD YESTERDAY, "I
DISAGREE WITH HILLARY CLINTON ON
VIRTUALLY EVERYTHING."
>> WELL, "VIRTUALLY" IS THE KEY
WORD.
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> I WAS GOING TO SAY, IT SEEMS
LIKE VIRTUALLY'S DOING A LOT OF
WORK IN THAT SENTENCE.
YOU SUPPORT A VERY SIMILAR LIST
OF POLICIES --
>> WELL, YES AND NO.
>> IN THIS CAMPAIGN.
>> AND LET ME SAY THIS.
AS YOU WELL KNOW, RACHEL, MEDIA
DRIVES ME NUTS.
RIGHT?
>> PRESENT COMPANY EXCEPTED?
>> WE LOVE YOU.
YOU'RE THE EXCEPTION.
BUT IT'S ALWAYS GOTCHA STUFF.
AND I CAN'T WALK DOWN A HALLWAY
IN THE NATION'S CAPITOL WITHOUT
PEOPLE BEGGING ME TO BEAT UP ON
HILLARY CLINTON, ATTACK HILLARY
CLINTON.
TELL ME WHY SHE'S THE WORST
PERSON IN THE WORLD.
I RESIST IT AND I RESIST IT AND
I RESIST IT.
BECAUSE I THINK UNLIKE OUR
REPUBLICAN FRIENDS THERE WHO
THINK THAT POLITICS IS ABOUT
ATTACKING EACH OTHER IN
INCREDIBLY STUPID AND
DESTRUCTIVE WAYS.
I THINK WHAT WE ARE TRYING TO DO
IS HAVE A SENSIBLE DEBATE ON
IMPORTANT ISSUES FACING AMERICA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT HAVING SAID THAT, LOOK, I
WOULD NOT HAVE RUN FOR
PRESIDENT -- I LOVE MY JOB AS
VERMONT SENATOR.
I WOULD NOT HAVE RUN IF I
BELIEVED THAT ESTABLISHMENT
POLITICS AND ESTABLISHMENT
ECONOMICS CAN SOLVE THE VERY
SERIOUS PROBLEMS THAT WE FACE.
I BELIEVE THAT WE HAVE AMONG
OTHER THINGS AN ECONOMY WHICH IS
RIGGED WHICH BENEFITS THE
WEALTHIEST PEOPLE AND WE HAVE A
CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM WHICH IS
CORRUPT.
AS A RUFLT CITIZENS UNITED NOW
YOU'VE GOT BILLIONAIRES POURING
IN HUGE AMOUNTS OF MONEY WHO
ELECT EXTREME RIGHT-WING
CANDIDATES.
NOW, I HAVE MANY DISAGREEMENTS
WITH HILLARY CLINTON.
AND ONE OF THEM IS THAT I DON'T
THINK IT'S GOOD ENOUGH JUST TO
TALK THE TALK ON CAMPAIGN
FINANCE REFORM.
YOU'VE GOT TO WALK THE WALK.
I AM THE ONLY DEMOCRATIC
CANDIDATE WHO DOES NOT HAVE A
SUPER PAC.
I AM NOT ASKING MILLIONAIRES AND
BILLIONAIRES FOR LARGE CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS.
WE ARE DOING IT THE
OLD-FASHIONED WAY.
750,000 AMERICANS, AVERAGE
CONTRIBUTION 30 BUCKS, HAVE
CONTRIBUTED TO MY CAMPAIGN.
MORE THAN ANY OTHER CANDIDATE IN
THE HISTORY OF THIS COUNTRY AT
THIS POINT.
SO WE'RE RUNNING A GRASSROOTS
ANTI-ESTABLISHMENT CAMPAIGN.
WE'RE TAKING ON BIG MONEY.
AND THAT'S WHY I THINK WE ARE
DOING AS WELL AS WE ARE DOING.
>> SENATOR, WE'RE GOING TO TAKE
A QUICK BREAK.
WHEN WE COME BACK, I HAVE A LOT
OF VERY SERIOUS QUESTIONS FOR
YOU.
BUT FIRST, YOU HAVE TO DO A
STUPID THING.
THIS IS TO TRY TO MAKE YOU HATE
ME AS MUCH AS YOU HATE THE REST
OF THE MEDIA.
>> NO, I'D NEVER HATE YOU.
>> THESE ARE NOT DESIGNED ABOUT
POLICY.
THEY ARE NOT DESIGNED TO MAKE
LOOK OR FEEL DUMB.
TAKE ONE.
>> HOW MANY PAIR OF UNDERWEAR DO
I HAVE?
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> I WOULD NEVER ASK -- IF YOU
CARE TO VOLUNTEER THE
INFORMATION --
>> AM I REALLY LARRY DAVID?
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> HERE WE GO.
>> WATCH, IT'S THE UNDERWEAR
QUESTION.
>> NO, I SWEAR.
HAD THERE BEEN ANY UNDERWEAR
QUESTIONS I WOULD BE TOO
EMBARRASSED TO ASK THEM.
I'D GET ALL RED AND BREAK OUT IN
HIVES.
DREAM JOB THAT YOU WOULD LIKE TO
HAVE RIGHT NOW IF YOU COULD NOT
BE A POLITICIAN.
>> PRESIDENT OF CNN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND IF I WERE PRESIDENT OF CNN,
TRUST ME, THE WAY MEDIA DEALS
WITH POLITICS WOULD RADICALLY
CHANGE.
MAYBE NBC.
THAT'S OKAY TOO.
I DIDN'T MEAN TO BE --
>> I WON'T TALK ABOUT THAT JUST
FOR OBVIOUS REASONS.
NUMBER TWO, WHAT DO YOU MOST
MISS THAT TECHNOLOGY HAS MADE
OBSOLETE?
>> BOOKS.
>> PAPER BOOKS INSTEAD OF --
>> PAPER BOOKS.
I MISS THE FACT THAT WHEN I'M IN
A CAR OR AT HOME THERE ARE NOT
ALL KINDS OF BUZZERS AND NOISES
GOING OFF MAKING ME A NERVOUS
WRECK.
I MISS PEACE AND QUIET, WHICH I
VERY MUCH ENJOY.
>> YOU WANT TO GO BACK TO THE
PREALERT TIME IN LIFE.
DO YOU CURSE?
[ LAUGHTER ]
>> NOT ON THIS SHOW.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND LAST ONE.
WHAT IS THE BIGGEST PUBLIC
MISCONCEPTION ABOUT YOU?
>> WELL, PEOPLE THINK I'M
GRUMPY.
[ LAUGHTER ]
PEOPLE THINK I AM TOO SERIOUS.
BUT I THINK WHAT PEOPLE DON'T
SEE IS I HAVE SEVEN BEAUTIFUL
GRANDCHILDREN WHO ARE THE JOY OF
MY LIFE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, WE'LL TAKE A
BREAK.
WE'LL K RIGHT BACK.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>>> WE'RE BACK -- WE'RE BACK NOW
WITH VERMONT SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS.
SENATOR, THANK YOU.
THE RACIALLY MOTIVATED SHOOTER
WHO KILLED NINE BLACK
CHURCHGOERS IN CHARLESTON, HE
GOT HIS GUN IN PART BECAUSE OF A
LOOPHOLE IN THE SYSTEM FOR
BACKGROUND CHECKS.
NOW, AS A CONGRESSMAN AND A
SENATOR FROM A RURAL STATE YOU
WERE MORE CONSERVATIVE ON SOME
GUN ISSUES IN THE PAST.
I HAVE SEEN YOUR VIEWS EVOLVE
SOME ON SOME GUN ISSUES IN
RECENT YEARS.
CAN YOU TELL ME WHAT POLICIES
YOU USED TO SUPPORT YOU THAT
DON'T SUPPORT ANYMORE?
>> LET ME TELL YOU SOMETHING
THAT MANY PEOPLE DON'T KNOW.
1988 I RAN FOR THE UNITED STATES
CONGRESS IN A THREE-WAY RACE.
AND WHAT THE GUN PEOPLE SAID,
YOU CAN VOTE FOR CANDIDATE A OR
CANDIDATE B, DON'T VOTE FOR
BERNIE SANDERS.
BECAUSE BACK IN 1988 I SAID IT
IS WRONG IN THIS COUNTRY FOR
PEOPLE TO BE BUYING ASSAULT
WEAPONS DESIGNED JUST TO KILL
HUMAN BEINGS.
SINCE I HAVE BEEN IN CONGRESS,
RACHEL, I HAVE VOTED FOR AN
INSTANT BACKGROUND CHECK WHICH
NEEDS TO BE MADE STRONGER AND
NEEDS TO BE EXPANDED.
I HAVE VOTED TO DO AWAY WITH THE
GUN SHOW LOOPHOLE.
AND WHAT I WANT TO SEE IS A DEAL
WITH THE STRAW MAN HE EXEMPTION
RIGHT NOW SO PEOPLE CAN LEGALLY
BUY GUNS AND GIVE IT TO
CRIMINALS.
I WANT TO SEE A RADICAL CHANGE
IN HOW WE DO MENTAL HEALTH IN
THIS COUNTRY BECAUSE YOU'VE GOT
THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE WALKING
AROUND THE STREETS OF AMERICA
WHO ARE SUICIDAL AND HOMICIDAL.
>> BUT AM I TRITE SAY YOU HAVE
EVOLVED SOME ON THESE ISSUES?
YOU DID VOTE AGAINST BACKGROUND
CHECKS, THE BRADY BILL --
>> I SUPPORTED BACKGROUND
CHECKS.
>> BUT YOU VOTED FIVE TIMES
AGAINST THE BRADY BILL.
>> THAT WAS ONE BILL THAT COMES
UP SEVERAL TIMES.
BUT HERE'S THE ISSUE.
LET ME BE VERY CLEAR ABOUT THIS.
BECAUSE ALL OF US, SOUTH
CAROLINA, GOD KNOWS, HAS SEEN
THE KINDS OF MASSACRES THAT ALL
OF AMERICA IS SEEING.
I BELIEVE THAT I AM IN A VERY
GOOD POSITION COMING FROM A
RURAL STATE THAT HAS VIRTUALLY
NO GUN CONTROL TO PUT TOGETHER A
CONSENSUS OF THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE, WHICH I THINK EXISTS,
WHICH SAYS WE ARE GOING TO KEEP
GUNS OUT OF THE HANDS OF PEOPLE
WHO SHOULD NOT HAVE THEM.
WE ARE GOING TO END THIS GUN
SHOW LOOPHOLE.
WE ARE GOING TO DEAL WITH THE
STRAW MAN SITUATION.
WE ARE GOING TO BAN WEAPONS THAT
ARE SOLELY DESIGNED TO KILL
PEOPLE.
I BELIEVE COMING FROM A RURAL
STATE THAT I CAN BRING TOGETHER
THE 60% OR 70% OF THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE WHO ARE SICK AND TIRED OF
SEEING THESE HORRIFIC MASSACRES
THAT APPEAR ALMOST EVERY COUPLE
OF WEEKS.
>> WE GOT ONE SPECIFIC VERY
INTERESTING VIEWER QUESTION ON
THIS SUBJECT FOR YOU.
IT CAME IN ON FACEBOOK FROM A
WOMAN NAMED MAGGIE THOMASSON.
AND SHE SAYS THIS -- "MY
QUESTION FOR BERNIE SANDERS IS
WHY DEVOTE AGAINST BANNING GUNS
ON AMTRAK?
WE CANNOT CARRY GUNS ON
AIRPLANES.
WHAT WAS HIS REASONING FOR
ALLOWING IT ON TRAINS?"
>> WELL, ACTUALLY, TO THE BEST
OF MY MEMORY, YOU CAN PUT
UNLOADED GUNS INTO THE BAGGAGE
DEPARTMENT OF A PLANE.
IN OTHER WORDS, IT'S NOT PEOPLE
CARRYING A GUN ON THE TRAIN.
IT'S PUTTING THEM IN BAGGAGE.
YOU'VE GOT HUNTERS WHO ARE GOING
FROM VERMONT TO THE MIDWEST, AND
THEY PUT THEIR WEAPONS UNLOADED
IN THE CARGO PART.
THAT'S THE REASON FOR IT.
>> BUT YOU CAN TRANSPORT THE
AMMUNITION ON YOUR TRAIN WITH
YOU.
YOU CAN ACCESS YOUR BAGGAGE FROM
ANYWHERE ON THE TRAIN.
THIS IS AN EXPANSION OF A PLACE
WHERE GUNS USED TO NOT BE AND
YOU SAID THEY SHOULD BE THERE.
>> NO, WHAT I'M SAYING IS WHAT I
VOTED ON FOR TRAINS IS THE SAME
AS EXISTS IN AIRPLANES.
IT IS THE SAME THING.
AND WHAT I THINK HERE, RACHEL,
IS IF WE ARE GOING TO MAKE
PROGRESS ON THIS ISSUE, AND I
KNOW HILLARY CLINTON HAS KIND OF
MISSTATE MY VIEW, AS A NATION WE
ARE GOING TO HAVE TO STOP
SHOUTING AT EACH OTHER AND WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE TO COME TOGETHER.
IT MEANS TO SAY THAT VERY STRONG
GUN CONTROL ADVOCATES MAY NOT
GET EVERYTHING THEY WANT AND
PEOPLE THINK THEY SHOULD HAVE A
MISSILE LAUNCHER IN THEIR BACK
YARD AS A CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHT,
MAY NOT HAVE THAT.
ALL RIGHT?
BUT THE QUESTION IS NOT SHOUTING
AT EACH OTHER.
THE QUESTION IS BRINGING PEOPLE
TOGETHER AROUND PROPOSALS THAT I
WOULD GET 60% OR 70% OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE BELIEVE IN.
AND I THINK I CAN DO THAT.
>> VOTING RIGHTS.
>> YES.
>> HAVE BECOME A PARTISAN ISSUE.
THEY DID NOT USED TO BE.
IN MY LIFETIME THEY DIDN'T FEEL
LIKE THEY WERE FOR A WHILE, BUT
THEY ARE NOW.
BROADLY SPEAKING, DEMOCRATS ARE
PUSHING TO EASE RESTRICTIONS ON
VOTING.
REPUBLICANS HAVE PUT NEW ONES
IN --
>> IT'S NOT EASING RESTRICTIONS.
WHAT DEMOCRATS ARE TRYING TO DO
IS MAKE SURE THAT EVERYBODY IN
THIS COUNTRY HAS A RIGHT TO VOTE
WHEN THEY'RE 18 YEARS OF AGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
I UNDERSTAND THAT.
LET ME SAY SOMETHING.
THIS MAY BE PERSONAL IF I RUN
FOR OFFICE.
YOU KNOW, SOMETIMES YOU LOSE,
SOMETIMES YOU WIN.
IT HAS NEVER OCCURRED TO ME AS A
CANDIDATE TO FIGURE OUT A WAY
THAT I COULD DENY THE VOTE TO
PEOPLE BECAUSE THEY MIGHT VOTE
AGAINST ME.
AND THE PEOPLE WHO DO THAT ARE
POLITICAL COWARDS.
THEY'RE AFRAID OF A FAIR
ELECTION.
WE HAVE A REAL CRISIS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
AND WE HAVE GOT TO PASS
LEGISLATION, MAYBE EVEN A
CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT, THAT
SAYS THAT EVERYBODY IN AMERICA
WHO'S 18 YEARS OF AGE OR OLDER
IS REGISTERED TO VOTE, END OF
DISCUSSION.
AND WHAT REPUBLICANS ARE DOING
IS SO UN-AMERICAN, IT IS SO
OUTRAGEOUS, THAT IT IS LITERALLY
BEYOND BELIEF.
THEY ARE POLITICAL COWARDS.
AND IF THEY CAN'T FACE A
RE-ELECTION THEY SHOULD GET
ANOTHER JOB.
>> AND AS A MATTER OF POLICY, IN
TERMS OF ELECTION LAW BY AND
LARGE IS STATE LAW.
>> THAT'S RIGHT.
>> AND BECAUSE REPUBLICANS HAVE
RUN THE TABLE IN THE SOUTH,
PARTICULARLY IN THE SOUTH VOTING
RIGHTS HAVE BEEN ROLLED BACK
MORE THAN AT ANY TIME SINCE THE
VOTING RIGHTS ACT.
IS THAT A FAILURE OF THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY TO NOT BE
ABLE --
>> THEN YOU'RE INTO ANOTHER
ISSUE, IS WHY THE DEMOCRATS HAVE
LOST THE SOUTH TO A LARGE
DEGREE.
IN MY VIEW, AND LET ME QUOTE
FROM MY FELLOW VERMONTER HOWARD
DEAN, DEMOCRATIC PARTY, AS
RADICAL AS IT MAY SEEM, SHOULD
BE A 50-STATE PARTY.
YOU CAN'T GIVE UP ON SOUTH
CAROLINA OR ALABAMA OR
MISSISSIPPI.
AND YOU'VE GOT TO START
SOMEWHERE AND GET GOOD
CANDIDATES.
AND THE OTHER THING HERE IS --
AND I'M GOING TO DO THIS IN THIS
CAMPAIGN.
I'M GOING TO GO OUT AND TALK TO
WHITE WORKING-CLASS AMERICANS
AND SAY WHY DO YOU KEEP VOTING
AGAINST YOUR OWN BEST INTERESTS?
[ APPLAUSE ]
WHY ARE WE VOTING -- WHY ARE YOU
VOTING FOR PEOPLE WHO ARE GOING
TO DENY YOU HEALTH CARE, WHO ARE
GOING TO SEND YOUR JOBS TO
CHINA, THEY'RE NOT GOING TO
RAISE THE MINIMUM WAGE?
AND WE HAVE GOT TO MAKE A MAJOR
FOCUS ON GETTING WHITE
WORKING-CLASS PEOPLE BACK INTO
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY TO SAY THAT
YOUR ENEMIES, THE PEOPLE WHO YOU
SHOULD BE OPPOSING ARE NOT GAY
PEOPLE, THEY'RE NOT IMMIGRANTS,
THEY ARE THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS
WHOSE GREED IS DESTROYING
AMERICA.
STAND WITH US.
LET'S TAKE THEM ON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> IT IS A BIPARTISAN TRADITION
OF PRESIDENTS IN THE MODERN ERA
TO ALWAYS PUT SOMEBODY FROM THE
OTHER PARTY IN THEIR CABINET.
IS THERE A REPUBLICAN IN THE
BERNIE SANDERS CABINET?
>> YOU WANT ME TO DESTROY SOME
NICE GUY'S POLITICAL CAREER
RIGHT HERE?
[ LAUGHTER ]
LOOK, I HAVE WORKED -- VETERAN'S
DAY IS COMING UP, BY THE WAY,
AND WE ALL I HOPE UNDERSTAND THE
SACRIFICE THAT SO MANY MEN AND
WOMEN HAVE MADE TO DEFEND THIS
COUNTRY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I'M VERY PROUD THAT I AM THE
FORMER CHAIRMAN OF THE VETERANS
COMMITTEE.
AND IN THAT REGARD I WORKED WITH
PEOPLE LIKE JOHN McCAIN IN THE
SENATE.
PEOPLE IN THE HOUSE.
REPUBLICANS.
IN ORDER TO PATS MOST
COMPREHENSIVE VETERANS HEALTH
CARE BILL IN THE MODERN HISTORY
OF THIS COUNTRY.
SO I CAN WORK WITH VETERANS.
BUT I ALSO -- I CAN WORK WITH
REPUBLICANS.
BUT THIS IS WHAT I ALSO WANT TO
SAY.
AND I SAY THIS I THINK UNIQUELY
OF ANY CANDIDATE, DEMOCRATIC OR
REPUBLICAN WHO'S RUNNING.
IF WE'RE GOING TO TRANSFORM
AMERICA SO THAT OUR ECONOMY
WORKS FOR ALL OF US AND NOT JUST
A HANDFUL OF PEOPLE ON THE TOP,
IF WE ARE GOING TO CHANGE A
CORRUPT CAMPAIGN FINANCE SYSTEM,
IT'S NOT JUST ELECTING BERNIE
SANDERS OR ANYBODY ELSE
PRESIDENT.
WE NEED A POLITICAL REVOLUTION.
THAT MEANS MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
HAVE GOT TO STAND UP AND GET
INVOLVED IN THE POLITICAL
PROCESS IN A WAY THAT WE HAVE
NOT DONE FOR MANY, MANY YEARS.
>> DO YOU THINK IT'S POSSIBLE?
I KNOW YOU BELIEVE IT'S
STRATEGICALLY WHAT YOU NEED.
>> LET ME BE HONEST WITH YOU,
RACHEL.
LET ME BE VERY HONEST WITH YOU.
AND YOU KNOW, OBVIOUSLY THIS IS
SELF-SERVING.
I RELIEVE -- WHY WOULD I BE
SELF-SERVING, RUNNING FOR
PRESIDENT?
I BELIEVE THAT A BERNIE SANDERS
NOMINATION, DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE
FOR PRESIDENT, COULD DO WHAT
WE'RE DOING RIGHT NOW, EXCITE A
LOT OF YOUNG PEOPLE,
WORKING-CLASS PEOPLE.
WE BRING OUT HUGE TURNOUTS TO
OUR RALLIES.
IF THE DEMOCRATS ARE GOING TO
TAKE BACK -- KEEP THE WHITE
HOUSE AND TAKE BACK THE SENATE
AND WIN GOVERNORSHIPS, WE NEED
TO GREATLY EXPAND VOTER TURNOUT.
I THINK OUR CAMPAIGN HAS THE
EXCITEMENT AND THE ENERGY TO DO
THAT.
IN THE SOUTH AND ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY.
>> SPEAKING OF ORGANIZING,
THIS -- I THINK WE'VE GOT A
PICTURE UP HERE.
THIS IS YOU IN 196 --
>> WHO'S THAT HANDSOME YOUNG
GUY?
>> I THINK AGE 21 ROUGHLY.
AND WHAT I BELIEVE YOU ARE DOING
HERE IS LEADING A SIT-IN AGAINST
SEGREGATED HOUSING AT THE
UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO.
SO HERE'S MY QUESTION.
WHAT IS THAT YOUNG ORGANIZER
THINKING?
AND WHAT DOES HE NEED TO LEARN
ABOUT THE WAY THE WORLD REALLY
WORKS?
>> WHAT HE WAS THINKING AT THAT
MOMENT IS EXACTLY THAT TIME, THE
EARLY '60s, THERE WERE
AFRICAN-AMERICAN YOUNG PEOPLE IN
GROUPS LIKE THE STUDENT
NON-VIOLENT COORDINATING
COMMITTEE WHO WERE GETTING THEIR
HEADS BUSTED OFF BY
SEGREGATIONISTS.
PEOPLE WERE BEING THROWN IN
JAIL.
DR. MARTIN LUTHER KING JR.
PEOPLE WERE REALLY SACRIFICING.
SO WHAT WE TRIED TO DO THERE IS
TO HELP OUR BROTHERS AND SISTERS
IN THE SOUTH DESEGREGATE.
BUT AT THE SAME TIME, AND WHAT
THAT DEMONSTRATION IS ABOUT, IS
THE STATE OF MY OWN UNIVERSITY,
THE UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO, STOP
KEEPING YOUR HOUSING THAT YOU
OWN SEGREGATED.
STOP SEGREGATED HOUSING AT THE
UNIVERSITY OF CHICAGO.
AND LATER I GOT INVOLVED WITH
SEGREGATED SCHOOLS IN THE CITY
OF CHICAGO.
>> SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS, THANK
YOU SO MUCH, SIR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> PLEASURE TO HAVE YOU HERE.
THANK YOU.
WE WILL BE RIGHT BACK.
WE'RE AT WINTHROP UNIVERSITY.
¶¶
>>> THEY ARE RELEVANT TO
WATERGATE AND THE COVER-UP.
>> I, WILLIAM JEFFERSON
CLINTON --
>> A PLAN THAT WILL PROVIDE
HEALTH CARE FOR EVERY AMERICAN.
>> WOMEN'S RIGHTS ARE HUMAN
RIGHTS ONCE AND FOR ALL.
>> SO HELP YOU GOD?
>> I DO.
>> I AM ABSOLUTELY --
>> ALTHOUGH WE WEREN'T ABLE TO
SHATTER THAT HARD AS GLASS
CEILING, THANKS TO YOU IT'S GOT
ABOUT 18 MILLION CRACKS IN IT.
>> I'M HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON.
>> HEY.
GREAT NAME.
I'M VAL.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>>> FORMER SECRETARY OF STATE
HILLARY RODHAM CLINTON.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
MADAM SECRETARY, THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR JOINING US.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
IT'S GREAT TO HAVE YOU HERE.
>> IT'S GREAT TO BE HERE.
>> YOU'RE SHAKING HANDS AND
GETTING VOTES EVEN RIGHT NOW
HERE.
>> WELL, I'M SHAKING HANDS
ANYWAY.
I HOPE I'M GETTING A FEW VOTES.
I'M GLAD TO BE HERE AT WINTHROP.
THIS IS GREAT.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> YOU HAVE A LOT OF FANS.
SO WE'RE IN THE SOUTH.
THIS IS THE FIRST IN THE SOUTH
FORUM.
>> YES.
>> YOU LIVED IN ARKANSAS FOR
ALMOST 20 YEARS.
>> YES.
>> BUT WHEN YOU LEFT THE WHITE
HOUSE, YOU DECIDED TO MOVE TO
NEW YORK INSTEAD OF RETURNING
BACK DOWN SOUTH.
>> RIGHT.
>> SHOULD SOUTHERN VOTERS READ
ANYTHING INTO THAT?
WILL YOU BE ABLE TO CHAMPION THE
SOUTH IF YOU ARE PRESIDENT?
>> WELL, I HAD, AS YOU SAID,
NEARLY 20 YEARS, GREAT YEARS IN
ARKANSAS.
MY DAUGHTER WAS BORN IN
I GOT MARRIED IN ARKANSAS.
I TAUGHT AT THE LAW SCHOOL AT
THE UNIVERSITY OF ARKANSAS.
I PRACTICED LAW ACROSS THE
STATE.
AND I LOVE ARKANSAS.
AND WHEN WE GOT OUT OF THE WHITE
HOUSE, WE DID MOVE TO NEW YORK,
BUT MY HUSBAND'S LIBRARY AND THE
CLINTON SCHOOL OF PUBLIC
SERVICE, ALL OF THAT IS IN
ARKANSAS, IN LITTLE ROCK.
IN FACT, AS WE SPEAK HE'S THERE
RIGHT NOW.
SO WE HAVE SO MANY TIES,
CONNECTIONS, DEAR FRIENDS, AND
YOU KNOW, IT WILL ALWAYS BE A
BIG PART OF WHO I AM.
>> IF YOU ARE ELECTED, YOU WILL
BE SUCCEEDING OUR NATION'S FIRST
AFRICAN-AMERICAN PRESIDENT.
>> MM-HMM.
>> WHAT DO YOU SAY TO
AFRICAN-AMERICAN VOTERS, EVEN
JUST PEOPLE IN THIS ROOM, WHO
ARE LOOKING AT A STAGE FULL OF
WHITE CANDIDATES TONIGHT FROM
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY, WONDERING
IF THEIR CHANCE FOR MEANINGFUL
CHANGE HAS PASSED?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I HAVE
BEEN COMMITTED TO AND WORKING ON
ISSUES THAT I THINK ARE
IMPORTANT TO ALL PEOPLE BUT IN
PARTICULAR TO PEOPLE WHO FEEL
AND ARE LEFT OUT, LEFT BEHIND,
MARGINALIZED.
YOU KNOW, MY FIRST JOB OUT OF
LAW SCHOOL WAS WITH THE
CHILDREN'S DEFENSE FUND, WORKING
FOR MARION WRIGHT EDELMAN FROM
BENNETSVILLE, SOUTH CAROLINA --
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I FEEL VERY STRONGLY THAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA DOESN'T GET THE
CREDIT HE DESERVES FOR THE GREAT
JOB HE'S DONE AS OUR PRESIDENT.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
I WANT TO BUILD ON THE PROGRESS
THAT HE'S MADE, BUT I WANT TO GO
FURTHER BECAUSE I THINK THAT HIS
PRINCIPAL CHALLENGE WAS SAVING
US FROM THE TERRIBLE FINANCIAL
CRISIS HE INHERITED, AND I THINK
HE PULLED US OUT OF THAT BIG
DITCH AND WE'RE NOW STANDING BUT
WE'RE NOT YET RUNNING.
SO FOR ME THIS IS ABOUT HOW DO
WE HAVE A NEW NEW DEAL, HOW DO
WE BEGIN TO GIVE EVERYBODY MORE
CHANCES.
I WANT TO BE THE PRESIDENT FOR
THE STRUGGLING, THE STRIVING AND
THE SUCCESSFUL, RACHEL.
I WANT EVERYONE TO FEEL THEY'VE
GOT A FUTURE IN THIS COUNTRY,
THAT IT'S GOING TO BE BETTER AND
BIGGER.
AND IN PARTICULAR I THINK WE'VE
GOT TO TAKE A HARD LOOK AT
WHAT'S HAPPENING ACROSS OUR
COUNTRY.
BUT IN PARTICULAR SINCE THIS IS
A FORUM ABOUT THE SOUTH, WE'VE
GOT SOME REALLY BIG ISSUES, LIKE
NOT ONLY ARE COMMUNITIES OF
COLOR BEING LEFT BEHIND AND
WE'VE GOT TO FIGURE OUT WHAT
WE'RE GOING TO DO ABOUT THAT,
BUT THIS RECENT STUDY, WHICH
SHOWS THAT WHITE MIDDLE-AGED
AMERICANS WITHOUT A HIGH SCHOOL
EDUCATION, YOU FIND THEM ACROSS
THE COUNTRY BUT THERE ARE A
DISPROPORTIONATE NUMBER OF THEM
ACROSS THE SOUTH, ARE DYING
EARLIER THAN THEIR PARENTS.
AND THEIR GRANDPARENTS.
AND WE'VE GOT A TERRIBLE CRISIS
OF HEALTH AND ADDICTION,
ALCOHOLISM, OBESITY.
WE'VE GOT REALLY BAD INDICATORS
FOR PEOPLE.
AND THAT'S THE KIND OF WORK I'VE
DONE ALL MY LIFE AND THAT'S WHAT
I WANT TO DO AS PRESIDENT, TO
REALLY BEGIN TO TURN AROUND SOME
OF THESE VERY DIFFICULT
CONDITIONS THAT PEOPLE ARE
COPING WITH.
>> VIEWERS IN BOTH PARTIES --
EXCUSE ME, VOTERS IN BOTH
PARTIES -- THERE'S THE TV BIAS.
VOTERS IN BOTH PARTIES ARE
CONCERNED THAT PART OF THE
REASON WE'RE NOT ADDRESSING
PROBLEMS LIKE THAT IS BECAUSE
THE SPECIAL INTERESTS GET WHAT
THEY WANT, THE MOST POWERFUL
SPECIAL INTERESTS GET WHAT THEY
WANT, EVEN WHEN IT HURTS REGULAR
AMERICANS AND THE REST OF THE
ECONOMY.
>> MM-HMM.
>> YOU HAVE RECEIVED A LOT OF
SUPPORT FROM PEOPLE WHO MADE
THEIR MONEY ON WALL STREET.
YOU HAVE A LOT OF WALL STREET
RELATIONSHIPS.
YOU'VE DONE PAID SPEECHES FOR
WALL STREET INSTITUTIONS.
THREE PAID SPEECHES FOR GOLDMAN
SACHS ALONE YOUR FIRST YEAR OUT
OF PUBLIC OFFICE, FOR WHICH THEY
PAID YOU OVER $600,000.
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO PEOPLE LIKE
SENATOR SANDERS WHO HAVE
CRITICIZED YOU AS BASICALLY
BEING TOO CLOSE TO THAT MOST
POWERFUL SPECIAL INTEREST, TOO
CLOSE TO WALL STREET INTERESTS
TO BE TRUSTED TO REEL THEM IN
WHEN THEY NEED TO BE REELED IN?
>> FIRST OF ALL, I REPRESENTED
NEW YORK.
SO I REPRESENTED UPSTATE NEW
YORK, RURAL NEW YORK, DYING
INDUSTRIAL TOWNS NEW YORK, AND I
REPRESENTED NEW YORK CITY, AND
THERE'S A LOT TO NEW YORK CITY
BEYOND WALL STREET.
BUT ANYONE WHO THINKS THAT THEY
CAN INFLUENCE WHAT I WILL DO
DOESN'T KNOW ME VERY WELL.
AND THEY CAN ACTUALLY LOOK AND
SEE WHAT I HAVE SAID AND DONE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- THROUGHOUT MY CAREER.
TAKE WALL STREET, FOR EXAMPLE.
I WENT TO WALL STREET.
I WENT TO THE NASDAQ IN DECEMBER
OF 2007 AND BASICALLY SAID, YOU
GUYS HAVE GOT TO STOP IT, WHAT
YOU ARE DOING IS NOT ONLY A
DISASTER FOR HOMEOWNERS BECAUSE
OF THE MORTGAGE FORECLOSURES AND
THE WAY THAT THEY HAD
MANIPULATED THE MORTGAGE MARKET,
BUT IT'S GOING TO HAVE DIRE
CONSEQUENCES FOR OUR COUNTRY.
I ALSO WAS ONE OF THE VERY FIRST
TO STAND UP AND SAY WE NEED TO
END THE SPECIAL TAX BENEFITS
THAT GO TO HEDGE FUNDS,
SOMETHING CALLED THE CARRIED
INTEREST LOOPHOLE.
SO I'VE BEEN ON THE RECORD.
AND PEOPLE CAN READ IT.
THEY KNOW WHAT I VOTED FOR.
THEY KNOW WHAT I'VE SAID.
BUT I THINK IT'S A BIGGER ISSUE.
I DO THINK THAT PEOPLE RIGHTLY
BELIEVE THAT CORPORATIONS AND
THE POWERFUL HAVE STACKED THE
DECK IN THEIR FAVOR AND AGAINST
EVERYBODY ELSE.
AND THAT'S NOT JUST WHAT HAPPENS
ON WALL STREET.
I MEAN, THE KOCH BROTHERS ARE
SOME OF THE BIGGEST DECK
STACKERS YOU CAN FIND.
AND THAT HAS NOTHING TO DO ABOUT
THE FINANCIAL MARKETS.
THEY ARE PROTECTING THEIR
CORPORATE INTERESTS.
THEY'RE PROTECTING THE FOSSIL
FUEL INDUSTRY.
THEY'RE PROTECTING THE
CONTINUATION OF PUMPING CARBON
INTO THE ATMOSPHERE.
WHAT DO WE HAVE TO DO ABOUT
THAT?
WELL, YES, YOU DO NEED A
PRESIDENT WHO WILL BE FORTH
RIGHT AND ABSOLUTELY CALL THEM
OUT.
EVERYBODY.
WHEREVER THEY ARE.
FOR WHAT THEY'RE DOING THAT
TILTS THE BALANCE AWAY FROM
VOTERS AND CITIZENS.
BUT VOTERS AND CITIZENS HAVE TO
HELP ME DO THAT.
AND HERE'S WHAT I MEAN BY THAT.
WE'VE GOT TO GET PEOPLE TO TURN
OUT AND VOTE.
IF WE ARE NOT ELECTING THE
LEADERS WHO ARE PROMOTING THESE
POLICIES, WE WOULD HAVE A BETTER
FIGHTING CHANCE TO GET BEYOND
WHAT IS HAPPENING WITH THE --
>> LET ME PRESS YOU ON THAT,
THOUGH.
BECAUSE IT'S NOT JUST WALL
STREET.
YOU'RE RIGHT.
AND IT'S A LOT OF DIFFERENT
TYPES OF SPECIAL ORGANIZED
SPECIAL INTERESTS.
AND ONE OF THE THINGS I FEEL
LIKE -- I'M A LIBERAL AND I AM A
POLICY-ORIENTED PERSON AND I
HAVE NOT A PERSON WHO'S
PREJUDICED ABOUT ANYBODY IN
TERMS OF WHERE THEY COME FROM.
I ALSO USE A LOT OF TECHNOLOGY.
THAT SAID I AM FREAKED OUT BY
THE POLITICAL INFLUENCE THAT THE
TECH INDUSTRY HAS RIGHT NOW,
PARTICULARLY IN THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY BECAUSE THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY IS THE MORE LIBERAL OF THE
TWO PARTIES AND I FEEL LIKE IF
THEY'RE GOING TO BE CAPTURED BY
THE HUGE AND RICHLY POWERFUL
TECH INDUSTRY I DON'T KNOW WHO
WILL EVER STAND UP TO THEM.
AND THERE'S A BIG REVOLVING DOOR
IN THE TECH INDUSTRY, AND THE
HIGHEST FLYERS IN THE DEMOCRATIC
PARTY.
DAVID PLOUFFE TO UBER, JAY
CARNEY TO AMAZON, CRYSTAL AYER
TO AIR BNB.
YOU HAVE SPEAKING FEES FROM
COMPANIES LIKE EBAY AND QUALCOMM
AND SALESFORCE.COM.
I'M NOT SAYING ANY OF THOSE
COMPANIES IS A BAD THING, BUT
THE TECH INDUSTRY NOW RIVALS
WALL STREET IN TERMS OF MONEY
AND INFLUENCE.
WHAT IS THE PROTECTION THAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE THAT THOSE
INDUSTRIES AREN'T JUST GOING TO
KEEP GETTING WHAT THEY WANT EVEN
WHEN IT HURTS THE REST OF US,
ESPECIALLY IF THE DEMOCRATS ARE
SO IN BED WITH THEM?
>> WELL, WE'VE NOW GONE ACROSS
THE COUNTRY, BECAUSE I THINK
YOU'RE RIGHT TO BROADEN THE
DISCUSSION.
>> YEAH.
>> AND IF YOU LOOK AT THE TECH
INDUSTRY, UNTIL RELATIVELY
RECENTLY THEY DIDN'T PAY MUCH
ATTENTION TO WASHINGTON, AS YOU
KNOW, BECAUSE THEY WERE TOO BUSY
INVENTING THINGS IN GARAGES --
>> AND BECOMING BILLIONAIRES.
EXACTLY.
SO LOOK, ANYTIME YOU HAVE AN
INDUSTRY THAT IS MATURING LIKE
THE TECH INDUSTRY CERTAINLY HAS,
AND THEY BEGIN THEN TO SAY HEY,
THERE MAY BE POLITICAL ADVANTAGE
TO WHAT WE NEED OUT OF
WASHINGTON, SO WE'D BETTER HAVE
CLOSER TIES, YOU HAVE TO TAKE A
HARD LOOK AT THAT.
I SUPPORT TAMMY BALDWIN'S BILL
TO STOP THE REVOLVING DOOR.
I DON'T THINK PEOPLE SHOULD BE
LEAVING CONGRESS OR AN
ADMINISTRATION AND IMMEDIATELY
GOING INTO INDUSTRIES THAT HAVE
A LOT OF BUSINESS BEFORE THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
LOOK, THIS IS NOT A NEW PROBLEM.
THIS IS AN AMERICAN PROBLEM.
WE HAVE THIS ROBUST, DYNAMIC
DEMOCRACY.
WE HAVE THIS FREE MARKET ECONOMY
WHICH I BELIEVE HAS PRODUCED AN
ENORMOUS ECONOMIC ADVANTAGE FOR
HARD-WORKING PEOPLE.
BUT WE'RE AT A POINT IN HISTORY
RIGHT NOW WHERE BOTH OUR
DEMOCRACY AND OUR ECONOMY ARE
NOT WORKING FOR THE MAJORITY.
THEY'RE WORKING FOR A SELECT
MINORITY VERY, VERY WELL.
AND WHAT I WANT TO DO AS
PRESIDENT IS TO MAKE THAT CASE
BUT TO MAKE IT IN A WAY THAT
PEOPLE WILL HEAR IT.
I'M WELL AWARE THAT PARTICULARLY
IN THE SOUTH I THINK A LOT OF
PEOPLE AGREE WITH ME THAT
THERE'S TOO MUCH POWER INVESTED
IN TOO FEW HANDS.
BUT I ALSO THINK THAT THEY MAY
NOT ALWAYS AGREE WITH THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY ABOUT WHAT
NEEDS TO BE DONE ABOUT IT.
SO WHAT I WANT IS A REAL
DIALOGUE WITH LEADERS FROM THE
SOUTH PUBLIC AND PRIVATE SECTOR
LEADERS WHO HAVE TO UNDERSTAND
WE ARE A 70% CONSUMPTION
ECONOMY.
IF PEOPLE'S WAGES AREN'T RISING,
IF PEOPLE ARE NOT SEEING THAT
THEIR LIFE IS GOING TO GET
BETTER AND THEIR KIDS' LIVES ARE
GOING TO GET BETTER, THAT'S BAD
FOR DEMOCRACY AND THAT'S BAD FOR
OUR ECONOMIC FUTURE.
WE HAVE TO HAVE A REALLY CANDID
DISCUSSION, WHICH IS ONE OF THE
REASONS WHY HAVING THIS FIRST IN
THE SOUTH FORUM MAKES SO MUCH
SENSE BECAUSE LOOK, IT'S NOT A
SURPRISE.
THE REPUBLICAN PARTY DOMINATES
IN THE SOUTH.
WE KNOW THAT.
AND IT'S BEEN A PRETTY ABRUPT
CHANGE OVER THE LAST 30 YEARS.
AND WE NEED TO UNDERSTAND MORE
ABOUT WHY PEOPLE EITHER ARE NOT
VOTING AT ALL, LEAVING THE FIELD
TO MAYBE THOSE THEY DISAGREE
WITH OR WHOSE INTERESTS ARE NOT
THE SAME, OR WHY OTHER PEOPLE
DON'T TRUST THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY
OR A PROGRESSIVE APPROACH TO
SOLVING THESE PROBLEMS.
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT AN ISSUE
THAT IS BECOMING LESS PARTISAN
OVER TIME.
AND THAT'S THE DEATH PENALTY.
>> YEAH.
>> YOU'VE DESCRIBED YOURSELF IN
THE PAST AS AN UNENTHUSIASTIC
SUPPORTER OF THE DEATH PENALTY.
YOU RECENTLY REITERATED YOU
STILL SUPPORT IT IN SOME CASES.
I REALLY BELIEVE THE DEATH
PENALTY SYSTEM IN THIS COUNTRY
IS A MESS.
JUST LOGISTICALLY WHEN IT COMES
TO --
>> IT IS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> IF THE SUPREME COURT STRUCK
DOWN THE DEATH PENALTY SOMETIME
SOON, AS JUSTICE SCALIA HAS
SUGGESTED THAT THEY MIGHT, WOULD
YOU BE DISAPPOINTED?
>> NO.
>> WOULD YOU THINK WE WERE
LOSING SOMETHING OF VALUE?
>> NO.
HERE'S WHAT I'VE SAID.
THE VAST MAJORITY OF DEATH
PENALTY CASE, AS YOU KNOW, ARISE
OUT OF STATE JUDICIAL
PROCEEDINGS.
AND I DO THINK A NUMBER OF
STATES, AGAIN, PREDOMINANTLY BUT
NOT EXCLUSIVELY IN THE SOUTH
HAVE MOVED MUCH TOO QUICKLY TO
TRY PEOPLE FOR CAPITAL OFFENSES
THAT CARRY THE DEATH PENALTY.
AND THE DEATH ROWS IN A NUMBER
OF SOUTHERN STATES ARE STILL
QUITE POPULATED EVEN THOUGH
PEOPLE GO THROUGH THEIR JUDICIAL
REMEDIES.
AND I DON'T THINK THAT YOU CAN
MAKE A CASE THAT ALL THAT NEEDED
TO BE DONE TO PROTECT AGAINST
DISCRIMINATION AND UNFAIRNESS
AND LACK OF DUE PROCESS HAS BEEN
DONE.
SO I THINK STATES SHOULD TAKE A
REALLY HARD LOOK AT THIS.
AND IF, YOU KNOW, THE SUPREME
COURT SAID NO, IT VIOLATES THE
EIGHTH AMENDMENT, IT'S CRUEL AND
UNUSUAL PUNISHMENT, I WOULD
BREATHE A SIGH OF RELIEF ABOUT
THAT BECAUSE I THINK MANY STATES
HAVE GONE WAY TOO FAR.
WHAT I WAS TALKING ABOUT,
THOUGH, IN MY REMARKS RECENTLY
WAS THE FEDERAL SYSTEM, WHERE
THE NUMBERS ARE MUCH SMALLER
BECAUSE THERE'S NOT THAT MUCH
FEDERAL JURISDICTION.
IT'S MORE FOCUSED.
AND I DO HAVE SOME, YOU KNOW,
QUESTIONS ABOUT REMOVING IT
COMPLETELY FOR TERRORISM AS AN
EXAMPLE --
>> BOSTON MARATHON.
YOU KNOW, RIGHT NOW KHALID
SHAIKH MOHAMMED, THE MASTERMIND
BEHIND THE 9/11 ATTACKS, IS
GOING THROUGH THE JUDICIAL
PROCESS.
WE HAD TIMOTHY McVEIGH WHO PUT A
BOMB AT THE FEDERAL BUILDING IN
OKLAHOMA CITY.
SO THERE ARE SOME REALLY HEINOUS
CRIMES THAT ARE IN MY VIEW STILL
ARGUABLY ONES THAT SHOULD
POTENTIALLY HAVE THE DEATH
PENALTY.
>> THE CHARLESTON MASSACRE THAT
HAPPENED IN SOUTH CAROLINA,
RACIALLY MOTIVATED KILLING OF
THOSE CHURCHGOERS?
>> RACIALLY MOTIVATED.
AND I THINK THAT'S THE KIND OF
CASE THAT WOULD CAUSE PEOPLE TO
HAVE A LEGITIMATE DISCUSSION
ABOUT WHETHER OR NOT IT'S
APPROPRIATE.
BUT THERE HAVE BEEN TOO MANY
CASES PUT INTO THE CAPITAL
OFFENSE CATEGORY THAN WHAT I
THINK IS MERITED.
>> ON ANOTHER CRIMINAL JUSTICE
MATTER AND ANOTHER ONE RELATED
TO SOUTH CAROLINA, THE COUNTRY
JUST RECOILED IN HORROR
RECENTLY.
WE HAD ANOTHER LAW ENFORCEMENT
VIDEO THAT CAPTIVATED THE
COUNTRY.
IN THIS CASE IT WAS A POLICE
OFFICER FILMED FLIPPING OVER AND
DRAGGING A HIGH SCHOOL STUDENT
IN A SOUTH CAROLINA CLASSROOM.
THAT OFFICER HAS BEEN FIRED.
THAT SAID, SOME STUDENTS WALKED
OUT OF THE SCHOOL TO PROTEST THE
OFFICER BEING FIRED.
AND I KNOW THAT YOU'VE SPOKEN
OUT ABOUT HOW INAPPROPRIATE YOU
FELT LIKE THAT OFFICER'S ACTIONS
WERE.
>> RIGHT.
>> HERE'S THE QUESTION.
SHOULD THERE BE POLICE OFFICERS
IN CLASSROOMS AT ALL HANDLING
SCHOOL DISCIPLINE MATTERS, AND
IF THEY ARE, IN SOME HIGH
SCHOOLS, SHOULD THEY BE IN ALL
HIGH SCHOOLS SO THAT WE ARE NOT
LOOKING AT A DISCRIMINATORY USE
OF BASICALLY THE CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM FOR SOME KIDS AND
NOT ALL?
>> WELL, THE FIRST THING I WOULD
SAY IS THAT WHAT HAPPENED IN THE
SCHOOL HERE IN SOUTH CAROLINA
WAS JUST APPALLING TO ME.
ADULTS SHOULD BE TRAINED TO USE
NON-VIOLENT, NON-CONFRONTATIONAL
MEASURES IN DEALING WITH SCHOOL
PROBLEMS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- DISCIPLINE PROBLEMS, WHATEVER
THEY MAY BE.
AND I THINK THAT WE HAVE -- WE
HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO TO TRY
TO ONCE AGAIN UNDERSTAND WHAT IS
THE BEST WAY TO DEAL WITH --
LET'S STAY WITH THE SCHOOL
EXAMPLE.
TO DEAL WITH KIDS WHO BRING
THEIR PROBLEMS TO SCHOOL.
BECAUSE A LOT OF KIDS WHO HAVE A
LOT OF PROBLEMS IN OUR SOCIETY
RIGHT NOW.
IN FACT, AS I RECALL THAT CASE,
THE YOUNG WOMAN WAS IN FOSTER
CARE.
WE'RE NOT DOING ENOUGH TO
SUPPORT EVERY CHILD.
SOME KIDS DON'T NEED A LOT OF
SUPPORT.
THEY GO TO SCHOOL, THEY GO HOME,
THEY'RE FINE.
BUT WE HAVE INCREASING NUMBERS
OF KIDS WHO NEED EXTRA HELP,
EXTRA ATTENTION, AND SOMETIMES
PSYCHOLOGICAL OR OTHER KINDS OF
COUNSELING.
IN FACT, I'M REALLY DISTRESSED
THAT WE HAVE A NEW UNFORTUNATE
FACT, AND THAT IS 51%, 51% OF
THE CHILDREN IN OUR PUBLIC
SCHOOLS TODAY ARE ELIGIBLE FOR
FREE OR REDUCED LUNCH.
IT'S THE FIRST TIME WE'VE EVER
BEEN ABOVE THE 50%.
THAT WE HAVE A MAJORITY OF KIDS
COMING FROM IMPOVERISHED
BACKGROUNDS IN OUR SCHOOLS.
WE CAN'T ACT LIKE IT'S THE
1950s.
WE HAVE TO ACT LIKE IT IS, 2015.
WHAT ARE WE GOING TO DO TO HELP
EVERY SINGLE CHILD?
AND FOR ME THAT --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DOES THAT INCLUDE POLICE
OFFICERS IN SCHOOLS, THOUGH?
>> I THINK THAT HAS TO BE A LAST
RESORT.
I THINK THERE CAN BE SOME PEOPLE
WITH LAW ENFORCEMENT BACKGROUNDS
WHO ARE TRAINED TO DEAL WITH
VERY DIFFICULT SITUATIONS.
BUT IT'S HARD FOR ME TO
UNDERSTAND WHY THE SUSPENSION
AND EXPULSION RATE IS SO MUCH
HIGHER FOR BLACK KIDS THAN FOR
WHITE KIDS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
THERE'S A LARGER ISSUE HERE,
THOUGH, RACHEL.
AND I MET WITH A GROUP OF
MOTHERS IN CHICAGO A FEW DAYS
AGO, MOTHERS OF YOUNG PEOPLE WHO
HAVE DIED EITHER AT THE HANDS OF
POLICE OR AT THE HANDS OF
CIVILIANS OR GANG MEMBERS.
AND I SAT AT THAT TABLE AND I
LISTENED TO THE MOTHERS TALK
ABOUT WHAT IT WAS LIKE TO -- IN
ONE MOM'S CASE IN CHICAGO HER
DAUGHTER HAD JUST COME BACK FROM
BEING IN A GROUP THAT PERFORMED
AT PRESIDENT OBAMA'S SECOND
INAUGURATION.
SHE WAS HANGING OUT WITH FRIENDS
IN A PARK ACROSS FROM THE SCHOOL
SHE ATTENDED.
WAS HIT BY, MURDERED BY A STRAY
BULLET.
YOU KNOW, HER MOTHER WAS
WAITS
ING FOR HER TO COME HOME.
OR TALKING TO TRAYVON MARTIN'S
MOTHER.
YOU KNOW, I JUST THINK WE ALL
NEED TO TAKE A VERY BIG
COLLECTIVE BREATH AND ASK
OURSELVES WHAT IS HAPPENING?
AND WHAT IS MOTIVATING THE KIND
OF VIOLENCE WE'RE SEEING.
AND IT'S PARTICULARLY TROUBLING
WHEN IT'S FROM A POSITION OF
AUTHORITY, WHETHER IT'S IN A
SCHOOL OR FROM A POLICE OFFICER
ON THE STREET.
[ APPLAUSE ]
BUT THAT IS NOT THE ONLY PLACE
THIS IS HAPPENING.
IT'S HAPPENING IN OUR STREETS.
AS I WAS SITTING IN THAT MEETING
LISTENING TO THE PAIN AND THE
ANGUISH OF THE MOTHERS TALKING
TO ME, A 9-YEAR-OLD BOY IN
CHICAGO ON HIS WAY TO HIS
GRANDMOTHER'S HOUSE, HOLDING HIS
BASKETBALL, WHICH HE TOOK
EVERYWHERE WITH HIM, WAS LURED
INTO AN ALLEY AND SHOT.
HE WAS ASSASSINATED BECAUSE OF
SOME KIND OF GANG-RELATED FEUD
INVOLVING APPARENTLY HIS FATHER.
THIS HAS TO END.
I MEAN, IT'S ONE OF THE REASONS
WHY I'M SO PASSIONATE ABOUT GUN
SAFETY
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- AND ENDING THE VIOLENCE,
WHOEVER USES THE GUN.
PEOPLE NEED TO STOP AND THINK.
I'M NOT SAYING IT'S NEVER, EVER
REQUIRED IN LAW ENFORCEMENT.
I WOULD NEVER SAY THAT.
BUT IT DOESN'T NEED TO BE THE
FIRST CHOICE.
IT DOESN'T NEED TO BE THE ONLY
TOOL THAT WE GIVE OUR LAW
ENFORCEMENT OFFICERS TO DEAL
WITH DIFFICULT SITUATIONS.
AND IN MANY OF THE SHOOTINGS
WE'VE SEEN, THE WALTER SCOTT
SHOOTING, I MEAN, WHY?
YOU KNOW, IT MAKES NO SENSE WHY
THAT HAPPENED.
I THINK WE'VE GOT TO DO A BETTER
JOB WORKING WITH PEOPLE IN
POSITIONS OF AUTHORITY TO DEAL
WITH THE RUN-OF-THE-MILL
DISCIPLINARY ISSUES OR THE
PROBLEMS ON THE STREET.
I STILL CAN'T GET OVER THAT ERIC
GARNER IN STATEN ISLAND IN NEW
YORK DIED FROM A CHOKE HOLD.
HE WAS SELLING LOOSE CIGARETTES.
THAT'S ALL HE WAS DOING.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND YEAH, WAS IT AGAINST THE
LAW?
YEAH, IT WAS AGAINST THE LAW.
BUT I MET -- HIS MOTHER WAS ONE
OF THE PEOPLE THERE.
AND HE HAD KIDS.
HE HAD A FAMILY.
AND OKAY.
SO MAYBE HE SHOULDN'T HAVE BEEN
SELLING CIGARETTES.
BUT DID HE DESERVE TO DIE
BECAUSE OF THAT?
ABSOLUTELY NOT.
SO WE ALL NEED TO SAY WAIT A
MINUTE, TIME OUT, LET'S WORK ON
MAKING THIS FAIR, REASONABLE,
AND PEACEFUL INSOFAR AS
POSSIBLE.
>> WE ARE GOING TO TAKE A BREAK.
WE'RE GOING TO COME BACK WITH
ROUND 2.
I'M GOING TO MAKE YOU DO THIS.
I'LL EXPLAIN
¶¶
>>> WE ARE BACK WITH FORMER
SECRETARY OF STATE HILLARY
CLINTON.
HERE'S HOW THIS GOES.
QUESTIONS IN HERE ARE NOT POLICY
QUESTIONS.
THEY'RE ALSO NOT DESIGNED TO
MAKE YOU LOOK OR FEEL DUMB.
SO DON'T BLAME ME FOR MAKING YOU
DO THIS.
EVERYBODY ELSE DID.
PICK ONE.
>> THE ACADEMY AWARD GOES TO.
>> YEAH.
EXCEPT OPPOSITE.
BECAUSE IT'S NO REWARD.
ALL RIGHT.
IF YOU HAD TIME TO LEARN A NEW
LANGUAGE WHICH LANGUAGE WOULD
YOU PICK?
>> SPANISH.
>> WHY?
>> BECAUSE WE HAVE A LOT OF
SPANISH-SPEAKING PEOPLE IN OUR
COUNTRY.
I WANT TO SXHUKT BETTER WITH
THEM.
>> INTROVERT OR EXTROVERT?
>> I AM AN INTRO EXTROVERT.
HERE'S WHAT I MEAN BY THAT.
I LOVE BEING WITH PEOPLE.
I LOVE ALL OF THE EXCITEMENT AND
I LOVE MEETING PEOPLE AND
HEARING THEIR STORIES.
BUT I ALSO LIKE TIME ALONE AND I
LIKE TO THINK AND RELAX AND
SLEEP AND STUFF LIKE THAT.
SO I GUESS I'M A LITTLE OF BOTH.
>> ALL RIGHT.
THAT IS A HARD ONE.
YOU'RE NOT ALLOWED TO SQUIRM OUT
OF IT.
I'LL LET YOU KNOW IN ADVANCE.
>> CAN I DELEGATE IT TO SOMEONE
ELSE?
>> NO.
THERE ARE NO LIFELINES ON THIS
STAGE.
IF YOU HAD TO PICK SOMEBODY, YOU
HAD TO, FROM THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL FIELD THIS YEAR TO
BE YOUR VICE PRESIDENT, THERE
WAS A NATIONAL CRISIS AND THERE
HAD TO BE A UNITY TICKET AND IT
WAS FOR THE GOOD OF THE NATION
AND THOSE WERE YOUR NATIONS,
THOSE 15 MEN AND WOMEN, WHO
WOULD YOU CHOOSE?
RUIN YOUR LIFE RIGHT HERE.
DO IT.
>> WELL, I'M GOING TO SAY
WHOEVER I NAME WILL REALLY GET
HURT IN THE REPUBLICAN PARTY.
AND SO I DON'T KNOW IF I WANT TO
DO THAT.
BUT -- WOW.
>> YOU COULD DO IT TACTICALLY.
YOU COULD --
>> YEAH, I COULD.
[ LAUGHTER ]
YOU KNOW, THERE ARE REPUBLICANS
I COULD PICK.
JUST NONE OF THEM.
>> OKAY.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
BUT FOR THIS QUESTION YOU'VE GOT
TO PICK ONE OF THEM.
>> YOU KNOW, RACHEL, I'M NOT
GOING TO PICK ONE OF THEM.
I KNOW YOU'RE GOING TO BE
DISAPPOINTED.
I KNOW THAT PEOPLE ARE GOING TO
SAY I DODGED THE QUESTION.
THE FACT IS I AM DODGING IT.
I DON'T WANT TO PICK ANY OF
THEM.
TO BE MY RUNNING MATE.
I'LL WORK WITH THEM ALL BUT I
DON'T WANT THEM TO BE MY RUNNING
MATE.
>> WHEN I SAY THE PHRASE "HUSH
PUPPY," DO YOU THINK FOOD,
FOOTWEAR, OR FIDO?
>> I THINK THE FIRST TWO.
EATING HUSH PUPPIES IN MY HUSH
PUPPIES.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU FOR LETTING ME DO
THAT.
BLACK MARK AGAINST YOU FOR
SQUIRMING OUT OF THE VP ONE.
>> I'M SORRY.
>> HERE'S A SERIOUS QUESTION.
OF ALL OF THE CANDIDATES ON THE
DEMOCRATIC SIDE YOU ARE RIGHTLY
OR WRONGLY CONSIDERED TO BE THE
MOST HAWKISH.
YOU HAVE SUPPORTED ALL OF
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S MILITARY
INTERVENTIONS AND SOME THAT HE
HASN'T.
OBVIOUSLY THE IRAQ WAR FOR WHICH
YOU HAVE APOLOGIZED.
YOU SAID THAT WAS A MISTAKE.
BOMBING LIBYA EARLIER THAN WE
EVENTUALLY DID.
NOW WITH SYRIA NO-FLY ZONE.
FOR AMERICAN MILITARY FAMILIES
WHO HAVE SEEN DEPLOYMENT AFTER
DEPLOYMENT AFTER DEPLOYMENT FOR
THE LAST 14 YEARS, WHEN I LOOK
AT YOUR RECORD I THINK A
PRESIDENT HILLARY CLINTON WOULD
NOT BE EXPECTED TO SLOW THAT
DEPLOYMENT PACE.
IS IT FAIR FOR PEOPLE TO EXPECT
THAT YOU WOULD BE A MORE
AGGRESSIVE COMMANDER IN CHIEF
THAN PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS BEEN?
>> NO.
AND HERE'S WHY.
I SPENT A LOT OF TIME WITH
PRESIDENT OBAMA IN THE SITUATION
ROOM STRUGGLING OVER A LOT OF
REALLY DIFFICULT DECISIONS.
I THINK THE NEXT PRESIDENT'S
GOING TO HAVE THE SAME AND MAYBE
DIFFERENT BUT CONTINUATIONS OF
SOME OF THE ONES WE CURRENTLY
HAVE TO STRUGGLE OVER AS WELL.
I WANT US TO USE DIPLOMACY,
WHICH IS WHY I SPENT 18 MONTHS
PUTTING TOGETHER THE SANCTIONS
AGAINST IRAN SO WE COULD FORCE
THEM TO THE NEGOTIATING TABLE TO
TRY TO PREVENT THEM FROM GETTING
A NUCLEAR WEAPON AND END THE
TALK OF BOMBING THEM AND GOING
TO WAR AGAINST THEM BUT INSTEAD
USING DIPLOMACY.
THAT IS HOW I WILL APPROACH
THESE ISSUES.
HOWEVER, I WILL NOT, I THINK
IT'S IRRESPONSIBLE TO RULE OUT
FORCE.
I JUST WILL NOT DO THAT.
BUT IT SHOULD ALWAYS BE THE LAST
RESORT, NOT THE FIRST CHOICE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THE LAST TIME THAT YOU AND I
SPOKE ON MSNBC, YOU DEFENDED
PRESIDENT CLINTON'S SIGNING THE
DEFENSE OF MARRIAGE ACT IN 1996
AS SOMETHING THAT WAS INTENDED
TO HEAD OFF A MOVEMENT FOR A
FEDERAL CONSTITUTIONAL
AMENDMENT.
>> RIGHT.
>> ON THAT SAME ISSUE THAT WOULD
HAVE BEEN EVEN WORSE THAN DOMA
WAS.
>> RIGHT.
>> THERE'S BEEN A LITTLE BIT OF
A BACKLASH TO SOME OF THOSE
COMMENTS YOU MADE INCLUDING FROM
SOME OF YOUR OWN SUPPORTERS AND
SENATOR SANDERS SAYING THAT
ACTUALLY IN TIME, 1996, THERE
WASN'T A CONSTITUTIONAL
AMENDMENT IN THE WORKS AT THE
TIME.
IS THAT TRUE?
DO YOU STAND BY WHAT YOU SAID OR
IS THAT A MISCHARACTERIZATION OF
WHAT WAS GOING ON THEN?
>> WELL, CERTAINLY IN THINKING
BACK ON IT THOSE WERE PRIVATE
CONVERSATIONS THAT PEOPLE DID
HAVE.
AND I AM, YOU KNOW, MORE THAN
WILLING TO SAY AGAIN THAT THAT
WAS SOMETHING THAT CAME UP IN
PRIVATE DISCUSSIONS THAT I HAD.
THE IMPORTANT THING IS DOMA IS
GONE.
THE CONSTITUTION --
>> THE WORRY -- SORRY.
THE WORRY ABOUT A CONSTITUTIONAL
AMENDMENT WAS BEING DISCUSSED
PRIVATELY IF NOT PUBLICLY.
>> YES.
AND LOOK WHAT HAPPENED UNDER THE
GEORGE W. BUSH ADMINISTRATION
WHEN IT WAS KARL ROVE'S STRATEGY
TO PUT CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENTS
ON STATE BALLOTS WHICH ALL BUT A
FEW PASSED.
IT WAS ONE OF THE REASONS WHY I
THINK THAT THE KERRY CAMPAIGN
HAD SOME CHALLENGES IN 2004.
THIS WAS A VERY REAL PROBLEM
THAT PEOPLE WERE CONCERNED
ABOUT.
AND YOU KNOW, IF I'M WRONG ABOUT
THE PUBLIC DEBATE, I OBVIOUSLY
TAKE RESPONSIBILITY FOR THAT.
BUT I THINK THE IMPORTANT THING
IS THAT WE ARE NOW BEYOND THAT.
AND MY HUSBAND HAS CERTAINLY
SAID AND I AGREE WITH WHAT HE
SAID, THAT YOU KNOW, NOW
THANKFULLY WE HAVE MOVED TO A
STAGE WHERE MARRIAGE EQUALITY IS
THE LAW OF THE LAND.
WHAT WE HAVEN'T YET DONE IS TO
DEAL WITH THE DISCRIMINATION
THAT STILL EXISTS AND TO TRY TO
FIGURE OUT HOW YOU CAN HELP
PEOPLE WHO CAN NOW LEGALLY GET
MARRIED ON SATURDAY AND THEN GET
FIRED ON MONDAY.
AND THAT'S THE NEXT BIG
CHALLENGE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ON THAT POINT, HOUSTON IS NOW
THE LARGEST CITY IN THE COUNTRY
THAT HAS NO ANTI-DISCRIMINATION
LAW BECAUSE VOTERS THERE BY MORE
THAN A 20-POINT MARGIN RESCINDED
IT.
YOU CAN GET FIRED FOR YOUR BOSS
THINKING YOU'RE GAY.
YOU CAN GET THROWN OUT OF YOUR
HOUSE IF YOU'RE TRANSGENDER.
THAT'S LAW NOW IN HOUSTON.
AND HOUSTON IS IN TEXAS.
BUT HOUSTON IS A BLUE DOT IN
TEXAS.
THEY HAVE A LESBIAN MAYOR AND
THEY HAVE A LOT OF PROGRESSIVE
THINGS ABOUT THAT CITY.
IF THE PROGRESSIVE MOVEMENT AND
DEMOCRATS WHO SUPPORT THAT KIND
OF THING CAN'T BUILD AND HOLD
THAT KIND OF A BASIC CIVIL
RIGHTS PROTECTION IN A CITY LIKE
HOUSTON, IS THERE SOMETHING
WRONG?
WHY DID THAT VOTE GO SO BADLY?
BECAUSE IT WASN'T EVEN CLOSE.
>> WELL, RACHEL, LOOK AT WHAT
HAPPENED BECAUSE YOU'RE RIGHT.
THIS ORDINANCE IS SIMILAR TO
ORDINANCES ACROSS AMERICA
INCLUDING IN OTHER CITIES IN
TEXAS.
RIGHT?
BUT WHAT THE FAR RIGHT DID VERY
SUCCESSFULLY IS TO REALLY
ENGENDER A LOT OF FEAR AND A LOT
OF ANXIETY AND CREATE THIS
BACKLASH AGAINST THIS ORDINANCE.
AND THEY USED, YOU KNOW, THE
BATHROOM ISSUE.
AND YET YOU COULD GO TO ANOTHER
CITY IN TEXAS LIKE SAN ANTONIO
AND YOU WOULD KNOW THAT THAT WAS
TOTALLY WITHOUT MERIT, THAT
THERE WAS NO BASIS FOR IT.
NOW, I THINK THAT THIS IS A
REMINDER THAT IF YOU STAND FOR
EQUAL RIGHTS, IF YOU STAND
AGAINST DISCRIMINATION, YOU
DON'T JUST DO IT ONCE AND YOU'RE
DONE.
YOU'VE GOT TO KEEP FIGHTING FOR
IT AND YOU'VE GOT TO KEEP
STANDING UP FOR IT.
YOU'VE GOT TO KEEP MOVING
FORWARD.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> ALL RIGHT.
I WANT TO INTRODUCE YOU TO
SOMEBODY.
THIS IS YOU ON YOUR WEDDING DAY.
>> OH, YEAH.
>> OCTOBER 1, 1975.
IF YOU BOTH HAD THOSE HAIRCUTS
RIGHT NOW YOU WOULD BE SO HIP IT
HURT.
>> YEAH, I KNOW.
>> BUT SOMEBODY WHO IS TRYING
RIGHT NOW FOR THE SECOND TIME TO
ASCEND TO THAT SAME OFFICE WHICH
HE HAS ALREADY HELD, IF YOU
COULD GO BACK IN TIME AND TELL
THAT YOUNG WOMAN NOT TO WAIT,
THAT SHE'S THE FUTURE PRESIDENT
AND SHE SHOULD GO FIRST --
>> NO.
>> WOULD YOU TELL HER THAT?
BECAUSE THAT WAS ABSOLUTELY NOT
IN HER MIND.
I MEAN, I WAS PRACTICING LAW.
I WAS, YOU KNOW, CHAIRING THE
BOARD OF THE CHILDREN'S DEFENSE
FUND IN ARKANSAS, ADVOCATE FOR
CHILDREN AND FAMILIES.
AND I WAS ABOUT TO BE APPOINTED
TO THE LEGAL SERVICES
CORPORATION BY PRESIDENT CARTER.
I HAD A VERY FULL PLATE OF
THINGS I LOVE TO DO.
AND I DID NOT EVER SERIOUSLY
THINK ABOUT RUNNING FOR OFFICE
UNTIL 1998, WHEN I GOT -- OR
'99.
1999, WHEN I GOT CONVINCED TO
RUN FOR THE SENATE.
SO NO.
WE LOOK SO YOUNG AND HIS HAIR IS
NOT WHITE.
IT'S A LONG TIME AGO.
>> YOU GUYS SHOULD GO BACK TO
THOSE HAIRCUTS, THOUGH.
I KNOW I'M NOT SUPPOSED TO GIVE
YOU ADVICE.
BUT HONESTLY, THAT'S VERY HIP
RIGHT NOW.
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, YEAH.
I'M LOOKING AT THAT -- I
ACTUALLY -- AND I KNOW WOMEN OF
A CERTAIN AGE WILL REMEMBER
THIS.
THAT WAS A PERMANENT.
>> YEAH.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> IT WAS A PERMANENT AND I HAD
SUCH STRAIGHT HAIR -- I KNEW
WE'D END UP TALKING ABOUT HAIR.
I HAD SUCH STRAIGHT HAIR IT TOOK
LIKE THREE TIMES TO GET IT.
BUT YEAH, THAT WAS OUR WEDDING
DAY.
OH, MY GOSH.
IT WAS GREAT.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
THANK YOU SO MUCH.
>> I WANT TO THANK EVERYBODY AT
WINTHROP UNIVERSITY IN ROCK