SPINA I KNOW IT'S HARD NOT TO
INTERRUPT.
>> ARE YOU DISAPPOINTED BY THE
LIKELY REPUBLICAN AND DEMOCRATIC
NOMINEES?
>> WHAT DIFFERENCE AT THIS POINT
IS A MAY?
JOHN: WE HAVE HEARD SO MUCH FROM
THE REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS.
NOW IT'S TIME TO HEAR FROM THE
LIBERTARIANS.
THE THREE TOPPLING PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATE DEBATE HERE TONIGHT.
IN OUR TWO-PART LIBERTARIAN
PRESIDENTIAL FORUM.
AND NOW, JOHN STOSSEL.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: WELCOME TO OUR LIBERTARIAN
FORUM.
TONIGHT IS THE FIRST OF TWO
DEBATES AMONG THE LIBERTARIAN
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES.
GIVEN THAT THE PRESIDENTIAL
FRONT-RUNNERS, HILLARY CLINTON
AND DONALD TRUMP HAVE HUGE
UNFAVORABILITY RATINGS WORSE
THAN ANY CANDIDATE IN 30 YEARS,
IT'S TIME TO HEAR FROM -- WITH
US TONIGHT ARE THE THREE LEADING
LIBERTARIAN CANDIDATES AND I SAY
BLEEDING BECAUSE THEY PLACE
FIRST, SECOND AND THIRD IN
POLLING CONDUCTED BY THE
LIBERTARIAN PARTY.
FIRST FORMER NEW MEXICO GOVERNOR
GARY JOHNSON AND THEN TECH
ENTREPRENEUR, JOHN McAFEE,
THIRD LIBERTARIAN REPUBLIC
FOUNDER AUSTIN PETERSEN.
CANDIDATES TONIGHT'S RULES ARE
SIMPLE.
I OR SOMEONE ELSE WILL ASK YOU A
QUESTION AND YOU GET ONE MINUTE
TO RESPOND, 30 SECONDS FOR A
FOLLOW-UP RESPONSE RATE IF YOU
GO OVER YOUR TIME YOU WILL HEAR
THIS.
PLEASE DON'T GO PAST YOUR TIME.
BEFORE WE START THE QUESTIONS
EACH CANDIDATE HAS AN OPENING
STATEMENT TO GOVERNOR JOHNSON
SINCE YOU WERE FIRST IN THE
EARLY POLLS YOU START.
>> WELL I AM GARY JOHNSON AND I
WOULD LIKE EVERYONE TO KNOW THAT
I HAVE A WONDERFUL FAMILY.
HIS SON ERIC, DAUGHTER SAEB
GRANDDAUGHTER CORA AND FIANCÉ
BEST FRIEND KATE.
KATE AND I SHARE A PASSION FOR
HEALTH AND WELLNESS AND IT'S
GREAT TO BE IN LOVE AND I'M IN
LOVE.
I HAVE ALSO BEEN ON TO BEND OVER
MY ENTIRE LIFE.
I WAS THE KID THAT WAS THROWING
NEWSPAPERS BUT IN COLLEGE I
STARTED A ONE-MAN HANDYMAN
BUSINESS AND ACTUALLY GREW THAT
BUSINESS TO EMPLOY OVER 1000
PEOPLE.
MONEY FOR ME, BUSINESS FOR ME
HAS ALWAYS REPRESENTED FREEDOM.
I SOLD THE BUSINESS IN 1999.
NOBODY LOST THEIR JOBS.
THE BUSINESS WENT ON TO NEW
HEIGHTS.
IN BUSINESS I LEARNED SOME
REALLY VALUABLE LESSONS.
ONE IS THE MAGIC OF SHARING IN
THE PROCESS.
THE OTHER IS SHOWING UP ON TIME,
KEEPING YOUR WORD.
IT'S AMAZING HOW THE SIMPLE
PRINCIPLES WORK.
I GOT ELECTED GOVERNOR OF NEW
MEXICO.
I'VE NEVER BEEN INVOLVED IN
POLITICS BEFORE PRIOR TO GETTING
ELECTED GOVERNOR OF NEW MEXICO.
NEW MEXICO IS A STATE THAT IS TO
HAVE SOMEONE DEMOCRAT.
I PROMISE TO BRING A COMMONSENSE
BUSINESS APPROACH TO STATE
GOVERNMENT.
IN THAT CONTEXT I MAY HAVE
VETOED MORE LEGISLATION THAN THE
OTHER 49 GOVERNORS IN THE
COUNTRY COMBINED.
750 FEET DOES, THOUSANDS OF THEM
LINE ITEM VETOES.
I THINK IT MADE A DIFFERENCE.
I GOT ELECTED BY BIGGER MARGIN
THE SECOND TIME.
I'M ALSO AN ATHLETE AND
ADVENTURE.
I'VE CLIMBED THE HIGHEST
MOUNTAINS ON EACH OF THE SEVEN
CONTINENTS, SOMETHING THAT WAS
THE GOAL OF MINE AND SOMETHING
THAT I HAVE ACHIEVED.
I'M HOPING TO RIDE THE DIVIDE
NEXT SUMMER IF I'M NOT ELECTED
PRESIDENT.
JOHN: MR. McAFEE.
>> LIBERTARIANISM IS GROUNDED IN
THE CONCEPT OF LIBERTY BUT THAT
IS LIBERTY QUITE SLIPPERY MEANS
OUR BODIES AND OUR MINDS BELONG
TO OURSELVES IS LIBERTY IS
WHEN GOVERNMENTS DECIDE WHAT IS
RIGHT OR WRONG REGARDING WHAT WE
MAY DO WITH OURSELVES.
EVERY LAW THAT IS TRY TO
RESTRICT OR LIMIT PERSONAL
FREEDOMS AND PERSONAL LIBERTY
HAS FAILED.
GOVERNMENTS AND COUNTRIES HAVE
FROM ALLIES PROSTITUTION OR
HOMOSEXUALITY.
LEGISLATE WHAT IDEAS WE MAY
TEACH OUR CHILDREN.
THEY CRIMINALIZE THE SUBJECT OF
ALCOHOL OR OTHER DRUGS AND WHAT
IS THE RESULT?
OUR WAR ON DRUGS HAS NOT
DIMINISHED BECAUSE THE
CONSUMPTION OF ILLEGAL DRUGS HAS
NEARLY FILLED OUR PRISONS WITH
NONVIOLENT CITIZENS AND CREATED
THE MOST POWERFUL AND BRUTAL JOB
CARTEL IN THE WORLD.
PROHIBITION DID NOT REDUCE THE
CONSUMPTION OF ALCOHOL.
IT CREATED SUFFERING THROUGH
PUNISHMENT AND GAVE LIVES TO
ORGANIZED CRIME.
IDEAS LIKE EVOLUTION BUT IDEAS
HAVE A LIFE OF THEIR OWN AND
CANNOT BE EXTINGUISHED.
LIBERTY WHICH IS PERSONAL
FREEDOM CANNOT BE RESTRICTED
THROUGH LAWS.
IT CAN ONLY BE UNJUSTLY PUNISHED
AS IT IS EXPRESSED.
GIVING RISE TO SUFFERING
THROUGHOUT SOCIETY.
WE ARE ALL LIBERTARIANS ON THE
STAGE AND YOU ARE LIBERTARIANS
HERE.
I'M HOPING THAT THIS DEBATE WILL
MAKE CLEAR TONIGHT THE VALUE OF
LIBERTY IN ALL THINGS RATE THE
FACT THAT LIBERTY IS VERY
EXISTENCE DEPENDS ON PRIVACY AND
IT'S THE FOUNDATION OF A SANE
AND PROSPEROUS SOCIETY.
JOHN: MR. PETERSON.
[APPLAUSE]
>> FIRST OFF THANK YOU JOHN AND
THANK YOU TO FOX BUSINESS FOR
HOSTING THIS FORUM BUT I WAS
BORN IN INDEPENDENCE MISSOURI.
WAS RAISED IN A HORSE FARM A
SHORT DRIVE FROM A TOWN CALLED
LIBERTY.
COINCIDENCE?
I WILL LET YOU BE THE JUDGE.
I LEARNED ABOUT ECONOMIC LIBERTY
WHEN MY PARENTS SENT ME INTO THE
FIELDS TO PLAY IN THE
CHRYSANTHEMUMS AND SELL THEM TO
PEOPLE IN MY SMALL TOWN.
LEARN ABOUT PERSONAL LIBERTY
FROM THOSE WHO TAUGHT ME ABOUT
THE GOLDEN RULE.
I BELIEVE PEOPLE ARE INHERENTLY
GOOD AND THEY CAN BE TRUSTED
WITH FREEDOM AND THAT FREEDOM
SHOULD BE AS EXPANSIVE AS
POSSIBLE.
THE ROLE OF GOVERNMENT IS TO
PROTECT OUR LIBERTY, NOT OUR
SECURITY.
THAT'S WHAT THE 2ND AMENDMENT IS
FOR.
I'M A GRASSROOTS CANDIDATE WITH
A REAL NATIONAL CAMPAIGN.
I HAVE AN ARMY BEHIND MY BACK UP
AND VOLUNTEERING FOR ME AND
FINANCING ME THE ENTIRE WAY.
I'M A FISCALLY CONSERVATIVE
CANDIDATE FOR $0 CAMPAIGN DEBT
AND I BUDGETED MY FUNDS IN THE
SAME MANNER THAT I WOULD GOVERN.
I'M PROVING THAT YOU CAN DO MORE
WITH LESS.
I MAY BE THE YOUNGEST CANDIDATE
IN THIS RACE BUT I'M THE OLDEST
IN LIBERTARIAN YEARS.
I'M THE ANTI-ESTABLISHMENT
CANDIDATE IN THIS
ANTI-ESTABLISHMENT PARTY.
I'M HERE TO SHAKE THINGS UP AND
INSPIRE A GENERATIONAL LIBERTY
MOVEMENT.
I BELIEVE I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE
ON THE STAGE TO INSPIRE
COALITION OF LIBERTARIANS
CONSERVATIVES REASONABLE
DEMOCRATS AND INDEPENDENTS BACK
TO WIN.
I'M PRO-LIFE, PRO-CONSTITUTION
AND PRO-FREEDOM.
MY PLAN IS TO TAKE OVER THE
GOVERNMENTS I CAN LEAVE EVERYONE
ALONE.
THANK YOU.
THE REVOLUTION CONTINUES.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: ON TWO QUESTIONS.
THE MAIN HITS A YEAR BUT
LIBERTARIANS ARE COUPLE OF
THINGS.
THE FIRST IS WE ARE NAÏVE OR
SOFT ON TERROR.
WE DON'T UNDERSTAND THE NEED TO
KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
WE ARE ISOLATIONISTS.
GOVERNOR JOHNSON YOU SAID YOU
WOULD CUT MILITARY SPENDING.
WHY WOULD AMERICANS FEEL SAFE
WITH U.S. PRESIDENT?
>> THERE IS A VERY REAL
TERRORIST THREAT OUT THERE AND
TO ADDRESS THAT WE NEED TO CUT
OFF THE FUNDING BUT WHEN IT
COMES TO MILITARY INTERVENTION I
THINK OUR MILITARY INTERVENTIONS
HAVE MADE THINGS WORSE.
THE FACT THAT WE PUT TROOPS ON
THE GROUND IN THE FACT THAT WE
DROP ALMS AND.
JOHN: FLIGHTS KILL THOUSANDS OF
INNOCENT PEOPLE MAKING THE
SITUATION MUCH WORSE.
ALSO THIS REALLY THE
CAPRICIOUSNESS IF YOU WILL OF
THE EXECUTIVE TO ENGAGE IN THESE
MILITARY INTERVENTIONS AS
OPPOSED TO INVOLVING CONGRESS.
I WOULD LOVE TO SEE A SIMPLIFIED
MECHANISM FOR CONGRESS WEIGHING
IN ON OUR MILITARY INTERVENTION,
SOMETHING THAT I THINK IS REALLY
CORNERSTONE TO OUR SYSTEM OF
GOVERNMENT LET CONGRESS DEBATE
AND DISCUSS MILITARILY
INTERVENING.
JOHN: MR. McAFEE PEOPLE SAY
LIBERTARIANS ARE ISOLATIONISTS.
>> ISOLATIONISTS IN TERMS OF
OTHER NATIONS.
NOT AT ALL.
I THINK ISOLATIONISM IS TAKING
ON THE ROLE OF WORLD POLICING
MAKING US A SEPARATE ENTITY FROM
THE REST OF THE WORLD WERE -- WE
ARE THE POLICEMAN AND YOU ARE
THE PEOPLE WE POLICE.
WE ARE NOT ISOLATIONISTS AT ALL.
WE ARE INCLUSIVE.
OUR INTERFERENCE IN THE AFFAIRS
OF FOREIGN STATES DROPPING BOMBS
ON FAMILIES WHERE MOTHERS AND
FATHERS ARE KILLED OUR BROTHERS
AND SISTERS.
I WOULD BE ANGRY TO AND YOU
WOULD BE ANGRY TOO.
IT'S NOT ISOLATIONISM TO SAY WE
NEED TO BRING OUR CHIPS HOME OR
THAT WE NEED TO STOP INTERFERING
WITH THE AFFAIRS OF FOREIGN
NATIONS.
IT'S REALITY AND PRACTICALITY.
JOHN: MR. PETERSEN.
>> OBVIOUSLY TERRORISM IS A
THREAT BUT WE HAVE GOT TO RESIST
THESE POLITICIANS WHO ARE GOING
TO FEAR MONGER AS AN EXCUSE TO
TAKE AWAY OUR LIBERTIES.
WE HAVE GOT TO STAND UP TO
PEOPLE WHO USE EVERY TRAGEDY AS
AN EXCUSE TO TAKE AWAY OUR
CONSTITUTIONAL RIGHTS.
ALBUS AND THOMAS JEFFERSON HAD
THE ISLAMIC TERRORIST OF HIS DAY
AND HE MANAGED TO FIGHT THEM
CONSTITUTIONALLY PROTECTED 9/11
CONGRESSMAN RON PAUL WENT TO THE
CONGRESS AND ASKED FOR LETTERS
OF REPRISAL.
CONGRESS SHOULD UPDATE THESE
LETTERS.
ARTICLE I SECTION 8 OF THE
CONSTITUTION WOULD GIVE US A
POWERFUL 225 BASIS IN A WAY THAT
DOESN'T INVOLVE INVASION
OCCUPATION AND NATION-BUILDING.
NO MATTER WHAT THEY WANT TO
DEFEND OUR NATIONAL SECURITY WE
SHOULD ONLY GO TO WAR WITH THE
DECORATION OF WAR.
THE PRESIDENT SHOULD ALWAYS OBEY
THE CONSTITUTION AND THE FINE
COMMANDER-IN-CHIEF HAVE PROMISED
TO ONLY GO TO WORK ITS
CONSTITUTIONAL AND TO OBEY THE
LAW.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: A QUICK ANSWER PLEASE,
WHEN IS A RIGHT TO GO TO WORK?
>> WHEN ATTACKED.
>> MY QUESTION IS WHETHER WE
HAVE WORE?
JOHN: PEOPLE WANT TO KILL US.
>> WE ARE OPERATING UNDER THE --
THE WAR IS --
JOHN: WHEN SHOULD CONGRESS, IF
WE HAVE A SIGNIFICANT THREAT
THERE ARE CIRCUMSTANCES WHEN THE
UNITED STATES MAY GO TO WAR BUT
WE SHOULD ONLY DO SO THROUGH DUE
PROCESS.
>> ANOTHER THING WE ARE
CRITICIZED FOR, WE ARE SOFT ON
DRUGS.
PEOPLE THINK LIBERTARIAN MEANS
LIBERTINE.
SOME SAY LIBERTARIANS ENCOURAGE
DRUG USE.
MR. McAFEE YOU FIRST.
>> WHAT IS A DRUG?
ALMOST EVERYONE IN AMERICA JOINS
OUT THE HALL.
COFFEE IS A DRUG.
CIGARETTES OR DRUGS.
BEING SOFT ON DRUGS WHAT DOES
THAT ACTUALLY MEAN?
I THINK WHAT'S HAPPENING NOW WE
HAVE DECLARED WAR AND EVERYTHING
INCLUDING DRUGS.
WHY?
CERTAIN PEOPLE PREFER ALCOHOL TO
MARIJUANA OR CERTAIN PEOPLE
PREFER OR WANTED TO HEROIN.
WHAT IS THE DIFFERENCE?
TO HEROIN ADDICT ADDICTION IS
ITS OWN PUNISHMENT.
IS THAT BEING SOFT?
NO.
YOU ARE RESPONSIBLE FOR THE
REPERCUSSIONS OF YOUR CHOICES
AND IF YOU ARE TAKING DRUGS YOU
HAVE TO LIVE WITH THAT.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: THANK YOU CANDIDATES AND
VIEWERS I THANK YOU FOR YOUR
SUGGESTIONS VIA SOCIAL MEDIA.
IF MORE OF YOU WANT TO JOIN THE
DISCUSSION FOLLOW ME AT
TWITTERED AT JOHN STOSSEL AND
USE THE HASHTAG STOSSEL FOR MORE
LIKE MY FACEBOOK PAGE SO YOU CAN
POST THERE.
COMING UP QUESTIONS ABOUT THE
SIZE OF GOVERNMENT.
WHAT SHOULD WE CUT AND MORE
ABOUT WAR.
WHEN SHOULD WE GO TO WAR?
BAD AND MUCH MORE WHEN WE
RETURN.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: WELCOME BACK TO OUR
LIBERTARIAN PRESIDENTIAL FORUM.
ON FACEBOOK LONNIE POST PEOPLE
SAY LIBERTARIANS WILL CUT THE
SAFETY NET, WELFARE PROGRAMS TO
NONEXISTENT SO HOW WOULD YOU
ADDRESS THE WELFARE STATE AND
SHOULD BE REPLACED?
HOW IS IT NOT EFFECTIVE IN WHAT
SHOULD HAPPEN?
MR. PETERSEN.
>> I AM ATTACKING PLAN THAT
WOULD CUT ACROSS-THE-BOARD.
THIS IS CALLED BAIT CUTTING PLAN
AND THIS WOULD PUT US ON THE
PATH OF A BALANCED BUDGET.
YES I DO THINK WE NEED TO CUT
AWAY SOME OF THE SOCIAL SAFETY
NETS THAT WE SHOULD NOT DO IT
OVERNIGHT.
MY PLAN CUTS 1 PENNY FOR EVERY
FEDERAL DOLLAR ACROSS-THE-BOARD
THAT IF CONGRESS DECIDES ONE
PROGRAM IS TOO IMPORTANT SUCH AS
MEDICARE AND MEDICAID THEY COULD
MAKE IT AN EQUAL CORRESPONDING
CUT.
ALSO MOVES THE BUDGET --
BALANCED BUDGET AMENDMENT TO ME
TO FORCE CONGRESS TO LIVE WITH
THEIR ME MEANS.
18% OF THE TOTAL GDP, THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE TO BALANCE
THEIR CHECKBOOK, SO SHOULD
CONGRESS THAT RIGHT NOW THE GDP,
DEBT-TO-GDP RATIO IS 105%.
FORCE THEM TO STAY WITH THEM A
LOT NO MORE THAN 18% OF GDP CUT
THE BUDGET ACROSS-THE-BOARD.
EVERYBODY TAKES A HAIRCUT.
THAT'S HOW WE SHRINK GOVERNMENT
AND NOBODY'S GOING TO BE
HURTING.
JOHN: NOBODY IS GOING TO BE
HURTING HE SAYS.
PEOPLE SAY LIBERTARIANS ARE NOT
GOING TO TAKE AT THE POOR.
>> HAVING BEEN GOVERNOR OF NEW
MEXICO I CAN IDENTIFY WHAT I
BELIEVE ARE THOSE PEOPLE THAT
ARE TRULY IN NEED AND IF THERE
WAS A SAFETY NET I THINK THAT
WOULD BE BAD.
I WANT TO SUPPORT THOSE THAT ARE
TRULY IN NEED THAT WE HAVE GONE
WAY UP THE LINE WHEN IT COMES TO
THAT.
I THINK THE BIGGEST ISSUE FACING
THIS COUNTRY RIGHT NOW IS THE
FACT THAT GOVERNMENT IS TOO BIG.
SPENDS TOO MUCH MONEY AND TAXES
TOO MUCH.
I WOULD BE PROPOSING A BALANCED
BUDGET TO CONGRESS WHICH WOULD
BE A 20% REDUCTION IN FEDERAL
SPENDING AND TO DO THAT YOU'VE
GOT TO INCLUDE MEDICAID,
MEDICARE, MILITARY SPENDING AND
TO DO THAT YOU WOULD DEVOLVE
MEDICAID AND MEDICARE TO THE
STATES.
IN MY HEART OF HEARTS AS
GOVERNOR OF NEW MEXICO IS THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WOULD HAVE
GIVEN ME A MEDICAID AND MEDICARE
WITH 20% LESS MONEY I COULD HAVE
DELIVERED HEALTH CARE.
I COULD HAVE ADMINISTERED OR
SEEN THE ADMINISTRATION 20% LESS
MONEY TO DELIVER THOSE SERVICES.
WHEN IT COMES TO THE MILITARY A
20% REDUCTION IN THE MILITARY
ONLY GOES BACK A HANDFUL OF
YEARS.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: MR. McAFEE WOULD YOU CUT
THE WELFARE PROGRAMS FOR THE
POOR?
>> THIS IS A COMPLEX ISSUE.
LET'S LOOK AT THE SOCIAL
SECURITY.
THEY HAVE THE LARGEST DRAIN ON
THE FEDERAL BUDGET AT OVER
$700 BILLION AND GET EVERYONE ON
SOCIAL SECURITY PAID MONEY THAT
THEY WORKED HARD TO EARN INTO A
SYSTEM THAT THE GOVERNMENT
PROMISED WOULD PAY THEM BACK
WHEN THEY WERE OLDER.
[APPLAUSE]
THAT IS A COMMITMENT THAT WE
MADE AS A GOVERNMENT AND AS
LIBERTARIANS DO WE NOT MEET OUR
COMMITMENTS?
IT'S AN OBLIGATION.
IF THE ALLEGATIONS THAT WE ARE
NOT MEETING WHICH ARE THE
PROBLEM.
THE VETERANS.
WE SEND YOUNG MEN AND WOMEN OFF
TO WAR SAYING RISK YOUR LIFE AND
YOUR LIMB FOR YOUR COUNTRY AND
WHEN YOU COME BACK WITHOUT LIMBS
WE ARE SORRY.
WE WILL GIVE YOU THE LOWEST
POSSIBLE CARE.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN'S ARE NICE THOUGHTS BUT
WHAT SPECIFICALLY WOULD YOU CUT?
AGENCIES FOR EXAMPLE.
>> THE STATE IS A GREAT -- THAT
EVERYONE ENDEAVORS TO LIVE AT
THE EXPENSE OF EVERYONE ELSE.
I WOULD CUT THE MALL.
UNITED STATES SHOULD NOT BE
CHARITY.
CHARITY IS GIVEN FROM THE HEART.
WE NEED TO GET BACK TO THAT.
THAT IS WHAT MADE AMERICA GREAT.
WE HAVE TO REMOVE THE ROLE OF
CHARITY AND SOCIETY.
FAMILIES FRIENDS NEIGHBORS
CHURCHES AND COMMUNITIES
SOCIETY.
WHERE IS THE LOVE FOR ONE
ANOTHER?
GOVERNMENT DOESN'T LOVE US.
WE NEED TO GO BACK TO A SYSTEM
WHERE PEOPLE CAN TAKE CARE OF
ONE ANOTHER.
THE CATHOLIC CHURCH WOULD LOVE
TO STEP IN AND DO CHARITY BUT
THE GOVERNMENT GETS IN THE WAY
AND OBAMACARE HAS DESTROYED OUR
HEALTH CARE HEALTH CARE SYSTEM.
AS PRESIDENT I WOULD DEMAND
CONGRESS OVERTURN THE ACA ON DAY
ONE.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: GOVERNOR JOHNSON DO YOU
AGREE?
>> A COUPLE OF STANDUP STARTUP
ABOUT.
THE DEPARTMENT OF CONGRESS
PROMOTES CRONY CAPITALISM MORE
THAN THE DEPARTMENT OF CONGRESS.
[APPLAUSE]
A PERSON OF EDUCATION, HERE AT
THE ARGUMENTS.
ONE OF YOUR IGNORANCE IS THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT GIVES EACH
STATE 11 CENTS OUT OF EVERY
SCHOOL DOLLAR IN EVERY STATE
SPENT BY THE COMES WITH 15 CENTS
WORTH OF STRINGS ATTACHED BY THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SAYS YOU HAVE
TO DO ABC AND D INHERES 11 CENTS
TO DO THAT.
THE DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION WAS
ESTABLISHED AFTER JIMMY CARTER,
NOT GEORGE WASHINGTON.
WHAT IS VALUE-ADDED ABOUT THE
DEPARTMENT OF EDUCATION SINCE
CARTER DID THAT?
NOTHING.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: THANK YOU GENTLEMEN.
COMING UP SOME UNCOMFORTABLE
PERSONAL QUESTIONS FOR EACH
CANDIDATE THAT FIRST BEFORE WE
RETURN A LITTLE BIT ABOUT TERRY
SPECIFICALLY, ISIS.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: WE ARE BACK WITH THE THREE
LEADING LIBERTARIAN PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES.
ONE THING DEMOCRATS REPUBLICANS
AND LIBERTARIANS AGREE ON IS ITS
GOVERNMENT'S JOB TO PROTECT US
FROM FOREIGN THREATS.
HE PEOPLE SAY LIBERTARIANS WON'T
MAKE US SAFE.
MR. McAFEE AS PRESIDENT WHAT
WOULD YOU DO ABOUT ISIS?
>> THAT'S AN EASY ANSWER.
I DIDN'T GET A CHANCE TO SAY
WHICH PROGRAM.
THE FDA SERVES A VERY LIMITED
PURPOSE.
[APPLAUSE]
WHAT WOULD I DO ABOUT ISIS?
ISIS IT'S A PROBLEM OF
INTELLIGENCE GATHERING MORE THAN
ANYTHING ELSE.
WE HAVE THE CAPACITY.
IS ANYBODY DOING TERRORIST ACTS
INSIDE OF CHINA OR RUSSIA?
THEY ARE SO FAR AHEAD OF US FROM
A CYBERSECURITY STANDPOINT
MEANING INTELLIGENCE GATHERING
IN THE MODERN AGE.
WE SHOULD KNOW WELL IN ADVANCE
BEFORE EVERY TERRORIST ATTACK ON
THE PLANET AND YET WE DO NOT.
WE DO NOT OR IF WE DO WE ARE NOT
TELLING ANYBODY.
IT'S ONE OF THE GREATEST
TRAGEDIES THAT WE NEED NEW
TRAINING.
WE NEED TO MAKE OURSELVES UP TO
DATE.
WE ARE 20 YEARS BEHIND THE
CHINESE AND RUSSIA.
JOHN: THAT ALONE WOULD PROTECT
US?
>> I'M SORRY?
JOHN: INTELLIGENCE ALONE WOULD
PROTECT US?
>> LET ME GIVE AN EXAMPLE.
WE HAVE THE CAPACITY USING
PATTERN RECOGNITION WITHOUT
HAVING TO LISTEN TO ANYBODY'S
CONVERSATION OR INVADE ANYBODY'S
PRIVACY TO DETERMINE WHAT A
TERROR CELL IS.
THEY HAVE ANONYMOUS MEDICATIONS.
LEADERS WILL TAKE A DIFFERENT
PHONE AND THROW IT AWAY EVERY
DAY.
THEY USE ONLY OUTGOING
PHONECALLS.
WHEN A TERRORIST ATTACK IS ABOUT
TO HAPPEN THERE IS A FLOW
THROUGH THE CHAIN OF COMMAND.
THESE THINGS ARE EASILY
IDENTIFIABLE IN TODAY'S CYBER
SCIENCE WORLD RATED SO IF WE
COULD PROTECT THEM AND PREVENT
EVERY TERRORIST ATTACK WOULD
THAT NOT HELP US?
>> THE FIRST OF A WOULD DO IS
OBEY THE CONSTITUTION RESPECT
THE FOURTH AMENDMENT RIGHT TO
AMERICAN CITIZENS.
WE CAN FIGHT ISIS.
THEY HAVEN'T ATTACKED OUR OWN --
HABITAT FOR HOMELAND SUCH AS
GARLAND TEXAS SO THEY ARE
SINCERE THREAT THAT IF WE OBEY
THE CONSTITUTION AND WE FOLLOW
THE ADVICE OF THE FOUNDERS AND
WE LISTEN TO CONGRESSMAN RON
PAUL THERE ARE THOUSANDS OF
GRIZZLED VETERANS THAT ARE JUST
ACHING FOR AN OPPORTUNITY TO DO
THEIR COUNTRY A FAVOR.
IT WOULD BE MORE THAN HAPPY TO
GO OVER AND TAKE CARE OF THESE
PEOPLE.
I TRUST THE CONSTITUTION.
I TRUST THOMAS JEFFERSON DID I
TRUST THE FOUNDERS BUT I BELIEVE
THAT IF WE FOLLOW THE LAW WE CAN
PROTECT OURSELVES AND SECURE
LIBERTIES AT THE SAME TIME.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: MR. JOHNSON, GOVERNOR
JOHNSON SENATOR CRUZ SAID WE
SHOULD CARPET BOMB ISIS INTO
OBLIVION.
I DON'T KNOW OF SAND CAN GLOW IN
THE DARK THAT WE WILL FIND OUT.
>> I THINK THIS IS A PROBLEM,
HOW WE HAVE ADDRESSED THIS
PROBLEM.
WE HAVE ADDRESSED THESE PROBLEMS
WITH BOMBS AND NOT OUR BRAINS.
WE NEED TO CUT OFF THE FUNDING
TO ISIS AND WE NEED TO HAVE
CONGRESS DECLARE WAR ON ISIS.
NOT THAT THEY HAVEN'T BEEN THE
AGGRESSOR BUT WHERE DID AL QAEDA
GO?
WELL GEE WOODCUT THAT HAD OFF
AND NOW HAVE ISIS AND WENT ISIS
GOES, SOMETHING ELSE IS GOING TO
ARISE.
WE NEED TO CONTINUE IS HAPPENING
IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
THE DECLARATION OF WAR FROM
CONGRESS AND LET'S CUT OFF THEIR
FUNDING.
JOHN: A QUICK ANSWER FROM
TWITTER.
SOMEONE CALLED HOPE ASKS WHAT
YOU AND ALL FOREIGN AID?
>> AGAIN WE HAVE COMMITMENTS AS
A U.S. GOVERNMENT TO A NUMBER OF
OTHER FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS THAT
DO NOT INVOLVE POLICING AND
THESE COMMITMENTS IT MADE WOULD
HAVE TO KEEP, I'M SORRY WE DO
HAVE ALLIES AND WE DO HAVE
ENEMIES IN THIS WORLD.
IF YOU THINK WE DON'T YOU SHOULD
LOOK AT WHAT CHINA HAS BEEN
DOING TO US FOR THE PAST YEAR.
21 MILLION RECORDS FOUND IN THE
OFFICE OF PERSONNEL MANAGEMENT.
THEY BROKEN TO THE PENTAGON, THE
FBI AND HOMELAND SECURITY.
WE ARE AT WAR WITH CHINA.
THIS IS A FUNDAMENTAL ISSUE AND
WE ARE SIMPLY NOT PAYING
ATTENTION TO IT SO WE HAVE TO
KEEP OUR COMMITMENTS TO FOREIGN
NATIONS AT THE SAME TIME WENT TO
STOP POLICING THE WORLD.
WE HAVE PROBLEMS HERE AT HOME.
JOHN: FOREIGN AID MR. PETERSEN.
>> I DO NOT BELIEVE IN FOREIGN
AID AND I WOODCUT EVERY ANY OF
FOREIGN AID.
>> I DON'T LIKE THE TERM ALL,
BUT FOREIGN AID SOUNDS LIKE FOOD
AND MEDICINE WHEN THE REALITY IS
IT'S PROPPING UP FOREIGN
GOVERNMENT, TAKING OUT -- GIVING
THE MONEY TO ANOTHER.
SO THEORETICALLY GUESS WE SHOULD
CUT OFF FOREIGN AID.
THIS IS MONEY WE COULD BE
SPENDING IN OUR COUNTRY AS
OPPOSED TO OTHERS.
JOHN: COMING UP ABORTION COME
AGAIN MARRIAGE, HEALTH CARE,
HELPING POOR PEOPLE BUT NEXT
PERSONAL ISSUES.
HER REASON YOU MAY NOT WANT TO
VOTE FOR THEM.
I WILL BRING THOSE UP, NEXT.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: WHERE ARE BACK BUT THE
FIRST EVER NATIONALLY TELEVISED
LIBERTARIAN PRESIDENTIAL FORUM.
I AM A LIBERTARIAN.
I SAY AND IF YOU WOULD MAKE A --
THAT ARE PRESENT THAN OUR
TWO-FRONT RUNNERS.
THE AUDIENCE AGREES BUT THERE
ARE A COUPLE OF THINGS THAT MAKE
ME WONDER ABOUT EACH OF YOU.
GOVERNOR JOHNSON YOU HAVE
ALREADY RUN FOR PRESIDENT AND
YOU LOST, BADLY.
SOME PEOPLE SAY YOU ARE TOO LOW
KEY, TO INSPIRE PEOPLE LIKE YOU
ARE STONED ON MARIJUANA.
AND IN FACT THE ANALOGY COULD
HIGH SOMETIMES.
I PERSONALLY DON'T CARE BUT A
LOT OF AMERICANS WILL.
WOULD YOU SAY TO THE TWO POINTS
YOU ARE TOO LOW KEY AND YOU
ADMIT USING MARIJUANA?
>> I AM ONE OF 130 MILLION
PEOPLE IN THAT CATEGORY.
[APPLAUSE]
I HAVEN'T HAD A DRINK OF ALCOHOL
AND 29 YEARS PRAYED I HAVE
ALWAYS MAINTAINED THAT
LEGALIZING MARIJUANA WOULD LEAD
TO LESS OVERALL SUBSTANCE ABUSE
BECAUSE PEOPLE WILL FIND IT SUCH
A SAFER ALTERNATIVE THAN ALL THE
OTHER SUBSTANCES OUT THERE
STARTING WITH ALCOHOL.
AND WITH REGARD TO GETTING
BEATEN LAST TIME I WANT
EVERYBODY TO KNOW I AM A FIERCE
COMPETITOR AND YES WE GOT THE
FAMILY GOT BEAT THAT LAID BUT
THIS GO-ROUND AT THE HEART OF
THIS IS THE PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE
COMMISSION.
I'M SUING THE PRESIDENTIAL
DEBATE COMMISSION.
THIS IS AT THE HEART OF IT.
[APPLAUSE]
THE ONLY WAY A THIRD PARTY WILL
WIN IS IF THEY ARE IN THE
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE WHICH IS
SOMETHING THAT CAN HAPPEN 16% OF
THE POLLS THIS ELECTION.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: MR. McAFEE.
>> I HAVE A HARD TIME PICKING
AND CHOOSING.
JOHN: WHEN I GOOGLED YOU YOU
SOUND A LITTLE FLAKY.
POLICE ACCUSED YOU OF UNLICENSED
DRUG MANUFACTURING PREVIEWER
PERSON OF INTEREST IN THE MURDER
OF A NEIGHBOR.
YOU LEFT AND WENT TO BLOGGER
MULLAH.
YOU ARE STILL TECHNICALLY A
FUGITIVE BUT THEY DON'T SEEM
THAT INTERESTED IN GRABBING YOU.
[APPLAUSE]
IN AMERICA YOU ARE ARRESTED FOR
DRIVING UNDER THE AM FLOODS OF
XANAX.
WHY SHOULD PEOPLE TRUST YOU?
>> LET'S LOOK AT THE ABSOLUTE
FACTS.
WHAT ARE THE CHANCES OF MY
SURVIVAL IF I WERE MANUFACTURING
ILLEGAL DRUGS IN CENTRAL
AMERICA?
[APPLAUSE]
IF I WERE REALLY DOING THAT I
WOULD HAVE A READY SECOND
HALF-LIFE SO THAT'S ISSUE ONE.
NUMBER TWO I WAS NEVER CHARGED
WITH MURDER AND I'M CERTAINLY
NOT A FUGITIVE FROM JUSTICE.
THAT'S AN ABSOLUTELY FALSE
STATEMENT AND ALL THAT CHECKS
OUT ON THE WEB.
I DID ESCAPE TO GUATEMALA?
WHY DID I'VE PROBLEMS?
I WAS ASKED FOR 2 MILLION-DOLLAR
DONATION TO THE RULING
GOVERNMENT.
I SAID NO.
EXACTLY ONE WEEK LATER MY
PROPERTY WAS RATED BY 42 ARM
SHOULDERS WHO SHOT MY DAUGHTER
IN FRONT OF MY EYES.
THAT WAS THE PROBLEM I HAD WITH
THE POLICE.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: THE DUI?
>> THE DUI THAT'S THE STUPIDEST
THING I'VE EVER DONE AND I OWN
UP TO IT GREAT.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: AUSTIN PETERSEN HERE'S MY
PROBLEM WITH YOU.
YOU ARE 12 YEARS OLD.
YOU ARE NOT OLD ENOUGH.
[LAUGHTER]
>> I'M 35 SO I'M
CONSTITUTIONALLY ELIGIBLE.
[APPLAUSE]
ON JULY 4, 1776 THOMAS JEFFERSON
WAS 33 YEARS OLD PREACHING'S
MEDICINE WAS 25 YEARS OLD.
THE MARQUIS DAY LAFAYETTE WAS 18
AND ALEXANDER HAMILTON WAS 18.
IT WAS YOUNG MAN THAT FOUNDED
THIS COUNTRY AND YOUNG PEOPLE
WILL RESTORE IT YOUNG LEADERS
WILL TAKE THEIR COUNTRY BACK.
WE WILL TAKE OUR COUNTRY BACK.
IT'S THE YOUNG PEOPLE THAT ARE
GOING TO FIGHT FOR IT.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: BACK TO ISSUES.
FORD FISCHER SYNTHESIS VIDEO.
SMALL GOVERNMENT REPUBLICANS WHO
ARE UNHAPPY WITH REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATES MAY HAVE A CLEAR
REASON TO VOTE LIBERTARIAN AND
HOW WOULD YOU SELL YOURSELF AS A
LIBERTARIAN NOMINEE TO
DISENFRANCHISED IMMIGRANTS
VOTER'S?
JOHN: GOVERNOR JOHNSON.
>> DISENFRANCHISED DEMOCRAT
VOTERS.
THE WEB SITE I SAID WHAT THEY
THINK EVERYONE SHOULD GET ON
THAT WEB SITE AND TAKE THE
QUESTIONS AND SEE WHO YOU
PARAPET.
I HAVE ISSUES WITH THE SITE THAT
I TOOK THE TEST A COUPLE WEEKS
AGO AND I SIDED WITH MYSELF 90%
OF THE TIME.
I THINK THEY HAVE FIXED THAT BUT
AMAZINGLY THE NEXT PERSON THAT I
SIDED WITH WAS BERNIE SANDERS AT
73% SO THE INITIAL REACTION WAS
YOU GOT TO BE KIDDING AND THEN
THE NEXT REACTION WAS I GET IT,
I GET IT.
ON THE CIVIL LIBERTIES SIDE COME
ON THE SOCIAL SIDE, AND THE
MILITARY INTERVENTION SIDE, YOU
KNOW WHAT?
I ADVOCATED FOR LEGALIZING
MARIJUANA.
I AM THE HIGHEST OFFICIAL TO DO
THAT ALTHOUGH BERNIE WORLD NOT A
BAD IDEA BUT I'M GLAD THAT HE IT
THERE IS A REAL CONNECTION.
>> I JUST WANT TO SAY GOVERNOR
JOHNSON HAS STATED THAT IT DOES
SIDE WITH SOCIAL ISSUES AND WE
HAD A BIG KERFYE FULL AND A WEEK
BECAUSE GOVERNOR JOHNSON ESTATE
HE BELIEVES THAT BAKER SHOULD BE
FORCED TO BEG WEDDING CAKES FOR
PEOPLE THAT THEY DISAGREE WITH,
COUPLES AND THIS IS A BIG BUMP.
>> I THINK IF YOU DISCRIMINATE
ON THE BASIS OF RELIGION I THINK
THAT IS A BLACK HOLE.
I THINK WE SHOULD BE ABLE TO
DISCRIMINATE IF YOU STINK OR
YOU'RE NOT WEARING SHOES BUT IF
WE DISCRIMINATE ON THE BASIS OF
RELIGION, TO ME THAT'S DOING
HARM TO THE CLASS OF PEOPLE.
JOHN: SHOULD THEY BE REQUIRED TO
BAKE A CAKE --.
>> I THINK MUSLIMS IN THIS
COUNTRY BE BANNED BY ALL SORTS
OF BUSINESSES BECAUSE IT WOULD
BE THE POPULAR THING TO DO.
JOHN: MAKE THE CAKE FOR THE
WEDDING.
>> THAT WOULD BE MY CONTENTION
IN THE EXAMPLE I CITED, THE
EXAMPLE I CITED HOW ABOUT THE
UTILITY, THE UTILITY THAT IS
PRIVATELY-OWNED AND BECAUSE IT'S
THE ONLY MARKET THAT I HAVE TO
BUY MY ELECTRICITY THEY ARE
GOING TO CUT ME OFF FOR
RELIGIOUS REASONS.
JOHN: MR. McAFEE YOU GET A
CHANCE TO WEIGH IN.
>> IF YOU ARE THE ONLY BAKER IN
TOWN IT MAY BE A PROBLEM BUT NO
ONE IS FORCING YOU TO BUY
ANYTHING OR TO CHOOSE ONE PLACE
OVER ANOTHER.
WHY SHOULD I BE FORCED TO DO
ANYTHING IF I AM NOT HARMING
YOU.
AM I HARM YOU BY NOT SELLING YOU
SOMETHING?
NO IT'S MY CHOICE TO SELL IN
YOUR CHOICE TO BUY.
JOHN:.
>> I VETOED HATE CRIME IN NEW
MEXICO.
PROSECUTE ME ON THE BASIS OF THE
CRIME, NOT MY INTENTION.
I THINK THEIR RELIGION IS THEIR
RELIGION IS THE BLACK HOLE IN
THAT SAME CATEGORY BUT IF YOU
ARE GOING TO START
DISCRIMINATING AGAINST PEOPLE
BECAUSE OF RELIGION YOU WERE
GOING TO FIND A WHOLE CLASS OF
PEOPLE DISCRIMINATED AGAINST AND
YOU MAY BE INCLUDED IN THAT SO
IT IS HARM TO OTHERS.
JOHN: THE FUNDAMENTAL LACK OF
UNDERSTANDING THE FREE MARKET
COULD YOU HAVE TO ALLOW THE
MARKETPLACE TO WORK TO THE
GOVERNMENT CANNOT STAMP OUT
BIGOTRY.
THE GOVERNMENT IS NOT SUPPOSED
TO MAKE US INTO BETTER PEOPLE.
THE UNITED STATES WAS FOUNDED SO
WE COULD BE WHATEVER WE WANTED.
I HATE BIGOTRY AND I WILL STAND
OUTSIDE OF PEOPLE STORE AND
ENCOURAGE A BOYCOTT.
I STAND UP OR MIGHT RENSIN THERE
A RIGHTS.
EVERYONE SHOULD BE EQUAL BEFORE
THE LAW BUT --
JOHN: OUT OF TIME TIME.
COMING UP ABORTION, MARRIAGE,
THE DEATH PENALTY AND MORE.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: BAREBACK WITH THEIR
LIBERTARIAN PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
MR. PETERSEN LINEAGE DISHES OF
HUMANA POINTS AND YOU ARE
PRO-LIFE.
HE WOULD HAVE GOVERNMENT BAN
ABORTION.
>> THE FIRST THING I DO IS TRY
TO FIND EVERY NON-SOURCE OF
MISHORY INJURY CAN TO END
ABORTION AND THERE ARE OPTIONS.
THOUGH THE WAR ON DRUGS WOULD
ALLOW WOMEN TO PURCHASE BIRTH
CONTROL OF THE COUNTS -- COUNTER
THAT CONGRESS WRITES THE LAW.
WE SHOULD BE MORALLY PRO-LIFE
THAT ALL HUMANS DESERVE THE SAME
RIGHT TO LIFE LIBERTY AND THE
PURSUIT OF HAPPINESS AND WE
SHOULD FIND EVERY OPPORTUNITY TO
SAVE LIVES.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: DO YOU WANT TO MAKE ANY
POINTS ON THAT?
>> THIS IS WHERE AUSTIN AND I
DISAGREE.
I THINK A WOMAN'S RIGHT TO HER
OWN BODY IS ONE OF THE
FUNDAMENTAL ISSUES IN THIS
COUNTRY.
[APPLAUSE]
>> WARM PARTLY I DO NOT THINK
IT'S A FEDERAL GOVERNMENT'S JOB
OR THE STATE GOVERNMENTS JOB TO
INTERFERE IN THIS PROCESS.
[APPLAUSE]
>> HOW CAN THERE BE A DECISION
MORE DIFFICULT THAN ABORTION AND
WHO SHOULD BE MAKING THAT
DECISION OTHER THAN THE WOMAN
INVOLVED?
NO ONE.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: LIGHTNING ROUND.
DO YOU SUPPORT THE DEATH
PENALTY?
I WAS THERE WITH YOU JOHN.
>> IT'S A MOST BARBARIC THING
IMAGINABLE.
[APPLAUSE]
>> ESOLA NOT.
THE GOVERNMENT KILLS INNOCENT
PEOPLE EVERY YEAR AND WE SHOULD
PUT A STOP TO IT.
>> NO I DID NOT SUPPORT THE
DEATH PENALTY.
JOHN: MARRIAGE?
>> I'M AT AUSTIN AND A BAR.
[LAUGHTER]
AS LONG AS YOU GRANT ME THE
RIGHT TO A HETEROSEXUAL MARRIAGE
THEN IT YOU CAN MARRY WHOEVER
YOU PLEASE.
>> I'M HAPPY WHEN ANYONE FINDS
LOVE PICKED A PRIVATE CONTRACT,
KEEP GOVERNMENT OUT OF IT
COMPLETELY.
[APPLAUSE]
>> AS THEY DO SUPPORT MARRIAGE
EQUALITY AND WHEN YOU SAY GET
GOVERNMENT OUT OF THE COMPLETELY
WHAT I CAME TO FIND OUT IF THERE
ARE LITERALLY THOUSANDS OF LAWS
ON THE BOOKS AND YOU WOULD HAVE
TO GO THROUGH -- YOU WOULD
LITERALLY HAVE TO GO THROUGH AND
CHANGE EVERY SINGLE LAW SUPPOSED
TO JUST RECOGNIZING MARRIAGE
EQUALITY YOU WOULD NOT HAVE TO
CHANGE A WORD IN ANY OF THESE
LAWS.
JOHN: WOMEN ARE PAID LESS THAN
MEN TO REACH A GOVERNMENT BE
INVOLVED IN FIXING THAT?
>> FIRST OF ALL WOMEN SHOULD BE
PAID THE SAME AS A MAN, EQUAL
PAY EQUAL WORK.
JOHN: SHOULD GOVERNMENT
SHOULDN'T GET INVOLVED IN THAT?
THE DEVIL IS THE DETAILS AND
HAVING BEATO THIS MANY PIECES OF
LEGISLATION AS I HAVE I WOULD
FIND IT HARD-PRESSED TO SIGN
THAT LEGISLATION BUT I WOULD
KEEP AN OPEN MIND TO HOW THAT
LEGISLATION GOT WRITTEN.
I WILL TELL YOU THE DEVIL IS IN
THE DETAILS.
JOHN: SHOULD GOVERNMENT
INTERVENE?
>> PEOPLE SHOULD BE PAID BASED
ON THEIR TALENTS AND WHAT THEY
DO AND THEIR POOR DIGNITY
WHETHER YOU ARE A MAN OR A WOMAN
JOHN: WHO DECIDES, GOVERNMENT OR
BUSINESS?
>> THE EMPLOYEE DECIDES.
WHEN THERE IS ONE MORE THAN ONE
BUSINESS IN THE WORLD, WORK FOR
SOMEBODY ELSE.
>> THE UNFORTUNATE TRUTH IS THE
REASON THERE'S THIS QUOTE GENDER
PAY GAP IS BECAUSE OF WOMEN'S
CHOICES.
WOMEN FALLOUT OF THE WORD WERE
SPRAYED THEY HAVE CHILDREN.
THEY DON'T WORK AS LONG HOURS.
WHEN WE LOOK AT ECONOMIC DATA
SIDE-BY-SIDE THE TRUTH IS THE
GENDER PAY GAP CLOSES AND NOW
MORE WOMEN GET MORE DEGREES THAN
35 YEARS AND YOUNGER THOSE WOMEN
ARE ASKED TO MAKE YOU MORE
BECAUSE MORE OF WOMEN ARE GOING
TO COLLEGE THAN MEN.
JOHN: SO SHOULD GOVERNMENT FORCE
MEN TO GET INTO COLLEGE?
THE GOVERNMENT SHOULD STAY OUT
OF IT.
JOHN: LAST QUESTION.
SUPPOSE NONE OF YOU EXISTS.
YOU HAVE A CHOICE BETWEEN VOTING
FOR TOM FOR CLINTON.
WHO?
>> I WOULD CHOOSE NONEXISTENT.
[APPLAUSE]
>> I DON'T VOTE FOR PEOPLE THAT
I DON'T BELIEVE IN.
>> YOU ARE ASKING ME TO CHOOSE
BETWEEN A CASE OF THE MEASLES
AND A BLADDER INFECTION.
I DON'T KNOW, CANNOT DO THAT.
JOHN: GOVERNOR JOHNSON.
>> I WOULD VOTE FOR THE
LIBERTARIAN CANDIDATE.
I WOULD VOTE FOR A THIRD PARTY
CANDIDATE IF NONE OF US WERE A
PEER.
MY FIRST VOTE FOR LIBERTARIAN
CANDIDATE WAS AGAINST REAGAN IN
HIS SECOND TERM.
THE LID OFF OF SPENCER.
JOHN: THAT'S THE END OF OUR
FIRST DEBATE.
THE SECOND HALF OF THIS FORUM
WILL AIR NEXT FRIDAY.
WHEN WE RETURNED TONIGHT
ANALYSIS OF THE DEBATE SO FAR
FROM FOX BUSINESS.
[APPLAUSE]
JOHN: WE HAVE HEARD FROM THE
CANDIDATES SO WHAT HAVE WE
LEARNED SO FAR?
WAS ASKED TO SMART LIBERTARIANS.
KENNEDY HOST OF HER OWN SHOW
HERE ON FOX.
AND MATT WELCH EDITOR-IN-CHIEF
OF REASON MAGAZINE.
WHO DO YOU LIKE SO FAR?
[APPLAUSE]
>> I LIKED ALL THREE OF THEM IN
DIFFERENT WAYS.
JOHN McAFEE CAME OUT WITH A
LOT OF ENERGY.
HE IS STRANGE IN A WAY THAT I
APPRECIATED.
I THINK THE FUNDAMENTAL THING
THAT LIBERTARIAN HAS THE TENSION
BETWEEN A SENSE OF PURITY
SOMEONE WHO WILL REPRESENT
DIVISION THROUGH A DISTILLED IN
A SENSE OF PRAGMATISM WHO WE
THINK CAN SELL IT TO PEOPLE WHO
THEY KNOW WHAT LIBERTARIAN MADE
SO ALL THREE OF THEM ARE
DIFFERENT POLES OF THAT.
KENNEDY: THE MONMOUTH UNIVERSITY
POLL THAT SHOWS GARY JOHNSON
COULD BE POLLING AT 11% AGAINST
TRUMP WITH DONALD TRUMP ONLY
HAVING 34%.
JOHN: WE HADN'T MENTIONED THAT
YET YET THESE ARE THE RECENT
POLLS WHERE GARY JOHNSON 11% BY
11% UP AGAINST TRUMP.
KENNEDY: PEOPLE ARE HAMMERING
FOR THIRD HARDY PAID THE
LIBERTARIAN PARTY HAS A BALLOT
BUT I THINK ALL 50 STATES AND I
I THINK THEREFORE PEOPLE WOULD
BE PAYING MUCH MORE ATTENTION TO
THESE IDEAS.
AND THE PRAGMATISM.
JOHN: WE HAVE NEVER SEEN
TWO-FRONT RUNNERS WHO ARE SO
HATED.
>> DESERVEDLY SO.
KENNEDY: IF YOU HAVE LIBERTY
BACK ON THE STAGE IN THESE
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATES IT
COMPLETELY CHANGES THE RACE
PREVIEW HAVE THE LEFT-WING THAT
IS SO FRUSTRATED WITH THAT
GOVERNMENT AND IF YOU HAVE
SOMEONE WHO CAN LOGICALLY SHOW
THAT GOVERNMENT IS THE CAUSE OF
THIS FRUSTRATION AND FLEMING
TAKE -- LIMITED LIMITING IT WILL
ONLY GET BETTER.
JOHN: MY PRODUCER IS TELLING ME
YOU GUYS HAVE SOME COMPLAINTS
ABOUT SOME OF THESE ANSWERS.
>> AUSTIN WAS ALL NERVOUS AND
WAS GIVING THE RAND PAUL 1 PENNY
LINE AND SOUND LIKE ANY OTHER
POLITICIAN AND 25% OF HIS
ANSWERS AND JOHN McAFEE, WHAT
THE HELL HAPPENED THERE?
THE GUY -- GUATEMALA, I DON'T
KNOW.
SO YEAH GARY JOHNSON I THINK
STUMBLES A LITTLE BIT WHEN HE
TRIES TO EXPLAIN EXACTLY WHAT
HIS POSITION IS ABOUT NAZI CAKES
AND EQUAL PAY FOR EQUAL WORK IN
A WAY THAT I THINK WILL RUB SOME
LIBERTARIAN THE RUNWAY.
KENNEDY: JOHN McAFEE REMINDED
ME OF THE GUY YOU ARE AS TALK
WITH AT A BONFIRE.
WHAT IS LIBERTY?
YOU ARE RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT,
WHAT YOU TELL ME WHAT I THINK
AUSTIN HAS A LOT OF IDEALISM AND
YOUTH BUT HE TALKS IN A SERIES
OF BUMPER STICKERS.
THAT CAN BE A LITTLE ANNOYING.
STANEK THIS PRESIDENTIAL RACE
SOMEHOW IS GIVEN US AS
GOVERNMENT MUCH MORE BIG BIG
GOVERNMENT AND BARACK OBAMA
DEMOCRAT AND TRUMP.
[LAUGHTER]
SO AT SOME POINT LIMITED
GOVERNMENT THERE WAS A TEA PARTY
MOVEMENT.
I SWEAR TO GOD IT HAPPENED
RECENTLY AND ELECTED A LOT OF
PEOPLE LIKE RAND FOLLOWED OTHER
PEOPLE WHO HAVE A SERIOUS
COMMITMENT TO LIMITED
GOVERNMENT.
AS IT IS ON THE LEFT TO PEOPLE
WHO WANT TO GET GOVERNMENT OUT
OF THE BOARDROOM IN THE BEDROOM
AND THE DRUG ROOM AND OTHER
ROOMS THAT JOHN McAFEE LIKES
TO HANG OUT.
KENNEDY: NO ONE HAS BEEN ABLE TO
EFFECTIVELY CREATE A COALITION
OF THOSE PEOPLE THUS FAR BUT WE
WILL SEE IF THERE'S A TRULY
VIABLE NATIONAL LIBERTARIAN
CANDIDATE IF THEY TAKE PEOPLE
CONSIDER THEMSELVES TO BE
FISCALLY CONSERVATIVE AND
SOCIALLY LIBERAL OR SOCIALLY
AWKWARD IN THE CASE OF
LIBERTARIANS.
I THINK THAT DESCRIBES THE
MAJORITY OF VOTERS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
JOHN: THANK YOU KENNEDY, THANK
YOU MATT.
WE HAVE MORE DEBATE COMING UP
NEXT FRIDAY, THE SECOND PART OF
THIS DEBATE TRADEMARK TOPICS
IMMIGRATION PRIVACY GLOBAL
WARMING PLUS QUESTIONS FROM "FOX
NEWS" FOLKS LIKE THIS OBNOXIOUS
GUY.
>> HERE'S MY QUESTION FOR THE
LIBERTARIAN GENIUSES.
JOHN: BAD AN