>> THANK YOU, GEORGE.
MARTHA AND I ARE HONORED TO BE
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
THE CANDIDATES ARE ALL HERE.
AND WE WELCOME YOU AT HOME AND
THIS AUDIENCE OF MORE THAN 1,000
NEW HAMPSHIRE VOTERS.
AND WE ARE READY TO BEGIN.
>> PROMISING TO CARPET-BOMB
UNTIL THE DESERT GLOWS.
>> OUR GOAL IS TO PUT TOGETHER A
COALITION TO DESTROY ISIS.
>> IT DOESN'T MAKE YOU SOUND
STRONG.
>> ALL OF US MUST STAND UP AND
SPEAK OUT.
>> IT MAKES YOU SOUND LIKE
YOU'RE IN OVER YOUR HEAD.
>> FIGHT FOR WHAT YOU BELIEVE
IN.
>> THIS IS A FIGHT WE HAVE TO
WIN.
>> THE RACE IS TIGHT.
COULDN'T BE CLOSER.
BETWEEN HILLARY AND BERNIE RIGHT
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
AND NOW IN JUST MOMENTS, WITH SO
MUCH ON THE LINE, THEY FACE EACH
OTHER AND THE COUNTRY LIVE FROM
SAINT ANSELM COLLEGE IN
MANCHESTER, NEW HAMPSHIRE, THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE.
HERE AGAIN, DAVID MUIR AND
MARTHA RADDATZ.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND WE DO SAY GOOD EVENING TO
YOU FROM NEW HAMPSHIRE TONIGHT.
OVER THE NEXT TWO HOURS WE'RE
GOING TO HAVE A CHANCE TO TAKE A
MEASURE OF THE CANDIDATES VYING
TO BE THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE FOR
PRESIDENT.
IT OF COURSE IS THE MOST
IMPORTANT THING WE DO AS A
DEMOCRACY, CHOOSING A PRESIDENT.
THE INDIVIDUAL WHO WILL LEAD US
THROUGH PEACE AND PROSPERITY,
THROUGH WAR AND CONFLICT.
>> THEY HAVE ALL ANSWERED MANY
QUESTIONS IN THE PAST FEW
MONTHS.
BUT MUCH HAS CHANGED IN THE
WORLD SINCE THEY LAST DEBATED
FIVE WEEKS AGO.
AND THIS IS THE LAST DEBATE OF
THE YEAR.
IN LESS THAN TWO MONTHS VOTERS
IN THIS STATE WILL GO TO THE
POLLS.
>> SO PLEASE WELCOME THE
CANDIDATES FOR THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINATION FOR PRESIDENT.
SECRETARY HILLARY CLINTON.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR MARTIN O'MALLEY.
>> AND SENATOR BERNIE SANDERS.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> AND GOOD EVENING TO YOU ALL.
THE RULES FOR TONIGHT ARE VERY
BASIC AND HAVE BEEN AGREED TO BY
ALL THREE CAMPAIGNS IN ADVANCE.
CANDIDATES CAN TAKE UP TO A
MINUTE AND A HALF TO RESPOND
DIRECTLY TO A QUESTION.
FOR A REBUTTAL, FOR A FOLLOW-UP
45 SECONDS WILL BE ALLOWED.
THERE ARE GREEN, YELLOW, AND RED
LIGHTS THAT EACH CANDIDATE WILL
SEE TO SIGNAL WHEN TIME IS
RUNNING OUT AND WHEN THEY'RE
SUPPOSED TO BE FINISHED WITH
THEIR ANSWERS.
>> WE WILL BE TACKLING MANY
CRITICAL ISSUES RIGHT HERE
TONIGHT, AND WE BEGIN WITH
OPENING STATEMENTS IN
ALPHABETICAL ORDER AND SECRETARY
CLINTON.
>> WELL, THANK YOU.
AND I'M DELIGHTED TO BE HERE AT
NEW HAMPSHIRE FOR THIS DEBATE.
YOU KNOW, THE AMERICAN PRESIDENT
HAS TO BOTH KEEP OUR FAMILY SAFE
AND MAKE THE ECONOMY GROW IN A
WAY THAT HELPS EVERYONE, NOT
JUST THOSE AT THE TOP.
THAT'S THE JOB.
I HAVE A STRATEGY TO COMBAT AND
DEFEAT ISIS WITHOUT GETTING US
INVOLVED IN ANOTHER GROUND WAR,
AND I HAVE PLANS TO RAISE
INCOMES AND DEAL WITH A LOT OF
THE PROBLEMS THAT KEEP FAMILIES
UP AT NIGHT.
I'M VERY CLEAR THAT WE HAVE A
DISTINCT DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
THOSE OF US ON THIS STAGE
TONIGHT AND ALL OF OUR
REPUBLICAN COUNTERPARTS.
FROM MY PERSPECTIVE, WE HAVE TO
PREVENT THE REPUBLICANS FROM
ROLLING BACK THE PROGRESS THAT
WE'VE MADE.
THEY WOULD REPEAL THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT, NOT IMPROVE IT.
THEY WOULD GIVE MORE TAX BREAKS
TO THE SUPER WEALTHY AND
CORPORATIONS, NOT TO THE MIDDLE
CLASS.
AND THEY WOULD, DESPITE ALL
THEIR TOUGH TALK ABOUT
TERRORISM, CONTINUE TO LET
PEOPLE WHO ARE ON THE NO-FLY
LIST BUY GUNS.
SO WE HAVE A LOT OF WORK TO DO
IN THIS CAMPAIGN TO MAKE IT
CLEAR WHERE WE STAND IN THE
DEMOCRATIC PARTY, WHAT WE WILL
DO FOR OUR COUNTRY, AND I LOOK
FORWARD TO THIS EVENING'S
DISCUSSION OF REAL ISSUES THAT
FACE THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
THANK YOU.
>> THANK YOU, SECRETARY CLINTON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> MARTHA, THANK YOU.
TONIGHT WE HAVE A DIFFERENT
DEBATE THAN THE DEBATES THAT WE
HAVE BEEN ALLOWED TO HAVE SO
FAR.
BECAUSE TONIGHT IS DIFFERENT
BECAUSE OF THIS REASON.
THAT IN THE COURSE OF THIS
PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN AMERICA
HAS AGAIN BEEN ATTACKED BY
JIHADI TERRORISTS.
AMERICAN LIVES TAKEN FROM US.
SO YES, WE MUST TALK ABOUT OUR
IDEAS TO MOVE OUR ECONOMY
FORWARD.
BUT THE FIRST JOB OF THE
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
IS TO PROTECT THE PEOPLE OF THE
UNITED STATES.
I VISITED WITH A NUMBER OF OUR
NEIGHBORS IN NORTHERN VIRGINIA
AT A MOSQUE LAST FRIDAY.
AND AS I LOOKED OUT THERE AT THE
EYES OF OUR NEIGHBORS, I ALSO
LOOKED IN THE EYES OF VETERANS.
I LOOKED INTO THE EYES OF BOY
SCOUTS.
I LOOKED INTO THE EYES OF MOMS
AND DADS WHO WOULD DO ANYTHING
IN THEIR POWER TO PROTECT OUR
COUNTRY'S VALUES AND OUR
FREEDOMS.
WHAT OUR NATION NEEDS RIGHT NOW
IS TO REALIZE THAT WHILE WE FACE
A TERROR DANGER WE ALSO FACE A
DIFFERENT SORT OF POLITICAL
DANGER AND THAT IS THE DANGER
THAT DEMOCRACIES FIND THEMSELVES
SUSCEPTIBLE TO WHEN UNSCRUPULOUS
LEADERS TRY TO TURN US UPON EACH
OTHER.
WHAT OUR COUNTRY NEEDS RIGHT NOW
IS NEW LEADERSHIP THAT WILL
BRING US TOGETHER AROUND THE
VALUES THAT UNITE US, AROUND THE
FREEDOMS THAT WE SHARE AS
AMERICANS.
WE WILL RISE TO THE CHALLENGE OF
ISIL.
AND WE WILL RISE TOGETHER TO THE
CHALLENGES THAT WE FACE IN OUR
ECONOMY.
BUT WE WILL ONLY DO SO IF WE
HOLD TRUE TO THE VALUES AND THE
FREEDOMS THAT UNITE US.
WHICH MEANS WE MUST NEVER
SURRENDER THEM TO TERRORISTS,
MUST NEVER SURRENDER OUR
AMERICAN VALUES TO RACISTS, MUST
NEVER SURRENDER THEM TO THE
FASCIST PLEAS OF BILLIONAIRES
WITH BIG MOUTHS.
WE ARE A BETTER COUNTRY THAN
THIS.
OUR ENDURING SYMBOL IS NOT THE
BARBED WIRE FENCE.
IT IS THE STATUE OF LIBERTY.
AND AMERICA'S BEST DAYS ARE IN
FRONT OF US IF WE MOVE FORWARD
TOGETHER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS.
>> GOOD EVENING.
I AM RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES BECAUSE IT IS
TOO LATE FOR ESTABLISHMENT
POLITICS AND ESTABLISHMENT
ECONOMICS.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
BECAUSE OUR ECONOMY IS RIGGED,
BECAUSE WORKING PEOPLE ARE
WORKING LONGER HOURS FOR LOWER
WAGES, AND ALMOST ALL OF THE NEW
WEALTH AND INCOME BEING CREATED
IS GOING TO THE TOP 1%.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
BECAUSE I'M GOING TO CREATE AN
ECONOMY THAT WORKS FOR WORKING
FAMILIES, NOT JUST BILLIONAIRES.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
BECAUSE WE HAVE A CAMPAIGN
FINANCE SYSTEM WHICH IS CORRUPT,
WHERE BILLIONAIRES ARE SPENDING
HUNDREDS OF MILLIONS OF DOLLARS
TO BUY CANDIDATES WHO WILL
REPRESENT THEIR INTEREST RATHER
THAN THE MIDDLE CLASS AND
WORKING FAMILIES.
I'M RUNNING BECAUSE WE NEED TO
ADDRESS THE PLANETARY CRISIS OF
CLIMATE CHANGE AND TAKE ON THE
FOSSIL FUEL INDUSTRY AND
TRANSFORM OUR ENERGY SYSTEM AWAY
FROM FOSSIL FUEL TO ENERGY
EFFICIENCY AND SUSTAINABLE
ENERGY.
I'M RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT
BECAUSE I WANT A NEW FOREIGN
POLICY, ONE THAT TAKES ON ISIS,
ONE THAT DESTROYS ISIS, BUT ONE
DOES NOT -- ONE THAT DOES NOT
GET US INVOLVED IN PERPETUAL
WARFARE IN THE QUAGMIRE OF THE
MIDDLE EAST BUT RATHER WORKS
AROUND A MAJOR COALITION OF
WEALTHY AND POWERFUL NATIONS
SUPPORTING MUSLIM TROOPS ON THE
GROUND.
THAT'S THE KIND OF COALITION WE
NEED.
AND THAT'S THE KIND OF COALITION
I WILL PUT TOGETHER.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU.
AND THANK YOU ALL.
WE DO HAVE A LOT OF IMPORTANT
ISSUES TO GET HERE TONIGHT, AND
WE WANT TO ADDRESS THE
CONTROVERSY OF THE LAST 24 HOURS
RIGHT OFF THE TOP BECAUSE WE
HEARD SOME OF THE MOST HEATED
RHETORIC OF THE CAMPAIGN SO FAR
BETWEEN TWO OF THE CAMPAIGNS ON
THIS STAGE TONIGHT.
SENATOR SANDERS, YOU FIRED A
CAMPAIGN STAFFER.
YOU HAVE SUED THE DEMOCRATIC
NATIONAL COMMITTEE.
ALL OF THIS AFTER YOUR CAMPAIGN
ACKNOWLEDGED THAT SOME OF YOUR
STAFFERS "IRRESPONSIBLY ACCESSED
DATA FROM ANOTHER CAMPAIGN."
THE CLINTON CAMPAIGN CALLED THIS
A VERY EGREGIOUS BRAEP OF DATA
AND ETHICS AND SAID "OUR DATA
WAS STOLEN."
DID THEY OVERSTATE THIS, OR WERE
YOUR STAFFERS ESSENTIALLY
STEALING PART OF THE CLINTON
PLAYBOOK?
>> DAVID, LET ME GIVE YOU A
LITTLE BIT OF BACKGROUND HERE.
THE DNC HAS HIRED
ON TWO OCCASIONS THERE WERE
BREACHES IN INFORMATION.
TWO MONTHS AGO OUR STAFF FOUND
INFORMATION ON OUR COMPUTERS
FROM THE CLINTON CAMPAIGN.
AND WHEN OUR STAFFERS SAID WHOA,
WHAT'S GOING ON HERE, THEY WENT
TO THE DNC QUIETLY.
THEY WENT TO THE VENDOR AND SAID
HEY, SOMETHING IS WRONG.
AND THAT WAS QUIETLY DEALT WITH.
NONE OF THAT INFORMATION WAS
LOOKED AT.
OUR STAFF AT THAT POINT DID
EXACTLY THE RIGHT THING.
A FEW DAYS AGO A SIMILAR
INCIDENT HAPPENED.
THERE WAS A BREACH BECAUSE THE
DNC VENDOR SCREWED UP.
INFORMATION CAME TO OUR
CAMPAIGN.
IN THIS CASE OUR STAFF DID THE
WRONG THING.
THEY LOOKED AT THAT INFORMATION.
AS SOON AS WE LEARNED THAT THEY
LOOKED AT THAT INFORMATION, WE
FIRED THAT PERSON.
WE ARE NOW DOING AN INDEPENDENT
INTERNAL INVESTIGATION TO SEE
WHO ELSE WAS INVOLVED.
THIRDLY, WHAT I HAVE A REAL
PROBLEM WITH, AND AS YOU
MENTIONED, THIS IS A PROBLEM.
I RECOGNIZE IT IS A PROBLEM.
BUT WHAT THE DNC DID
ARBITRARILY, WITHOUT DISCUSSING
IT WITH US, IS SHUT OFF OUR
ACCESS TO OUR OWN INFORMATION,
CRIPPLING OUR CAMPAIGN.
THAT IS AN EGREGIOUS ACT.
I'M GLAD THAT LATE LAST NIGHT
THAT WAS RESOLVED.
FOURTHLY, I LOOK FORWARD TO
WORKING WITH SECRETARY CLINTON
FOR AN INVESTIGATION, AN
INDEPENDENT INVESTIGATION ABOUT
ALL OF THE BREACHES THAT HAVE
OCCURRED FROM DAY ONE IN THIS
CAMPAIGN BECAUSE I AM NOT
CONVINCED THAT INFORMATION FROM
OUR CAMPAIGN MAY NOT HAVE ENDED
UP IN HER CAMPAIGN.
DON'T KNOW THAT.
BUT WE NEED AN INDEPENDENT
INVESTIGATION, AND I HOPE
SECRETARY CLINTON WILL AGREE
WITH ME FOR THE NEED OF THAT.
LAST POINT.
WHEN WE SAW THE BREACH TWO
MONTHS AGO, WE DIDN'T GO RUNNING
TO THE MEDIA AND MAKE A BIG DEAL
ABOUT IT.
AND IT BOTHERS ME VERY MUCH THAT
RATHER THAN WORKING ON THIS
ISSUE TO RESOLVE IT IT HAS
BECOME MANY PRESS RELEASES FROM
THE CLINTON CAMPAIGN -- LATER.
>> YOU DO MENTION THE DNC VENDOR
BUT YOU SAID OF YOUR STAFF THAT
THEY DID THE WRONG THING.
>> ABSOLUTELY.
>> DOES SECRETARY CLINTON
DESERVE AN APOLOGY TONIGHT?
>> YES.
I APOLOGIZE.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
DO YOU ACCEPT?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> NOT ONLY DO I APOLOGIZE TO
SECRETARY CLINTON, AND I HOPE WE
CAN WORK TOGETHER ON AN
INDEPENDENT INVESTIGATION FROM
DAY ONE.
I WANT TO APOLOGIZE TO MY
SUPPORTERS.
THIS IS NOT THE TYPE OF CAMPAIGN
THAT WE RUN.
AND IF I FIND ANYBODY ELSE
INVOLVED IN THIS, THEY WILL ALSO
BE FIRED.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, HE'S
APOLOGIZED.
HOW DO YOU REACT?
>> I VERY MUCH APPRECIATE THAT
COMMENT, BERNIE.
IT REALLY IS IMPORTANT THAT WE
GO FORWARD ON THIS.
I KNOW THAT YOU NOW HAVE YOUR
DATA BACK AND THAT THERE HAS
BEEN AN AGREEMENT FOR AN
INDEPENDENT INQUIRY INTO WHAT
DID HAPPEN.
OBVIOUSLY, WE WERE DISTRESSED
WHEN WE LEARNED OF IT BECAUSE
WE'VE WORKED VERY HARD.
I SAID IN THE BEGINNING OF THIS
CAMPAIGN, WE WANTED TO REACH AS
MANY VOTERS AS POSSIBLE.
AND WE HAVE TENS OF THOUSANDS OF
VOLUNTEERS DOING THAT AND
ENTERING DATA ALL THE TIME TO
KEEP UP WITH WHAT PEOPLE ARE
TELLING US.
AND SO NOW THAT I THINK, YOU
KNOW, WE'VE RESOLVED YOUR DATA,
WE'VE AGREED ON AN INDEPENDENT
INQUIRY, WE SHOULD MOVE ON
BECAUSE I DON'T THINK THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE ARE ALL THAT
INTERESTED IN THIS.
I THINK THEY'RE MORE INTERESTED
IN WHAT WE HAVE TO SAY ABOUT ALL
THE BIG ISSUES FACING US.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DAVID, FOR CRYING OUT LOUD,
OUR COUNTRY HAS BEEN ATTACKED.
WE HAVE PRESSING ISSUES
INVOLVING HOW WE'RE GOING TO
ADAPT TO THIS CHANGING ERA OF
WARFARE.
OUR ECONOMY, PEOPLE ARE WORKING
HARDER AND BEING LEFT BEHIND.
YOU WANT TO KNOW WHY THINGS
DON'T GET DONE IN WASHINGTON?
BECAUSE FOR THE LAST 24 HOURS
WITH THOSE ISSUES BEING SO
URGENT TO PEOPLE AS THEY TUNE IN
TONIGHT, WONDERING HOW THEY'RE
GOING TO EVEN BE ABLE TO BUY
PRESENTS FOR THEIR KIDS, INSTEAD
WE'RE LISTENING TO THE BICKERING
BACK AND FORTH.
MAYBE THAT'S NORMAL POLITICS IN
WASHINGTON.
BUT THAT IS NOT THE POLITICS OF
HIGHER PURPOSE THAT PEOPLE
EXPECT FROM OUR PARTY.
WE NEED TO ADDRESS OUR SECURITY
ISSUES.
WE NEED TO ADDRESS THE ECONOMIC
ISSUES AROUND THE KITCHEN TABLE.
AND IF PEOPLE WANT TO HAVE MORE
HIGH-MINDED POLITICS AND WANT TO
MOVE OUR COUNTRY FORWARD, GO ON
TO MARTINOMALLEY.COM AND HELP MY
CAMPAIGN MOVE OUR COUNTRY
FORWARD.
>> ALL THREE CANDIDATES WEIGHING
IN.
>> LET ME AGREE WITH SECRETARY
CLINTON.
WE HAD THIS INCIDENT BEFORE.
WITH YOUR FAMOUS E-MAILS.
RIGHT?
AND WHAT I SAID AND I THINK WHAT
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY IS SAYING AND
I HOPE YOU SAY IS WHEN THE
MIDDLE CLASS OF THIS COUNTRY IS
DISAPPEARING, WHEN WE HAVE
MASSIVE INCOME AND WEALTH
INEQUALITY, WHEN WE'RE THE ONLY
MAJOR COMPANY ON EARTH NOT
GUARANTEEING HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE, ALL THE ISSUES THE
GOVERNOR TALKED ABOUT, THE
SECRETARY TALKED ABOUT, THOSE
ARE THE ISSUES.
MEDIA NOTWITHSTANDING.
THOSE ARE THE ISSUES THAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE WANT DISCUSSED.
I HOPE THOSE ARE THE ISSUES
WE'LL DISCUSS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, LET'S MOVE
ON TO SOME OF THOSE ISSUES.
IT IS JUST SIX DAYS BEFORE
CHRISTMAS, AS WE ALL KNOW IN
THIS COUNTRY.
IT'S TYPICALLY A JOYFUL TIME AS
IT IS THIS YEAR AS WELL.
BUT IT'S ALSO AN ANXIOUS TIME.
PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS ACKNOWLEDGED
THAT WHAT WE SAW IN SAN
BERNARDINO WAS AN ACT OF
TERRORISM.
BUT WE REMEMBER THE PRESIDENT
SAID RIGHT BEFORE THANKSGIVING
THERE IS NO KNOWN SPECIFIC AND
CREDIBLE INTELLIGENCE INDICATING
A PLOT ON THE HOMELAND.
WE NOW KNOW THAT THIS COUPLE HAD
ASSEMBLED AN ARSENAL.
THEY WERE NOT ON LAW
ENFORCEMENT'S RADAR.
THEY WERE COMPLETELY UNDETECTED.
SO AS WE APPROACH ANOTHER
HOLIDAY, WITH THE PRESIDENT
AGAIN SAYING LATE THIS WEEK NO
CREDIBLE THREAT, SECRETARY
CLINTON, HOW CONFIDENT SHOULD
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE BE THAT
THERE AREN'T OTHERS LIKE THAT
COUPLE RIGHT NOW IN THE U.S.
GOING UNDETECTED?
AND WHAT WOULD YOU DO AS
PRESIDENT TO FIND THEM?
>> WELL, FIRST, THE MOST
IMPORTANT JOB OF BEING PRESIDENT
IS OBVIOUSLY TO KEEP OUR COUNTRY
SAFE AND TO KEEP THE FAMILIES OF
AMERICA SAFE.
I HAVE A PLAN THAT I'VE PUT
FORWARD TO GO AFTER ISIS.
NOT TO CONTAIN THEM BUT TO
DEFEAT THEM.
AND IT HAS THREE PARTS.
FIRST, TO GO AFTER THEM AND
DEPRIVE THEM OF THE TERRITORY
THEY OCCUPY NOW IN BOTH SYRIA
AND IRAQ.
SECONDLY, TO GO AFTER AND
DISMANTLE THEIR GLOBAL NETWORK
OF TERRORISM.
AND THIRDLY, TO DO MORE TO KEEP
US SAFE.
UNDER EACH OF THOSE THREE PARTS
OF MY PLAN I HAVE VERY SPECIFIC
RECOMMENDATIONS ABOUT WHAT TO
DO.
OBVIOUSLY, IN THE FIRST WE DO
HAVE TO HAVE AN AMERICAN-LED AIR
CAMPAIGN.
WE HAVE TO HAVE ARAB AND KURDISH
TROOPS ON THE GROUND.
SECONDLY, WE'VE GOT TO GO AFTER
EVERYTHING FROM NORTH AFRICA TO
SOUTH ASIA AND BEYOND.
AND THEN MOST IMPORTANTLY, HERE
AT HOME.
I THINK THERE ARE THREE THINGS
THAT WE HAVE TO GET RIGHT.
WE HAVE TO DO THE BEST POSSIBLE
JOB OF SHARING INTELLIGENCE AND
INFORMATION.
THAT NOW INCLUDES THE INTERNET.
BECAUSE WE HAVE SEEN THAT ISIS
IS A VERY EFFECTIVE RECRUITER,
PROPAGANDIST, AND INCITER AND
CELEBRATOR OF VIOLENCE.
THAT MEANS WE HAVE TO WORK MORE
CLOSELY WITH OUR GREAT TECH
COMPANIES.
THEY CAN'T SEE THE GOVERNMENT AS
AN ADVERSARY.
WE CAN'T SEE THEM AS
OBSTRUCTIONIST.
WE'VE GOT TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE
CAN DO MORE TO UNDERSTAND WHO IS
SAYING WHAT AND WHAT THEY'RE
PLANNING.
AND WE MUST WORK MORE CLOSELY
WITH MUSLIM AMERICAN
COMMUNITIES.
JUST LIKE MARTIN, I MET WITH A
GROUP OF MUSLIM AMERICANS THIS
PAST WEEK TO HEAR FROM THEM
ABOUT WHAT THEY'RE DOING TO TRY
TO STOP RADICALIZATION.
THEY WILL BE OUR EARLY WARNING
SIGNAL.
THAT'S WHY WE NEED TO WORK WITH
THEM, NOT DEMONIZE THEM AS THE
REPUBLICANS HAVE BEEN DOING.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DAVID, I AM THE VERY FIRST
POST-9/11 MAYOR AND THE VERY
FIRST POST-9/11 GOVERNOR.
I UNDERSTAND FROM THE GROUND UP
THAT WHEN ATTACKS LIKE SAN
BERNARDINO HAPPEN, WHEN THE
ATTACKS LIKE THE ATTACKS OF 9/11
HAPPEN, THAT WHEN PEOPLE CALL
911 THE FIRST PEOPLE THAT SHOW
UP ARE THE LOCAL FIRST
RESPONDERS.
MANY OF THE THINGS SECRETARY
CLINTON SAID ARE ABSOLUTELY
TRUE.
BUT THEY UNDERSCORE A LACK OF
INVESTMENT THAT WE HAVE AS A
NATION FAILED TO MAKE OVER THESE
LAST 15 YEARS IN INTELLIGENCE
GATHERING, INTELLIGENCE
ANALYSIS, INTELLIGENCE SHARING.
NOT ONLY IN THEATER, IN SYRIA
AND IRAQ AND OTHER PLACES WHERE
WE INVOLVED OURSELVES IN
TOPPLING DICTATORS WITHOUT
HAVING ANY IDEA WHAT COMES NEXT,
BUT HERE IN THE HOMELAND AS WE
PROTECT PEOPLE FROM THIS THREAT
OF THE LONE WOLFS AND THESE
CHANGING TACTICS AND STRATEGIES.
I BELIEVE THAT'S WHAT'S HAPPENED
HERE-S THAT THE PRESIDENT HAD US
ON THE RIGHT COURSE BUT IT'S A
LACK OF BATTLE TEMPO.
WE HAVE TO INCREASE THE BATTLE
TEMPO.
WE HAVE TO BRING A MODERN WAY OF
GETTING THINGS DONE AND FORCING
THE SHARING OF INFORMATION AND
DOING A MUCH BETTER JOB OF
ACTING ON IT IN ORDER TO PREVENT
THESE SORTS OF ATTACKS IN THE
FUTURE.
>> WE'RE GOING TO BREAK DOWN
THESE ISSUES TONIGHT.
BUT I DO WANT TO GO TO SENATOR
SANDERS BECAUSE THE CONCERN
GOING INTO CHRISTMAS IS
SIGNIFICANT, AS YOU KNOW.
A NEW ABC NEWS POLL SHOWS 77% OF
AMERICANS HAVE LITTLE OR NO
CONFIDENCE IN THE GOVERNMENT'S
ABILITY TO PREVENT A LONE WOLF
ATTACK.
HOW WOULD YOU SPECIFICALLY FIND
WOULD-BE TERRORISTS WHO ARE
GOING UNDETECTED?
>> I'M ONE OF THE 77%.
I THINK THIS IS A VERY DIFFICULT
ISSUE.
AND LET ME AGREE WITH MUCH OF
WHAT THE SECRETARY AND THE
GOVERNOR HAVE SAID.
LET ME TELL YOU WHAT I THINK WE
HAVE GOT TO DO.
I THINK IT'S A TWO-PRONGED
ISSUE.
NUMBER ONE, OUR GOAL IS TO CRUSH
AND DESTROY ISIS.
WHAT IS THE BEST WAY TO DO IT?
WELL, I THINK THERE ARE SOME
DIFFERENCES OF OPINION HERE.
PERHAPS BETWEEN THE SECRETARY
AND MYSELF.
I VOTED AGAINST THE WAR IN IRAQ
BECAUSE I THOUGHT UNILATERAL
MILITARY ACTION WOULD NOT
PRODUCE THE RESULTS THAT WERE
NECESSARY AND WOULD LEAD TO THE
KIND OF UNRAVELING AND
INSTABILITY THAT WE SAW IN THE
MIDDLE EAST.
I DO NOT BELIEVE IN UNILATERAL
AMERICAN ACTION.
I BELIEVE IN ACTION IN WHICH WE
PUT TOGETHER A STRONG COALITION
OF FORCES, MAJOR POWERS AND THE
MUSLIM NATIONS.
I THINK ONE OF THE HEROES IN A
REAL QUAGMIRE OUT THERE, IN A
DANGEROUS AND DIFFICULT WORLD,
ONE OF THE HEROES WHO WE SHOULD
RECOGNIZE IN THE MIDDLE EAST IS
KING ABDULLAH II OF JORDAN.
THIS SMALL COUNTRY HAS WELCOMED
IN MANY REFUGEES.
AND ABDULLAH SAID SOMETHING
RECENTLY VERY IMPORTANT.
HE SAID, YES, INTERNATIONAL
TERRORISM IS BY DEFINITION AN
INTERNATIONAL ISSUE.
BUT IT IS PRIMARILY AN ISSUE OF
THE MUSLIM NATIONS WHO ARE
FIGHTING FOR THE SOUL OF ISLAM.
WE THE MUSLIMS SHOULD LEAD THE
EFFORT ON THE GROUND.
AND I BELIEVE HE IS ABSOLUTELY
RIGHT.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, IN THE
WAKE OF THE SAN BERNARDINO
ATTACK, YOU ALL EMPHASIZED GUN
CONTROL.
BUT OUR LATEST POLL SHOWS THAT
MORE AMERICANS BELIEVE ARMING
PEOPLE, NOT STRICTER GUN LAWS,
IS THE BEST DEFENSE AGAINST
TERRORISM.
ARE THEY WRONG?
>> WELL, I THINK YOU HAVE TO
LOOK AT BOTH THE TERRORISM
CHALLENGE THAT WE FACE ABROAD
AND CERTAINLY AT HOME AND THE
ROLE THAT GUNS PLAY IN
DELIVERING THE VIOLENCE THAT
STALKS US.
CLEARLY, WE HAVE TO HAVE A VERY
SPECIFIC SET OF ACTIONS TO TAKE.
WHEN SENATOR SANDERS TALKS ABOUT
A COALITION, I AGREE WITH HIM
ABOUT THAT.
WE'VE GOT TO BUILD A COALITION
ABROAD.
WE ALSO HAVE TO BUILD A
COALITION AT HOME.
ABROAD WE NEED A COALITION THAT
IS GOING TO TAKE ON ISIS.
I KNOW HOW HARD THAT IS.
I KNOW IT ISN'T SOMETHING YOU
JUST HOPE PEOPLE WILL DO --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, CAN WE
STICK TO GUN CONTROL?
>> I'M GETTING TO THAT.
BECAUSE I THINK IF YOU ONLY
THINK ABOUT THE COALITION ABROAD
YOU'RE MISSING THE MAIN POINT,
WHICH IS WE NEED A COALITION
HERE AT HOME.
GUNS IN AND OF THEMSELVES IN MY
OPINION WILL NOT MAKE AMERICANS
SAFER.
WE LOSE 33,000 PEOPLE A YEAR
ALREADY TO GUN VIOLENCE.
ARMING MORE PEOPLE TO DO WHAT I
THINK IS NOT THE APPROPRIATE
RESPONSE TO TERRORISM.
I THINK WHAT IS --
[ APPLAUSE ]
-- IS CREATING MUCH DEEPER,
CLOSER RELATIONS AND, YES,
COALITIONS WITHIN OUR OWN
COUNTRY.
THE FIRST LINE OF DEFENSE
AGAINST RADICALIZATION IS
MUSLIM AMERICAN COMMUNITY.
PEOPLE WHO WE SHOULD BE
WELCOMING AND WORKING WITH.
I WORRY GREATLY THAT THE
RHETORIC COMING FROM THE
REPUBLICANS, PARTICULARLY DONALD
TRUMP, IS SENDING A MESSAGE TO
MUSLIMS HERE IN THE UNITED
STATES AND LITERALLY AROUND THE
WORLD THAT THERE IS A CLASH OF
CIVILIZATIONS, THAT THERE IS
SOME KIND OF WESTERN PLOT OR
EVEN WAR AGAINST ISLAM, WHICH
THEN I BELIEVE FANS THE FLAMES
OF RADICALIZATION.
SO GUNS HAVE TO BE LOOKED AT AS
ITS OWN PROBLEM, BUT WE ALSO
HAVE TO FIGURE OUT HOW WE'RE
GOING TO DEAL WITH THE
RADICALIZATION HERE IN THE
UNITED STATES.
>> ON THIS ISSUE --
>> WAIT JUST A MOMENT, PLEASE,
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
SENATOR SANDERS, WE'VE SEEN
THOSE LONG LINES OF PEOPLE
BUYING GUNS IN RECORD NUMBERS
AFTER THE PARIS ATTACKS.
WOULD YOU DISCOURAGE PEOPLE FROM
BUYING A GUN?
>> IT'S A COUNTRY IN WHICH
PEOPLE CHOOSE TO BUY GUNS.
I THINK HALF OF THE -- MORE THAN
HALF OF THE PEOPLE IN MY OWN
STATE OF VERMONT, MY GUESS HERE
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, ARE GUN
OWNERS.
THAT'S THE RIGHT OF PEOPLE.
BUT THIS IS WHAT I DO BELIEVE.
I BELIEVE THAT WHEN WE HAVE SOME
300 MILLION GUNS IN THIS
COUNTRY, I BELIEVE THAT WHEN WE
HAVE SEEN THESE HORRIFIC MASS
KILLINGS NOT ONLY IN SAN
BERNARDINO BUT IN COLORADO AND
MOVIE THEATERS IN COLORADO, I
THINK WE HAVE GOT TO BRING
TOGETHER THE VAST MAJORITY OF
THE PEOPLE WHO DO IN FACT
BELIEVE IN SENSIBLE GUN SAFETY
REGULATIONS.
FOR EXAMPLE, TALKING ABOUT
POLLS.
A POLL RECENTLY CAME OUT,
OVERWHELMING MAJORITY OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE SAY WE SHOULD
STRENGTHEN THE INSTANT
BACKGROUND CHECK.
WHO DENIES THAT IT IS CRAZY --
[ APPLAUSE ]
WHO DENIES THAT IT IS CRAZY TO
ALLOW PEOPLE TO OWN GUNS WHO ARE
CRIMINALS OR ARE MENTALLY
UNSTABLE?
WE'VE GOT TO ELIMINATE THE
SHOW LOOPHOLE.
IN MY VIEW, WE HAVE GOT TO SEE
THAT WEAPONS DESIGNED BY THE
MILITARY TO KILL PEOPLE ARE NOT
IN THE HANDS OF CIVILIANS.
I THINK THERE IS A CONSENSUS
I'M NOT GOING TO SAY THAT
EVERYBODY IS IN AGREEMENT.
IT'S A DIVIDED COUNTRY ON GUNS.
BUT THERE IS A BROAD CONSENSUS
ON SENSIBLE GUN SAFETY
REGULATIONS THAT I, COMING FROM
A STATE THAT HAS VIRTUALLY NO
GUN CONTROL, WILL DO MY BEST TO
BRING TOGETHER.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR SANDERS.
I THINK WE'RE GOING TO GO ON --
>> WE WANT TO TOUCH ON SOMETHING
THAT --
>> DAVID --
>> GOVERNOR --
>> EXCUSES ME, NO.
>> WE HAVE TO ABIDE BY THE RULES
HERE.
WE'LL CALL ON YOU SHORTLY.
I DO WANT TO PICK UP ON
SOMETHING --
>> -- ACTUALLY PASSED
COMPREHENSIVE GUN SAFETY
LEGISLATION WITH A BAN ON COMBAT
ASSAULT WEAPONS, DAVID.
AND LOOK, THERE ARE PROFOUND
DIFFERENCES IN THIS RACE ON THIS
ISSUE.
SENATOR SANDERS VOTED AGAINST
THE BRADY BILL.
SENATOR SANDERS VOTED TO GIVE
IMMUNITY TO GUN DEALERS.
AND SENATOR SANDERS VOTED
AGAINST EVEN RESEARCH DOLLARS TO
LOOK INTO THIS PUBLIC HEALTH
ISSUE.
SECRETARY CLINTON CHANGES HER
POSITION ON THIS EVERY ELECTION
YEAR, IT SEEMS, HAVING ONE
POSITION IN 2000 AND THEN
CAMPAIGNING AGAINST PRESIDENT
OBAMA AND SAYING WE DON'T NEED
FEDERAL STANDARDS.
LOOK, WHAT WE NEED ON THIS ISSUE
IS NOT MORE POLLS.
WE NEED MORE PRINCIPLE.
WHEN ISIL DOES TRAINING VIDEOS
THAT SAY THE EASIEST WAY TO GET
A COMBAT ASSAULT WEAPON IN THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA IS AT A
GUN SHOW, THEN WE SHOULD ALL BE
WAKING UP.
WE NEED COMPREHENSIVE GUN SAFETY
LEGISLATION --
>> LET ME STAY WITH GUN CONTROL
FOR A MINUTE, THEN.
YOU TALK ABOUT ASSAULT WEAPONS.
EVEN IF YOU WERE ABLE TO BAN THE
PURCHASE OF ASSAULT WEAPONS
TOMORROW, AMERICANS ALREADY OWN
AN ESTIMATED 7 TO 10 MILLION
SEMI-AUTOMATIC RIFLES.
WOULD YOU MAKE IT ILLEGAL TO OWN
THOSE WEAPONS, FORCE PEOPLE TO
TURN THEM IN?
AND IF NOT, HOW WOULD BANNING
THE SALES REALLY MAKE A
DIFFERENCE?
>> BECAUSE, MARTHA, IT WOULD
PREVENT PEOPLE LIKE THE GUY WHO
JUST GOT CHARGED YESTERDAY
PERHAPS FROM BEING ABLE TO BUY A
COMBAT ASSAULT WEAPON.
WE ARE THE ONLY NATION, ONLY
DEVELOPED NATION --
>> AGAIN, I'M NOT TALKING ABOUT
BUYING.
WOULD YOU HAVE THEM CONFISCATED?
THE ONES THAT ARE ALREADY HERE.
>> NO, MARTHA, I WOULD NOT.
AND THAT'S NOT WHAT WE DID IN
MARYLAND.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT WE DID IN
MARYLAND?
WE OVERCAME THE NRA'S
OBJECTIONS.
WE OVERCAME ALL OF THE CROWDS
THAT WERE COMING DOWN THERE.
WE DID OUR OWN RALLIES.
AND AT LEAST IF WE ENACT THESE
LAWS IN A PROSPECTIVE WAY WE CAN
ADDRESS A MAJOR VULNERABILITY IN
OUR COUNTRY.
ISIL VIDEOS, ISIL TRAINING
VIDEOS ARE TELLING LOAN WOLFS
THE EASIEST WAY TO BUY A COMBAT
ASSAULT WEAPON IN AMERICA IS AT
A GUN SHOW, AND IT'S BECAUSE OF
THE FLIP-FLOPPING POLITICAL
APPROACH OF WASHINGTON THAT BOTH
OF MY TWO COLLEAGUES ON THE
STAGE HAVE REPRESENTED FOR THE
LAST 40 YEARS --
>> WHOA, WHOA, WHOA.
LET'S CALM DOWN A LITTLE BIT,
MARTIN.
>> YEAH, LET'S TELL THE TRUTH,
>> I AM TELLING THE TRUTH.
>> FIRST OF ALL, LET'S HAVE SOME
RULES HERE, COMMENTATORS.
>> WE WILL.
BUT LET ME JUST ESTABLISH THAT
FOR YOU, SENATOR.
GOVERNOR, WE ARE GOING TO CALL
IN TONIGHT -- IT'S VERY CLEAR
YOU HAVE A LOT TO SAY BUT PLEASE
WAIT UNTIL YOU'RE CALLED UPON.
AND SENATOR, HE INVOKED YOUR
RECORD --
>> HE SURE DID.
>> I'LL LET YOU RESPOND.
>> HE INVOKED MINE AS WELL.
>> SURE DID.
>> FOR A START, WE CAN DO ALL
THE GREAT SPEECHES WE WANT.
THEY'RE NOT GOING TO SUCCEED
UNLESS THERE'S A CONSENSUS.
IN 1988, JUST TO SET THE RECORD
STRAIGHT, GOVERNOR, I RAN FOR
THE U.S. HOUSE.
WE HAVE ONE HOUSE MEMBER FROM
VERMONT.
THREE CANDIDATES IN THE RACE.
ONE CANDIDATE SAID YOU KNOW
WHAT, I DON'T THINK IT'S A GREAT
IDEA THAT WE SELL AUTOMATIC
WEAPONS IN THIS COUNTRY THAT ARE
USED BY THE MILITARY TO KILL
PEOPLE VERY RAPIDLY.
GUN PEOPLE SAID -- THERE WERE
THREE CANDIDATES IN THE RACE.
YOU VOTE FOR ONE OF THE OTHERS,
BUT NOT BERNIE SANDERS.
I LOST THAT ELECTION BY 3
PERCENTAGE POINTS.
QUITE LIKELY FOR THAT REASON.
SO PLEASE DO NOT EXPLAIN TO ME
COMING FROM A STATE WHERE
DEMOCRATIC GOVERNORS AND
REPUBLICAN GOVERNORS HAVE
SUPPORTED VIRTUALLY NO GUN
CONTROL -- EXCUSE ME.
DO NOT TELL ME.
>> PAT LEAHY --
>> THAT I HAVE NOT SHOWN COURAGE
IN STANDING UP TO THE GUN
PEOPLE, IN VOTING TO BAN ASSAULT
WEAPONS, VOTING FOR INSTANT
BACKGROUND CHECKS, VOTING TO END
THE GUN SHOW LOOPHOLE, AND NOW
IN A POSITION TO CREATE A
CONSENSUS IN AMERICA ON GUN
SAFETY.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO MOVE ON HERE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU BROUGHT
UP DONALD TRUMP A SHORT TIME
AGO --
>> I DO.
AND THIS IS AN IMPORTANT ISSUE.
AND I KNOW WE'LL GET TO A LOT OF
OTHER CRITICAL ONES AS WELL.
I ACTUALLY AGREE WITH GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY ABOUT THE NEED FOR
COMMON SENSE GUN SAFETY
MEASURES, AND I APPLAUD HIS
RECORD IN MARYLAND.
I JUST WISH HE WOULDN'T
MISREPRESENT MINE.
I HAVE BEEN FOR THE BRADY BILL.
I HAVE BEEN AGAINST ASSAULT
WEAPONS.
I HAVE VOTED NOT TO GIVE GUN
MAKERS AND SELLERS IMMUNITY.
AND I ALSO KNOW -- AND I'M GLAD
TO SEE THIS.
SENATOR SANDERS HAS REALLY MOVED
IN FACE OF THE FACTS ABOUT WHAT
WE'RE CONFRONTING IN OUR
COUNTRY.
I KNOW THAT HE HAS SAID IN THE
TWO PREVIOUS DEBATES THAT HE
WANTS TO TAKE ON THIS IMMUNITY
ISSUE BECAUSE WE NEED TO SEND A
STRONG MESSAGE TO THE GUN
MANUFACTURERS, TO THE SELLERS,
TO THE GUN LOBBY.
AND I WOULD HOPE, SENATOR
SANDERS, THAT YOU WOULD JOIN THE
DEMOCRATS WHO ARE TRYING TO
CLOSE THE CHARLESTON LOOPHOLE,
THAT YOU WOULD SPONSOR OR
CO-SPONSOR LEGISLATION TO REMOVE
THE ABSOLUTE IMMUNITY.
WE NEED TO MOVE ON THIS
CONSENSUS THAT EXISTS IN THE
COUNTRY.
IT'S NO LONGER ENOUGH JUST TO
SAY THE VAST MAJORITY OF
AMERICANS WANT COMMON SENSE GUN
SAFETY MEASURES INCLUDING GUN
OWNERS.
WE NEED, AND ONLY THE THREE OF
US WILL DO THIS, NOBODY ON THE
REPUBLICAN SIDE WILL EVEN ADMIT
THERE'S A PROBLEM, AND IN
WHATEVER WAY THE THREE OF US CAN
WE NEED TO MOVE THIS AGENDA
FORWARD AND BEGIN TO DEAL WITH
THE GUN LOBBY AND THE
INTIMIDATION THAT THEY PRESENT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON FROM GUNS
HERE AND GO BACK TO SOMETHING
YOU MENTIONED A SHORT TIME AGO.
YOU BROUGHT UP DONALD TRUMP
FIRST HERE THIS EVENING.
WE'VE NOW SEEN THE POLLING DONE
WELL AFTER HIS PROPOSED BAN ON
MUSLIMS COMING TO AMERICA.
36% OF AMERICANS, MORE THAN 1/3,
AGREE WITH HIM.
YOU HAVE WEIGHED IN ALREADY ON
DONALD TRUMP.
YOU'VE WEIGHED IN ON THE
PROPOSED BAN.
BUT WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO THE
MILLIONS OF AMERICANS WATCHING
TONIGHT WHO AGREE WITH HIM?
ARE THEY WRONG?
>> WELL, I THINK A LOT OF PEOPLE
ARE UNDERSTANDABLY REACTING OUT
OF FEAR AND ANXIETY ABOUT WHAT
THEY'RE SEEING.
FIRST WHAT THEY SAW IN PARIS.
NOW WHAT THEY HAVE SEEN IN SAN
BERNARDINO.
AND MR. TRUMP HAS A GREAT
CAPACITY TO USE BLUSTER AND
BIGOTRY TO INFLAME PEOPLE AND TO
MAKE THEM THINK THERE ARE EASY
ANSWERS TO VERY COMPLEX
QUESTIONS.
SO WHAT I WOULD SAY IS, NUMBER
ONE, WE NEED TO BE UNITED
AGAINST THE THREATS THAT WE
FACE.
WE NEED TO HAVE EVERYBODY IN OUR
COUNTRY FOCUSED ON WATCHING WHAT
HAPPENS AND REPORTING IT IF IT'S
SUSPICIOUS, REPORTING WHAT YOU
HEAR, MAKING SURE THAT MUSLIM
AMERICANS DON'T FEEL LEFT OUT OR
MARGINALIZED AT THE VERY MOMENT
WHEN WE NEED THEIR HELP.
YOU KNOW, I WAS A SENATOR FROM
NEW YORK AFTER 9/11, AND WE
SPENT COUNTLESS HOURS TRYING TO
FIGURE OUT HOW TO PROTECT THE
CITY AND THE STATE FROM PERHAPS
ADDITIONAL ATTACKS.
ONE OF THE BEST THINGS THAT WAS
DONE, AND GEORGE W. BUSH DID
THIS, AND I GIVE HIM CREDIT, WAS
TO REACH OUT TO MUSLIM AMERICANS
AND SAY WE'RE IN THIS TOGETHER,
YOU ARE NOT OUR ADVERSARY, YOU
ARE OUR PARTNER.
AND WE ALSO NEED TO MAKE SURE
THAT THE REALLY DISCRIMINATORY
MESSAGES THAT TRUMP IS SENDING
AROUND THE WORLD DON'T FALL ON
RECEPTIVE EARS.
HE IS BECOMING ISIS'S BEST
RECRUITER.
THEY ARE GOING TO PEOPLE SHOWING
VIDEOS OF DONALD TRUMP INSULTING
ISLAM AND MUSLIMS IN ORDER TO
RECRUIT MORE RADICAL JIHADISTS.
I WANT TO EXPLAIN WHY THIS IS
NOT IN AMERICA'S INTEREST TO
REACT WITH THIS KIND OF FEAR AND
RESPOND TO THIS SORT OF BIGOTRY.
>> SECRETARY, THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS, I DID WANT TO
ASK YOU ABOUT A NEIGHBOR IN SAN
BERNARDINO WHO REPORTEDLY
WITNESSED PACKAGES BEING
DELIVERED TO THAT COUPLE'S HOME,
THAT IT SET OFF RED FLAGS BUT
THEY DIDN'T REPORT IT BECAUSE
THEY WERE AFRAID TO PROFILE.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO AMERICANS
AFRAID TO PROFILE?
IS IT EVER ACCEPTABLE?
>> THE ANSWER IS OBVIOUSLY IF
YOU SEE SUSPICIOUS ACTIVITY YOU
REPORT IT.
THAT'S KIND OF A NO-BRAINER.
IF SOMEBODY IS LOADING GUNS AND
AMMUNITION INTO A HOUSE, I THINK
IT'S A GOOD IDEA TO CALL 911.
DO IT.
>> BUT I'M ASKING ABOUT
PROFILING.
BECAUSE A LOT OF PEOPLE ARE
AFRAID OF THAT.
>> I WANT TO TALK ABOUT
SOMETHING ELSE BECAUSE SECRETARY
CLINTON I THINK MADE SOME
INTERESTING AND GOOD POINTS.
WHAT YOU HAVE NOW IS A VERY
DANGEROUS MOMENT IN AMERICAN
HISTORY.
THE SECRETARY IS RIGHT.
OUR PEOPLE ARE FEARFUL.
THEY ARE ANXIOUS ON A NUMBER OF
LEVELS.
THEY ARE ANXIOUS ABOUT
INTERNATIONAL TERRORISM.
AND THE POSSIBILITY OF ANOTHER
ATTACK ON AMERICA.
WE ALL UNDERSTAND THAT.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT ELSE THEY'RE
ANXIOUS ABOUT?
THEY'RE ANXIOUS ABOUT THE FACT
THAT THEY ARE WORKING INCREDIBLY
LONG HOURS, THEY'RE WORRIED
ABOUT THEIR KIDS AND THEY'RE
SEEING THE INCOME AND WEALTH
GOING TO THE TOP 1%.
AND THEY'RE LOOKING AT
WASHINGTON AND SAYING THE RICH
ARE GETTING MUCH RICHER, I'M
GETTING POORER, WHAT ARE YOU
GOING TO DO FOR MY KIDS?
AND SOMEBODY LIKE A TRUMP COMES
ALONG AND SAYS I KNOW THE
ANSWERS.
THE ANSWER IS THAT ALL OF THE
MEXICANS, THEY'RE CRIMINALS AND
RAPISTS, WE'VE GOT TO HATE THE
MEXICANS.
THOSE ARE YOUR ENEMIES.
WE HATE ALL THE MUSLIMS BECAUSE
ALL OF THE MUSLIMS ARE
TERRORISTS.
WE'VE GOT TO HATE THE MUSLIMS.
MEANWHILE, THE RICH GET RICHER.
SO WHAT I SAY TO THOSE PEOPLE
WHO GO TO DONALD TRUMP'S
RALLIES, UNDERSTAND, HE THINKS A
LOW MINIMUM WAGE IN AMERICA IS A
GOOD IDEA.
HE THINKS LOW WAGES ARE A GOOD
IDEA.
I BELIEVE WE STAND TOGETHER TO
ADDRESS THE REAL ISSUES FACING
THIS COUNTRY, NOT ALLOW THEM TO
DIVIDE US BY RACE OR WHERE WE
COME FROM.
LET'S CREATE AN AMERICA THAT
WORKS FOR ALL OF US, NOT THE
HANDFUL ON TOP.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
>> I WANT TO MOVE TO ANOTHER --
>> MARTHA --
>> NOT YET, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
I'LL COME TO YOU WHEN WE CALL ON
YOU.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> WHEN YOU COME BACK TO ME,
I'LL SHARE THAT STORY.
>> YOU'LL BE HAPPY.
I'LL LET YOU TALK THEN.
SECRETARY CLINTON, I WANT TO
TALK ABOUT A NEW TERRORIST TOOL
USED IN THE PARIS ATTACKS,
ENCRYPT
ENCRYPTION.
FBI DIRECTOR JAMES COMEY SAYS
TERRORISTS CAN HOLD SECRET
COMMUNICATIONS WHICH LAW
ENFORCEMENT CANNOT GET TO EVEN
WITH A COURT ORDER.
YOU'VE TALKED A LOT ABOUT
BRINGING TECH LEADERS AND
GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS TOGETHER,
BUT APPLE'S CEO TIM COOK SAID
REMOVING ENCRYPTION TOOLS FROM
OUR PRODUCTS ALTOGETHER WOULD
ONLY HURT LAW-ABIDING CITIZENS
WHO RELY ON US TO PROTECT THEIR
DATA.
SO WOULD YOU FORCE HIM TO GIVE
LAW ENFORCEMENT A KEY TO
ENCRYPTED TECHNOLOGY BY MAKING
IT LAW?
>> I WOULD NOT WANT TO GO TO
THAT POINT.
I WOULD HOPE THAT GIVEN THE
EXTRAORDINARY CAPACITIES THAT
THE TECH COMMUNITY HAS AND THE
LEGITIMATE NEEDS AND QUESTIONS
FROM LAW ENFORCEMENT THAT THERE
COULD BE A MANHATTAN-LIKE
PROJECT, SOMETHING THAT WOULD
BRING THE GOVERNMENT AND THE
TECH COMMUNITIES TOGETHER TO SEE
THEY'RE NOT ADVERSARIES, THEY'VE
GOT TO BE PARTNERS.
IT DOESN'T DO ANYBODY ANY GOOD.
IF TERRORISTS CAN MOVE TOWARD
ENCRYPTED COMMUNICATION THAT NO
LAW ENFORCEMENT AGENCY CAN BREAK
INTO BEFORE OR AFTER, THERE MUST
BE SOME WAY.
I DON'T KNOW ENOUGH ABOUT THE
TECHNOLOGY, MARTHA, TO BE ABLE
TO SAY WHAT IT IS.
BUT I HAVE A LOT OF CONFIDENCE
IN OUR TECH EXPERTS, AND MAYBE
THE BACK DOOR IS THE WRONG DOOR.
AND I UNDERSTAND WHAT APPLE AND
OTHERS ARE SAYING ABOUT THAT.
BUT I ALSO UNDERSTAND WHEN A LAW
ENFORCEMENT OFFICIAL CHARGED
WITH THE RESPONSIBILITY OF
PREVENTING ATTACKS, TO GO BACK
TO OUR EARLY QUESTIONS, HOW DO
WE PREVENT ATTACKS, WELL, IF WE
CAN'T KNOW WHAT SOMEONE IS
PLANNING WE ARE GOING TO HAVE TO
RELY ON THE NEIGHBOR OR, YOU
KNOW, THE MEMBER OF THE MOSQUE
OR THE TEACHER, SOMEBODY TO SEE
SOMETHING.
I JUST THINK THERE'S GOT TO BE A
WAY, AND I WOULD HOPE THAT OUR
TECH COMPANIES WOULD WORK WITH
GOVERNMENT TO FIGURE THAT OUT.
OTHERWISE, LAW ENFORCEMENT IS
BLIND.
BLIND BEFORE, BLIND DURING, AND
UNFORTUNATELY IN MANY INSTANCES
BLIND AFTER.
SO WE ALWAYS HAVE TO BALANCE
LIBERTY AND SECURITY, PRIVACY
AND SAFETY, BUT I KNOW THAT LAW
ENFORCEMENT NEEDS THE TOOLS TO
KEEP US SAFE.
AND THAT'S WHAT I HOPE, THERE
CAN BE SOME UNDERSTANDING AND
COOPERATION TO ACHIEVE.
>> AND GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, WHERE
DO YOU DRAW THE LINE BETWEEN
NATIONAL SECURITY AND PERSONAL
SECURITY?
>> I BELIEVE THAT WE SHOULD
NEVER GIVE UP OUR PRIVACY, NEVER
SHOULD GIVE UP OUR FREEDOMS IN
EXCHANGE FOR A PROMISE OF
SECURITY.
WE NEED TO FIGURE THIS OUT
TOGETHER.
WE NEED A COLLABORATIVE
APPROACH.
WE NEED NEW LEADERSHIP.
THE WAY THAT THINGS WORK IN THE
MODERN ERA IS ACTUALLY TO GATHER
PEOPLE AROUND THE TABLE AND
FIGURE THESE THINGS OUTS.
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT SHOULD
HAVE TO GET WARRANTS.
THAT'S NOT SOME SORT OF PASSE
ANTIQUE PRINCIPLE THAT
SAFEGUARDS OUR FREEDOMS.
BUT AT THE SAME TIME WITH NEW
TECHNOLOGIES I BELIEVE THAT THE
PEOPLE CREATING THESE
PROJECTS -- I MEAN THESE
PRODUCTS ALSO HAVE AN OBLIGATION
TO COME TOGETHER WITH LAW
ENFORCEMENT TO FIGURE THESE
THINGS OUT.
TRUE TO OUR AMERICAN PRINCIPLES
AND VALUES.
MY FRIEND KASHIF, WHO IS A
DOCTOR IN MARYLAND, BACK TO THIS
ISSUE OF OUR DANGER AS A
DEMOCRACY OF TURNING AGAINST
OURSELVES.
HE WAS PUTTING HIS 10 AND
12-YEAR-OLD BOYS TO BED THE
OTHER NIGHT.
AND HE IS A PROUD AMERICAN
MUSLIM.
AND ONE OF HIS LITTLE BOYS SAID
TO HIM, "DAD, WHAT HAPPENS IF
DONALD TRUMP WINS AND WE HAVE TO
MOVE OUT OF OUR HOMES?"
THESE ARE VERY, VERY REAL
ISSUES.
THIS IS A CLEAR AND PRESENT
DANGER IN OUR POLITICS WITHIN.
WE NEED TO SPEAK TO WHAT UNITES
US AS A PEOPLE.
FREEDOM OF WORSHIP, FREEDOM OF
RELIGION, FREEDOM OF EXPRESSION.
AND WE SHOULD NEVER BE CONVINCED
TO GIVE UP THOSE FREEDOMS IN
EXCHANGE FOR A PROMISE OF
GREATER SECURITY.
ESPECIALLY FROM SOMEONE AS
UNTRIED AND AS INCOMPETENT AS
DONALD TRUMP.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> MARTHA, WE'RE GOING TO TURN
NOW TO REFUGEES COMING TO
AMERICA.
AND ON THE SUBJECT OF REFUGEES,
MORE THAN HALF OF ALL AMERICANS
NOW SAY THEY OPPOSE TAKING IN
REFUGEES FROM SYRIA AND ACROSS
THE MIDDLE EAST.
SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU HAVE SAID
THAT IT WOULD UNDERMINE WHO WE
ARE AS AMERICANS SHUTTING OUR
DOORS.
BUT NEW HAMPSHIRE'S GOVERNOR,
WHERE WE ARE RIGHT HERE TONIGHT,
A DEMOCRAT AND A SUPPORTER OF
YOURS, IS AMONG MORE THAN 30
GOVERNORS WHO ARE NOW CONCERNED.
GOVERNOR MAGGIE HASSAN SAYS WE
SHOULD HALT ACCEPTANCE OF SYRIAN
REFUGEES UNTIL U.S. AUTHORITIES
CAN ASSURE THE VETTING PROCESS,
HALT SYRIAN REFUGEES, A PAUSE.
IS SHE WRONG?
>> WELL, I AGREE THAT WE HAVE TO
HAVE THE TOUGHEST SCREENING AND
VETTING --
>> BUT A HALT?
>> I DON'T THINK A HALT IS
NECESSARY.
WHAT WE HAVE TO DO IS PUT ALL OF
OUR RESOURCES THROUGH THE
DEPARTMENT OF HOMELAND SECURITY,
THROUGH THE STATE DEPARTMENT,
THROUGH OUR INTELLIGENCE
AGENCIES, AND WE HAVE TO HAVE AN
INCREASED VETTING AND SCREENING.
NOW, THIS TAKES, DAVID, 18
MONTHS TO 24 MONTHS, TWO YEARS.
SO I KNOW IT'S NOT GOING TO
HAPPEN OVERNIGHT.
AND EVERYTHING THAT CAN BE DONE
SHOULD BE DONE.
BUT THE PROCESS SHOULD MOVE
FORWARD WHILE WE ARE ALSO TAKING
ON ISIS, PUTTING TOGETHER THE
KIND OF STRATEGY THAT I'VE
ADVOCATED FOR, AND MAKING SURE
THAT THE VETTING AND THE
SCREENING IS AS TOUGH AS
POSSIBLE.
BECAUSE I DO BELIEVE THAT WE
HAVE A HISTORY AND A TRADITION.
THAT IS PART OF OUR VALUES
SYSTEM.
AND WE DON'T WANT TO SACRIFICE
OUR VALUES.
WE DON'T WANT TO MAKE IT SEEM AS
THOUGH WE ARE TURNING INTO A
NATION OF FEAR INSTEAD OF A
NATION OF RESOLVE.
SO I WANT US TO HAVE A VERY
TOUGH SCREENING PROCESS.
BUT I WANT THAT PROCESS TO GO
FORWARD.
AND IF AT THE END OF 18 MONTHS,
24 MONTHS THERE ARE PEOPLE WHO
HAVE BEEN CLEARED, AND I WOULD
PRIORITIZE WIDOWS AND ORPHANS
AND THE ELDERLY, PEOPLE WHO MAY
HAVE RELATIVES, FAMILIES, OR
NOWHERE ELSE TO GO.
I WOULD PRIORITIZE THEM.
AND THAT WOULD I THINK GIVE THE
AMERICAN PUBLIC A BIT MORE OF A
SENSE OF SECURITY ABOUT WHO IS
BEING PROCESSED AND WHO MIGHT
END UP COMING AS REFUGEES.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, OBVIOUSLY
YOU WERE GOVERNOR YOURSELF AT
ONE TIME.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO NEW
HAMPSHIRE'S GOVERNOR TONIGHT?
IS SHE WRONG ON THIS?
>> NO, WHAT I WOULD SAY IS THIS
IS LOOK, I WAS THE FIRST OF THE
THREE OF US TO CALL FOR AMERICA
TO SEPTEMBER 65,000 REFUGEES WE
WERE ASKED TO ACCEPT.
AND IF THIS HUMANITARIAN CRISIS
INCREASES, WE SHOULD ACCEPT
MORE.
>> SO THE IDEA OF A HALT OR A
PAUSE?
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> DAVID, THERE ARE WIDER
VULNERABILITIES THAN WHEN IT
COMES TO REFUGEES.
I MET RECENTLY WITH SOME MEMBERS
OF THE CHALDEAN CHRISTIAN
COMMUNITIES AND THE WAIT TIMES
ARE A YEAR, 18 MONTHS, 24
MONTHS.
THERE IS A PRETTY EXCRUCIATING
PROCESS THAT REFUGEES GO
THROUGH.
WE NEED TO INVEST MORE IN TERMS
OF THE OTHER SORT OF VISAS AND
THE OTHER SORT OF WAIVERS.
WHAT THESE CHALDEAN FAMILIES
TOLD ME IS THEIR FAMILIES IN
SYRIA, WHEN ISIS MOVES INTO
THEIR TOWN, THEY ACTUALLY PAINT
A RED CROSS ACROSS THE DOOR AND
MARK THEIR HOMES FOR DEMOLITION,
AND THAT TELLS THE FAMILY YOU'D
BETTER GET OUT NOW.
THE SORT OF GENOCIDE AND
BRUTALITY THAT THE VICTIMS ARE
SUFFERING, THESE ARE NOT THE
PERPETRATORS.
WE NEED TO BE THE NATION WHOSE
ENDURING SYMBOL IS THE STATUE OF
LIBERTY, AND WE NEED TO ACT LIKE
THE GREAT COUNTRY WE ARE
ACCORDING TO OUR VALUES.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, WE'RE GOING
TO MOVE ON.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON.
>> EXCUSE ME.
MAY I HAVE A CHANCE TO RESPOND
TO THIS ISSUE?
>> WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON TO THE
FIGHT AGAINST ISIS.
YOU'RE THE ONE WHO TOLD US WE
HAVE TO FOLLOW THE RULES AND
BREAK IT OFF.
>> YEAH, BUT THE RULE INCLUDES
PEOPLE -- GOT IT.
ALL RIGHT.
>> LET'S KEEP GOING.
THANK YOU.
>> OKAY.
>> THANK YOU.
I DO WANT TO MOVE TO THE FIGHT
AGAINST ISIS.
FOR THE PEOPLE OF NEW HAMPSHIRE,
THE BRUTALITY OF ISIS IS
PERSONAL.
JAMES FOLEY GREW UP HERE.
THE FIRST HOSTAGE, A JOURNALIST,
BRUTALLY EXECUTED LAST YEAR.
YOU'VE ALL SAID ISIS IS A
RUTHLESS ENEMY AND MUST BE
STOPPED.
AL QAEDA AS WELL.
SENATOR
COALITION FORCES TO HELP DESTROY
AL QAEDA IN AFGHANISTAN.
CAN YOU EXPLAIN YOU WHY DON'T
SUPPORT SENDING U.S. COMBAT
TROOPS TO JOIN A COALITION TO
FIGHT ISIS?
>> I ALSO VOTED AND HELPED LEAD
THE EFFORT AGAINST THE WAR IN
IRAQ, WHICH WILL GO DOWN IN
HISTORY AS ONE OF THE WORST
FOREIGN BLUNDERS -- FOREIGN
POLICY BLUNDERS IN THE HISTORY
OF OUR COUNTRY.
I VOTED AGAINST THE FIRST GULF
WAR, WHICH SET THE STAGE I
BELIEVE FOR THE SECOND IRAQ WAR.
AND WHAT I BLEELIEVE RIGHT NOW,
AND I BELIEVE THIS IS TERRIBLY
IMPORTANT, IS THE UNITED STATES
OF AMERICA CANNOT SUCCEED OR BE
THOUGHT OF AS THE POLICEMAN OF
THE WORLD, THAT WHEN THERE'S AN
INTERNATIONAL CRISIS ALL OVER
THE WORLD, IN FRANCE AND IN THE
U.K. OR -- HEY, JUST CALL UP THE
AMERICAN MILITARY AND THE
AMERICAN TAXPAYERS, THEY'RE
GOING TO SEND THE TROOPS, AND IF
THEY HAVE TO BE IN THE MIDDLE
EAST FOR 20 OR 30 YEARS NO
PROBLEM.
>> BUT WHY AL QAEDA, WHY NOT
ISIS?
>> I HAVE A PROBLEM WITH THAT,
MARTHA.
WHAT I BELIEVE HAS GOT TO HAPPEN
IS THERE MUST BE AN
INTERNATIONAL COALITION
INCLUDING RUSSIA, A
WELL-COORDINATED EFFORT.
BUT I AGREE, AS I MENTIONED A
MOMENT AGO, WITH KING ABDULLAH.
THIS IS A WAR FOR THE SOUL OF
ISLAM.
THE TROOPS ON THE GROUND SHOULD
NOT BE AMERICAN TROOPS.
THEY SHOULD BE MUSLIM TROOPS.
I BELIEVE THAT COUNTRIES LIKE
SAUDI ARABIA AND QATAR HAVE GOT
TO STEP UP TO THE PLATE, HAVE
GOT TO CONTRIBUTE THE MONEY THAT
WE NEED AND THE TROOPS THAT WE
NEED TO DESTROY ISIS WITH
AMERICAN SUPPORT.
>> THE ADMINISTRATION HAS TRIED
THAT OVER AND OVER AGAIN.
IF IT DOESN'T WORK AND THIS
THREAT IS SO GREAT, WHAT'S YOUR
PLAN B?
>> MY PLAN IS TO MAKE IT WORK,
TO TELL SAUDI ARABIA THAT
INSTEAD OF GOING TO WAR IN
YEMEN, THEY ONE OF THE
WEALTHIEST COUNTRIES ON EARTH
ARE GOING TO HAVE TO GO TO WAR
AGAINST ISIS.
TO TELL QATAR THAT INSTEAD OF
SPENDING $200 BILLION ON THE
WORLD CUP MAYBE THEY SHOULD PAY
ATTENTION TO ISIS WHICH IS AT
THEIR DOORSTEP.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, YOU TOO
HAVE RULED OUT A LARGE U.S.
COMBAT FORCE, YET YOU SUPPORT
SENDING IN SPECIAL OPERATIONS
FORCES TO SYRIA AND SENDING 100
TO 200 TROOPS TO IRAQ TO DO
EXPLOITATION KILL RAIDS.
WE'VE ALREADY LOST ONE DELTA
FORCE MEMBER IN A RAID.
IT'S LOOKED VERY MUCH TO ME LIKE
WE'RE ALREADY IN GROUND COMBAT
ON FREQUENT TRIPS I'VE MADE
THERE.
SO ARE YOU FOOLING AMERICANS
WHEN YOU SAY WE'RE NOT PUTTING
AMERICAN COMBAT TROOPS BACK INTO
SYRIA OR IRAQ?
>> NO.
NOT AT ALL.
I THINK THAT WHAT WE'RE FACING
WITH ISIS IS ESPECIALLY
COMPLICATED.
IT WAS A DIFFERENT SITUATION IN
AFGHANISTAN.
WE WERE ATTACKED FROM
AL QAEDA WAS BASED IN
AFGHANISTAN.
WE WENT AFTER THOSE WHO HAD
ATTACKED US.
WHAT'S HAPPENING IN SYRIA AND
IRAQ IS THAT BECAUSE OF THE
FAILURES IN THE REGION,
INCLUDING THE FAILURE OF THE
PRIOR GOVERNMENT IN BAGHDAD, LED
BY MALIKI, THERE HAS BEEN A
RESURGENCE OF SUNNI ACTIVITIES
AS EXEMPLIFIED BY ISIS, AND WE
HAVE TO SUPPORT SUNNI ARAB AND
KURDISH FORCES AGAINST ISIS
BECAUSE I BELIEVE IT WOULD BE
NOT ONLY A STRATEGIC MISTAKE FOR
THE UNITED STATES TO PUT GROUND
COMBAT TROOPS IN AS OPPOSED TO
SPECIAL OPERATORS, AS OPPOSED TO
TRAINERS BECAUSE THAT IS EXACTLY
WHAT ISIS WANTS.
THEY'VE ADVERTISED THAT.
THEY WANT AMERICAN TROOPS BACK
IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
THEY WANT AMERICAN SOLDIERS ON
THE GROUND FIGHTING THEM.
GIVING THEM MANY MORE TARGETS
AND GIVING THEM A GREAT
RECRUITING OPPORTUNITY.
SO I THINK IT'S
WRONG POLICY FOR US TO BE EVEN
IMAGINING WE'RE GOING TONED UP
PUTTING TENS OF THOUSANDS OF
AMERICAN TROOPS INTO SYRIA AND
IRAQ TO FIGHT ISIS.
AND WE DO HAVE TO FORM A
COALITION.
I KNOW HOW HARD THAT IS.
I HAVE FORMED THEM.
I PUT TOGETHER A COALITION
INCLUDING ARABS WITH RESPECT TO
LIBYA AND A COALITION TO PUT
SANCTIONS ONTO IRAN.
AND YOU HAVE TO REALLY WORK HARD
AT IT.
AND THE FINAL THING I WOULD SAY,
BRINGING DONALD TRUMP BACK INTO
IT, IF YOU'RE GOING TO PUT
TOGETHER A COALITION IN THE
REGION, TO TAKE ON THE THREAT OF
ISIS, YOU DON'T WANT TO ALIENATE
THE VERY COUNTRIES AND PEOPLE
YOU NEED TO BE PART OF THE
COALITION.
AND SO THAT IS PART OF THE
REASON WHY THIS IS SO DIFFICULT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I WANT TO
FOLLOW UP ON THAT.
YOU DO SUPPORT SENDING SPECIAL
OPERATIONS FORCES THERE.
YOU SUPPORT WHAT THE PRESIDENT
HAS DONE ALREADY.
ONE OF THE LESSONS PEOPLE DRAW
FROM VIETNAM AND WARS SINCE IS
THAT A LITTLE FORCE CAN TURN
INTO A LITTLE MORE AND A LITTLE
MORE.
PRESIDENT OBAMA CERTAINLY DIDN'T
EXPECT TO BE SENDING 30,000
ADDITIONAL TROOPS INTO
AFGHANISTAN THE FIRST YEAR OF
HIS PRESIDENCY.
ARE YOU PREPARED TO RUN THE RISK
OF A BIGGER WAR TO ACHIEVE YOUR
GOALS TO DESTROY ISIS, OR ARE
YOU PREPARED TO GIVE UP ON THOSE
GOALS IF IT REQUIRES A LARGER
FORCE?
>> I JUST THINK YOU'RE ASKING A
QUESTION WITH A FALSE CHOICE.
I BELIEVE IF WE LEAD AN AIR
COALITION, WHICH WE ARE NOW IN
THE POSITION OF DOING AND
INTENSIFY IT, IF WE CONTINUE TO
BUILD BACK UP THE IRAQI ARMY,
WHICH HAS HAD SOME RECENT
SUCCESS IN RAMADI, AS YOU KNOW,
IF WE GET BACK TALKING TO THE
TRIBAL SHEIKS IN ANBAR TO TRY TO
REBUILD THOSE RELATIONSHIPS,
WHICH WERE VERY SUCCESSFUL, IN
GOING AFTER AL QAEDA IN IRAQ, IF
WE GET THE TURKS TO PAY MORE
ATTENTION TO ISIS THAN THEY'RE
PAYING TO THE KURDS, IF WE DO
PUT TOGETHER THE KIND OF
COALITION WITH THE SPECIFIC
TASKS THAT I AM OUTLINING, I
THINK WE CAN BE SUCCESSFUL IN
DESTROYING ISIS.
SO THAT'S WHAT I'M FOCUSED ON.
THAT'S WHAT I'VE OUTLINED.
AND THAT'S WHAT I WOULD DO AS
PRESIDENT.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
YOU'VE EMPHASIZED THE NEED FOR
MORE HUMAN INTELLIGENCE ON THE
GROUND.
WHAT IS IT OUR INTELLIGENCE
COMMUNITY IS NOT DOING NOW THAT
NEEDS TO BE DONE?
>> WELL, WE HAVE INVESTED
NOWHERE NEAR WHAT WE SHOULD BE
INVESTING IN HUMAN INTELLIGENCE
ON THE GROUND.
AND WHAT I'M TALKING ABOUT IS
NOT ONLY THE COVERT, CIA
INTELLIGENCE, I'M ALSO TALKING
ABOUT DIPLOMATIC INTELLIGENCE.
I MEAN, WE'VE SEEN TIME AND TIME
AGAIN, ESPECIALLY IN THIS VERY
TROUBLED REGION OF NATION-STATE
FAILURES, AND THEN WE HAVE NO
IDEA WHO THE NEXT GENERATION OF
LEADERS ARE THAT ARE COMING
FORWARD.
SO WHAT I WOULD SAY IS NOT ONLY
DO WE NEED TO BE THINKING IN
MILITARY TERMS BUT WE DO OUR
MILITARY A DISSERVICE WHEN WE
DON'T GREATLY DIAL UP THE
INVESTMENT WE ARE MAKING IN
DIPLOMACY AND HUMAN INTELLIGENCE
AND WHEN WE FAIL TO DIAL UP
PROPERLY THE ROLE OF SUSTAINABLE
DEVELOPMENT IN ALL OF THIS.
AS PRESIDENT I WOULD MAKE THE
ADMINISTRATOR OF USAID AN ACTUAL
CABINET MEMBER.
WE HAVE TO ACT IN A MUCH MORE
WHOLE OF GOVERNMENT APPROACH AS
GENERAL DEMPSEY SAID.
AND I DO BELIEVE, AND I DISAGREE
SOMEWHAT WITH ONE OF MY
COLLEAGUES, THIS IS A GENERAL
O'SIDAL THREAT.
THEY HAVE NOW CREATED A SAFE
HAVEN IN THE VACUUM THAT WE
ALLOWED TO BE PARTLY AND BECAUSE
OF OUR BLUNDERS, TO BE CREATED
TO BE CREATED IN THE AREAS OF
SYRIA AND IRAQ.
WE CANNOT ALLOW SAFE HAVENS.
AND AS A LEADER OF MORAL NATIONS
AROUND THIS EARTH WE NEED TO
COME UP WITH NEW ALLIANCES AND
NEW WAYS TO PREPARE FOR THESE
NEW SORTS OF THREATS.
BECAUSE MARTHA, THIS WILL NOT BE
THE LAST REGION WHERE
NATION-STATES FAIL.
AND YOU'VE SEEN A LITTLE BIT OF
THIS EMERGING IN THE AFRICAN
UNION AND THE THINGS THAT THEY
HAVE DONE TO BETTER STABILIZE
SOMALIA.
WE NEED TO PAY ATTENTION HERE IN
CENTRAL AMERICA AS WELL.
THIS IS THE NEW TYPE OF THREATS
THAT WE'RE FACING AND WE NEED TO
LEAD AS A NATION IN CONFRONTING
IT AND PUTTING TOGETHER NEW
ALLIANCES AND NEW COALITIONS.
>> THANK YOU.
>> I JUST WANT TO QUICKLY ADD,
MARTHA, ONE OF THE REASONS WHY I
HAVE ADVOCATED FOR A NO-FLY ZONE
IS IN ORDER TO CREATE THOSE SAFE
REFUGES WITHIN SYRIA, TO TRY TO
PROTECT PEOPLE ON THE GROUND
BOTH FROM ASSAD'S FORCES, WHO
ARE CONTINUING TO DROP BARREL
BOMBS, AND FROM ISIS.
AND OF COURSE IT HAS TO BE
DECONFLICTED WITH THE RUSSIANS,
WHO ARE ALSO FLYING IN THAT
SPACE.
I'M HOPING THAT BECAUSE OF THE
VERY RECENT ANNOUNCEMENT OF THE
AGREEMENT AT THE SECURITY
COUNCIL WHICH EMBODIES ACTUALLY
AN AGREEMENT THAT I NEGOTIATED
BACK IN GENEVA IN JUNE OF 2012,
WE'RE GOING TO GET A DIPLOMATIC
EFFORT IN SYRIA TO BEGIN TO TRY
TO MAKE A TRANSITION.
A NO-FLY ZONE WOULD PREVENT THE
OUTFLOW OF REFUGEES AND GIVE US
A CHANCE TO HAVE SOME SAFE
SPACES.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I'D LIKE
TO GO BACK TO THAT IF I COULD.
ISIS DOESN'T HAVE AIRCRAFT.
AL QAEDA DOESN'T HAVE AIRCRAFT.
SO WOULD YOU SHOOT DOWN A SYRIAN
MILITARY AIRCRAFT OR A RUSSIAN
AIRPLANE?
>> I DO NOT THINK IT WOULD COME
TO THAT.
WE ARE ALREADY DEFLICONFLICTINGR
SPACE --
>> BUT ISN'T THAT A DECISION YOU
SHOULD MAKE NOW, WHETHER --
>> NO, I DON'T THINK SO.
>> YOU ARE ADVOCATING THIS --
>> I AM ADVOCATING THE NO-FLY
ZONE BOTH BECAUSE I THINK IT
WOULD HELP US ON THE GROUND TO
PROTECT SYRIANS.
I'M ALSO ADVOCATING IT BECAUSE I
THINK IT GIVES US SOME LEVERAGE
IN OUR CONVERSATIONS WITH
RUSSIA.
NOW THAT RUSSIA HAS JOINED US IN
THE SECURITY COUNCIL, HAS ADO
ADOPTED AN AGREEMENT THAT WE
HASHED OUT A LONG DAY IN GENEVA
THREE YEARS AGO, NOW I THINK WE
CAN HAVE THOSE CONVERSATIONS.
THE NO-FLY ZONE I WOULD HOPE
WOULD BE ALSO SHARED BY RUSSIA.
IF THEY WOULD BEGIN TO TURN
THEIR MILITARY ATTENTION AWAY
FROM GOING AFTER THE ADVERSARIES
OF ASSAD TOWARD ISIS AND PUT THE
ASSAD FUTURE ON THE POLITICAL
AND DIPLOMATIC TRACK WHERE IT
BELONGS --
>> EXCUSE ME.
>> I'M GOING TO TAKE THIS TO
SENATOR SANDERS NEXT --
>> THE CRUCIAL COMMENT --
THERE'S A DIFFERENCE OF OPINION
WITH SECRETARY CLINTON ON THIS.
OUR DIFFERENCES ARE FAIRLY DEEP
ON THIS ISSUE.
WE DISAGREED ON THE WAR IN IRAQ.
WE BOTH LISTENED TO THE
INFORMATION FROM BUSH AND
CHENEY.
I VOTED AGAINST THE WAR.
BUT I THINK -- AND I SAY THIS
WITH DUE RESPECT.
THAT I WORRY TOO MUCH THAT
SECRETARY CLINTON IS TOO MUCH
INTO REGIME CHANGE AND A LITTLE
BIT TOO AGGRESSIVE WITHOUT
KNOWING WHAT THE UNINTENDED
CONSEQUENCES MIGHT BE.
YES, WE COULD GET RID OF SADDAM
HUSSEIN, BUT THAT DESTABILIZED
THE ENTIRE REGION.
YES, WE COULD GET RID OF
GADHAFI, A TERRIBLE DICTATOR,
BUT THAT CREATED A VACUUM FOR
ISIS.
YES, WE COULD GET RID OF ASSAD
TOMORROW, BUT THAT WOULD CREATE
ANOTHER POLITICAL VACUUM THAT
WOULD BENEFIT ISIS.
SO I THINK YEAH, REGIME CHANGE
IS EASY, GETTING RID OF
DICTATORS IS EASY, BUT BEFORE
YOU DO THAT YOU'VE GOT TO THINK
ABOUT WHAT HAPPENS THE DAY
AFTER.
AND IN MY VIEW WHAT WE NEED TO
DO IS PUT TOGETHER BROAD
COALITIONS TO UNDERSTAND THAT
WE'RE NOT GOING TO HAVE A
POLITICAL VACUUM FILLED BY
TERRORISTS, THAT IN FACT WE ARE
GOING TO MOVE STEADILY AND MAYBE
SLOWLY TOWARD DEMOCRATIC
SOCIETIES.
IN TERMS OF ASSAD, A TERRIBLE
DICTATOR, BUT I THINK IN SYRIA
THE PRIMARY FOCUS NOW MUST BE
DESTROYING ISIS AND WORKING OVER
THE YEARS TO GET RID OF ASSAD.
THAT'S THE SECONDARY ISSUE.
>> THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT I JUST
SAID AND WHAT I JUST DESCRIBED.
>> YEAH, BUT SECRETARY
CLINTON -- SECRETARY CLINTON --
>> BECAUSE NOW WE HAVE A U.N.
SECURITY COUNCIL THAT WILL
ENABLE US TO DO THAT.
WITH ALL DUE RESPECT, SENATOR,
YOU VOTED FOR REGIME CHANGE WITH
RESPECT TO LIBYA.
YOU JOINED THE SENATE IN VOTING
TO GET RID OF GADHAFI, AND YOU
ASKED THAT THERE BE A SECURITY
COUNCIL VALIDATION OF THAT WITH
A RESOLUTION.
ALL OF THESE ARE VERY DIFFICULT
ISSUES.
I KNOW THAT.
I'VE BEEN DEALING WITH THEM FOR
A LONG TIME.
AND OF COURSE WE HAVE TO
CONTINUE TO DO WHAT IS NECESSARY
WHEN SOMEONE LIKE GADHAFI, A
DESPOT WITH AMERICAN BLOOD ON
HIS HANDS, IS OVERTURNED.
BUT I'LL TELL YOU WHAT WOULD
HAVE HAPPENED IF WE HAD NOT
JOINED WITH OUR EUROPEAN
PARTNERS AND OUR ARAB PARTNERS
TO ASSIST THE PEOPLE IN LIBYA.
YOU WOULD BE LOOKING AT SYRIA.
NOW THE LIBYANS ARE TURNING
THEIR ATTENTION TO TRY TO
DISLODGE ISIS FROM ITS FOOTHOLD
AND BEGIN TO TRY TO MOVE
TOGETHER TO HAVE A UNIFIED
NATION.
>> I WAS NOT THE SECRETARY OF
STATE --
>> SENATOR SANDERS, HOLD ON.
ONE MOMENT, PLEASE.
I'M GOING TO ASK THE SECRETARY
HERE BECAUSE THERE DOES APPEAR
TO BE SOME DAYLIGHT HERE BETWEEN
THE POLICIES, AT LEAST WITH
RESPECT TO WHEN YOU TAKE OUT
SYRIAN PRESIDENT BASHAR AL
ASSAD.
RIGHT NOW OR DO YOU WAIT?
DO YOU TACKLE ISIS FIRST?
YOU HAVE SAID, SECRETARY
CLINTON, THAT YOU COME TO THE
CONCLUSION THAT WE HAVE TO
PROCEED ON BOTH FRONTS AT ONCE.
WE HEARD FROM THE SENATOR JUST
THIS WEEK THAT WE MUST PUT ASIDE
THE ISSUE OF HOW QUICKLY WE GET
RID OF ASSAD AND COME TOGETHER
WITH COUNTRIES INCLUDING RUSSIA
AND IRAN TO DESTROY ISIS FIRST.
IS HE WRONG?
>> I THINK WE'RE MISSING THE
POINT HERE.
WE ARE DOING BOTH AT THE SAME
TIME.
>> BUT THAT'S WHAT HE'S SAYING,
WE SHOULD PUT THAT ASIDE FOR NOW
AND GO AFTER ISIS.
>> WELL, I DON'T AGREE WITH
THAT.
BECAUSE WE WILL NOT GET THE
SUPPORT ON THE GROUND IN SYRIA
TO DISLODGE ISIS IF THE FIGHTERS
THERE WHO ARE NOT ASSOCIATED
WITH ISIS BUT WHOSE PRINCIPAL
GOAL OF GETTING RID OF ASSAD
DON'T BELIEVE THERE IS A
POLITICAL, DIPLOMATIC CHANNEL
THAT IS ONGOING.
WE NOW HAVE THAT
WE HAVE THE U.N. SECURITY
COUNCIL ADOPTING A RESOLUTION
THAT LAYS OUT A TRANSITION PATH.
IT'S VERY IMPORTANT WE OPERATE
ON BOTH AT THE SAME TIME.
AND LET ME JUST SAY A WORD ABOUT
COALITION BUILDING BECAUSE I'VE
HEARD SENATOR SANDERS SAY THIS.
I KNOW HOW HARD IT IS TO BUILD
COALITIONS.
I THINK IT WOULD BE A GRAVE
MISTAKE TO ASK FOR ANY MORE
IRANIAN TROOPS INSIDE SYRIA.
THAT IS LIKE ASKING THE ARSONIST
TO COME AND POUR MORE GAS ON THE
FIRE.
THE IRANIANS GETTING MORE OF A
PRESENCE IN SYRIA, LINKING WITH
HEZBOLLAH, THEIR PROXY IN
LEBANON, WOULD THREATEN ISRAEL
AND WOULD MAKE IT MORE DIFFICULT
FOR US TO MOVE ON A PATH TO HAVE
A TRANSITION THAT AT SOME POINT
WOULD DEAL WITH ASSAD'S FUTURE.
>> I HAPPEN TO THINK --
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> SHE SAYS WE HAVE TO PROCEED
ON BOTH FRONTS AT ONCE.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON IS RIGHT.
THIS IS A COMPLICATED ISSUE.
I DON'T THINK ANYONE HAS A
MAGICAL SOLUTION.
BUT THIS IS WHAT I DO BELIEVE.
YES, OF COURSE ASSAD IS A
TERRIBLE DICTATOR.
BUT I THINK WE HAVE GOT TO GET
OUR FOREIGN POLICIES AND
PRIORITIES RIGHT.
THE IMMEDIATE -- IT IS NOT ASSAD
WHO IS ATTACKING THE UNITED
STATES.
IT IS ISIS.
AND ISIS IS ATTACKING FRANCE AND
ATTACKING RUSSIAN AIRLINERS.
THE MAJOR PRIORITY RIGHT NOW IN
TERMS OF OUR FOREIGN AND
MILITARY POLICY SHOULD BE THE
DESTRUCTION OF ISIS.
AND I THINK -- AND I THINK WE
BRING TOGETHER THAT BROAD
COALITION INCLUDING RUSSIA TO
HELP US DESTROY ISIS.
AND WORK ON A TIMETABLE.
TO GET RID OF ASSAD, HOPEFULLY
THROUGH DEMOCRATIC ELECTIONS.
FIRST PRIORITY, DESTROY ISIS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU.
>> MAY I OFFER A DIFFERENT
GENERATION'S PERSPECTIVE ON
THIS?
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> DURING THE COLD WAR -- DURING
THE COLD WAR WE GOT INTO A BAD
HABIT OF ALWAYS LOOKING TO SEE
WHO WAS WEARING THE JERSEY OF
THE COMMUNISTS AND WHO WAS
WEARING THE U.S. JERSEY.
WE GOT INTO A BAD HABIT OF
CREATING BIG BUREAUCRACIES, OLD
METHODOLOGIES TO UNDERMINE
REGIMES THAT WERE NOT FRIENDLY
TO THE UNITED STATES.
LOOK WHAT WE DID IN IRAN WITH
MOSSADEGH.
AND LOOK AT THE RESULTS WE'RE
STILL DEALING WITH BECAUSE OF
THAT.
I WOULD SUGGEST TO YOU THAT WE
NEED TO LEAVE THE COLD WAR
BEHIND US AND WE NEED TO PUT
TOGETHER NEW ALLIANCES AND NEW
APPROACHES TO DEALING WITH THIS
AND WE NEED TO RESTRAIN
OURSELVES.
I MEAN, I KNOW SECRETARY CLINTON
WAS GLEEFUL WHEN GADHAFI WAS
TORN APART.
WHEN THE WORLD NO DOUBT IS A
BETTER PLACE WITHOUT HIM.
BUT LOOK, WE DIDN'T KNOW WHAT
WAS HAPPENING NEXT.
AND WE FELL INTO THE SAME TRAP
WITH ASSAD, SAYING AS IF IT'S
OUR JOB TO SAY ASSAD MUST GO.
WE HAVE A ROLE TO PLAY IN THIS
WORLD.
BUT WE NEED TO LEAVE THE COLD
WAR AND THAT SORT OF ANTIQUATED
THINKING BEHIND.
>> YOU CRITICIZED SECRETARY
CLINTON FOR WHAT CAME NEXT.
WHAT'S YOUR PROPOSAL FOR WHAT
COMES AFTER ASSAD?
>> I BELIEVE THAT WE NEED TO
FOCUS ON DESTROYING ISIL.
THAT IS THE CLEAR AND PRESENT
DANGER.
AND I BELIEVE THAT WE CAN
SPRINGBOARD OFF OF THIS NEW U.N.
RESOLUTION AND WE SHOULD CREATE
AS SECRETARY CLINTON INDICATED,
AND I AGREE WITH THAT, THAT
THERE SHOULD BE A POLITICAL
PROCESS.
BUT WE SHOULDN'T BE THE ONES
DECLARING THAT ASSAD MUST GO.
WHERE DID IT EVER SAY IN THE
CONSTITUTION, WHERE IS IT
WRITTEN IT IS THE JOB OF THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA OR ITS
SECRETARY OF STATE TO DETERMINE
WHEN DICTATORS HAVE TO GO?
WE HAVE A ROLE TO PLAY IN THIS
WORLD.
BUT IT IS NOT THE WORLD -- THE
ROLE OF TRAVELING THE WORLD
LOOKING FOR NEW MONSTERS TO
DESTROY.
>> DAVID.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON --
>> YOU KNOW --
>> SINCE HE HAS BEEN MAKING ALL
KINDS OF COMMENTS, I THINK IT'S
FAIR TO SAY ASSAD HAS KILLED BY
LAST COUNT ABOUT 250,000
SYRIANS.
THE REASON WE ARE IN THE MESS
WE'RE IN, THAT ISIS HAS THE
TERRITORY IT HAS, IS BECAUSE OF
ASSAD.
I
OPPOSITION BACK IN THE DAY WHEN
I WAS STILL SECRETARY OF STATE
BECAUSE I WORRIED WE WOULD END
UP EXACTLY WHERE WE ARE NOW.
AND SO WHEN WE LOOK AT THESE
COMPLEX PROBLEMS, I WISH IT
COULD BE EITHER OR.
I WISH WE COULD SAY YES,
GO DESTROY ISIS AND LET'S LET
ASSAD CONTINUE TO DESTROY SYRIA,
WHICH CREATES MORE TERRORISTS,
MORE EXTREMISTS BY THE MINUTE.
NO.
WE NOW FINALLY ARE WHERE WE NEED
TO BE.
WE HAVE A STRATEGY AND A
COMMITMENT TO GO AFTER ISIS,
WHICH IS A DANGER TO US AS WELL
AS THE REGION --
>> SECRETARY --
>> -- AND WE FINALLY HAVE A U.N.
SECURITY COUNCIL RESOLUTION
BRINGING THE WORLD TOGETHER TO
GO AFTER A POLITICAL TRANSITION
IN SYRIA.
>> COULD I JUST --
>> IF THE UNITED STATES DOES NOT
LEAD, THERE IS NOT ANOTHER
LEADER.
THERE IS A VACUUM.
AND WE HAVE TO LEAD IF WE'RE
GOING TO BE SUCCESSFUL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> S
GO AHEAD.
SENATOR SANDERS, A LAST WORD ON
THIS.
>> OF COURSE THE UNITED STATES
MUST LEAD.
BUT THE UNITED STATES IS NOT THE
POLICEMAN OF THE WORLD.
THE UNITED STATES MUST NOT BE
INVOLVED IN PERPETUAL WARFARE IN
THE MIDDLE EAST.
THE UNITED STATES AT THE SAME
TIME CANNOT SUCCESSFULLY FIGHT
ASSAD AND ISIS.
ISIS NOW IS THE MAJOR PRIORITY.
LET'S GET RID OF ASSAD LATER.
LET'S HAVE A DEMOCRATIC SYRIA.
BUT THE FIRST TASK IS TO BRING
COUNTRIES TOGETHER TO DESTROY
ISIS.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU.
WHEN WE COME BACK HERE TONIGHT,
THE OTHER MAJOR ISSUES OF THIS
ELECTION.
JOBS, THE ECONOMY, HEALTH CARE.
WHICH CANDIDATES WILL MAKE THE
BEST CASE FOR THE MIDDLE CLASS
AS OUR COVERAGE OF THE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE CONTINUES RIGHT AFTER
THIS ON ABC.
>> Announcer: ABC LIVE COVERAGE
OF THE NEW HAMPSHIRE DEMOCRATIC
DEBATE WILL CONTINUE IN A
MOMENT.
>> Announcer: LIVE FROM SAINT
ANSELM COLLEGE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE,
HERE AGAIN ARE DAVID MUIR AND
MARTHA RADDATZ.
>>> WELCOME BACK TONIGHT.
AS YOU CAN SEE, WE HAVE A PACKED
AUDIENCE HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE,
AND WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE.
WE'VE ALREADY HAD A SPIRITED
CONVERSATION HERE AT THE TOP OF
THE BROADCAST ABOUT ISIS, ABOUT
CONCERNS OF TERROR HERE ON THE
HOME FRONT.
AND AS WE AWAIT SECRETARY
CLINTON SFWAJ HERE, WE'RE GOING
TO BEGIN WITH THE ECONOMY.
WE WANT TO TURN TO AMERICAN
JOBS, WAGES, AND RAISES IN THIS
COUNTRY.
AND DO WE BELIEVE SECRETARY
CLINTON WILL BE COMING AROUND
THE CORNER ANY MINUTE.
BUT IN THE MEANTIME WE WANT TO
START WITH THIS EYE-OPENING
NUMBER.
SENATOR SANDERS, THIS QUESTION
GOES TO YOU FIRST ANYWAY.
IN 1995 THE MEDIAN AMERICAN
HOUSEHOLD INCOME WAS $52,600 IN
TODAY'S MONEY.
THIS YEAR IT'S $53,600.
THAT'S 20 MORE YEARS ON THE JOB
WITH JUST A 2% RAISE.
IN A SIMILAR TIME FRAME RAISES
FOR CEO UP MORE THAN 200%.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SORRY.
>> WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE HERE.
AND SECRETARY, YOU'LL GET A
CHANCE ON THIS TOO.
BUT AS I POINTED OUT, CEO PAY UP
200% IN THAT TIME.
FOR THAT FAMILY UP JUST 2%.
YOU'VE ALL SAID YOU WOULD RAISE
THE MINIMUM WAGE.
BUT SENATOR SANDERS, SPEAK TO
THAT HOUSEHOLD TONIGHT.
20 YEARS, JUST A 2% RAISE.
HOW AS PRESIDENT WOULD YOU GET
THEM A RAISE RIGHT AWAY?
>> FIRST OF ALL, WE RECOGNIZE
THAT WE'VE GOT A RIGGED ECONOMY.
AS YOU'VE INDICATED.
MIDDLE CLASS IN THIS COUNTRY FOR
THE LAST 40 YEARS HAS BEEN
DISAPPEARING.
ARE WE BETTER OFF TODAY THAN WE
WERE WHEN BUSH LEFT OFFICE?
ABSOLUTELY.
BUT AS YOU'VE INDICATED, FOR
MILLIONS OF AMERICAN WORKERS,
PEOPLE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, ALL
OVER AMERICA, THEY'RE WORKING
LONGER HOURS FOR LOW WAGES,
DEEPLY WORRIED ABOUT THEIR KIDS.
SO WHAT DO WE DO?
FIRST STATEMENT WE MAKE IS WE
TELL THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS THEY
CANNOT HAVE IT ALL.
FOR A START.
THEY'RE GOING TO START PAYING
THEIR FAIR SHARE OF TAXES.
SECOND OF ALL IS YOU RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE TO A LIVING WAGE.
15 BUCKS AN HOUR OVER THE NEXT
SEVERAL YEARS.
NEXT THING YOU DO, PAY EQUITY
FOR WOMEN WORKERS.
WOMEN SHOULD NOT BE MAKING 79
CENTS ON THE DOLLAR COMPARED TO
MEN.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NEXT THING THAT WE DO, REAL
UNEMPLOYMENT.
OFFICIAL UNEMPLOYMENT 5%.
REAL UNEMPLOYMENT 10%.
YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT OFF THE
CHARTS.
WE REBUILD OUR CRUMBLING
INFRASTRUCTURE, OUR ROADS, OUR
BRIDGES, OUR RAIL SYSTEM.
WE CREATE 13 MILLION JOBS WITH A
TRILLION-DOLLAR INVESTMENT.
FURTHERMORE, IN A COMPETITIVE
GLOBAL ECONOMY IT IS IMPERATIVE
THAT WE HAVE THE BEST-EDUCATED
WORKFORCE IN THE WORLD.
THAT IS WHY I'M GOING TO HAVE A
TAX ON WALL STREET SPECULATION
TO MAKE CERTAIN THAT PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES IN
AMERICA ARE TUITION-FREE.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, WHAT WOULD
YOU PROPOSE THAT WOULD BE
DIFFERENT?
HOW WOULD YOU GIVE THE MIDDLE
CLASS A RAISE AND WITHOUT
WAITING ANOTHER 20 YEARS FOR
ANOTHER 2%?
>> LOOK, THESE ARE THE THINGS WE
DID IN MY OWN STATE THROUGH THE
RECESSION.
WE ACTUALLY -- WE ACTUALLY
PASSED A LIVING WAGE.
WE RAISED THE MINIMUM WAGE.
WE ACTUALLY RAISED IT TO THE
HIGHEST GOALS OF ANY STATE IN
THE NATION, OUR MINORITY AND
WOMEN PARTICIPATION GOALS.
BECAUSE WE UNDERSTOOD THAT THE
WAY YOU REINVIGORATE AND MAKE
FAIR MARKET AMERICAN CAPITALISM
WORK IS TO MAKE THE CHOICES IN
THE INVESTMENTS THAT INCLUDE
MORE PEOPLE MORE FULLY IN THE
ECONOMIC SUCCESS OF YOUR STATE.
ALL THROUGH THE RECESSION WE
DEFENDED THE HIGHEST MEDIAN
INCOME IN AMERICA AND THE SECOND
HIGHEST MEDIAN INCOME FOR
AFRICAN-AMERICAN FAMILIES.
HOW?
BY ACTUALLY DOING MORE FOR
EDUCATION.
WE INCREASED EDUCATION FUNDING
BY 37%.
WE WERE THE ONLY STATE IN
AMERICA THAT WENT FOUR YEARS IN
A ROW WITHOUT A PENNY'S INCREASE
TO COLLEGE TUITION.
WE INVESTED MORE IN OUR
INFRASTRUCTURE.
AND WE SQUARED OUR SHOULDERS TO
THE GREAT BUSINESS OPPORTUNITY
OF THIS ERA.
AND THAT IS MOVING OUR ECONOMY
TO A 100% CLEAN ELECTRIC ENERGY
FUTURE.
WE CREATED 2,000 NEW JOBS IN THE
SOLAR INDUSTRY.
AND WE FOUGHT EVERY SINGLE DAY
TO ADOPT MORE INCLUSIVE ECONOMIC
PRACTICES.
SO DAVID, THE CONCLUSION OF ALL
OF THOSE THINGS IS THIS.
THEY WEREN'T HOPES, THEY WEREN'T
DREAMS.
THEY WEREN'T AMORPHOUS GOALS OUT
THERE.
WE ACTUALLY TOOK ACTIONS TO DO
THESE THINGS.
AND AS PRESIDENT I HAVE PUT
FORWARD 15 STRATEGIC GOALS THAT
WILL MAKE WAGES GO UP AGAIN FOR
ALL AMERICAN FAMILIES.
UNIVERSAL NATIONAL SERVICE IS AN
OPTION FOR EVERY KID IN AMERICA
TO CUT YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT.
AND I'M THE ONLY CANDIDATE ON
THIS STAGE TO PUT FORWARD A NEW
AGENDA FOR AMERICA'S CITIES SO
WE CAN EMPLOY MORE PEOPLE IN THE
HEART OF GREAT AMERICAN CITIES
AND GET THEM BACK TO WORK.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
SECRETARY CLINTON, AS YOU WERE
WALKING IN I WAS TALKING ABOUT
THE MEDIAN AMERICAN HOUSEHOLD
GETTING A 2% RAISE OVER THE LAST
20 YEARS, THAT CEO PAY IN THAT
SAME TIME FRAME HAS GONE UP
200%.
SO FOR THOSE FAMILIES WATCHING
TONIGHT, HOW DO YOU GET THEM A
RAISE IF YOU'RE PRESIDENT?
>> WELL, I'VE BEEN TALKING TO A
LOT OF THESE FAMILIES, AND THIS
IS SUCH AN OUTRAGE, BOTH BECAUSE
IT'S BAD FOR OUR ECONOMY, WE'RE
A 70% CONSUMPTION ECONOMY,
PEOPLE NEED TO FEEL OPTIMISTIC
AND CONFIDENT, THEY NEED TO
BELIEVE THEIR HARD WORK IS GOING
TO BE REWARDED, AND IT'S BAD FOR
OUR DEMOCRACY.
IT'S ABSOLUTELY THE CASE THAT IF
PEOPLE FEEL THAT THE GAME IS
RIGGED THAT HAS CONSEQUENCES.
I THINK IT'S GREAT STANDING UP
HERE WITH THE SENATOR AND THE
GOVERNOR TALKING ABOUT THESE
ISSUES BECAUSE YOU'RE NOT GOING
TO HEAR ANYTHING LIKE THIS FROM
ANY OF THE REPUBLICANS WHO ARE
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT.
THEY DON'T WANT TO RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE.
THEY DON'T WANT TO DO ANYTHING
TO INCREASE INCOMES.
AT THE CENTER OF MY ECONOMIC
POLICY IS RAISING INCOMES
BECAUSE PEOPLE HAVEN'T BEEN ABLE
TO GET AHEAD AND THE COSTS OF
EVERYTHING, FROM COLLEGE TUITION
TO PRESCRIPTION DRUGS HAS GONE
UP.
OF COURSE WE HAVE TO RAISE THE
MINIMUM WAGE.
OF COURSE WE HAVE TO DO MORE TO
INCENTIVIZE PROFIT SHARING LIKE
WE SEE WITH MARKET BASKET RIGHT
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE AND NEW
ENGLAND, WHERE ALL OF THE BL
EMPLOYEES GET A CHANCE TO SHARE
IN THE PROFITS.
AND WE'VE GOT TO DO MORE ON
EQUAL PAY FOR EQUAL WORK.
THAT MEANS PASS THE PAYCHECK
FAIRNESS ACT SO WE HAVE
TRANSPARENCY ABOUT HOW MUCH
PEOPLE ARE MAKING.
THAT'S THE WAY TO GET WOMEN'S
WAGES UP.
AND THAT'S GOOD FOR THEM AND
GOOD FOR THEIR FAMILIES AND GOOD
FOR OUR COMMUNITIES.
AND THERE IS A LOT WE CAN DO IN
COLLEGE AFFORDABILITY.
I HAVE DEBT-FREE TUITION PLANS,
FREE COMMUNITY COLLEGE PLANS,
GETTING STUDENT DEBT DOWN.
I ALSO AM VERY COMMITTED TO
GETTING THE PRICE OF DRUGS DOWN.
AND THERE'S A LOT.
YOU CAN GO TO MY WEBSITE,
HILLARYCLINTON.COM, AND READ
ABOUT IT.
BUT I GUESS THE FINAL THING I
WOULD SAY IS THIS IS THE KIND OF
DEBATE WE NEED TO TAKE TO THE
REPUBLICANS IN THE FALL.
>> SECRETARY, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> THIS IS THE ELECTION ISSUES
THEY'RE GOING TO HAVE TO RESPOND
TO.
>> WE'RE GOING TO TALK ABOUT
COLLEGE EDUCATION IN A MOMENT.
BUT SECRETARY CLINTON, I DID
WANT TO ASK YOU, THE LAST TIME
YOU RAN FOR PRESIDENT "FORTUNE"
MAGAZINE PUT YOU ON ITS COVER
WITH THE HEADLINE "BUSINESS
LOVES HILLARY," POINTING OUT
YOUR SUPPORT FOR MANY CEOs IN
CORPORATE AMERICA.
I'M CURIOUS, EIGHT YEARS LATER,
SHOULD CORPORATE AMERICA LOVE
HILLARY CLINTON?
>> EVERYBODY SHOULD.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
LOOK, I HAVE SAID, I WANT TO BE
THE PRESIDENT FOR THE
STRUGGLING, THE STRIVING, AND
THE SUCCESSFUL.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE THE WEALTHY
PAY THEIR FAIR SHARE, WHICH THEY
HAVE NOT BEEN DOING.
I WANT THE BUFFETT RULE TO BE IN
EFFECT WHERE MILLIONAIRES HAVE
TO PAY 30% TAX RATES INSTEAD OF
10% TO NOTHING IN SOME CASES.
I WANT TO MAKE SURE WE REIN IN
THE EXCESSIVE USE OF POLITICAL
POWER TO FEATHER THE NEST AND
SUPPORT THE SUPER WEALTHY.
BUT I ALSO WANT TO CREATE JOBS.
AND I WANT TO BE A PARTNER WITH
THE PRIVATE SECTOR.
I'M PARTICULARLY KEEN ON
CREATING JOBS IN SMALL BUSINESS.
MY DAD WAS A SMALL BUSINESSMAN,
A REALLY SMALL BUSINESS.
I WANT TO DO MORE TO HELP
INCENTIVIZE AND CREATE MORE
SMALL BUSINESSES.
SO IF PEOPLE WHO ARE IN THE
PRIVATE SECTOR KNOW WHAT I STAND
FOR, IT'S WHAT I FOUGHT FOR AS A
SENATOR, IT'S WHAT I WILL DO AS
PRESIDENT, AND THEY WANT TO BE
PART OF ONCE AGAIN BUILDING OUR
ECONOMY SO IT WORKS FOR
EVERYBODY, MORE POWER TO THEM.
BECAUSE THEY ARE THE KIND OF
BUSINESS LEADERS WHO UNDERSTAND
THAT IF WE DON'T GET THE
AMERICAN ECONOMY MOVING AND
GROWING WE'RE NOT GOING TO
RECOGNIZE OUR COUNTRY AND WE'RE
NOT GOING TO GIVE OUR KIDS THE
SAME OPPORTUNITIES THAT WE HAD.
>> SECRETARY, THANK YOU.
SENATOR SANDERS, I WANT TO STAY
ON THIS AND ASK YOU HOW BIG A
ROLE DOES CORPORATE AMERICA PLAY
IN A HEALTHY ECONOMY AND WILL
CORPORATE AMERICA LOVE A
PRESIDENT SANDERS?
>> NO, I THINK THEY WON'T.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SO HILLARY AND I HAVE A
DIFFERENCE.
THE CEOs OF LARGE MULTINATIONALS
MAY LIKE HILLARY.
THEY AIN'T GOING TO LIKE ME.
AND WALL STREET IS GOING TO LIKE
ME EVEN LESS.
AND THE REASON FOR THAT IS WE'VE
GOT TO DEAL WITH THE ELEPHANT IN
THE ROOM, WHICH IS THE GREED,
RECKLESSNESS, AND ILLEGAL
BEHAVIOR ON WALL STREET.
WHEN YOU HAVE SIX FINANCIAL
INSTITUTIONS IN THIS COUNTRY
THAT ISSUE 2/3 OF THE CREDIT
CARDS AND 1/3 OF THE MORTGAGES.
WHEN 3 OUT OF 4 OF THEM ARE
LARGER TODAY THAN WHEN WE BAILED
THEM OUT BECAUSE THEY ARE TOO
BIG TO FAIL.
WE'VE GOT TO RE-ESTABLISH
GLASS-STEAGALL.
WE'VE GOT TO BREAK THE LARGE
FINANCIAL INSTITUTIONS UP.
SO I DON'T
THAT, I DON'T THINK I'M GOING TO
GET A WHOLE LOT OF CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS FROM WALL STREET.
I DON'T HAVE A SUPER PAC.
I DON'T WANT CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS FROM CORPORATE
AMERICA.
AND LET ME BE CLEAR.
WHILE THERE ARE SOME GREAT
CORPORATIONS CREATING JOBS AND
TRYING TO DO THE RIGHT THING, IN
MY VIEW, AND I SAY THIS VERY
SERIOUSLY, THE GREED OF THE
BILLIONAIRE CLASS, THE GREED OF
WALL STREET IS DESTROYING THIS
ECONOMY AND IS DESTROYING THE
LIVES OF MILLIONS OF AMERICANS.
WE NEED AN ECONOMY THAT WORKS
FOR THE MIDDLE CLASS, NOT JUST A
HANDFUL OF BILLIONAIRES.
AND I WILL FIGHT AND LEAD TO
MAKE THAT HAPPEN.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
GOVERNOR, LET ME JUST ASK YOU,
BECAUSE IT IS AN IMPORTANT
QUESTION, HOW IMPORTANT A ROLE
DO YOU THINK CORPORATE AMERICA
PLAYS IN A HEALTHY ECONOMY IN
THE U.S.?
>> LOOK, I LOOK AT OUR ECONOMY
AS AN ECOSYSTEM.
AND THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS
THAT THE MORE FULLY PEOPLE
PARTICIPATE THE MORE OUR WORKERS
EARN, THE MORE THEY WILL SPEND.
THE MORE OUR ECONOMY WILL GROW.
AND MOST HEADS OF BUSINESSES,
LARGE, MEDIUM, AND SMALL,
UNDERSTAND THAT.
BUT THERE IS A BETTER WAY
FORWARD THAN EITHER OF THOSE
OFFERED BY MY TWO OPPONENTS HERE
ON THIS STAGE.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO FIX WHAT AILS
OUR ECONOMY.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO MAKE WAGES GO
UP FOR EVERYONE BY EITHER TRYING
TO REPLACE AMERICAN CAPITALISM
WITH SOCIALISM, WHICH BY THE WAY
THE REST OF THE WORLD IS MOVING
AWAY FROM.
NOR WILL WE FIX IT BY SUBMITTING
TO SORT OF WALL STREET-DIRECTED
CRONY CAPITALISM.
AND FOR MY PART I HAVE
DEMONSTRATED THE ABILITY TO HAVE
THE BACKBONE TO TAKE ON WALL
STREET IN WAYS THAT SECRETARY
CLINTON NEVER, EVER HAS.
IN FACT, IN THE LAST DEBATE VERY
SHAMEFULLY SHE TRIED TO HIDE HER
COZY RELATIONSHIP WITH WALL
STREET BIG BANKS BY INVOKING THE
ATTACKS OF 9/11.
I BELIEVE THAT THE WAY FORWARD
FOR OUR COUNTRY IS TO ACTUALLY
REINVIGORATE OUR ANTITRUST
DEPARTMENT WITH THE DIRECTIVE TO
PROMOTE FAIR COMPETITION.
THERE'S MERGERS THAT ARE
HAPPENING IN EVERY ASPECT OF OUR
COUNTRY THAT IS BAD FOR
COMPETITION AND IT'S BAD FOR
UPWARD MOBILITY OF WAGES.
AND THE WORST TYPE OF
CONCENTRATION, SECRETARY
CLINTON, IS THE CONCENTRATION OF
THE BIG BANKS.
THE BIG SIX BANKS THAT YOU WENT
TO AND SPOKE TO AND TOLD THEM
OH, YOU WEREN'T RESPONSIBLE FOR
THE CRASH, NOT BY A LONG SHOT.
AND THAT'S WHY TODAY YOU STILL
CANNOT SUPPORT, AS I DO,
BREAKING UP THE BIG BANKS AND
MAKING SURE THAT WE PASS A
MODERN-DAY GLASS-STEAGALL LIKE
WE HAD IN LATE 1999 BEFORE IT
WAS REPEALED AND LED TO THE
CRASH WHERE SO MANY MILLIONS OF
FAMILIES LOST THEIR JOBS AND
THEIR HOMES.
AND I WAS ON THE FRONT LINES OF
THAT LOOKING INTO THE EYES OF MY
NEIGHBORS --
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY --
>> OKAY.
>> I DO WANT TO ASK YOU,
SECRETARY CLINTON.
LET ME JUST ASK YOU --
>> LET ME RESPOND --
>> WE DID -- SECRETARY CLINTON,
LET ME JUST ASK YOU --
>> LET ME RESPOND VERY QUICKLY.
NUMBER ONE --
>> AND IN PARTICULAR --
>> NUMBER ONE, THERE ARE
CURRENTLY TWO HEDGE FUND
BILLIONAIRES RUNNING ADS AGAINST
ME HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
THEY STARTED IN IOWA.
NOW, YOU'D HAVE TO ASK YOURSELF
WHY ARE THEY RUNNING ADS AGAINST
ME?
AND THE ANSWER IS BECAUSE THEY
KNOW I WILL GO RIGHT AFTER THEM,
THAT I WILL NOT LET THEIR AGENDA
BE AMERICA'S AGENDA.
SECONDLY, I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT
TO POINT OUT THAT ABOUT 3% OF MY
DONATIONS COME FROM PEOPLE IN
THE FINANCE AND INVESTMENT
WORLD.
YOU CAN GO TO OPENSECRETS.ORG
AND CHECK THAT.
I HAVE MORE DONATIONS FROM
STUDENTS AND TEACHERS THAN I DO
FROM PEOPLE ASSOCIATED WITH WALL
STREET.
[ APPLAUSE ]
NOW, NUMBER THREE, AND LET ME
SAY THIS.
WHEN GOVERNOR O'MALLEY WAS
HEADING THE DEMOCRATIC GOVERNORS
ASSOCIATION, HE HAD NO TROUBLE
AT ALL GOING TO WALL STREET TO
RAISE MONEY TO RUN CAMPAIGNS FOR
DEMOCRATIC GOVERNORS.
AND HE ALSO HAD NO TROUBLE
APPOINTING AN INVESTMENT BANKER
TO BE IN CHARGE OF HIS CONSUMER
PROTECTION BUREAU WHEN HE WAS
GOVERNOR.
SO YOU KNOW, AGAIN, THE
DIFFERENCE BETWEEN US AND THE
REPUBLICANS IS NIGHT AND DAY.
AND THERE IS ONLY ONE PERSON ON
THIS STAGE WHO VOTED TO TAKE
AWAY AUTHORITY FROM THE S.E.C.
AND THE COMMODITIES FUTURE
TRADING COMMISSION, THAT THEY
COULD NO LONGER REGULATE WHAT
ARE CALLED SWAPS AND
DERIVATIVES, WHICH ACTUALLY
CONTRIBUTED TO THE COLLAPSE OF
LEHMAN BROTHERS, AND THAT WAS
SENATOR SANDERS.
SO IF WE'RE GOING TO BE TALKING
LIKE THIS, WE CAN, AND MAYBE WE
CAN SCORE SOME POLITICAL POINTS.
BUT THE FACT IS EVERY ONE OF US
STANDS FOR THE KIND OF ECONOMY
THAT WILL WORK BETTER FOR EVERY
AMERICAN.
AND IF THAT MEANS TAKING ON WALL
STREET, I HAVE A PLAN THAT IS
TOUGH AND COMPREHENSIVE AND
PRAISED BY A LOT OF FOLKS WHO
SAY IT GOES FURTHER THAN WHAT
BOTH SENATOR SANDERS AND
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY ARE PROPOSING.
>> LET ME JUST --
[ APPLAUSE ]
LET ME JUST JUMP IN.
MY NAME WAS INVOKED.
>> SENATOR.
>> SO WITH THAT INVOCATION LET
ME SAY A FEW WORDS.
SECRETARY CLINTON, I DON'T HAVE
A SUPER PAC.
I DON'T GET ANY MONEY FROM WALL
STREET.
YOU HAVE GOTTEN A WHOLE LOT OF
MONEY OVER THE YEARS FROM WALL
STREET.
BUT MOST IMPORTANTLY, WHEN YOU
LOOK AT WHAT HAPPENED IN THE
1990s, GO TO BERNIESANDERS.COM.
I'LL ADVERTISE MY WEBSITE AS
WELL.
AND WHAT YOU'LL FIND IS THAT I
LED -- HELPED LEAD THE EFFORT AS
A MEMBER OF THE HOUSE FINANCIAL
COMMITTEE AGAINST ALAN
GREENSPAN, AGAINST A GUY NAMED
BILL CLINTON -- MAYBE YOU KNOW
HIM.
MAYBE YOU DON'T.
AGAINST THE REPUBLICAN
LEADERSHIP, WHO ALL THOUGHT IT
WOULD BE A GREAT IDEA TO MERGE
INVESTMENT BANKS AND COMMERCIAL
BANKS AND LARGE INSURANCE
COMPANIES.
WHAT A BRILLIANT IDEA THAT WOULD
BE.
GO TO YOUTUBE.
FIND OUT WHAT I SAID TO
GREENSPAN.
AT THE END OF THE DAY, IF TEDDY
ROOSEVELT WERE ALIVE TODAY --
AND THE GOVERNMENT MAKES A GOOD
POINT ABOUT TRADE, ANTI-TRADE,
ANTI-MONOPOLY ACTIVITIES.
WALL STREET TODAY HAS TOO MUCH
POLITICAL POWER.
IT HAS TOO MUCH ECONOMIC POWER.
IT TO GET DEREGULATED -- LISTEN
TO THIS.
THEY SPENT $5 BILLION IN
LOBBYING AND CAMPAIGN
CONTRIBUTIONS OVER A TEN-YEAR
PERIOD.
>> SENATOR SANDERS --
>> WALL STREET IS A THREAT TO
THE ECONOMY.
THEY'VE GOT TO BE BROKEN UP.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> AND WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON TO
HEALTH CARE.
SECRETARY CLINTON, THE
DEPARTMENT OF HEALTH AND HUMAN
SERVICES SAYS MORE THAN 17
MILLION AMERICANS WHO ARE NOT
INSURED NOW HAVE HEALTH COVERAGE
BECAUSE OF OBAMACARE.
BUT FOR AMERICANS WHO ALREADY
HAD HEALTH INSURANCE THE COST
HAS GONE UP 27% IN THE LAST FIVE
YEARS WHILE DEDUCTIBLES ARE UP
67%, HEALTH CARE COSTS ARE
RISING FASTER THAN MANY
AMERICANS CAN MANAGE.
WHAT'S BROKEN IN OBAMACARE THAT
NEEDS TO BE FIXED RIGHT NOW, AND
WHAT WOULD YOU DO TO FIX IT?
>> WELL, I WOULD CERTAINLY BUILD
ON THE SUCCESSES OF THE
AFFORDABLE CARE ACT AND WORK TO
FIX SOME OF THE GLITCHES THAT
YOU JUST REFERENCED.
NUMBER ONE, WE DO HAVE MORE
PEOPLE WHO HAVE ACCESS TO HEALTH
CARE.
WE HAVE ENDED THE TERRIBLE
SITUATION THAT PEOPLE WITH
PRE-EXISTING CONDITIONS WERE
FACED WITH WHERE THEY COULDN'T
FIND AT ANY AFFORDABLE PRICE
HEALTH CARE.
WOMEN ARE NOT CHARGED MORE THAN
MEN ANY LONGER FOR OUR HEALTH
INSURANCE.
AND WE KEEP YOUNG PEOPLE ON OUR
POLICIES UNTIL THEY TURN 26.
THOSE ARE ALL REALLY POSITIVE
DEVELOPMENTS.
BUT OUT-OF-POCKET COSTS HAVE
GONE UP TOO MUCH AND
PRESCRIPTION DRUG COSTS HAVE
GONE THROUGH THE ROOF.
AND SO WHAT I HAVE PROPOSED,
NUMBER ONE, IS A $5,000 TAX
CREDIT TO HELP PEOPLE WHO HAVE
VERY LARGE OUT-OF-POCKET COSTS
BE ABLE TO AFFORD THOSE.
NUMBER TWO, I WANT MEDICARE TO
BE ABLE TO NEGOTIATE FOR LOWER
DRUG PRICES JUST LIKE THEY
NEGOTIATE WITH OTHER COUNTRIES'
HEALTH SYSTEMS.
WE END UP PAYING THE HIGHEST
PRICES IN THE WORLD.
AND I WANT US TO BE ABSOLUTELY
CLEAR ABOUT MAKING SURE THE
INSURANCE COMPANIES IN THE
PRIVATE EMPLOYER POLICY ARENA AS
WELL AS IN THE AFFORDABLE CARE
EXCHANGES ARE PROPERLY REGULATED
SO THAT WE ARE NOT BEING GAMED.
AND I THINK THAT'S AN IMPORTANT
POINT TO MAKE BECAUSE I'M GOING
THROUGH AND ANALYZING THE POINTS
YOU WERE MAKING, MARTHA.
WE DON'T HAVE ENOUGH COMPETITION
AND WE DON'T HAVE ENOUGH
OVERSIGHT OF WHAT THE INSURANCE
COMPANIES ARE CHARGING EVERYBODY
RIGHT NOW.
>> BUT YOU DID SAY THOSE WERE
GLITCHES.
>> YES.
>> JUST GLITCHES?
>> WELL, THEY'RE GLITCHES
BECAUSE --
>> 27% IN THE LAST FIVE YEARS,
DEDUCTIBLES UP 67%?
>> IT IS.
BECAUSE PART OF THIS IS THE
STARTUP CHALLENGES THAT THIS
SYSTEM IS FACING.
WE HAVE FOUGHT AS DEMOCRATS FOR
DECADES TO GET A HEALTH CARE
PLAN.
I KNOW.
I'VE GOT THE SCARS TO SHOW FROM
THE EFFORT BACK IN THE EARLY
'90s.
WE WANT TO BUILD ON IT AND FIX
IT.
AND I'M CONFIDENT WE CAN DO
THAT.
AND IT WILL HAVE EFFECTS IN THE
PRIVATE MARKET.
AND ONE OF THE REASONS IN SOME
STATES WHY THE PERCENTAGE COST
HAS GONE UP SO MUCH IS BECAUSE
GOVERNORS THERE WOULD NOT EXTEND
MEDICAID.
AND SO PEOPLE ARE STILL GOING TO
GET HEALTH CARE, THANKFULLY, IN
EMERGENCY ROOMS, IN HOSPITALS.
THOSE COSTS ARE THEN ADDED TO
THE OVERALL COST, WHICH DOES
INCREASE THE INSURANCE PREMIUMS
FOR PEOPLE IN THE PRIVATE
SYSTEM.
>> I WAS ON THE COMMITTEE --
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I WANT YOU
TO RESPOND TO WHAT SHE WAS
SAYING, BUT YOU'RE INSTEAD
CALLING FOR SINGLE PAYER HEALTH
CARE.
>> EXACTLY.
>> PEOPLE WON'T HAVE TO PAY
DEDUCTIBLES OR PREMIUMS BUT THEY
WILL HAVE TO PAY NEW TAXES.
WITH Y
CAN YOU TELL US SPECIFICALLY HOW
MUCH PEOPLE WILL BE EXPECTED TO
PAY?
>> LET ME SAY THIS.
AS A MEMBER OF THE HEALTH
EDUCATION COMMITTEE THAT HELPED
WRITE THE AFFORDABLE HEALTH CARE
ACT, MUCH OF WHAT SECRETARY
CLINTON SAID BENDING THE
OBSCENITY OF THE PRE-EXISTING
SITUATION IS A STEP FORWARD.
17 MILLION MORE PEOPLE HAVE
HEALTH CARE.
IT IS A STEP FORWARD.
BUT THIS IS WHAT WE ALSO HAVE TO
SAY.
NOT ONLY ARE DEDUCTIBLES RISING,
29 MILLION AMERICANS STILL HAVE
NO HEALTH INSURANCE AND MILLIONS
OF PEOPLE CAN'T AFFORD TO GO TO
THE DOCTOR.
MAJOR CRISIS AND PRIMARY HEALTH
CARE.
HERE IS THE BOTTOM LINE.
WHY IS IT THAT THE UNITED STATES
OF AMERICA TODAY IS THE ONLY
MAJOR COUNTRY ON EARTH THAT DOES
NOT GUARANTEE HEALTH CARE TO ALL
PEOPLE AS A RIGHT?
WHY IS IT --
[ APPLAUSE ]
WHY IS IT THAT WE ARE -- WHY IS
IT THAT WE SPEND ALMOST THREE
TIMES PER CAPITA AS
SPEND IN THE U.K.?
50% MORE THAN WHAT THEY PAY IN
FRANCE.
COUNTRIES THAT GUARANTEE HEALTH
TO ALL OF THEIR PEOPLE AND IN
MANY CASES HAVE BETTER HEALTH
CARE OUTCOMES.
BOTTOM LINE, THIS TIES INTO
CAMPAIGN FINANCE REFORM.
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES, THE
DRUG COMPANIES ARE BRIBING THE
UNITED STATES CONGRESS.
WE NEED TO PASS A MEDICARE FOR
ALL SINGLE PAYER SYSTEM.
IT WILL LOWER THE COST OF HEALTH
CARE FOR A MIDDLE-CLASS FAMILY
BY THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS A YEAR.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, YOU DIDN'T
REALLY TELL US SPECIFICALLY HOW
MUCH PEOPLE WILL BE EXPECTED TO
PAY --
>> BUT THEY WILL NOT BE PAYING,
MARTHA, ANY PRIVATE INSURANCE.
SO IT'S UNFAIR TO SAY IN
TOTAL --
>> BUT YOU CAN'T TELL US
SPECIFICALLY --
>> YOU ARE ADDING UP THE FACT
YOU'RE NOT PAYING ANY PRIVATE
INSURANCE, BUSINESSES ARE NOT
PAYING ANY PRIVATE INSURANCE.
THE AVERAGE MIDDLE-CLASS FAMILY
WILL BE SAVING THOUSANDS OF
DOLLARS A YEAR.
>> OKAY.
LET'S GO TO TALK ABOUT THE HIGH
COST OF COLLEGE EDUCATION AND
FOR THAT WE TURN TO THE
EXECUTIVE DIRECTOR OF THE NEW
HAMPSHIRE INSTITUTE OF POLITICS,
RIGHT HERE
COLLEGE, NEIL LEVESQUE.
>> THIS AUDITORIUM IS FILLED
WITH MANY SAINT ANSELM COM
STUDENTS.
THEY KNOW THE OUTSTANDING
STUDENT DEBT RIGHT NOW IN
AMERICA IS $1.3 TRILLION, THAT
PRIVATE EDUCATION COSTS HAVE
GONE UP IN THE LAST DECADE 26%
AND 40% MORE PUBLIC EDUCATION.
KNOWING THAT, WE KNOW YOU WANT
TO MAKE PUBLIC EDUCATION MORE
AFFORDABLE BUT HOW DO YOU REALLY
LOWER THE COST?
SENATOR SANDERS, YOU MENTIONED A
FEW MINUTES AGO THAT YOU WANT
FREE TUITION FOR PUBLIC
COLLEGES.
>> AND UNIVERSITIES.
>> HOW DOES THAT REALLY LOWER
THE COST OTHER THAN JUST
SHIFTING THE COST TO TAXPAYERS?
>> NEIL, I THINK WE'VE GOT TO
WORK ON A TWO-PRONGED APPROACH.
AND YOUR POINT IS ABSOLUTELY
WELL TAKEN.
THE COST OF COLLEGE EDUCATION IS
ESCALATING A LOT FASTER THAN THE
COST OF INFLATION.
THERE ARE A LOT OF FACTORS
INVOLVED IN THAT.
AND THAT IS THAT WE HAVE SOME
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES THAT
ARE SPENDING A HUGE AMOUNT OF
MONEY ON FANCY DORMITORIES AND
ON GIANT FOOTBALL STADIUMS.
MAYBE WE SHOULD FOCUS ON QUALITY
EDUCATION WITH WELL-PAID FACULTY
MEMBERS.
BUT --
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I UNDERSTAND IN MANY
UNIVERSITIES A HECK OF A LOT OF
VICE PRESIDENTS WHO EARN A BIG
SALARY.
BUT BOTTOM LINE IS THIS IS THE
YEAR 2015.
IF WE ARE GOING TO BE
COMPETITIVE IN THE GLOBAL
ECONOMY WE NEED THE BEST
EDUCATED WORKFORCE.
IT IS INSANE TO MY MIND,
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF YOUNG
PEOPLE TODAY, BRIGHT QUALIFIED
PEOPLE CANNOT GO TO COLLEGE
BECAUSE THEY CANNOT AFFORD,
THEIR FAMILIES CANNOT AFFORD TO
SEND THEM.
MILLIONS COMING OUT OF SCHOOL AS
YOU INDICATED DEEPLY IN DEBT.
WHAT DO WE DO?
MY PROPOSAL IS TO PUT A
SPECULATION TAX ON WALL STREET,
RAISE VERY SUBSTANTIAL SUMS OF
MONEY, NOT ONLY MAKE PUBLIC
COLLEGES AND UNIVERSITIES
TUITION-FREE BUT ALSO
SUBSTANTIALLY LOWER INTEREST
RATES ON STUDENT DEBT.
YOU HAVE FAMILIES OUT THERE
PAYING 6%, 8%, 10% ON STUDENT
DEBT, REFINANCE THEIR HOMES AT
3%.
WHAT SENSE IS THAT?
SO I THINK WE NEED RADICAL
CHANGES IN THE FUNDING OF HIGHER
EDUCATION.
WE SHOULD LOOK AT COLLEGE TODAY
THE WAY HIGH SCHOOL WAS LOOKED
AT 60 YEARS AGO.
ALL YOUNG PEOPLE WHO HAVE THE
ABILITY SHOULD BE ABLE TO GET A
COLLEGE EDUCATION.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, HOW DO YOU
PROPOSE -- GOVERNOR O'MALLEY,
HOW DO YOU PROPOSE LOWERING SOME
OF THESE COSTS ASSOCIATED WITH
HIGHER EDUCATION?
>> THIS ONE FALLS UNDER THE
CATEGORY OF I HAVE ACTUALLY DONE
THIS.
AS THE GOVERNOR WE ACTUALLY MADE
THE GREATER INVESTMENTS SO THAT
WE COULD GO FOUR YEARS IN A ROW
WITHOUT A PENNY'S INCREASE TO
COLLEGE TUITION.
MY PLAN ACTUALLY GOES FURTHER
THAN SENATOR SANDERS BECAUSE A
BIG CHUNK OF THE COST IS
ACTUALLY ROOM AND BOARD AND
BOOKS AND FEES.
SO AS A NATION WE NEED TO
INCREASE WHAT WE INVEST IN PELL
GRANTS.
YES, WE NEED TO MAKE IT EASIER
FOR PARENTS TO REFINANCE.
BUT STATES NEED TO DO MORE AS
WELL.
AND I PROPOSE A BLOCK GRANT
PROGRAM THAT WILL KEEP THE
STATES IN THE GAME AS WELL.
I BELIEVE THAT ALL OF OUR KIDS
SHOULD GO INTO AN INCOME-BASED
REPAYMENT PLAN.
I'M JOINED TONIGHT BY MY TWO
DAUGHTERS, TARA AND GRACE.
MY OLDEST DAUGHTER'S A TEACHER.
THEIR MOTHER'S HERE AS WELL.
WE WERE PROUD OF THEM ON
GRADUATION DAY, WEREN'T WE,
KATIE, AND WE'RE GOING TO BE
PROUD FOR THE REST OF OUR LIVES.
WE HAD TO BORROW SO MUCH MONEY
TO SEND THEM TO COLLEGE.
AND WE'RE NOT THE ONLY ONES.
THERE ARE FAMILIES ALL ACROSS
AMERICA WHO AREN'T ABLE TO
CONTRIBUTE TO OUR ECONOMY
BECAUSE OF THIS CRUSHING STUDENT
LOAN.
I ALSO PROPOSE THAT WE CAN PAY
FOR THIS WITH A TAX ON
HIGH-VOLUME TRADES, AND WE NEED
TO BECAUSE MY DAD WENT TO
COLLEGE AFTER COMING BACK FROM
WORLD WAR II ON A G.I. BILL BUT
TODAY WE'RE THE ONLY NATION ON
THE PLANET THAT'S SADDLING OUR
KIDS WITH A LIFETIME OF BILLS.
THAT'S A DRAG ON THE ECONOMY.
IT'S ONE OF THE KEY INVESTMENTS
WE NEED TO MAKE.
I WAS FLATTERED THAT SECRETARY
CLINTON TWO MONTHS LATER
BORROWED SO MANY OF MY PROPOSALS
TO INCORPORATE INTO HERS.
AND IN OUR PARTY UNLIKE THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY WE ACTUALLY
BELIEVE THAT THE MORE OUR PEOPLE
LEARN THE MORE THEY WILL EARN
AND HIGHER EDUCATION SHOULD BE A
RIGHT FOR EVERY KID.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
[ APPLAUSE ]
SECRETARY CLINTON, HOW DOES YOUR
PLAN DIFFERENTIATE FROM YOUR
OPPONENTS'?
>> I HAVE WHAT I CALL THE NEW
COLLEGE COMPACT BECAUSE I THINK
EVERYBODY HAS TO HAVE SOME SKIN
IN THIS GAME, NEIL.
NUMBER ONE, STATES HAVE BEEN
DISINVESTING IN HIGHER
EDUCATION.
IN FACT, I THINK NEW HAMPSHIRE
IN-STATE TUITITION FOR PUBLIC
COLLEGE AND UNIVERSITY IS AMONG
THE HIGHEST IF NOT THE HIGHEST
IN THE COUNTRY.
SO STATES OVER A PERIOD OF
DECADES HAVE PUT THEIR MONEY
ELSEWHERE, INTO PRISONS, INTO
HIGHWAYS, INTO THINGS OTHER THAN
HIGHER EDUCATION.
SO UNDER MY COMPACT THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT WILL MATCH MONEY THAT
THE STATES BEGIN TO PUT BACK IN
TO THE HIGHER EDUCATION SYSTEM.
SECONDLY, I DON'T BELIEVE IN
FREE TUITION FOR EVERYBODY.
I BELIEVE WE SHOULD FOCUS ON
MIDDLE-CLASS FAMILIES, WORKING
FAMILIES AND POOR KIDS WHO HAVE
THE AMBITION AND THE TALENT TO
GO TO COLLEGE AND GET AHEAD.
SO I HAVE PROPOSED DEBT-FREE
TUITION, WHICH I THINK IS
AFFORDABLE, AND I WOULD MOVE A
LOT OF THE PELL GRANT AND OTHER
AID INTO THE ARENA WHERE IT
COULD BE USED FOR LIVING
EXPENSES.
SO I'VE PUT ALL THIS TOGETHER.
AGAIN ON MY WEBSITE.
AND I'M PLEASE THED THAT I'VE
GOTTEN SUCH A GOOD RESPONSE.
I WANT TO QUICKLY SAY THAT ONE
OF THE AREAS SENATOR SANDERS
TOUCHED ON IN TALKING ABOUT
EDUCATION AND CERTAINLY TALKING
ABOUT HEALTH CARE IS HIS
COMMITMENT TO REALLY CHANGING
THE SYSTEMS.
FREE COLLEGE, A SINGLE PAYER
SYSTEM FOR HEALTH CARE.
AND IT'S BEEN ESTIMATED WE'RE
LOOKING AT 18 TO 20 TRILLION
DOLLARS, ABOUT A 40% INCREASE IN
THE FEDERAL BUDGET.
AND I HAVE LOOKED AT HIS
PROPOSED PLANS FOR HEALTH CARE,
FOR EXAMPLE.
AND IT REALLY DOES TRANSFER
EVERY BIT OF OUR HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM INCLUDING PRIVATE HEALTH
CARE TO THE STATES TO HAVE THE
STATES RUN.
AND I THINK WE'VE GOT TO BE
REALLY THOUGHTFUL ABOUT HOW
WE'RE GOING TO AFFORD WHAT WE
PROPOSE, WHICH IS WHY EVERYTHING
THAT I HAVE PROPOSED I WILL TELL
YOU EXACTLY HOW I'M GOING TO PAY
FOR IT INCLUDING COLLEGE.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THANK YOU.
>> CAN I RESPOND --
>> BACK TO YOU, DAVID.
>> WE'RE GOING TO GET RIGHT INTO
THIS, SENATOR, BECAUSE WE'RE
GOING TO ASK ABOUT TAXES NEXT.
>> MY NAME WAS --
>> SHE WAS ASKING ABOUT THAT.
>> BUT SECRETARY CLINTON IS
WRONG.
AS YOU KNOW.
BECAUSE I KNOW YOU KNOW A LOT
ABOUT HEALTH CARE.
YOU KNOW THAT THE UNITED STATES
PER CAPITA PAYS FAR AND AWAY
MORE THAN ANY OTHER COUNTRY.
AND IT IS UNFAIR TO SAY SIMPLY
HOW MUCH MORE THE PROGRAM WILL
COST WITHOUT MAKING SURE THAT
PEOPLE KNOW WE ARE DOING AWAY
WITH THE COST OF PRIVATE
INSURANCE AND THAT THE MIDDLE
CLASS WILL BE PAYING
SUBSTANTIALLY LESS FOR HEALTH
CARE UNDER SINGLE PAYER THAN
UNDER SECRETARY CLINTON'S
PROPOSAL.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> WELL, THE ONLY THING I --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, HOLD ON
ONE MOMENT.
SENATOR SANDERS --
>> PROPOSALS GO AND SEND --
>> I WANT TO ASK -- SECRETARY
CLINTON, PLEASE.
>> MY ANALYSIS IS THAT YOU ARE
GOING TO HAVE TO GET MORE TAXES
OUT OF MIDDLE-CLASS FAMILIES.
I'M THE ONLY --
>> SO LET'S ASK ABOUT THAT.
SECRETARY CLINTON, LET'S TURN TO
TAXES.
>> NO MIDDLE CLASS TAX RAISES.
>> WHICH IS WHERE WE'RE GOING
NEXT.
WE'RE GOING TO TAXES HERE.
>> NOW THIS IS GETTING TO BE
FUN.
>> THIS IS FUN.
THIS IS DEMOCRACY AT WORK.
AND SECRETARY CLINTON, LET ME
ASK YOU ABOUT YOUR TAX PLAN
BECAUSE FROM THE CRUSHING COST
OF COLLEGE EDUCATION THE NEXT
QUESTION MOST FAMILIES HAVE IS
WILL MY TAXES GO UP UNDER THE
NEXT PRESIDENT?
YOU HAVE SAID IT'S YOUR GOAL NOT
TO RAISE TAXES ON FAMILIES
MAKING UNDER $250,000 A YEAR, A
GOAL, BUT CAN YOU SAY THAT'S A
PROMISE AS YOU STAND HERE
TONIGHT?
>> THAT IS A PLEDGE THAT I'M
MAKING --
>> A PROMISE?
>> -- WHEN I RAN IN 2008.
YES.
AND IT WAS THE SAME ONE THAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA MADE.
BECAUSE I DON'T THINK WE SHOULD
BE IMPOSING NEW BIG PROGRAMS
THAT ARE GOING TO RAISE
MIDDLE-CLASS FAMILIES' TAXES.
WE JUST HEARD THAT MOST FAMILIES
HAVEN'T HAD A WAGE INCREASE
SINCE 2001.
SINCE, YOU KNOW, THE END OF THE
LAST CLINTON ADMINISTRATION WHEN
INCOMES DID GO UP FOR EVERYBODY.
AND WE'VE GOT TO GET BACK TO
WHERE PEOPLE CAN SAVE MONEY
AGAIN, WHERE THEY CAN INVEST IN
THEIR FAMILIES, AND I DON'T
THINK A MIDDLE-CLASS TAX SHOULD
BE PART OF ANYBODY'S PLAN RIGHT
NOW.
>> LET ME RESPOND --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON --
>> PLEASE.
>> NUMBER ONE, MOST IMPORTANT
ECONOMIC REALITY OF TODAY IS
THAT OVER THE LAST 30 YEARS
THERE HAS BEEN A TRANSFER OF
TRILLIONS OF DOLLARS FROM THE
MIDDLE CLASS TO THE TOP 1/10 OF
1% WHO ARE SEEING A DOUBLING OF
THE PERCENTAGE OF WEALTH THAT
THEY OWN.
NOW, WHEN SECRETARY CLINTON SAYS
I'M NOT GOING RAISE TAXES ON THE
MIDDLE CLASS, LET ME TELL YOU
WHAT SHE IS SAYING.
SHE IS DISAGREEING WITH FDR AND
SOCIAL SECURITY, LBJ ON
MEDICARE, AND WITH THE VAST
MAJORITY OF PROGRESSIVE
DEMOCRATS IN THE HOUSE AND THE
SENATE WHO TODAY ARE FIGHTING TO
END THE DISGRACE OF THE UNITED
STATES BEING THE ONLY MAJOR
COUNTRY ON EARTH THAT DOESN'T
PROVIDE PAID FAMILY AND MEDICAL
LEAVE.
WHAT THE LEGISLATION IS IS $1.61
A WEEK.
NOW, YOU CAN SAY THAT'S A TAX ON
THE MIDDLE CLASS.
IT WILL PROVIDE THREE MONTHS
PAID FAMILY AND MEDICAL LEAVE
FOR THE WORKING FAMILIES OF THIS
COUNTRY.
I THINK SECRETARY CLINTON A BUCK
61 A WEEK IS A PRETTY GOOD
INVEST.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
LET ME BRING IN GOVERNOR
O'MALLEY.
>> I HAVE BEEN FOR PAID FAMILY
LEAVE --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> DAVID, THANK YOU.
>> I HAVE A WAY TO PAY FOR IT
THAT ACTUALLY MAKES THE
WEALTHIEST PAY FOR IT.
NOT EVERYBODY ELSE.
>> EVERY DEMOCRAT AND SENATOR IS
IN SUPPORT OF THIS PROPOSAL
INTRODUCED BY YOUR GOOD FRIEND
AND MY GOOD FRIEND, KRISTEN
GILLIBRGI
GILLIBR
GILLIBRAND.
THAT IS THE LEGISLATION OUT
THERE THAT WILL PROVIDE FAMILY
AND MEDICAL LEAVE.
>> WE HEARD THE PROMISE FROM
SECRETARY CLINTON BECAUSE PEOPLE
WANT TO KNOW ABOUT THEIR TAX,
WILL THEY GO UP.
SHE HAS PROMISED HERE TONIGHT
NOT TO RAISE THEM ON FAMILIES
MAKING 250,000 OR LESS.
CAN YOU MAKE THAT SAME PROMISE
IF YOU'RE ELECTED --
>> NO, I'VE NEVER MADE A PROMISE
LIKE THAT.
BUT UNLIKE EITHER OF THESE TWO
FINE PEOPLE I'VE ACTUALLY
BALANCED A BUDGET EVERY SINGLE
YEAR.
I WAS ONE OF ONLY SEVEN STATES
THAT HAD A AAA BOND RATING.
AT THE TIME I LEFT THE AVERAGE
TAX BURDEN ON MARYLAND FAMILIES
WAS THE SAME AS WHEN I STARTED.
BUT I DID PASS A MORE
PROGRESSIVE INCOME TAX AND ASKED
THE HIGHEST-EARNING PEOPLE TO
PAY ANOTHER 14%.
DAVID, THIS IS THE BIG -- I
AGREE, BY THE WAY, THAT WE
SHOULD HAVE PAID FAMILY LEAVE.
AND I AGREE WITH SENATOR SANDERS
ON THAT.
AND JUST LIKE SOCIAL SECURITY
AND UNLIKE THE REPUBLICANS I
THINK WE SHOULD ACTUALLY EXPAND
SOCIAL SECURITY AND INCREASE
AVERAGE MONTHLY BENEFITS.
BUT LOOK, THERE'S ONE BIG
ENTITLEMENT WE CAN NO LONGER
AFFORD AS A COUNTRY.
AND THAT IS THE ENTITLEMENT THAT
THE SUPER WEALTHY AMONG US,
THOSE EARNING MORE THAN A
MILLION DOLLARS, FEEL THAT
THEY'RE ENTITLED TO PAY LOWER
INCOME TAX RATES AND A FAR LOWER
PREFERRED INCOME TAX RATE WHEN
IT COMES TO CAPITAL GAINS.
IF WE WERE TO RAISE THE MARGINAL
RATE TO 45% FOR PEOPLE EARNING
MORE THAN A MILLION DOLLARS AND
IF WE TAX CAPITAL GAINS
ESSENTIALLY THE SAME WE DO
EARNINGS FROM HARD WORK AND
SWEAT AND TOIL, YOU COULD
GENERATE $800 BILLION OVER THE
NEXT TEN YEARS AND THAT WOULD DO
SO MUCH GOOD FOR AFFORDABLE
COLLEGE, DEBT-FREE COLLEGE,
CUTTING YOUTH UNEMPLOYMENT IN
HALF, INVESTING IN OUR CITIES
AGAIN.
SO THE THINGS I HAVE DONE IN
OFFICE ARE THE THINGS THAT
ACTUALLY INVEST IN GROWING OUR
ECONOMY AND MAKING WAGES GO UP.
THAT'S THE ISSUE WE NEED TO
TACKLE AS AMERICANS, AND WE CAN
DO IT AND WE KNOW HOW.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, THANK YOU.
A SPIRITED DEBATE ON TAXES.
AND THERE WILL BE MUCH MORE OF
THE DEMOCRATIC DEBATE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE WHEN WE COME BACK
RIGHT HERE ON ABC.
MORE IN A MOMENT.
>> Announcer: ABC NEWS LIVE
COVERAGE OF THE NEW HAMPSHIRE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE WILL CONTINUE
IN A MOMENT.
>>> WELCOME BACK TONIGHT TO NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
THE DEMOCRATIC DEBATE CONTINUES
HERE ON ABC.
AND SECRETARY CLINTON, WE WANT
TO TURN TO RACE NOW IN AMERICA.
THERE IS A REAL CONCERN IN THIS
COUNTRY FROM BLACK LIVES MATTER
AND FROM OTHER COMMUNITY GROUPS
THAT WE'RE JUST NOW SEEING WITH
SMARTPHONES AND CELL PHONES WHAT
MANY HAVE BEEN DEALING WITH FOR
YEARS WHEN THEY COME IN CONTACT
WITH POLICE.
BUT YOU ALSO HAVE MANY IN LAW
ENFORCEMENT WHO NOW SAY THERE'S
BEEN A SO-CALLED FERGUSON
EFFECT, POLICE HOLDING BACK
BECAUSE THEY'RE AFRAID OF
BACKLASH.
IN FACT, THE FBI DIRECTOR
CALLING IT A CHILL WIND BLOWING
THROUGH AMERICAN LAW
ENFORCEMENT.
SO IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, HOW
WOULD YOU BRIDGE THE DIVIDE
BETWEEN THE TWO?
>> WELL, DAVID, I THINK THIS IS
ONE OF THE MOST IMPORTANT
CHALLENGES FACING NOT JUST OUR
NEXT PRESIDENT BUT OUR COUNTRY.
WE HAVE SYSTEMIC RACISM AND
INJUSTICE AND INEQUITIES IN OUR
COUNTRY AND IN PARTICULAR IN OUR
JUSTICE SYSTEM THAT MUST BE
ADDRESSED AND MUST BE ENDED.
I FEEL VERY STRONGLY THAT WE
HAVE TO REFORM OUR CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM AND WE HAVE TO
FIND WAYS TO TRY TO BRING LAW
ENFORCEMENT TOGETHER AGAIN WITH
THE COMMUNITIES THAT THEY ARE
SWORN TO PROTECT.
TRUST HAS BEEN TOTALLY LOST IN A
LOT OF PLACES.
AT THE SAME TIME WE KNOW THAT IN
MANY PARTS OF OUR COUNTRY POLICE
OFFICERS ARE BRIDGING THOSE
DIVIDES AND THEY'RE ACTING
HEROICALLY.
THE YOUNG OFFICER WHO WAS KILLED
RESPONDING TO THE PLANNED
PARENTHOOD MURDERS.
THE OFFICER WHO TOLD THE VICTIMS
OF THE SAN BERNARDINO KILLINGS
THAT HE WOULD TAKE A BULLET
BEFORE THEM.
SO I THINK THAT WE NEED TO BUILD
ON THE WORK OF THE POLICING
COMMISSIONER THAT PRESIDENT
OBAMA IMPANELED.
WE NEED TO GET A BIPARTISAN
COMMITMENT TO WORK TOGETHER ON
THIS.
AND WE NEED TO HEAR THE VOICES
OF THOSE MEN AND WOMEN AND BOYS
AND GIRLS WHO FEEL LIKE
STRANGERS IN THEIR OWN COUNTRY
AND DO WHATEVER IS NECESSARY TO
NOT ONLY DEAL WITH THE IMMEDIATE
PROBLEMS WITHIN THE CRIMINAL
JUSTICE SYSTEM BUT MORE
OPPORTUNITIES, MORE JOBS, BETTER
EDUCATION SO THAT WE CAN BEGIN
TO REBUILD THAT VERY VALUABLE
ASSET KNOWN AS TRUST.
>> SECRETARY, THANK
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, HOW WOULD YOU
BRIDGE THE DIVIDE?
>> THERE IS NO ISSUE IN AMERICAN
PUBLIC POLICY THAT I HAVE WORKED
ON MORE DAY IN AND DAY OUT THAN
THIS PAINFUL ISSUE OF POLICING,
OF LAW ENFORCEMENT, CRIMINAL
JUSTICE AND RACE IN AMERICA.
WHEN I RAN IN 1999, DAVID, FOR
MAYOR OF BALTIMORE, OUR CITY BY
THAT YEAR HAD BECOME THE MOST
ADDICTED, VIOLENT, AND ABANDONED
IN AMERICA.
BUT WE CAME TOGETHER.
I BROUGHT PEOPLE TOGETHER OVER
SOME VERY DEEP RACIAL DIVIDES.
AND WE WERE ABLE TO PUT OUR CITY
ON THE PATH FOR THE BIGGEST
REDUCTION IN CRIME OF ANY MAJOR
CITY IN AMERICA OVER THE NEXT
TEN YEARS.
AS GOVERNOR WE CONTINUED TO WORK
TOGETHER.
WE REDUCED VIOLENT CRIME TO
30-YEAR LOWS.
BUT GET THIS.
WE ALSO REDUCED INCARCERATION
RATES TO 20-YEAR LOWS.
SO IT IS POSSIBLE ACTUALLY TO
FIND THE THINGS THAT ACTUALLY
WORK, THAT WE DID, INCREASING
DRUG TREATMENT, USING BIG DATA
TO BETTER PROTECT THE LIVES OF
YOUNG PEOPLE, CUT JUVENILE CRIME
IN HALF, AND IT'S ALSO POSSIBLE
TO IMPROVE HOW WE POLICE OUR
POLICE.
BUT THERE WASN'T A SINGLE DAY AS
MAYOR OF BALTIMORE THAT I WASN'T
ASKED WHETHER I WAS DELIVERING
ON THE PROMISE I MADE TO POLICE
THE POLICE.
WE REPORTED EXCESSIVE FORCE,
DISCOURTESY, USE OF LETHAL
FORCE.
IN FACT DROVE DOWN TO THREE OF
THE FOUR LOWEST YEARS ON RECORD
POLICE USE OF LETHAL FORCE.
AS A NATION WE HAVE TO EMBRACE
THIS MOMENT AND MAKE OUR
DEPARTMENTS MORE OPEN, MORE
TRANSPARENT, AND MORE
ACCOUNTABLE.
JUST AS WE REQUIRE EVERY MAJOR
DEPARTMENT, EVERY COUNTY TO
REPORT ITS MAJOR CRIMES, WE
SHOULD REQUIRE POLICE
DEPARTMENTS TO REPORT THEIR
DISCOURTESY, BRUTALITY,
EXCESSIVE FORCE.
THERE'S SO MUCH WORK THAT CAN BE
DONE, SO MUCH WE'VE LEARNED TO
DO BETTER.
WE NEED TO DO IT NOW AS A
NATION.
THIS IS OUR TIME AND OUR
OPPORTUNITY TO DO THAT.
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
AND SENATOR SANDERS, WHEN YOU
HEAR THE FBI DIRECTOR CALLING IT
A CHILL WIND BLOWING THROUGH
AMERICAN LAW ENFORCEMENT, DOES
THAT CONCERN YOU AS WELL WHEN
YOU --
>> WELL, THIS WHOLE ISSUE
CONCERNS ME.
AND I AGREE WITH MUCH OF WHAT
THE SECRETARY AND THE GOVERNOR
HAVE SAID.
BUT LET'S BE CLEAR.
TODAY IN AMERICA WE HAVE MORE
PEOPLE IN JAIL THAN ANY OTHER
COUNTRY ON EARTH.
2.2 MILLION PEOPLE.
PREDOMINANTLY AFRICAN-AMERICAN
AND HISPANIC.
WE ARE SPENDING $80 BILLION A
YEAR LOCKING UP OUR FELLOW
AMERICANS.
I THINK, AND THIS IS NOT EASY,
BUT I THINK WE NEED TO MAKE WAGE
A MAJOR EFFORT, TO COME TOGETHER
AS A COUNTRY AND END
INSTITUTIONAL RACISM.
WE NEED MAJOR, MAJOR REFORMS OF
A VERY BROKEN CRIMINAL JUSTICE
SYSTEM.
NOW, WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?
WELL, FOR A START IT MEANS THAT
POLICE OFFICERS SHOULD NOT BE
SHOOTING UNARMED PEOPLE,
PREDOMINANTLY AFRICAN-AMERICANS.
[ APPLAUSE ]
IT MEANS THAT WE HAVE TO RETHINK
THE SO-CALLED WAR ON DRUGS WHICH
HAS DESTROYED THE LIVES OF
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE, WHICH IS WHY
I HAVE TAKEN MARIJUANA OUT OF
THE CONTROLLED SUBSTANCE ACT.
SO THAT IT WILL NOT BE A FEDERAL
CRIME.
THAT IS WHY WE NEED TO MAKE --
[ APPLAUSE ]
THAT IS WHY WE NEED TO MAKE
POLICE -- AND I SPEAK AS A
FORMER MAYOR.
I WAS A MAYOR FOR EIGHT YEARS,
WORKED VERY CLOSELY WITH A GREAT
POLICE DEPARTMENT.
AND WHAT WE DID IS TRY TO MOVE
THAT DEPARTMENT TOWARD COMMUNITY
POLICING SO THAT THE POLICE
OFFICERS BECOME PART OF THE
COMMUNITY AND NOT AS WE SEE IN
SOME CITIES AN OPPRESSIVE FORCE.
WE NEED TO MAKE POLICE
DEPARTMENTS LOOK LIKE THE
COMMUNITIES THEY SERVE IN TERMS
OF DIVERSITY.
WE NEED TO END MINIMAL
SENTENCING.
WE NEED BASICALLY TO PLEDGE THAT
WE'RE GOING TO INVEST IN THIS
COUNTRY IN JOBS AND EDUCATION,
NOT MORE JAILS AND
INCARCERATION.
>> SENATOR, C
[ APPLAUSE ]
WE WANT TO TURN NOW TO AN ISSUE.
THIS NEXT ISSUE HAS DESTROYED SO
MANY FAMILIES ACROSS THE COUNTRY
AND IN PARTICULAR RIGHT HERE IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE, HEROIN.
AND THERE'S A STUNNING NEW
FIGURE OUT.
A RECENT POLL.
48% HERE IN THIS STATE ALONE SAY
THEY KNOW SOMEONE WHO HAS ABUSED
HEROIN.
WE'RE GOING TO TURN TONIGHT TO
DAN TOOEY OF THE "NEW HAMPSHIRE
UNION-LEADER" WHO HAS THIS
QUESTION.
>> NEW HAMPSHIRE HAS BEEN HARD
HIT BY THE HEROIN EPIDEMIC, AND
WE'RE ON TRACK TO HAVE TWICE AS
MANY OVERDOSE DEATHS THIS YEAR
AS IN 2013.
WHAT SPECIFICALLY WOULD YOU DO
TO ADDRESS THIS CRISIS?
>> SENATOR SANDERS, I'M GOING TO
TAKE THIS TO YOU FIRST BECAUSE
YOU'VE SEEN WHAT'S HAPPENED WITH
HEROIN RIGHT ON THE BORDER IN
YOUR OWN STATE.
>> THIS IS A TRAGEDY FOR NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
IT IS A TRAGEDY FOR MY STATE OF
VERMONT.
IT IS A TRAGEDY ALL OVER THIS
COUNTRY.
THE NUMBER OF HEROIN DEATHS ARE
GROWING VERY, VERY
SIGNIFICANTLY.
WHAT DO WE DO?
WELL, FOR A START THIS MAY SEEM
LIKE A RADICAL IDEA, BUT I THINK
WE HAVE GOT TO TELL THE MEDICAL
PROFESSIONAL AND DOCTORS WHO ARE
PRESCRIBING OPIATES AND THE
PHARMACEUTICAL INDUSTRY THAT
THEY HAVE GOT TO START GETTING
THEIR ACT TOGETHER, WE CANNOT
HAVE THIS HUGE NUMBER OF OPIATES
OUT THERE THROUGHOUT THIS
COUNTRY WHERE YOUNG PEOPLE ARE
TAKING THEM, GETTING HOOKED, AND
THEN GOING TO HEROIN.
SECOND OF ALL, AND THE REASON I
BELIEVE IN A HEALTH CARE FOR ALL
PROGRAM, WE NEED TO UNDERSTAND
THAT ADDICTION IS A DISEASE, NOT
A CRIMINAL ACTIVITY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND THAT MEANS -- AND THAT MEANS
RADICALLY CHANGING THE WAY WE
DEAL WITH MENTAL HEALTH AND
ADDICTION ISSUES.
WHEN SOMEBODY IS ADDICTED AND
SEEKING HELP, THEY SHOULD NOT
HAVE TO WAIT THREE, FOUR MONTHS
IN ORDER TO GET THAT HELP.
THEY SHOULD BE ABLE TO WALK IN
THE DOOR TOMORROW AND GET A
VARIETY OF TREATMENTS THAT WORK
FOR THEM.
SO THOSE ARE SOME OF THE AREAS
THAT I THINK WE'VE GOT TO MOVE
ON.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
SECRETARY CLINTON?
>> YOU KNOW, ON MY VERY FIRST
VISIT TO NEW HAMPSHIRE IN THIS
CAMPAIGN I WAS IN
WAS ASKED WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO
DO ABOUT THE HEROIN EPIDEMIC?
AND ALL OVER NEW HAMPSHIRE I MET
GRANDMOTHERS WHO ARE RAISING
CHILDREN BECAUSE THEY LOST THE
FATHER OR THE MOTHER TO AN
OVERDOSE.
I MET YOUNG PEOPLE WHO ARE
DESPERATELY TRYING TO GET CLEAN
AND HAVE NOWHERE TO GO BECAUSE
THERE ARE NOT ENOUGH FACILITIES.
SO THIS IS A MAJOR EPIDEMIC, AND
IT HAS HIT NEW HAMPSHIRE AND
VERMONT PARTICULARLY HARD.
I'VE HAD I'VE HAD TWO TOWN
HALLS, ONE IN KEENE, ONE IN
LACONIA, TALKING ABOUT WHAT TO
DO AND I'VE HEARD SOME GREAT
IDEAS ABOUT HOW LAW ENFORCEMENT
IS CHANGING ITS BEHAVIOR, HOW
THE RECOVERY COMMUNITY IS
REACHING OUT.
I WAS PROUD TO GET THE
ENDORSEMENT OF MAYOR WALSH OF
BOSTON WHO HAS MADE HIS STRUGGLE
WITH ALCOHOLISM A REAL CLARION
CALL FOR ACTION IN THIS ARENA.
SO I'VE LAID OUT A FIVE-POINT
PLAN OF WHAT WE CAN DO TOGETHER.
I WOULD LIKE THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT TO OFFER $10 BILLION
OVER TEN YEARS TO WORK WITH
STATES, AND I REALLY APPLAUD
GOVERNOR HASSAN FOR TAKING UP
THIS CHALLENGE AND
WITH A PLAN.
WE NEED TO DO MORE ON THE
PRESCRIBING END OF IT.
THERE ARE TOO MANY OPIOIDS BEING
PRESCRIBED AND THAT LEADS
DIRECT
DIRECTLY NOW TO HEROIN
ADDICTION.
AND WE NEED TO CHANGE THE WAY WE
DO LAW ENFORCE SXMT WE NEED MORE
PROGRAMS AND FACILITIES SO WHEN
SOMEBODY'S READY TO GET HELP
THERE'S A PLACE FOR THEM TO GO.
AND EVERY LAW ENFORCEMENT SHOULD
CARRY THE ANTIDOTE TO OVERDOSE
IN THE LOCK ZONE SO THEY CAN
SAVE LIVES THAT ARE ON THE BRINK
OF EXPIRING.
>> SECRETARY, THANK YOU.
>> I ACTUALLY KNOW A GREAT DEAL
ABOUT THIS ISSUE.
AND I HAVE A DEAR FRIEND, PLAYED
MUSIC WITH HIM FOR YEARS,
REMEMBER WHEN HE CAME HOME WITH
HIS BABY GIRL, AND NOW SHE'S NO
LONGER WITH US BECAUSE OF
ADDICTION AND OVERDOSE.
THE LAST TIME IN NEW HAMPSHIRE I
HAD TO TAKE A BREAK SHORTLY
AFTER LANDING AND CALL HOME AND
COMFORT A FRIEND WHOSE MOTHER
HAD DIED OF AN OVERDOSE.
DRUGS HAVE TAKEN FAR TOO MANY OF
OUR CITIZENS.
IT'S A HUGE PUBLIC HEALTH
CHALLENGE.
IN OUR OWN CITY I MENTIONED
BEFORE WE HAD BECOME THE MOST
ADDICTED CITY IN AMERICA.
BUT TOGETHER EVERY SINGLE YEAR I
EXPANDED DRUG TREATMENT FUNDING
WITHIN OUR CITY AND THEN I
EXPANDED IT IN OUR STATE, AND WE
WERE SAVING LIVES EVERY SINGLE
YEAR DOING THE THINGS THAT WORK,
INTERVENING EARLIER,
UNDERSTANDING THE CONTINUUM OF
CARE THAT'S REQUIRED UNTIL WE
GOT HIT LIKE EVERY OTHER STATE
IN THE STATE, IN THE UNITED
STATES, ESPECIALLY IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE AND IN THE NORTHEAST
WITH THIS OPIOID ADDICTION.
THE OVERPRESCRIBING.
I AGREE, WE NEED BETTER -- WE
NEED TO REIN IN THE
OVERPRESCRIBING.
BUT I HAVE PUT FORWARD IN MY
PLAN A $12 BILLION FEDERAL
INVESTMENT.
WE HAVE TO INVEST IN THE LOCAL
PARTNERSHIPS.
AND THE BEST PLACE TO INTERVENE,
THE BEST INDICATOR OF WHEN A
PERSON IS ACTUALLY ON THE VERGE
OF KILLING THEMSELVES BECAUSE OF
AN ADDICTION, IS AT THE
HOSPITAL.
THAT VERY FIRST TIME THEY SHOW
UP WITH A NEAR MISS, WE SHOULD
BE INTERVENING THERE.
THAT'S WHAT I SAID TO MY OWN
PUBLIC HEALTH PEOPLE.
WHAT WOULD WE DO IF THIS WERE
EBOLA?
HOW WOULD WE ACT?
SO MANY MORE AMERICANS HAVE BEEN
KILLED BY THE COMBINATION OF
HEROIN AND THESE HIGHLY
ADDICTIVE PAIN PILLS, AND YET WE
REFUSE TO ACT.
THERE ARE THINGS THAT CAN BE
DONE.
GO TO MY WEBSITE.
MY PLAN IS THERE.
IT'S ONE OF 15 STRATEGIC GOALS
I'VE SET OUT TO MAKE OUR COUNTRY
A BETTER PLACE BY CUTTING THESE
SORT OF DEATHS IN HALF IN THE
NEXT FIVE YEARS.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, THANK YOU.
MARTHA.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I WANT TO
CIRCLE BACK TO SOMETHING YOUR
OPPONENTS HERE HAVE BROUGHT UP.
LIBYA IS FALLING APART.
THE COUNTRY IS A HAVEN FOR ISIS
AND JIHADISTS WITH AN ESTIMATED
2,000 ISIS FIGHTERS THERE TODAY.
YOU ADVOCATED FOR THAT 2011
INTERVENTION AND CALLED IT SMART
POWER AT ITS BEST.
AND YET EVEN PRESIDENT OBAMA
SAID THE U.S. SHOULD HAVE DONE
MORE TO FILL THE LEADERSHIP
VACUUM LEFT BEHIND.
HOW MUCH RESPONSIBILITY DO YOU
BEAR FOR THE CHAOS THAT FOLLOWED
ELECTIONS?
>> WELL, FIRST, LET'S REMEMBER
WHY WE BECAME PART OF A
COALITION TO STOP GADHAFI FROM
COMMITTING MASSACRES AGAINST HIS
PEOPLE.
THE UNITED STATES WAS ASKED TO
SUPPORT THE EUROPEANS AND THE
ARAB PARTNERS THAT WE HAD.
AND WE DID A LOT OF DUE
DILIGENCE ABOUT WHETHER WE
SHOULD OR NOT.
AND EVENTUALLY, YES, I
RECOMMENDED AND THE PRESIDENT
DECIDED THAT WE WOULD SUPPORT
THE ACTION TO PROTECT CIVILIANS
ON THE GROUND AND THAT LED TO
THE OVERTHROW OF GADHAFI.
I THINK THAT WHAT LIBYA THEN DID
BY HAVING A FULL FREE ELECTION
WHICH ELECTED MODERATES WAS AN
INDICATION OF THEIR CRYING NEED
AND DESIRE TO GET ON THE RIGHT
PATH.
NOW, THE WHOLE REGION HAS BEEN
RENDERED UNSTABLE, IN PART
BECAUSE OF THE AFTERMATH OF THE
ARAB SPRING, IN PART BECAUSE OF
THE VERY EFFECTIVE OUTREACH AND
PROPAGANDIZING THAT ISIS AND
OTHER TERRORIST GROUPS DO.
BUT WHAT WE'RE SEEING HAPPENING
IN LIBYA RIGHT NOW IS THAT THERE
HAS BEEN A FRAGILE AGREEMENT TO
PUT ASIDE THE DIFFERENCES THAT
EXIST AMONG LIBYANS THEMSELVES
TO TRY TO DISLODGE ISIS FROM
CERT, THE HOME TOWN OF GADHAFI,
AND TO BEGIN TO TRY TO CREATE A
NATIONAL GOVERNMENT.
YOU KNOW, THIS IS NOT EASY WORK.
WE DID A LOT TO HELP.
WE DID AS MUCH AS WE COULD
BECAUSE THE LIBYANS THEMSELVES
HAD VERY STRONG FEELINGS ABOUT
WHAT THEY WISHED TO ACCEPT.
BUT WE'RE ALWAYS LOOKING FOR
WAYS ABOUT WHAT MORE WE CAN DO
TO TRY TO GIVE PEOPLE A CHANCE
TO BE SUCCESSFUL.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, I WANT TO
GO BACK.
THAT GOVERNMENT LACKED
INSTITUTIONS AND EXPERIENCE.
IT HAD BEEN A FAMILY BUSINESS
FOR 40 YEARS.
ON THE SECURITY SIDE WE OFFERED
ONLY A MODEST TRAINING EFFORT
AND A VERY LIMITED ARMS BUY-BACK
PROGRAM.
LET ME ASK YOU THE QUESTION
AGAIN.
HOW MUCH RESPONSIBILITY DO YOU
BEAR FOR THE CHAOS THAT FOLLOWED
THOSE ELECTIONS?
>> MARTHA, WE OFFERED A LOT MORE
THAN THEY WERE WILLING TO TAKE.
WE OFFERED A LOT MORE.
WE ALSO GOT RID OF THEIR
CHEMICAL WEAPONS, WHICH WAS A
BIG HELP.
AND WE ALSO WENT AFTER A LOT OF
THE SHOULDER-FIRED MISSILES TO
ROUND THEM UP.
YOU KNOW, WE CAN'T -- IF WE'RE
NOT GOING TO SEND AMERICAN
TROOPS, WHICH THERE WAS NEVER
ANY IDEA OF DOING THAT, THEN TO
TRY TO SEND TRAINERS, TO TRY TO
SEND EXPERTS, IS SOMETHING WE
OFFERED.
EUROPEANS OFFERED, THE U.N.
OFFERED, AND THERE WASN'T A LOT
OF RESPONSIVENESS AT FIRST.
I THINK A LOT OF THE LIBYANS WHO
HAD BEEN FORCED OUT OF THEIR
COUNTRY BY GADHAFI WHO CAME BACK
TO TRY TO BE PART OF A NEW
GOVERNMENT, BELIEVED THEY KNEW
WHAT TO DO AND IT TURNED OUT
THEY WERE NO MATCH FOR SOME OF
THE MILITARISTIC FORCES INSIDE
THAT COUNTRY.
BUT I'M NOT GIVING UP ON LIBYA
AND I DON'T THINK ANYBODY
SHOULD.
WE'VE BEEN AT THIS A COUPLE OF
YEARS.
>> BUT WERE MISTAKES MADE?
>> WELL, THERE'S ALWAYS A
RETROSPECTIVE TO SAY WHAT
MISTAKES WERE MADE.
BUT I KNOW THAT WE OFFERED A LOT
OF HELP AND I KNOW IT WAS
DIFFICULT FOR THE LIBYANS TO
ACCEPT HELP.
WHAT WE COULD HAVE DONE IF THEY
HAD SAID YES WOULD HAVE BEEN A
LOT MORE THAN WHAT WE WERE ABLE
TO HAVE DONE.
>> SENATOR SANDERS.
>> THE SECRETARY IS RIGHT.
THIS IS A TERRIBLY COMPLICATED
ISSUE.
THERE ARE NO SIMPLE SOLUTIONS.
BUT WHERE WE HAVE A DISAGREEMENT
IS THAT I THINK IF YOU LOOK AT
THE HISTORY OF REGIME CHANGES,
YOU GO BACK TO MOSSADEGH IN
IRAN, YOU GO BACK TO SALVADOR
ALLENDE WHO WE OVERTHREW IN
CHILE, YOU GO BACK TO
OVERTHROWING SADDAM HUSSEIN IN
IRAQ, YOU GO BACK TO WHERE WE
ARE TODAY IN SYRIA WITH A
DICTATOR NAMED ASSAD, THE TRUTH
IS IT IS RELATIVELY EASY FOR A
POWERFUL NATION LIKE AMERICA TO
OVERTHROW A DICTATOR BUT IT IS
VERY HARD TO PREDICT THE
UNINTENDED CONSEQUENCES AND THE
TURMOIL AND THE INSTABILITY THAT
FOLLOWS AFTER YOU OVERTHROW THAT
DICTATOR.
SO I THINK SECRETARY CLINTON AND
I HAVE A FUNDAMENTAL
DISAGREEMENT.
I'M NOT QUITE THE FAN OF REGIME
CHANGE THAT I BELIEVE SHE IS.
>> MARTHA --
>> I WOULD JUST REPEAT THAT --
>> SECRETARY CLINTON --
>> I THINK IT'S ONLY FAIR TO PUT
ON THE RECORD SENATOR SANDERS
VOTED IN THE SENATE FOR A
RESOLUTION CALLING FOR ENDING
THE GADHAFI REGIME AND ASKING
THAT THE U.N. BE BROUGHT IN,
EITHER A CONGRESSIONAL VOTE OR A
U.N. SECURITY COUNCIL VOTE.
WE GOT A U.N. SECURITY COUNCIL
VOTE.
NOW, I UNDERSTAND THAT THIS IS
VERY DIFFICULT.
AND I'M NOT STANDING HERE TODAY
AND SAYING THAT LIBYA IS AS FAR
ALONG AS TUNISIA.
WE SAW WHAT HAPPENED IN EGYPT.
I CAUTIONED ABOUT A QUICK
OVERTHROW OF MUBARAK, AND WE NOW
ARE BACK WITH BASICALLY AN ARMY
DICTATORSHIP.
THIS IS A PART OF THE WORLD
WHERE THE UNITED STATES HAS
TRIED TO PLAY TWO DIFFERENT
APPROACHES.
ONE, WORK WITH THE TOUGH MEN,
THE DICTATORS, FOR OUR OWN
BENEFIT AND PROMOTE DEMOCRACY.
THAT'S A HARD ROAD TO WALK.
BUT I THINK THE RIGHT ROAD
FOR US TO TRY TO TRAVEL.
>> AND MARTHA, IN THIS CASE, AND
IN THIS CASE WE PROBABLY LET OUR
LUST FOR REGIME TOPPLING GET
AHEAD OF THE PRACTICAL
CONSIDERATIONS FOR STABILITY IN
THAT REGION.
AND I BELIEVE THAT ONE OF THE
BIG FAILINGS IN THAT REGION IS A
LACK OF HUMAN INTELLIGENCE.
WE HAVE NOT MADE THE INVESTMENTS
WE NEED TO MAKE TO UNDERSTAND
AND TO HAVE RELATIONSHIPS WITH
FUTURE LEADERS THAT ARE COMING
UP.
THAT'S WHAT CHRIS STEVENS WAS
TRYING TO DO.
BUT WITHOUT THE TOOLS, WITHOUT
THE SUPPORT THAT WAS NEEDED TO
DO THAT.
AND NOW WHAT WE HAVE IS A WHOLE
STRETCH NOW OF THE COAST OF
LIBYA, 100 MILES, 150 MILES,
THAT HAS NOW BECOME POTENTIALLY
THE NEXT SAFE HAVEN FOR ISIL.
THEY GO BACK AND FORTH BETWEEN
SYRIA AND THIS REGION.
WE HAVE TO STOP CONTRIBUTING TO
THE CREATION OF VACUUMS THAT
ALLOW SAFE HAVENS TO DEVELOP.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON HERE.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, THANK YOU
VERY MUCH FOR THAT.
AND WE'RE GOING TO MAKE A VERY
SHARP TURN AS WE WRAP THINGS UP
HERE.
SECRETARY CLINTON, FIRST LADIES,
AS YOU WELL KNOW, HAVE USED
THEIR POSITION TO WORK ON
IMPORTANT CAUSES LIKE LITERACY
AND DRUG ABUSE.
BUT THEY ALSO SUPERVISE THE
MENUS, THE FLOWERS, THE HOLIDAY
ORNAMENTS AND WHITE HOUSE DECOR.
I KNOW YOU THINK YOU KNOW WHERE
I'M GOING HERE.
YOU HAVE SAID THAT BILL CLINTON
IS A GREAT HOST AND LOVES GIVING
TOURS BUT MAY OPT OUT OF PICKING
FLOWER ARRANGEMENTS IF YOU'RE
ELECTED.
BILL CLINTON ASIDE, IS IT TIME
TO CHANGE THE ROLE OF A
PRESIDENT'S SPOUSE?
>> WELL, THE ROLE HAS BEEN
DEFINED BY EACH PERSON WHO'S
HELD IT.
AND I AM VERY GRATEFUL FOR ALL
MY PREDECESSORS AND MY
SUCCESSORS BECAUSE EACH OF THEM
NOT ONLY DID WHAT SHE COULD TO
SUPPORT HER HUSBAND AND OUR
COUNTRY BUT OFTEN CHOSE TO WORK
ON IMPORTANT ISSUES THAT WERE OF
PARTICULAR CONCERN.
OBVIOUSLY, MRS. OBAMA HAS BEEN A
TERRIFIC LEADER WHEN IT COMES TO
YOUNG PEOPLE'S HEALTH,
PARTICULARLY NUTRITION AND
EXERCISE.
AND I THINK HAS HAD A BIG
IMPACT.
SO WHOEVER IS PART OF THE FAMILY
OF A PRESIDENT HAS AN
EXTRAORDINARY PRIVILEGE OF NOT
ONLY HAVING A FRONT ROW SEAT ON
HISTORY BUT MAKING HER OR MAYBE
HIS CONTRIBUTION.
AND WITH RESPECT TO MY OWN
HUSBAND, I AM PROBABLY STILL
GOING TO PICK THE FLOWERS AND
THE CHINA FOR STATE DINNERS AND
STUFF LIKE THAT.
BUT I WILL CERTAINLY TURN TO HIM
AS PRIOR PRESIDENTS HAVE FOR
SPECIAL MISSIONS, FOR ADVICE,
AND IN PARTICULAR HOW WE'RE
GOING TO GET THE ECONOMY WORKING
AGAIN FOR EVERYBODY, WHICH HE
KNOWS A LITTLE BIT ABOUT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
>> I DO WANT TO FOLLOW UP HERE
FOR EACH OF YOU.
AND A SIMILAR LINE OF
QUESTIONING.
SENATOR SANDERS, YOUR WIFE JANE
SHARES AN OFFICE AT YOUR
CAMPAIGN HEADQUARTERS IN
BURLINGTON.
WE'VE SEEN THE PICTURES, THE
DESKS RIGHT NEXT TO EACH OTHER.
WOULD SHE HAVE A DESK CLOSE BY
IN THE WEST WING?
>> GIVEN THE FACT THAT SHE'S A
LOT SMARTER THAN ME, YES, SHE
WOULD.
AND LET ME BY THE WAY TAKE THIS
MOMENT TO CONGRATULATE HILLARY
CLINTON, WHO I THOUGHT NOT ONLY
DID AN OUTSTANDING JOB AS OUR
FIRST LADY BUT REDEFINED WHAT
THAT ROLE COULD BE.
SO I THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
THAT.
[ APPLAUSE ]
MY WIFE, JANE, HAS BEEN WAY BACK
WHEN BEFORE I KNEW HER A FOSTER
PARENT.
MANY, MANY KIDS CAME INTO HER
HOME AND RECEIVED THE KIND OF
LOVE THAT THEY DESPERATELY
NEEDED.
AND SHE TURNED AROUND MANY
LIVES.
SHE IS THE BEST PARENT AND
GRANDMOTHER THAT I KNOW.
SHE HAS DEVOTED HER LIFE, WHEN I
WAS MAYOR OF THE CITY OF
BURLINGTON, ACTUALLY WHEN I
FIRST MET HER, WE STARTED A
YOUTH OFFICE, WHICH STARTED
AFTERSCHOOL PROGRAMS FOR KIDS,
STARTED A CHILDCARE CENTER,
STARTED A YOUTH NEWSPAPER.
WE GOT THE KIDS INVOLVED IN A
WHOLE LOT OF ISSUES.
SHE LED THAT EFFORT.
SO I THINK AT A TIME WHEN SO
MANY OF OUR KIDS ARE DESPERATELY
LOOKING FOR CONSTRUCTIVE
ACTIVITY, WHERE TOO MANY OF OUR
KIDS ARE HANGING AROUND ON
STREET CORNERS POTENTIALLY
GETTING INTO TROUBLE, I THINK WE
NEED A FORCEFUL ADVOCATE FOR THE
CHILDREN, FOR TEENAGERS, FOR THE
LITTLE CHILDREN TO DEAL WITH THE
DYSFUNCTIONAL CHILDCARE SYSTEM,
AND I THINK MY WIFE WOULD DO A
GREAT JOB IN HELPING ME
ACCOMPLISH THOSE GOALS.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU.
[ APPLAUSE ]
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, YOU HAVE
TALKED ABOUT YOUR WIFE, KATIE,
HERE TONIGHT.
SHE'S A DISTRICT COURT JUDGE.
AND THE QUESTION FOR YOU IS
WOULD SHE HAVE TO GIVE THAT UP
AS FIRST LADY OR WILL SHE SHARE
AN OFFICE IN THE WEST WING AS
WELL?
>> THAT WOULD BE TOTALLY UP TO
HER.
I MEAN, KATIE HAS NEVER BEEN A
PERSON WHO LET HER HUSBAND'S
PROFESSIONAL CHOICES GET IN THE
WAY OF FOLLOWING HER DREAMS.
AND I THINK SHE GOT THAT FROM
HER MOTHER, ACTUALLY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
AND I READILY ADMIT THAT SHE IS
A FAR MORE ACCOMPLISHED LAWYER
THAN I WAS EVER ABLE TO BECOME
BEFORE I TOOK MY DETOUR.
SHE IS A DISTRICT COURT JUDGE IN
MARYLAND.
SHE PUTS IN A FULL DAY THERE.
WE'VE RAISED FOUR TERRIFIC KIDS.
AND YET WHEN SHE WAS FIRST LADY
OF THE STATE NOT ONLY WOULD SHE
GO TO WORK EVERY DAY AND SIT
THERE THROUGH A LOT OF SAD AND
GUT-WRENCHING CASES BUT THEN
SHE'D PUT IN ADDITIONAL TIME
BEING AN ADVOCATE AGAINST
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE.
MARYLAND MADE GREAT STRIDES ON
THAT BECAUSE OF HER ADVOCACY AND
HER UNDERSTANDING OF HOW THE
COURT PROCESS WORKS.
SHE WAS AN ADVOCATE AGAINST
BULLYING AND IMPLEMENTING
ANTI-BULLYING THINGS.
SO KATIE O'MALLEY WILL DO
WHATEVER KATIE O'MALLEY WANTS TO
DO REGARDLESS OF HER HUSBAND'S
SUCCESS IN GETTING ELECTED
PRESIDENT.
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY, THANK YOU.
WE'LL BE BACK WITH MUCH MORE
FROM NEW HAMPSHIRE.
THE DEMOCRATIC DEBATE CONTINUES
RIGHT AFTER THIS.
>> Announcer: ABC NEWS LIVE
COVERAGE OF THE NEW HAMPSHIRE
DEMOCRATIC DEBATE WILL CONTINUE
IN A MOMENT.
>> Announcer: LIVE FROM SAINT
ANSELM COLLEGE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE,
HERE AGAIN ARE DAVID MUIR AND
MARTHA RADDATZ.
>>> WELCOME BACK TONIGHT.
IT'S BEEN AN EVENING OF LIVELY
DISCUSSION AMONG THE CANDIDATES,
AND IT'S TIME FOR CLOSING
STATEMENTS.
WE BEGAN IN ALPHABETICAL ORDER.
SO WE'LL REVERSE THE ORDER AT
THE END AND BEGIN WITH YOU,
SENATOR SANDERS.
>> WELL, THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
HOSTING THIS DEBATE.
AND LET ME APPLAUD MY COLLEAGUES
UP HERE BECAUSE I THINK FRANKLY,
MAYBE I'M WRONG, BUT ON OUR
WORST DAY I THINK WE HAVE A LOT
MORE TO OFFER THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE THAN THE RIGHT-WING
EXTREMISTS TODAY.
[ APPLAUSE ]
MY FATHER CAME TO THIS COUNTRY
FROM POLAND AT THE AGE OF 17
WITHOUT A NICKEL IN HIS POCKET.
WHICH SPARKED MY INTEREST IN THE
NEED FOR IMMIGRATION REFORM
BECAUSE I KNOW WHAT IT'S LIKE TO
BE THE SON OF AN IMMIGRANT.
WE GREW UP IN A 3 1/2-ROOM
RENT-CONTROLLED APARTMENT IN
BROOKLYN, NEW YORK.
MY MOTHER'S DREAM, AND SHE DIED
VERY YOUNG, BUT MY MOTHER'S
DREAM FOR HER WHOLE LIFE WAS TO
BE ABLE TO GET OUT OF THAT
RENT-CONTROLLED APARTMENT AND
OWN A HOME OF HER OWN.
SHE NEVER LIVED TO SEE THAT.
BUT WHAT MY PARENTS DID
ACCOMPLISH IS THEY WERE ABLE TO
SEND BOTH OF THEIR SONS TO
COLLEGE.
WE WERE THE FIRST IN THE FAMILY.
SO I KNOW SOMETHING ABOUT
ECONOMIC ANXIETY AND LIVING IN A
FAMILY THAT DOES NOT HAVE
SUFFICIENT INCOME.
AND THAT IS WHY I AM PLEDGED IF
ELECTED PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES TO BRING ABOUT A
POLITICAL REVOLUTION WHERE
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE BEGIN TO
STAND UP AND FINALLY SAY ENOUGH
IS ENOUGH, THIS GREAT COUNTRY
AND OUR GOVERNMENT BELONG TO ALL
OF US, NOT JUST A HANDFUL OF
BILLIONAIRES.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR O'MALLEY.
>> MARTHA, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO THANK ALL OF THE
PEOPLE WHO HAVE TUNED IN
TONIGHT.
I WANT TO THANK THE GREAT PEOPLE
OF NEW HAMPSHIRE, WHERE DESPITE
ALL OF THE CYNICISM ABOUT BIG
MONEY AND BIG BANKS TAKING OVER
OUR POLITICS, HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE THE INDIVIDUAL
MATTERS.
MY WIFE, KATIE, AND I HAVE FOUR
TERRIFIC KIDS.
AND LIKE YOU THERE'S PROBABLY
NOTHING WE WOULDN'T DO TO GIVE
THEM A FUTURE THAT'S SAFER,
THAT'S HEALTHIER, WHERE THEY
HAVE MORE OPPORTUNITY THAN OUR
PARENTS AND GRANDPARENTS GAVE TO
US.
TONIGHT WHAT YOU LISTENED TO WAS
A HEALTHY EXCHANGE OF IDEAS
ABOUT HOW WE'D DO THAT.
THAT WHICH WE HAVE ALWAYS
PROVEN, THE CAPACITY TO DO
BETTER THAN ANY NATION IN THE
WORLD, TO TAKE ACTIONS THAT
INCLUDE MORE OF OUR PEOPLE MORE
FULLY IN THE ECONOMIC, SOCIAL,
AND POLITICAL LIFE OF OUR
COUNTRY.
WHEN YOU LISTEN TO THE
REPUBLICAN DEBATE THE OTHER
NIGHT, YOU HEARD A LOT OF ANGER
AND YOU HAD A LOT OF FEAR.
WELL, THEY CAN HAVE THEIR ANGER
AND THEY CAN HAVE THEIR FEAR.
BUT ANGER AND FEAR NEVER BUILT
AMERICA.
WE BUILD OUR COUNTRY BY ADOPTING
WAGE AND LABOR POLICIES
INCLUDING COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM WITH A
PATHWAY OF CITIZENSHIP FOR ALL.
WE DO IT BY INVESTING IN OUR
COUNTRY, BY INVESTING IN
INFRASTRUCTURE, BY INVESTING IN
THE SKILLS AND THE TALENTS OF
OUR PEOPLE WITH DEBT-FREE
COLLEGE, AND WE CAN DO IT AGAIN.
AND WE ALSO CREATE A BETTER
FUTURE FOR OUR KIDS WHEN WE
SQUARE OUR SHOULDERS TO THE
GREAT CHALLENGES OF OUR TIMES,
WHETHER IT'S TERROR TRYING TO
UNDERMINE OUR VALUES OR
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES TRYING TO GET US TO
SURRENDER OUR FREEDOMS AND OUR
VALUES IN THE FACE OF THIS
THREAT.
THE OTHER BIG CHALLENGE WE HAVE
IS CLIMATE CHANGE.
THE GREATEST BUSINESS
OPPORTUNITY TO COME TO THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA IN 100
YEARS, WE NEED TO EMBRACE THIS.
I HAVE PUT FORWARD A PLAN THAT
DOES THIS, THAT MOVES US TO 100%
CLEAN ELECTRIC GRID BY 2050.
JOIN THIS GAIN FOR THE FUTURE.
NEW LEADERSHIP IS WHAT OUR
COUNTRY NEEDS TO MOVE US OUT OF
THESE DIVIDED AND POLARIZED
TIMES.
THANK YOU.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> GOVERNOR, THANK YOU.
SECRETARY CLINTON.
>> ON JANUARY 20th, 2017 THE
NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES WILL WALK INTO THE WHITE
HOUSE.
IF HEAVEN FORBID THAT NEXT
PRESIDENT IS A REPUBLICAN, I
THINK IT'S PRETTY CLEAR WE KNOW
WHAT WILL HAPPEN.
A LOT OF THE RIGHTS THAT HAVE
BEEN WON OVER THE YEARS FROM
WOMEN'S RIGHTS TO VOTER RIGHTS
TO GAY RIGHTS TO WORKER RIGHTS
WILL BE AT RISK.
SOCIAL SECURITY, WHICH
REPUBLICANS CALL A PONZI SCHEME,
MAY FACE PRIVATIZATION.
OUR VETS MAY SEE THE VA HOSPITAL
THAT NEEDS TO BE IMPROVED AND
MADE BETTER FOR THEM TURNED OVER
TO PRIVATIZATION.
PLANNED PARENTHOOD WILL BE
DEFUNDED.
THE LIST GOES ON BECAUSE THE
DIFFERENCES ARE SO STARK.
YOU KNOW, EVERYBODY SAYS EVERY
ELECTION'S IMPORTANT.
AND THERE'S TRUTH TO THAT.
THIS IS A WATERSHED ELECTION.
I KNOW HOW IMPORTANT IT IS THAT
WE HAVE A DEMOCRAT SUCCEED
PRESIDENT OBAMA IN THE WHITE
HOUSE.
AND I WILL DO ALL THAT I CAN IN
THIS CAMPAIGN TO REACH OUT AND
EXPLAIN WHAT I STAND FOR AND
WHAT I WILL DO AS PRESIDENT.
YOU KNOW, I BECAME A GRANDMOTHER
15 MONTHS AGO.
AND SO I SPENT A LOT OF TIME
THINKING ABOUT MY
GRANDDAUGHTER'S FUTURE.
BUT AS PRESIDENT I WILL SPEND
EVEN MORE TIME THINKING ABOUT
THE FUTURES OF ALL THE KIDS AND
THE GRANDCHILDREN IN THIS
COUNTRY BECAUSE I WANT TO MAKE
SURE EVERY SINGLE CHILD HAS A
CHANCE TO LIVE UP TO HIS OR HER
GOD-GIVEN POTENTIAL.
IF YOU WILL JOIN ME IN THIS
CAMPAIGN, WE WILL MAKE THAT A
MISSION.
THANK YOU, GOOD NIGHT, AND MAY
THE FORCE BE WITH YOU.
[ CHEERS AND APPLAUSE ]
>> THANK YOU TO THE TNDS TONCAN
TONIGHT.
THANK YOU TO THE AUDIENCE HERE
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE AT SAINT
ANSELM.
AND THANK YOU TO THE AUDIENCE AT
HOME.
WE WISH ALL OF YOU AT HOME A
HAPPY, SAFE HOLIDAY.