>>> WE'RE TALKING TO ALL THE
REMAINING CANDIDATES IN THE RACE
FOR THE WHITE HOUSE ON THE EVE
OF MORE CRUCIAL CONTESTS.
>> IT'S AN UNPRECEDENTED MOMENT.
HOURS AFTER HILLARY CLINTON AND
DONALD TRUMP LAUNCHED
HIGH-PROFILE TAEXS AGAINST ONE
ANOTHER ON FOREIGN POLICY.
>> TONIGHT, FROM THE NATION'S
CAPITAL, THE FINAL FIVE
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES ON
VOLATILITY AROUND THE WORLD.
>> WE NEED STEADY HANDS.
NOT A PRESIDENT WHO SAYS HE'S
NEUTRAL ON MONDAY, PRO-ISRAEL ON
TUESDAY AND WHO KNOWS WHAT ON
WEDNESDAY.
>> I THINK I'M VERY DIFFERENT
THAN HILLARY CLINTON.
SHE DOESN'T KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
MY POLICY.
SHE WOULDN'T KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
IT.
HER POLICIES, OBVIOUSLY, DIDN'T
WORK.
ALL YOU HAVE TO DO IS LOOK AT
LIBYA.
>> CLOSER TO HOME, QUESTIONS ON
A TURBULENT CAMPAIGN.
>> YOU WANT TO BEAT DONALD
TRUMP, THE WAY TO DO IT IS BEAT
DONALD AT THE BALLOT BOX.
>> THEY'RE GOING TO PICK THE
MOST EXPERIENCED, THE PERSON WHO
CAN BEAT HILLARY CLINTON.
ME.
>> SUPPORTING EACH OTHER WILL
ALWAYS TRUMP SELFISHNESS.
>> THIS IS A CNN PRESIDENTIAL
PRIMETIME EVENT UNLIKE ANY FORUM
YOU'VE SEEN BEFORE.
>> THIS MAY BE ONE OF THE MOST
CONSEQUENTIAL CAMPAIGNS OF OUR
LIFETIME.
>> YOU'RE GOING TO SAY THAT WITH
THE GREATEST VOTE I'VE EVER
CAST.
>> FIVE CANDIDATES, TWO PARTIES,
ONE NETWORK, ONE NIGHT.
IT ALL BEGINS RIGHT NOW.
>>> WELCOME TO OUR CNN ELECTION
SPECIAL.
WE ARE ABOUT TO HEAR FROM THE
FINAL FIVE.
ALL THE PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATES
STILL IN CONTENTION FOR THE
NATION'S HIGHEST OFFICE.
THE REPUBLICAN GOVERNOR OF OHIO,
JOHN KASICH, JOINS US NOW.
THANKS FOR STARTING US OFF.
>> GOOD TO BE WITH YOU.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT AIPAC.
YOU SAID THERE IS NOT ANY
PROSPECT FOR PEACE UNTIL THE
PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY, HAMAS AND
HEZBOLLAH TAKE REAL STEPS TO
LIVE PEACEFULLY.
THEY ALSO HAVE TO RECOGNIZE
ISRAEL AS A JEWISH STATE.
THAT DOESN'T SOUND LIKE THERE'S
REALLY A CHANCE FOR PEACE IN
YOUR OPINION.
HEZBOLLAH, HAMAS?
>> ANDERSON, WHY ARE WE LIVING
IN A DREAM WORLD UNTIL THEY
RECOGNIZE ISRAEL'S RIGHT TO
EXIST, HOW COULD YOU EVER HAVE A
TWO-STATE SOLUTION?
YOU KNOW, THIS IS PRETTY CLEAR.
WHEN THE PRIME MINISTER CAME
HERE AND TALKED ABOUT THE IRAN
DEAL, HE TALKED ABOUT THE
FUNDAMENTAL CHANGE HE THOUGHT
THEY SHOULD HAVE EXHIBITED
BEFORE WE SIGNED AN AGREEMENT.
I FOUND IT TO BE COMPELLING.
>> ANYTHING YOU CAN DO AS
PRESIDENT TO MOVE HEZBOLLAH,
HAMAS, THE PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY
IN THAT DIRECTION?
>> THERE'S ALWAYS A WAY IN WHICH
YOU'D TALK BACK CHANNELS.
AND WE DO HAVE SOME LIMITED
LEVERAGE OVER THE PALESTINIAN
AUTHORITY, BUT THE PALESTINIAN
AUTHORITY HAS BEEN FEEDING A
LOTD OF HATRED FOR 30, 40 YEARS
AND TEACHING THEIR KIDS ABOUT
SUICIDE KILLERS AND ALL THESE
OTHER CRAZY THINGS.
SO IS THERE -- ARE THERE BACK
CHANNELS IN WHICH YOU CAN SAY,
LOOK, TWO-STATE SOLUTION IS
POSSIBLE BUT THERE'S SOME
PRECONDITIONS.
YOU DON'T EVER GO TO AN EVENT OR
NEGOTIATION WHERE YOU DON'T HAVE
SOME SENSE OF HOW IT'S GOING TO
WORK OUT.
THEN IT BECOMES AN EXPERIENCE IN
NOTHING BUT FRUSTRATION.
THAT'S NOT WHERE YOU WANT TO BE.
>> IN THE SPEECH TODAY YOU ALSO
SAID WE CANNOT BE NEUTRAL IN
DEFENDING OUR ALLIES REFERENCE
NO DOUBT TO DONALD TRUMP WHO
TALKED ABOUT BEING NEUTRAL IN
NEGOTIATIONS.
WOULD DONALD TRUMP BE A STAUNCH
ENOUGH ALLY OF ISRAEL?
>> YOU ASK HIM, OKAY?
I CAN JUST TELL YOU ABOUT ME.
35 YEARS I'VE SUPPORTED ISRAEL.
IT'S NOT JUST ISRAEL.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE WE
STRENGTHEN NATO, MAKE SURE PUTIN
UNDERSTANDS WE WILL ARM THE
UKRAINIANS SO THEY CAN FIGHT FOR
FREEDOM, PROVIDING THEM WITH A
LETHAL DEFENSIVE EQUIPMENT THAT
THEY NEED.
WE NEED TO MAKE IT CLEAR TO THE
CHINESE WHAT WE EXPECT FROM
THEM.
IT DOESN'T MEAN WE HAVE TO
RATTLE SABERS.
WE SHOULD NOT GET INVOLVED IN
CIVIL WARS BUT, CLEARLY, WHEN IT
COMES TO ISIS, WE HAVE TO
DESTROY ISIS WITH A COALITION OF
THE ARABS AND ALSO THE EUROPEANS
LED BY US.
THESE ARE SIMPLE THINGS REALLY.
>> WHAT ABOUT MILITARY AID TO
ISRAEL.
SENIOR REPUBLICAN ON THE HOUSE
BUDGET COMMITTEE.
YOU PROPOSED CUTS TO A LOT OF
FEDERAL PROGRAMS, FREEZING
MILITARY AID TO ISRAEL, ISRAEL
CURRENTLY RECEIVES ABOUT $3
BILLION IN AID.
WOULD THAT STILL BE ON THE
TABLE, AN AREA TO CUT OR --
>> WE STILL HAVE TO CONTINUE TO
MAKE SURE THAT ISRAEL HAS
MILITARY SUPERIORITY,
PARTICULARLY IN THE AIR.
OF COURSE, I WAS A SUPPORTER OF
THE IRON DOME WHICH IS CRITICAL
IN EARLY DAYS.
THE ARAB PROGRAM.
NO, I THINK WE DON'T WANT TO
EVER PUT THEM IN A POSITION
WHERE THEY DON'T HAVE
SUPERIORITY.
>> SO NO CUTS TO ISRAEL AT ALL
ON MILITARY AID?
>> I DON'T SEE ANY REASON TO DO
THAT OR TO SAY THAT TODAY.
WE WANT TO MAKE SURE THEY'RE
STRONG AND THE STRONGEST IN THE
REGION.
>> YOU ALSO SAID TODAY JERUSALEM
IS THE ETERNAL CAPITAL OF
ISRAEL.
THAT'S YOUR QUOTE.
THE LAST THREE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTS DID NOT MOVE THE U.S.
EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM, DUD NOT
RECOGNIZE JERUSALEM AS THE
CAPITAL.
WHY WERE THEY WRONG?
>> TAKE THE STATEMENT FOR WHAT
IT IS.
IT IS THE ETERNAL CAPITAL OF
ISRAEL.
>> SHOULD THE EMBASSY BE THERE?
>> I WOULD PREFER THAT.
WE HAVE OTHER THINGS WE HAVE TO
DO UP FRONT WHICH IS TO MAKE
SURE THEY HAVE SECURITY.
BACK CHANNELS TO THE
PALESTINIANS.
AND I'M TOLD TODAY THAT THERE
ARE -- THERE'S SOME PROGRESS
WITH THE PALESTINIANS IN TERMS
OF KEEPING SOME OF THE LID ON
THE VIOLENCE.
THE STABBINGS HAVE BEEN
TERRIBLE.
BUT PERHAPS THERE ARE STILL SOME
THINGS THAT THEY DO TO TRY TO
KEEP A LID ON THE SITUATION.
MY WHOLE POINT ANDERSON AS
REGARD ISRAEL AND THE WHOLE
MIDDLE EAST IS WE LOOK FOR SFA
BILITY.
WE'LL NOT HAVE ANY LONG-TERM
PEACE.
IT'S A MATTER OF GETTING THROUGH
EACH DAY WITH A LID ON THINGS
OVER THERE.
WE CAN MAKE MORE PROGRESS BUT
IT'S TOUGH OVER THERE.
>> TED CRUZ TALKED ABOUT
ACKNOWLEDGING JERUSALEM AS THE
CAPITAL DAY ONE.
MOVING THE EMBASSY THERE.
YOU ARE SAYING THAT'S A MISTAKE?
>> I'M JUST SAYING LET'S TAKE
ONE THING AT A TIME.
>> DOES IT IMPACT THE PEACE
PROCESS?
>> THERE'S SOME THINGS YOU SAY
THAT YOU KNOW ARE JUST GOING TO
GET YOU NOWHERE.
NOBODY MADE A STRONGER SPEECH
TODAY ABOUT MY SUPPORT OVER ALL
OF MY PROFESSIONAL CAREER FOR
ISRAEL.
AND WHAT I THINK WE NEED TO DO
VIS-A-VIS THE PALESTINIANS,
HAMAS, HEZBOLLAH, IRAN.
I CALLED FOR THE SUSPENSION OF
THEU RAN NUCLEAR AGREEMENT
BECAUSE OF THEIR BALLISTIC
MISSILE VOOLGSSS AND VIOLATING
THE SPIRIT OF THE AGREEMENT.
BUT LOOK, ANDERSON, IT'S EASY TO
MAKE A LOT OF STATEMENTS.
WHEN YOU HAVE A LOT OF
EXPERIENCE IN THIS MATTER, WHICH
I HAD SERVING 18 YEARS ON THE
ARMED SERVICES COMMITTEE AND
BEING IN THE PENTAGON AFTER 9/11
AT THE REQUEST OF SECRETARY RUMS
FELD TO HELP SOLVE SOME OF THEIR
PROBLEMS OVER THERE, YOU LEARN
TO CHOOSE YOUR WORDS CAREFULLY.
TODAY I THINK I WAS VERY STRONG
IN THAT SPEECH.
I RECEIVED AN OVERWHELMING
RESPONSE FROM THE BEGINNING AND
ALL THE WAY THROUGH THAT TALK,
AND I THINK I'VE SAID ENOUGH AT
THIS POINT.
>> YOU HAVE A LOT OF GOVERNMENT
EXPERIENCE.
DONALD TRUMP TRUMPETS HIS
BUSINESS EXPERIENCE.
>> I HAVE THAT, TOO.
>> MAKING DEALS.
IS EXPERIENCE IN BUSINESS,
MAKING DEALS IN BUSINESS, DOES
IT TRANSFER TO STATESMANSHIP?
DOES IT TRANSFER BETWEEN MAKING
DEALS BETWEEN COUNTRIES OR IS
THAT A WHOLE OTHER --
>> THAT'S A GOOD QUESTION.
WHEN YOU ARE A POLITICIAN,
PEOPLE WONDER IF YOU CAN
TRANSFER IT TO BUSINESS.
I DID.
I HAD GOOD SUCCESS WHEN I WORKED
AS A BANKER AND AS A BOARD
MEMBER.
SECONDLY IN BUSINESS, THERE'S
NOT AN AUTOMATIC ABILITY TO
UNDERSTAND POLITICS.
IT'S NOT THE SAME.
SOME PEOPLE CAN MAKE THE
TRANSITION.
OTHER PEOPLE CANNOT.
>> IS IT ABOUT MAKING DEALS IN
BUSINESS OR MORE MOVING -- YOU
ARE DEALING WITH COUNTRIES, A
LOT OF FACTORS.
>> IT'S MORE COMPLICATED, MORE
NUANCED.
AND BUT YOU KNOW, I HAD GREAT
SUCCESS IN TERMS OF BUSINESS
AGREEMENTS.
AND, OF COURSE, THE BALANCED
BUDGET WHICH I WAS ABLE TO DO
WITH THE CLINTON ADMINISTRATION
IN ADDITION TO WELFARE REFORM.
AND, BY THE WAY, MASSIVE REFORM
OF THE PENTAGON.
I WAS INVOLVED IN SIGNIFICANT
THINGS THERE.
AND THEN IN OHIO.
THE TIME I WAS IN BUSINESS,
ALMOST TEN YEARS I WAS OUT, WAS
ABSOLUTELY INVALUABLE TO ME TO
UNDERSTAND IN A REAL WAY WHAT
MOVES THE ECONOMY.
BUT IT'S BACK AND FORTH.
I'M THE ONLY ONE THAT HAS THE
LEGISLATIVE AND EXECUTIVE AND
BUSINESS EXPERIENCE IN THE RACE.
>> YOU TALKED ABOUT THE
PENTAGON.
DONALD TRUMP SAID IT'S TIME TO
RETHINK NATO BECAUSE IT COSTS
TOO MUCH.
NATO PARTNERS SHOULD BE PONYING
UP MORE.
>> THAT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE.
WE'LL HAVE TO STRENGTHEN NATO.
NATO HAS TO BE STRONGER NOT ONLY
VIS-A-VIS PUTIN AND WHAT COULD
HAPPEN IN CENTRAL EUROPE BUT WE
WANT OUR ALLIES TO SHARE
INTELLIGENCE WITH US.
WE NEED TO COME CLOSER TOGETHER.
AND THEY HAVE TO BE PART OF THE
COALITION TO BE ABLE TO DESTROY
ISIS.
>> IS IT RECKLESS THEN OF A
POTENTIAL LEADER TO TALK
ABOUT --
>> I WOULD NEVER SPEAK THAT WAY
BECAUSE WE NEED NATO.
WE ALL WISH THEY WOULD DO MORE.
>> YOU ARE SAYING IT SENDS A
WRONG MESSAGE TO DO THAT?
>> I DON'T THINK ANYONE IS
PAYING THAT MUCH ATTENTION.
AS A LEADER OF THIS COUNTRY YOU
WANT TO BE CAREFUL.
I WOULDN'T SAY THAT NOW.
IT'S COOPERATION ON THE
INTELLIGENCE SIDE.
IT'S COOPERATION, FRANKLY, ON
THE ABILITY TO PUT COALITIONS
TOGETHER, WORK AGAINST IRAN IF
THEY VIOLATE THE AGREEMENT.
THERE'S SO MANY REASONS WHICH WE
NEED TO HAVE STRONGER
RELATIONSHIPS AROUND THE WORLD
AND NOT JUST WITH NATO.
WE HAVE TO STRENGTHEN OUR
RELATIONSHIP WITH SOME OF OUR
ALLIES IN THE MIDDLE EAST,
PARTICULARLY THE EGYPTIANS,
JORDANIANS, GULF STATES.
THE SAUDIS, THAT'S A TRICKY
SITUATION.
ANOTHER PLACE TO KEEP OUR EYE ON
AND THAT'S TURKEY.
AND YOU KNOW, NOW THE TALK
WITH --
>> SUICIDE BOMBING THERE.
>> I KNOW.
THEY ARE BLAMING THAT ON ISIS.
BUT A SITUATION IS IN EUROPE
THEY'RE TRYING TO WORK A DEAL
WITH TURKEY TO DEAL WITH THE
PROBLEM OF THE MIGRANTS, THE
REFUGEES.
WHAT'S INTERESTING IS THEY ARE
NOW BEGINNING TO TALK ABOUT
PERHAPS THIS SAN OPENING FOR
TURKEY TO GET IN THE EU.
WE NEED TO PULL TURKEY TO THE
WEST.
THEY ARE A GATEWAY TO WHAT WE
NEED TO DO IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
>> TALKING ABOUT ISIS.
ONE OF THE PILLARS OF YOUR
PRESIDENCY WOULD BE TO KEEP ISIS
OUT OF LIBYA.
WOULD YOU USE U.S. TROOPS TO DO
THAT?
>> FIRST OF ALL, THAT'S A MAJOR
MISTAKE OF THE ADMINISTRATION
AND HILLARY.
WE SHOULD HAVE LET GADHAFI STAY
THERE.
BY KNOCKING HIM OUT, WE TURNED
THIS INTO THE WILD WEST.
THERE'S ABOUT SEVEN CITIES IN
LIBYA WE HAVE TO PAI ATTENTION
TO.
WE COULD USE SOME AIR POWER.
WE CAN SUPPORT PEOPLE THAT WANT
TO DEAL WITH THE SITUATION THERE
BUT WHEN IT RELATES TO ISIS IN
IRAQ AND ALSO IN SYRIA, IT'S
GOING TO BE NECESSARY TO DO IT.
>> SO YOU ARE SAYING LIBYA IS
WORSE NOW THAN UNDER GADHAFI?
>> YES.
>> YOU WOULD HAVE KEPT GADHAFI
IN POWER?
>> ANY TIME YOU START GETTING IN
THE MIDDLE OF THESE KIND OF
PROBLEMS DIRECTLY, WHICH IS WHAT
WE DID, YOU CREATE PROBLEMS.
>> SO IT WAS A MISTAKE TO
ORPHTHROW GADHAFI?
>> IT WAS A TERRIBLE MISTAKE AND
IT WAS HILLARY THAT REALLY
PUSHED IT.
I WAS A VERY YOUNG CONGRESSMAN
WE HAD TROOPS IN LEBANON.
>> RONALD REAGAN TRIED TO KNOCK
OUT GADHAFI.
>> STAY ON ONE THING HERE.
IN LOBE NONE WHEN THEY WANTED TO
KEEP THE TROOPS THERE, PRESIDENT
REAGAN DID.
IT WAS SOON AFTER THAT WE
WITHDREW OUR TROOPS BECAUSE OF
THE BOMBING IN THE BARRACKS.
BUT REAGAN SENT A MESSAGE TO
GADHAFI WITH A MISSILE.
HE DIDN'T PUT TROOPS ON THE
GROUND.
IT GOT GADHAFI'S ATTENTION.
HE DISARMED HIS NUCLEAR
OPERATION.
ONE OTHER THING I POINTED OUT
TODAY THAT MAY HAVE BEEN LOST.
I'VE BEEN TALKING ABOUT GIVING
THE KIND OF SUPPORT WE NEED TO
THE PEOPLE IN AFGHANISTAN.
BUT I DON'T WANT TO STAY THERE
FOREVER.
GIVE THEM THE SUPPORT.
GIVE THEM THE AIR POWER THAT
THEY NEED.
LET THEM BE ABLE TO MANAGE ON
THE GROUND AND IN THE AIR.
BUT THE UNITED STATES SHOULD NOT
BE IN AFGHANISTAN FOR THE REST
OF OUR LIVES.
>> CAN THE U.S. EFFECT CHANGE IN
AFGHANISTAN WITHOUT HAVING A
PRESENCE ON THE GROUND?
>> I THINK THERE'S A WAY WE
COULD, IN FACT, BE ABLE TO DEAL
WITH TROUBLE WHEN THEY POP UP.
BUT TO HAVE A HUGE TROOP
PRESENCE THERE FOR A VERY LONG
TIME --
>> -- OR SPECIAL FORCES OR
SOMETHING LIKE THAT?
>> BUT YOU DON'T WANT TO SET A
TIM
TIMELINE.
THAT'S ANOTHER BIG MISTAKE.
CHRCHLTHS IS SOMETHING PRESIDENT
OBALLA DID EARLY ON.
>> AND THAT'S NOT SMART.
THAT'S WHY YOU HAVE TO
UNDERSTAND FOREIGN POLICY AND
HOW TO CONDUCT IT AND HOW TO
LEVERAGE THE SUPPORT YOU HAVE
AND HOW DO YOU BRING PEOPLE IN
AND MANAGE THESE.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT CUBA.
PRESIDENT OBAMA IS THERE.
YOU'VE BEEN CRITICAL OF THE
OPENING OF THE COMPANY.
R
UNDER YOUR PRESIDENCY, WOULD
COMPANIES BE FORCED OUT?
>> WE CAN'T EVEN MEET WITH THESE
LADIES WHO HAVE BEEN MARCHING
EVERY SINGLE SUNDAY TO ASK FOR
HUMAN RIGHTS AND PEOPLE TO BE --
THE PRESIDENT HASN'T EVEN
TOUCHED GROUND AND CASTRO IS
CRITICIZING THE UNITED STATES.
THE PRESIDENT SAYS WE'RE
COMMUNICATING.
>> HAS THAT SHIP SAILED?
BUSINESS IS GOING IN.
UNDER YOUR PRESIDENCY, WOULD YOU
TAKE IT OUT?
>> I'D HAVE TO THINK ABOUT
EXACTLY WHAT I WOULD DO.
BUT LET ME SAY ONE OTHER THING.
WE TALK ABOUT NATO.
IT'S ABSOLUTELY CREDITICAL THAT
THE PRESIDENT WORK WITH NATO NOW
SO THAT IF IRAN DOES VIOLATE
THAT NUCLEAR DEAL THAT HE PUT
TOGETHER THAT WE PUT THE
SANCTIONS BACK ON.
SOME PEOPLE SAY RIP IT UP RIGHT
NOW.
I'VE CALLED FOR A FREEZE ON THE
NUCLEAR DEAL BECAUSE OF THE
BALLISTIC MISSILE VIOLATIONS AND
VIOLATING THE SPIRIT OF THE
DEAL.
IF THEY VIOLATE THE DEAL IN
PRINCIPLE, WE WOULDN'T HAVE TO
WANT TO DO THIS ALONE.
WE'D WANT TO DO THIS WITH THE
EUROPEANS.
AND THE PROBLEM IS MONEY.
PEOPLE GO OVER, THEY MAKE MONEY.
AND THEN TIME COMES TO TAKE
ACTION AND WE PUT MONEY AHEAD OF
WHAT WE KNOW IS A SECURITY.
>> WHEN I ASKED YOU ABOUT NATO
AND TRUMP YOU SAID AS LEADER YOU
WOULDN'T SAY THAT KIND OF THING.
>> I'M NOT SAYING IT NOW.
>> AND YOU HAVE BEEN VERY
CAREFUL NOT TO DIRECTLY ATTACK
DONALD TRUMP.
>> HE'S DEAD WRONG ON NATO.
HE'S DEAD WRONG.
>> DO YOU THINK HE'S READY TO
BE --
>> THAT'S UP TO THE PEOPLE TO
DECIDE.
THAT GETS TO BE PERSONAL ABOUT
MY FEELINGS ABOUT HIS
COMPETENCE.
JUST LOOK AT HIS STATEMENTS.
I'M TELLING YOU WHAT I THINK
ABOUT IT.
AND TO SAY THAT WE NEED TO
WITHDRAW FROM NATO?
WE'RE NOT GOING TO --
>> HE'S NOT SAYING WITHDRAW.
HE'S SAYING LOWER --
>> WHAT DOES THAT MEAN?
WE NEED DEEPER RELATIONS.
IMAGINE WHEN THE FOLKS AT
CHARLIE WERE MURDERED, THE
MAGAZINE.
THEY HAD A SERVICE, A MILLION
PEOPLE IN SERVICE.
WE DIDN'T SEND ANYBODY.
WHAT ARE WE THINKING?
HOW DO WE DIS AN ALLY LIKE
ISRAEL AND NOT HAVE THE
PRESIDENT MEET WITH THE PRIME
MINISTER.
OR A RED LINE OR DUMPING GADHAFI
OUT.
THESE ARE THINGS THAT SOAK
CONFUSION IN THE FINDS OF NOT
ONLY OUR FRIENDS BUT OUR
ENEMIES.
>> LET'S TALK IMMIGRATION.
ARIZONA VOTES TOMORROW.
MAJOR ISSUE THERE, OBVIOUSLY,
IMMIGRATION.
THE LAST DEBATE YOU SAID YOU
COULD PASS A BILL TO PUT
UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS ON A
PATH TO LEGALIZATION IN YOUR
FIRST 100 DAYS IN OFFICE WHICH
PUTS YOU AT ODDS WITH THE TWO
REMAINING REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES.
BUT CLOSER TO HILLARY CLINTON
THAN YOU TOR THE REPUBLICANS.
>> RONALD REAGAN TRIED TO SOLVE
THIS PROBLEM.
WE NEVER FINISHED THE BORDER.
MY POSITION HAS BEEN CLEAR.
FINISH THE BORDER.
NO ONE COMES IN.
IF YOU TRY TO SNEAK IN, YOU'RE
GOING BACK.
GUEST WORKER PROGRAM, OKAY.
YOU'VE COME IN, WORK, GO BACK.
FOR THE 11.5 MILLION WHO ARE
HERE, IF THEY'VE NOT COMMITTED A
CRIME SINCE THEY'VE BEEN HERE,
THEY'LL PAY BACK TAXES, A FINE,
PROBABLY BE DELAYED IN TERMS OF
WHEN THEY CAN GET BENEFITS AND
THEY'LL BE LEGALIZED, NOT
CITIZENS.
THE NOTION THAT WE'LL GO INTO
HOMES AND GRAB PEOPLE OUT OF
THEIR HOMES WITH THEIR KIDS ON
THE FRONT PORCH CRYING, THIS
ISN'T GOING TO HAPPEN IN
AMERICA.
>> THERE WON'T BE A DEPORTATION
FORCE?
NO MATTER WHAT FRTRUMP OR OTHER
SAY?
>> IT'S NEVER HAPPENED.
THEY QUOTE THESE THINGS THAT ARE
NOT ACCURATE.
IF YOU HAVE A DEPORTATION ORDER
YOU'LL HAVE TO LEAVE.
THAT'S THE LAW IN AMERICA.
THE IDEA THAT WE'RE GOING TO GO
AROUND IN THE NEIGHBORHOODS
PICKING THESE PEOPLE UP IS JUST
NOT, FIRST OF ALL, NOT PRACTICAL
AND NOT THE WAY WE BEHAVE.
ARE WE JUST GOING TO YANK THEM
OUT, HANDCUFF THEM AND PUT THEM
IN A CAR, THEIR KIDS ARE THERE,
BREAKING UP FAMILIES?
THAT'S NOT -- I DIDN'T SAY IT
COULD PASS IN 100 DAYS.
I'LL GET THEM A PLAN IN 100 DAYS
COUPLED WITH THE ECONOMIC
CHANGES I WANT ON TAX CUTS AND
BALANCED BUDGETS AND COMMON
SENSE REGULATORY.
>> THERE'S A NEW CNN POLL OUT.
THE GOOD NEWS -- DO YOU LIKE
GOOD NEWS OR BAD NEWS FIRST?
>> I'M A BAD NEWS FIRST GUY BUT
I'LL GIVE YOU THE GOOD NEWS
FIRST.
THE ONLY REPUBLICAN THAT BEATS
HILLARY CLINTON IN A
HEAD-TO-HEAD MATCHUP.
51% TO 45%.
70% OF REPUBLICANS THINK YOU
SHOULD DROP OUT BECAUSE IT'S
IMPOSSIBLE FOR YOU TO WIN ENOUGH
DELEGATES TO BE THE PARTY'S
NOMINEE.
>> I DON'T THINK ANYBODY IS
GOING TO HAVE ENOUGH DELEGATES
TO WIN THE NOMINATION BEFORE THE
CONVENTION.
THIS IS GOING TO GO TO THE
IF I HADN'T WON OHIO AND TRUMP
HAD WON OHIO, HE'D BE THE
NOMINEE, BUT HE DIDN'T.
>> 70% OF REPUBLICANS WHO SAY
YOU SHOULD DROP OUT YOU SAY --
>> I DON'T KNOW WHO THEY ARE.
PEOPLE HAVE BEEN TELLING ME ALL
ALONG WHAT THE POLLS ARE AND
PUNDITS TELL ME WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN AND THEY'VE NEVER BEEN
WRONG.
I THINK GOD CREATED PUNDITS TO
MAKE ASTROLOGIERS LOOK GOOD.
I HAVE THE SKILL, THE
EXPERIENCE, THE VISION AND
RECORD TO FIX THE COUNTRY.
THAT LIKE REALLY MATTERS.
WE'RE GOING TO GET TO A
CONVENTION AND DELEGATES ARE
GOING TO THINK ABOUT WHO CAN
WIN?
I'M THE ONLY ONE THAT CAN WIN A
GERM ELECTION.
AND WHO CAN BE PRESIDENT?
I HAVE THE EXPERIENCE TO DO IT.
>> LAST WEEK YOU HAD GOVERNOR
ROMNEY CAMPAIGNING WITH YOU IN
OHIO.
DIDN'T ENDORSE YOU BUT URGING
PEOPLE IN OHIO TO VOTE FOR YOU.
A PROPONENT OF STRATEGIC VOTING.
HE IN UTAH AND ARIZONA HE'S PUT
OUTS THE ROBO CALL.
I WANT TO PLAY IT FOR YOU AND
GET YOU TO TALK ABOUT IT.
>> HELLO, THIS IS MITT ROMNEY.
I'M CALLING TO ASK YOU TO JOIN
ME IN SUPPORTING TED CRUZ FOR
PRESIDENT THIS TUESDAY IN THE
UTAH REPUBLICAN CAUCUSES.
THIS IS THE TIME FOR REPUBLICANS
ACROSS THE SPECTRUM TO UNITE
BEHIND TED.
HE IS THE ONLY REPUBLICAN
CANDIDATE WHO CAN DEFEAT DONALD
TRUMP.
AT THIS POINT, A VOTE FOR JOHN
KASICH IS A VOTE FOR DONALD
TRUMP.
>> CAMPAIGNING FOR YOU LAST WEEK
IN OHIO.
DOES IT MAKE ANY SENSE?
>> OF COURSE IT DOESN'T.
YOU COME OUT AND SAY HE'S GOT A
GREAT RECORD AND THE NEXT WEEK.
BUT LOOK.
IF HE SAYS TO VOTE FOR SOMEBODY
ELSE IS, YOU KNOW, A VOTE FOR
TRUMP OR WHATEVER.
YOU JUST READ THE POLLS.
I'M THE ONLY ONE THAT WINS THE
GENERAL.
ARE WE THINKING ABOUT -- I DON'T
GET THIS.
ARE WE THINKING ABOUT JUST WHAT
HAPPENS IN A REPUBLICAN PRIMARY?
WE HAVE TO WIN THE GENERAL
ELECTION AND BEAT HILLARY AND
HAVE SOMEBODY THAT HAS DOMESTUC
AND FOREIGN POLICY EXPERIENCE,
WHICH I HAVE.
>> SENATOR TED CRUZ, AND HE'LL
BE OUT HERE SHORTLY SAID IF YOU
WEREN'T IN THE RACE HE COULD GET
ENOUGH DELEGATES TO WIN AND YOU
ARE STAYING IN AS AN AUDITION TO
BE TRUMP'S VICE PRESIDENT.
WHAT DO YOU SAY?
>> THERE'S ZERO CHANCE I'D BE
VICE PRESIDENT WITH EITHER OF
THEM.
>> NO CHANCE?
>> ZERO.
BELOW ZERO, ACTUALLY.
AND SECONDLY --
>> WOULDN'T BE INTERESTED?
>> NOT INTERESTED.
AND SECONDLY, ANDERSON, IF I
HADN'T WON OHIO, TRUMP WOULD BE
THE NOMINEE RIGHT NOW.
PEOPLE FORGET THAT THEY WANTED
ME TO GET OUT AND GET BEHIND
MARCO.
GREAT GUY, BY THE WAY.
I DIDN'T.
LET ME JUST TELL YOU.
MY MESSAGE OF HOPE, MY MESSAGE
OF HOW WE CAN FIX THE PROBLEMS
OF INCOME INSECURITY, HOW WE CAN
FIX THE PROBLEM OF LACK OF WAGE
INCREASES AND WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN TO OUR CHILDREN IS A
VITAL MESSAGE.
>> SO CRUZ --
>> IT'S IMPORTANT FOR ME TO BE
OUT THERE TO HAVE THIS VOICE AND
THE VOICE OF MY TEAM HEARD
ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
>> WHEN CRUZ CALLS YOU A SPOILER
CANDIDATE YOU SAY --
>> THAT'S NAME CALLING.
THAT'S NAME CALLING.
DON'T NAME CALL.
>> JOHN BOEHNER, GOOD FRIEND OF
YOURS GOING BACK TO YOUR DAYS IN
CONGRESS, HE SAID IF WE DON'T
HAVE A NOMINEE WHO CAN WIN ON
THE FIRST BALLOT, I'M FOR NONE
OF THE ABOVE.
THEY ALL HAD A CHANCE TO WIN.
NONE OF THEM WON.
I'M FOR PAUL RYAN TO BE OUR
NOMINEE.
SHOULD HE --
>> HE WALKED THAT STATEMENT
BACK.
HE SAID HE WAS FOR ME.
>> HE DID?
>> YES.
SHOULD IT BE LIMITED TO SOMEONE
WHO RAN?
>> I'M NOT GOING TO TELL THE
DELEGATES WHAT TO DO ON THIS.
I'VE BEEN TO A CONVENTION IN
1976 WHEN DONALD REAGAN TOOK ON
AN INCUMBENT PRESIDENT, GERALD
FORD.
WE GOT TOGETHER THE DELEGATES.
THEY WERE EXTREMELY SERIOUS AS
THEY ALWAYS WILL BE.
AND THEY WILL MEASURE, BECAUSE
THEY'RE GOING TO BE POLITICAL
TYPES, LOCAL PARTY OFFICIALS,
FORMER MEMBERS OF CONGRESS,
MEMBERS OF THE LEGISLATURE.
THEY WILL TRY TO DECIDE WHO CAN
WIN IN THE FALL AND WHO CAN BE
PRESIDENT.
TODAY WHEN WE TALK ABOUT ALL
THIS PROCESS, IT'S ALL LIKE, WHO
IS GOING TO BE NOMINATED?
WE SHOULDN'T FORGET THE MOST
IMPORTANT THING.
WHO CAN LEAD THIS COUNTRY?
>> AT THE CONVENTION, DONALD
TRUMP SAID THERE COULD BE RIOTS
IF HE'S NOT MADE THE NOMINEE.
YOU ARE THE GOVERNOR OF OHIO.
THIS WOULD HAPPEN UNDER YOUR
WATCH.
ARE YOU PLANNING TO CALL OUT THE
OHIO NATIONAL GUARD JUST IN
CASE?
>> WE ALWAYS MANAGE EVENTS WHERE
WE THINK THERE COULD BE PROBLEMS
AS BEST WE CAN.
BUT THAT KIND OF LANGUAGE IS NOT
ACCEPTABLE.
IN ADDITION TO THAT --
>> NOT ACCEPTABLE FOR A LEADER
TO MAKE?
>> YEAH.
>> WHAT KIND OF LANGUAGE SHOULD
A LEADER SAY?
>> I WENT TO THE CONVENTION.
GAVE IT THE BEST I COULD AND
DIDN'T WIN.
GOD BLESS EVERYBODY HERE AND GOD
BLESS AMERICA.
AND LET'S GET BEHIND THE PERSON
THAT WON AND LET'S MOVE FORWARD
AND WIN THE WHITE HOUSE.
>> DO YOU THINK THAT ENCOURAGES
PEOPLE TO RIOT?
>> I DON'T THINK THAT KIND OF
LANGUAGE IS GOOD.
YOU DON'T THINK IT IS.
I KNOW YOU DON'T THINK IT IS.
NEITHER DO I.
NOR DO PEOPLE WHEN THEY HEAR IT.
IT'S NOT A HEAD SHAKE.
WE'RE RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA TO
BE THE LEADER OF THE WORLD, THE
COMMANDER IN CHIEF AND LEAD THIS
COUNTRY FORWARD.
WE HAVE TO BE BETTER THAN THAT
KIND OF LANGUAGE.
>> GOVERNOR JOHN KASICH, THANK
YOU.
>>> WE'RE GOING TO HEAR FROM
DONALD TRUMP SHORTLY.
NEXT IT'S SENATOR TED CRUZ'S
>>> WELCOME BACK TO OUR CNN
ELECTION SPECIAL.
THE FINAL FIVE CANDIDATES STILL
IN CONTENTION FOR THE NATION'S
HIGHEST OFFICE.
TEXAS SENATOR TED CRUZ IS WITH
ME RIGHT NOW.
SENATOR, THANKS FOR JOINING US.
>> THANK YOU FOR HAVING ME.
YOU'VE ATTACKED DONALD TRUMP IN
OUR APAIC SPEECH SUGGESTING HE'S
NOT PRO-ISRAEL ENOUGH.
THAT HE'S NOT NECESSARILY
AGAINST THE IRAN DEAL.
WHAT DO YOU BACK ANY OF THAT UP?
I LISTENED TO HIS SPEECH
CAREFULLY.
HE WAS AGAINST THE IRAN DEAL,
VERY PRO-ISRAEL.
WHAT DO YOU SAY?
>> IT'S INTERESTING.
YOU CAN LISTEN TO DONALD TRUMP
ON ANY GIVEN DAY AND HE CAN GIVE
YOU THREE DIFFERENT ANSWERS IN
THE COURSE OF THE DAY.
>> DID YOU LISTEN TO HIS SPEECH?
>> I LISTENED TO PART OF HIS
SPEECH.
>> WHAT DID YOU THINK?
>> I THINK IT WAS AN
IMPROVEMENT.
HE CLEARLY HIRED SOMEONE TO
WRITE THAT SPEECH FOR HIM.
THEY WERE DIFFERENT FROM WHAT HE
SAID IN THE COURSE OF THE
CAMPAIGN?
>> WHAT WAS DIFFERENT?
>> FOR EXAMPLE, HE SAID TWO
DEBATES AGO IF HE WERE PRESIDENT
HE WOULD BE, QUOTE, NEUTRAL
BETWEEN ISRAEL AND PALESTINE.
>> TO TRY TO NEGOTIATE A DEAL.
>> THAT GETS IT EXACTLY WRONG.
THAT SUGGESTS THAT HE BUYS INTO
THE MORAL EQUIVALENCY MANY IN
THE MEDIA PITCH.
IF YOU DON'T KNOW THE DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN YOUR FRIENDS AND
ENEMIES.
IF YOU THINK THE STATE OF ISRAEL
THAT IS DEFENDING ITSELF AGAINST
TERRORISM IS SOMEHOW MORALLY
EQUIVALENT TO TERRORISTS WHO ARE
MURDERING AMERICANS, MURDERING
ISRAELIS WHO ARE STRAPPING
DYNAMITE TO THEIR CHEST.
>> HE WAS NOT NEUTRAL IN THAT
SPEECH TODAY.
>> HE DIDN'T SAY THAT BUT DONALD
IS AN INTERESTING FELLOW BECAUSE
HE CAN SAY TOTALLY DIFFERENT
POLICY POSITIONS IN THE COURSE
OF A DAY FROM ONE END TO THE
OTHER.
BUT ON -- WITH RESPECT TO THE
IRAN DEAL ALSO IN THE DEBATES.
HE SAID, NO, HE'D NOT RIP UP THE
IRANIAN NUCLEAR DEAL.
INSTEAD, HE WOULD RENEGOTIATE
IT.
HE'D GET A BETTER DEAL.
ANYONE WHO SAYS THAT DOESN'T
UNDERSTAND THE AYATOLLAH
KHOMEINI.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT PEACE
NEGOTIATION IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
YOU'VE CRITICIZED TRUMP
SUGGESTING THERE'S NO DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN HIM AND HILLARY CLINTON,
THAT THEY BOTH WANT TO NEGOTIATE
A PEACE DEAL.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH NEGOTIATING A
PEACE DEAL?
>> NOTHING IS WRONG WITH
NEGOTIATING A PEACE DEAL IF THE
PALESTINIANS WILL COME AND SEEK
PEACE.
THE BARRIER TO PEACE IS NOT
ISRAEL.
ISRAEL WANTS PEACE, HAS WANTED
PEACE EVERY DAY OF ITS
EXISTENCE.
THE BARRIER IS THE PALESTINIANS.
>> SO WHAT DO THE PALESTINIANS
NEED TO DO IN ORDER FOR YOU AS
PRESIDENT TO NEGOTIATE A PEACE
AGREEMENT?
>> LOOK, IN ORDER FOR THERE TO
BE A PEACE AGREEMENT, THE
PALESTINIANS NEED TO ACKNOWLEDGE
ISRAEL'S RIGHT TO EXIST AS A
JEWISH STATE.
>> THEY'VE ACKNOWLEDGED THAT.
THE PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY HAS
ACKNOWLEDGED A TWO-STATE
SOLUTION.
>> BUT THEY DO NOT ACKNOWLEDGE
ISRAEL'S RIGHT TO XUFT AS A
JEWISH STATE.
THE PALESTINIAN AUTHORITY IS IN
A SO-CALLED UNITY GOVERNMENT
WITH HAMAS.
A TERRORIST ORGANIZATION.
THE PA CELEBRATES WHEN
TERRORISTS MURDER.
AN AMERICAN TEXAN JUST RECENTLY
MURDERED BY A PALESTINIAN
TERRORIST.
THE P.A. CELEBRATES THAT AND
COMPENSATE THE FAMILIES OF THE
TERRORIST FOR MURDERING INNOCENT
AMERICANS.
>> SO IF THE PALESTINIANS SAY
THEY ACCEPT ISRAEL'S RIGHT TO
EXIST AS A JEWISH STATE --
>> AND THEY HAVE TO RENOUNCE
TERRORISM.
STOP INCITING TERRORISM.
STOP PAYING THE FAMILIES OF
TERRORISTS.
>> I'M HAPPY TO TRY TO BROKER A
DEAL FROM THE BEGINNING, BUT THE
DIFFERENCE IS YOU NEED A
PRESIDENT WHO STANDS WITH ISRAEL
WHO DOESN'T ACCEPT THIS MORAL
EQUIVALENCE THAT THE
PALESTINIANS ARE SOMEHOW THE
SAME AS THE ISRAELIS WHEN THE
P.A. IS CELEBRATING TERRORISTS
MURDERING WOMEN AND CHILDREN.
IT'S NOT A MORAL EQUIVALENCE AND
IT'S THE SAME -- WHAT DONALD
TRUMP DOES IS THE SAME THING
HILLARY CLINTON DOES.
WHEN HAMAS WAS RAINING ROCKETS
ON TO ISRAEL AND HAMAS WAS
KEEPING THEIR MISSILES IN
ELEMENTARY SCHOOLS, HILLARY
CLINTON GAVE AN INTERVIEW WHERE
SHE SAID YOU HAVE TO UNDERSTAND,
GAZA IS REALLY SMALL.
THEY DON'T HAVE ANY OTHER PLACE
TO PUT THEM.
>> WHEN DID TRUMP SAY THAT?
>> THAT'S HILLARY CLINTON.
>> YOU SAID THEY'RE THE SAME.
>> THEY BOTH ACCEPT THE MORAL
EQUIVALENCE AND REFUSE TO
ACKNOWLEDGE HOW THEY ARE
DIFFERENT.
>> WHAT WAS STRIKING IN TRUMP'S
SPEECH HE REFERRED TO PALESTINE
WHICH WAS JUST VERY ODD.
PALESTINE HADN'T EXISTED SINCE
1948, AND IT WAS CLEARLY A
SPEECH WHERE, YOU KNOW, ONE OF
THE CHALLENGES WITH FOREIGN
POLICY IS THAT DONALD'S
KNOWLEDGE OF THE WORLD IS VERY
LIMITED.
AT A CNN DEBATE, HUGH HEWITT
ASKED HIM ABOUT --
>> LET'S GET BACK TO THE MIDDLE
EAST.
WE'LL TALK ABOUT THE TRIAD
ANOTHER TIME.
LET'S TALK ABOUT THE MIDDLE
EAST.
YOU WANT TO MOVE THE U.S.
EMBASSY FROM TEL AVIV TO
JERUSALEM AND YOU'D START THE
PROCESS ON DAY ONE.
>> YES.
>> PRESIDENT REAGAN SAID THE
SAME THING.
HE WANTS TO MOVE THE EMBASSY.
BOTH PRESIDENT BUSHS SAID THE
SAME THING.
WHEN THEY TOOK OFFICE, THEY
DIDN'T DO IT CITING SECURITY
CONCERNS.
WHY DO YOU THINK YOU WOULD BE
DIFFERENT?
>> I WILL DO WHAT I SAY.
WE WILL MOVE THE EMBASSY TO
JERUSALEM.
AND YOU'RE RIGHT.
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS HAVE
SAID THIS FOR YEAR AFTER YEAR
AFTER YEAR.
AND IT'S ACTUALLY U.S. LAW.
IN EVERY OTHER COUNTRY ON
EARTH --
>> BUT THERE IS A WAIVER IN
THERE.
EVERY SIX MONTHS THE PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES CAN SIGN A
WAIVER SAYING I'M NOT DOING IT
FOR NATIONAL SECURITY.
EVERY PRESIDENT HAS DONE THAT.
>> WE'VE HAD PRESIDENTS WHO HAVE
EXERCISED THEIR WAIVER.
TODAY AT AIPAC, HILLARY CLINTON
AND DONALD TRUMP PROMISED TO
MOVE THE EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM.
EVERYONE WATCHING THEM KNOWS IF
THEY GET INTO THE WHOURKS
THEY'LL EXERCISE THE WAIVER AND
WON'T MOVE IT TO JERUSALEM.
HILLARY'S HUSBAND BILL CLINTON,
THAT'S WHAT HE DID IS EXERCISE
THE WAIVER.
THE DIFFERENCE IS WHEN I SAY I'M
GOING TO DO SOMETHING, I DO IT.
>> IRRESPECTIVE OF THE
CONSEQUENCES, THE ANG TER WOULD
GENERATE, THE SECURITY CONCERNS
IT COULD CAUSE THE DIPLOMATIC
REPERCUSSIONS FROM THE REST OF
THE ARAB WORLD.
>> THE DIFFERENCE IS WHEN I SAY
IT, I SAY IT TAKING THE
CONSEQUENCES INTO ACCOUNT.
IT'S NOT JUST EMPTY CAMPAIGN
RHETORIC.
BUT RATHER ON DAY ONE, BEGINNING
THE PROCESS OF MOVING THE
EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM, SENDS A
MESSAGE BOTH TO OUR FRIENDS AND
ALLIES.
TO OUR FRIENDS FOR SEVEN YEARS
THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION HASN'T
STOOD WITH US.
LET ME EXPLAIN THIS.
THIS IS IMPORTANT.
WE HAVE BEEN ABANDONING AND
ALIENATING OUR FRIENDS AND
ALLIES.
MOVING THE EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM
MAKES A STATEMENT THAT AMERICA
IS BACK.
AND IT ALSO MAKES A STATEMENT TO
THE ENEMIES, YES, MANY IN THE
ARAB WORLD WOULD BE VERY UPSET.
IRAN WILL BE FURIOUS AT MOVING
THE EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM.
AND IT MAKES A STATEMENT TO THE
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISTS WHO
WANT TO KILL US THAT AMERICA
WILL STAND UP TO THEM.
THE ERA OF APPEASEMENT IS OVER.
>> TODAY DONALD TRUMP SUGGESTED
THAT THE U.S. SHOULD RECONSIDER
ITS ROLE IN NATO DIMINISH THAT
ROLE, STOP SPENDING ALL THAT
MONEY FOR NATO COMMITMENTS.
DO YOU AGREE?
>> I DON'T.
I FOUND HIS REMARKS REALLY QUITE
ASTONISHING.
>> WHY?
>> TO SUGGEST HE'D VOLUNTARILY
WEAKEN NATO EITHER WITHDRAW
AMERICA FROM NATO OR DECREASE
OUR INVOLVEMENT FROM --
>> HE DIDN'T SAY WITHDRAW.
HE SAID DECREASE.
>> HE WASN'T CLEAR ON THE
DETAILS.
>> GERMANY HAS MORE OF AN
INTEREST THERE THAN THE UNITED
STATES.
>> DONALD IN ALL LIKELIHOOD HAS
NO AWAIRNESS WITH NTHIS.
UKRAINE USED TO BE THE THIRD
LARGEST NUCLEAR COUNTRY ON THE
FACE OF THE EARTH.
UKRAINE VOLUNTARILY GAVE UP ITS
NUCLEAR WEAPONS BECAUSE THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA CAME IN
AND SAID IF YOU HAND OVER THOSE
NUCLEAR WEAPONS, WE WILL ENSURE
YOUR TERRITORIAL INTEGRITY FROM
RUSSIA.
WE MADE A COMMITMENT.
THEN THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION
HAS BROKEN ITS WORD.
WHAT NATION ON EARTH THAT HAS
NUKES WOULD EVER VOLUNTARILY
GIVE IT UP AGAIN?
I BET YOU DOLLARS TO DOUGHNUTS
DONALD TRUMP HAS NO KNOWLEDGE
ABOUT ANY OF THAT.
HE'S NOT FOCUSOD PROTECTING US
AGAINST NUCLEAR WAR.
AND IT HAS BEEN RUSSIA'S
OBJECTIVE, PUTIN'S OBJECTIVE FOR
DECADES TO BREAK NATO.
TO BREAK IT APART.
>> HE SAYS IT'S A U.S. PROBLEM.
GERMANY AND OTHER NATO ALLIES
HAVE A BIGGER INTEREST THAN THE
UNITED STATES.
>> THAT IS SO --
>> THE MONEY THAT COULD BE SPENT
HERE AS OPPOSED TO OVER THERE.
>> THAT'S HOPELESSLY NAIVE.
WHAT DONALD TRUMP IS SAYING IS
THAT HE WOULD UNILATERALLY
SURRENDER TO RUSSIA AND PUTIN.
GIVE PUTIN A MASSIVE FOREIGN
POLICY VICTORY BY BREAKING NATO
AND ABANDONING EUROPE.
THAT'S GOING BACKWARDS.
YOU KNOW WHO WOULD AGREE WITH
THAT?
BARACK OBAMA.
TRUMP'S POLICY IDEA IS ENTIRELY
CONSISTENT WITH OBAMA
WITHDRAWING FROM --
>> WITHDRAWING FROM WHERE?
>> EUROPE.
WHEN YOU SAW LEADERS OF THE
WORLD MARCHING WITH PARIS AND
SINGULARLY ABSENT WAS AMERICA.
OBAMA WASN'T THERE.
KERRY WASN'T THERE.
NOBODY WAS THERE.
THAT REFLECTS OBAMA'S LEADING
FROM BEHIND.
TRUMP'S FOREIGN POLICY IS THE
OBAMA/HILLARY LEADING FROM
BEHIND.
HE SAID WE NEED TO WITHDRAW FROM
THE WHOLE WORLD.
THIS IS A DANGEROUS WORLD.
IF AMERICA WITHDRAWS WE GET THE
CHAOS OBAMA/CLINTON HAS
PRODUCED.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT YOUR
NATIONAL SECURITY ADVISERS.
YOU RELEASED A LIST OF YOUR
FOREIGN POLICY ADVISERS.
FRANK APNEY WAS ON THAT LIST.
FORMER DEPUTY SECRETARY OF
DEFENSE.
HE SAID MR. OBAMA SAY MUSLIM.
THE MUSLIM BROTHERHOOD PLACED
OPERATIVES THROUGHOUT THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
THAT SADDAM HUSSEIN PROBABLY WAS
BEHIND THE OKLAHOMA CITY
BOMBING.
THAT CHRIS CHRISTIE MAY HAVE
BEEN COMPLICIT IN TREASON BY
APPOINTING A MUSLIM AMERICAN TO
NEW JERSEY'S STATE JUDICIARY.
IS THIS SOMEONE WHOSE VIEWS YOU
AGREE WITH?
>> WOLF, I RECOGNIZE THAT FOLKS
IN THE MEDIA GET REALLY NERVOUS
WHEN YOU ACTUALLY CALL OUT
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
FRANK GAFFNEY IS SOMEONE I
RESPECT.
HE'S A SERIOUS THINKER WHO HAS
BEEN FOCUSED ON FIGHTING
JIHADISM.
FIGHTING JIHADISM ACROSS THE
GLOBE.
AND HE'S ENDURED ATTACKS FROM
THE LEFT, FROM THE MEDIA BECAUSE
HE SPEAKS OUT AGAINST RADICAL
ISLAMIC TERRORISM AND SPEAKS OUT
AGAINST, FOR EXAMPLE, THE
POLITICAL CORRECTNESS OF THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION THAT
EFFECTIVELY GETS IN BED WITH THE
MUSLIM BROTHERHOOD.
IT'S A TERRORIST ORGANIZATION.
>> WHEN HE SAID IN 2009 BARACK
HUSSEIN OBAMA WOULD HAVE TO BE
CONSIDERED AMERICA'S FIRST
MUSLIM PRESIDENT.
DO YOU AGREE WITH HIM ON THAT?
>> I DON'T KNOW WHAT HE SAID IN
2009.
>> I READ TO YOU THE QUOTE.
>> I DON'T HAVE THE FULL QUOTE.
HERE'S EVERY QUOTE, EVERY PERSON
SUPPORTING YOU, DO YOU AGREE
WITH EVERY STATEMENT.
THAT'S SILLINESS.
HERE'S MY VIEW.
WE NEED A COMMANDER IN CHIEF
THAT DEFENDS AMERICA.
AND DEFENDING AMERICA MEANS
DEFEATING RADICAL ISLAMIC TRUMP
AND DEFEATING ISIS.
WHAT IS COMPLETELY UNREASONABLE
IS BARACK OBAMA AND HILLARY
CLINTON'S CONSISTENT PATTERN OF
REFUSING TO EVEN SAY THE WORDS
RADICAL ISLAMIC TERRORISM.
WHEN WE SEE A TERROR ATTACK --
LET ME FINISH THIS POINT.
WHEN WE SEE A TERROR ATTACK IN
PARIS AND SAN BERNARDINO AND
PRESIDENT OBAMA SAYS, GOSH, I
DIDN'T REALIZE PEOPLE WERE
UPSET.
I GUESS I WASN'T WATCHING THE
CABLE NEWS AND THEN GIVES A
NATIONAL TV CONFERENCE WHERE HE
DOESN'T CALL OUT RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISTS BUT INSTEAD LECTURES
AMERICANS ON ISLAM PHOBIA.
WE NEED A COMMANDER IN CHIEF
KEEPING US SAFE.
>> I WANT TO BE PRECISE.
>> PEOPLE ARE FED UP WITH THIS
SILLINESS.
>> WOULD HE BE CONSIDERED YOUR
NATIONAL SECURITY ADVISER?
>> FRANK IS ONE OF A NUMBER OF
PEOPLE PART OF THE TEAM ADVISING
ME.
I APPRECIATE HIS GOOD COUNSEL.
>> SO THESE STATEMENT OOZE.
>> FRANK HAS BEEN LEADING THE
EFFORT TO FOCUS ON THE THREAT OF
AN ELECTRO MAGNETIC PULSE WHICH
WOULD BE A NUCLEAR WEAPON
DETONATED IN THE ATMOSPHERE THAT
COULD TAKE DOWN OUR ELECTRICAL
GRID.
COULD KILL TENS OF MILLIONS OF
AMERICANS.
AND ALL IRAN WOULD HAVE TO DO IS
FIRE ONE NUKE INTO THE
ATMOSPHERE.
THEY JUST NEED TO GET IT ABOVE
THE EASTERN SEABOARD AND THEY
COULD KILL TENS OF MILLIONS.
THAT IS VALUABLE WORK.
AND I'M CUR YURKS WOLF.
WHEN DOES THE MEDIA FOCUS ON
THREATS LIKE AN EMP?
>> WE FOCUS ON A LOT OF THAT.
HE SAYS THERE'S ON SOME
COMPELLING CIRCUMSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE OF SADDAM HUSSEIN'S
IRAQ BEING INVOLVED WITH THE
PEOPLE WHO PERPETRATED THE 1993
ATTACK ON THE WORLD TRADE CENTER
AND EVEN THE OKLAHOMA CITY
BOMBING.
YOU ARE A SMART GUY.
HAVE YOU SEEN ANY CIRCUMSTANTIAL
EVIDENCE TO BACK THAT UP?
>> I AM NOT GOING TO PLAY THE
GOTCHA GAME OF EVERY QUOTE EVERY
ADVISER MAY HAVE GIVEN.
YOU ARE WELCOME TO THROW THEM
OUT.
>> THAT WAS IN 2009.
>> I'M INTERESTED IN TALKING
ABOUT THE PROBLEMS IN THIS
COUNTRY.
THIS IS SILLINESS.
LET'S FOCUS ON REAL PROBLEMS
FACING AMERICA.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT CUBA.
>> GREAT.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA IS IN CUBA
RIGHT NOW.
YOU ARE A CUBAN AMERICAN AS WE
ALL KNOW.
YOU'VE SAID YOU WOULD SHUT DOWN
THE U.S. EMBASSY IN CUBA IF
ELECTED PRESIDENT.
WOULD YOU ALSO TERM NAT WHAT
U.S. BUSINESSES ARE NOW DOING IN
CUBA IMMEDIATELY UPON TAKING
OFFICE?
>> I WOULD ENFORCE THE LAW.
AND FEDERAL LAW PROHIBITS DOING
BUSINESS WITH CUBA.
AND THERE'S A REASON FOR THIS.
TO UNDERSTAND WHAT OBAMA IS
DOING IN CUBA YOU HAVE TO PUT IT
IN BROADER CONTEXT.
TODAY OBAMA IS THERE IN CUBA
WITH MOVIE STARS AND ROCK STARS.
AND THE FAR LEFT HAS ALWAYS
GLAMORIZED THE CASTROS IN CUBA.
THEY ARE CHIC AND GEVARA WAS
SUCH A YOUNG LOOKING
REVOLUTIONARY.
A HOMICIDAL MANIAC WHO TORTURED
PEOPLE.
BUT HE LOOKED GOOD.
AND AS BARACK OBAMA IS SITTING
THERE SIPPING MOJITOS WITH
BRUTAL COMMUNIST DICTATORS, HE
CAN'T BE BOTHERS TO MEET THE
DISSIDENTS OR VISIT WITH THE
LADIES IN WHITE OR HEAR THE
SCREAMS OF OPPRESSION.
AND WHAT OBAMA IS DOING IN CUBA
IS VERY MUCH THE SAME AS WHAT
HE'S DOING IN IRAN.
HE'S GIVING OVER $100 BILLION TO
THE AYATOLLAH KHOMEINI, THE
WORLD'S LEADING STATE SPONSOR OF
TERRORISM WHO CHANTS DEATH TO
AMERICA.
AND CUBA HE'S GIVING BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS TO THE CASTROS.
COMMUNIST DICTATORS --
>> YOU'D REVERSE ALL OF THAT?
>> WE SHOULD BE STANDING UP TO
ENEMIES OF AMERICA AND SHOULDN'T
GIVE BILLIONS OF DOLLARS TO
PEOPLE WHO HATE US AND WANT TO
KILL US.
THIS IS NOT --
>> THE CUBAN PEOPLE DON'T HATE
US.
>> HE'S GIVING THE MONEY --
>> BUT THE CUBAN PEOPLE WILL BEN
PUT IT FROM ALL THIS INVESTMENT
COMING IN.
>> NO, THEY WON'T.
IF YOU LOOK AT CUBA.
EVERY DOLLAR GOES TO THE
GOVERNMENT.
AND WHAT THIS WILL DO IS IT WILL
STRENGTHEN THE REPRESSIVE REGIME
OF FIDEL AND RAUL CASTRO.
IT WILL INCREASE CUBA SPREADING
TERRORISM THROUGHOUT LATIN
AMERICA AND ANTI-AMERICANISM.
MY FAMILY HAS FURSTHAND
EXPERIENCE WITH THIS.
MY DAD WAS IMPRISONED AND
TORTURED BY BATISTA IN CUBA.
AND MY TIA SONIA WAS IMPRISONED
BY CASTRO'S GOONS.
AND A COUPLE OF YEARS AGO, I HAD
THE PRIVILEGE OF MEETING WITH
SHARANSKY, THE FAMED DISSIDENT.
DESCRIBED HOW IN THE GULOG WHEN
RAUGAN WAS PRESIDENT, THAT THEY
WOULD PASS FROM CELL TO CELL
NOTES.
DID YOU HEAR WHAT PRESIDENT
REAGAN SAID?
EVIL EMPIRE.
ASH HEAP OF HISTORY.
TEAR DOWN THIS WALL.
THERE IS POWER TO THE PRESIDENT
STANDING UP AND SPEAKING THE
TRUTH TO EVIL.
AND WHAT THIS PRESIDENT DOES IS
EXACTLY THE OPPOSITE.
HE ABANDONS OUR FRIENDS AND
SHOWS WEAKNESS AND APPEASEMENT
AND GIVES BILLIONS TO OUR
ENEMIES WHO HATE US.
IT'S EXACTLY BACKWARDS.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT MIRACLES.
>> OKAY.
>> YOU SAID TODAY THERE IS PROOF
THAT THE GOD OF ABRAHAM,U ZACH
AND JACOB STILL PRODUCE
MIRACLES.
LINDSEY GRAHAM HELD A
FUND-RAISER FOR YOU HERE IN
WASHINGTON.
THAT'S A PRETTY BIG MIRACLE.
>> JUST A FEW WEEKS AGO HE WAS
OPENLY CALLING FOR MY MURDER, SO
THAT'S A REMARKABLE THING.
LISTEN, I LIKE LINDSEY.
HE'S GOT A WONDERFUL SENSE OF
HUMOR.
HE'S A PASSIONATE SUPPORTER OF
ISRAEL.
AND LINDSEY REFLECTS HE'S PART
OF WHAT WE'RE SEEING MORE
BROADLY ACROSS THE COUNTRY.
WE'RE SEEING REPUBLICANS UNITING
BEHIND THIS CAMPAIGN, COMING
TOGETHER.
WE'RE SEEING REPUBLICANS -- THE
FULL SPECTRUM FROM LINDSEY
GRAHAM AND MITT ROMNEY TO MIKE
LEE AND MARK LEVIN.
NOW THAT'S A BROAD SPECTRUM
ACROSS THE FULL COALITION OF
REPUBLICANS ARE UNITING BEHIND
OUR CAMPAIGN.
OUR CAMPAIGN IS THE ONLY
CAMPAIGN THAT HAS REPEATEDLY
BEATEN AND THAT CAN AND WILL
BEAT DONALD TRUMP.
>> ONE REPUBLICAN NOT ON THAT
LIST IS A REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL FRONT-RUNNER.
LISTEN TO WHAT HE SAID ABOUT YOU
OVER THE WEEKEND.
>> HE WAS BORN IN CANADA, LIVED
THERE FOUR YEARS.
HE WAS A CITIZEN OF CANADA 15 OR
16 MONTHS AGO.
HE WAS A CITIZEN OF CANADA.
CAN YOU BELIEVE IT?
HE BECAME A UNITED STATES
SENATOR AND THEN SAID, I DIDN'T
KNOW I WAS A CITIZEN OF CANADA.
LYING TED.
HE DIDN'T KNOW.
ONE OF THE BIGGEST LIARS I'VE
EVER SEEN IN MY LIFE.
I REALLY MEAN IT.
HE WALKS IN, THE EVANGELICALS
ARE WITH ME BECAUSE THEY KNOW
ONE THING ABOUT ME.
I'M NOT A LIAR.
BUT TED CRUZ WALKS IN, BIBLE
HIGH, BIBLE HIGH, PUTS IT DOWN
AND HE STARTS LYING.
>> ALL RIGHT.
YOUR RESPONSE.
>> LISTEN, EVERY TIME DONALD
GETS SCARED, HE BEGINS LASHING
OUT, ATTACKING.
HE BEGINS INSULTING, YELLING.
OFTEN BEGINS CURSING.
I'M SURPRISED HE DIDN'T CURSE IN
THAT PARTICULAR RIFF.
THAT WILL CHANGE.
AND, YOU KNOW, I WILL SAY THIS.
DONALD'S CAMPAIGN, HIS ENTIRE
CAMPAIGN IS BUILT ON A LIE.
I UNDERSTAND THE PEOPLE WHO ARE
SUPPORTING HIM.
>> WHAT'S THE LIE?
>> LET ME EXPLAIN.
I UNDERSTAND THE PEOPLE
SUPPORTING DONALD.
THEY ARE FRUSTRAITTED WITH
WASHINGTON.
WITH POLITICIANS IN BOTH PARTIES
THAT HAVE BEEN LYING TO US THAT
MAKE PROMISES AND GO TO
WASHINGTON AND DO THE EXACT
OPPOSITE OF WHAT THEY SAID.
BUT IF YOU ARE FED UP WITH
WASHINGTON, WITH THE CORRUPTION
OF WASHINGTON, THEN IT DOESN'T
MAKE ANY SENSE TO SUPPORT DONALD
TRUMP WHO HAS BEEN IMMESHED IN
THE CORRUPTION OF WASHINGTON.
THE LIE BEHIND DONALD'S CAMPAIGN
IS THAT HE'LL STAND UP TO
WASHINGTON.
HE IS THE SYSTEM.
DONALD TRUMP AND HILLARY CLINTON
ARE FLIP SIDES OF THE SAME COIN.
DONALD TRUMP HAS MADE BILLIONS
BUYING INFLUENCE IN WASHINGTON.
HILLARY CLINTON HAS MADE
MILLIONS SELLING INFLUENCE IN
WASHINGTON.
AND DONALD TRUMP HAS SUPPORTED
LIBERAL DEMOCRATIC POLITICIANS
FOR 40 YEARS FROM JIMMY CARTER
TO JOHN KERRY TO JOE BIDEN,
CHUCK SCHUMER, HARRY REID AND
HILLARY CLINTON AS A
PRESIDENTIAL CAMPAIGN.
AND DONALD TRUMP HAS ENRICHED
HIMSELF USING GOVERNMENT POWER.
AND IN EVERY INSTANCE, DONALD
BELIEVES GOVERNMENT IS THE
SOLUTION.
WHETHER IT WAS SUPPORTING THE
WALL STREET BAILOUT, WHICH HE
DID.
HE SUPPORTED OBAMA'S BAILOUT.
SUPPORTING THE OBAMA STIMULUS
PLAN.
OR USING EMINENT DOMAIN TO TAKE
THE HOMES OF LITTLE OLD LADIES
OR TO TRY TO DO SO IN ORDER TO
BUILD A PARKING LOT FOR HIS
CASINOS.
>> EVEN THOUGH HE CALLS YOU
LYING TED, YOU'VE JUST HEARD IT
RIGHT THERE, I ASKED HIM IF HE
MIGHT CONSIDER YOU AS HIS VICE
PRESIDENTIAL RUNNING MATE IF HE
GETS THE REPUBLICAN NOMINATION.
AND HE SAID CRAZIER THINGS
HAPPEN IN POLITICS.
HERE'S THE QUESTION.
ARE YOU OPEN TO BEING HIS VICE
PRESIDENTIAL RUNNING MATE?
>> I HAVE ZERO INTEREST
WHATSOEVER IN THIS.
AND LISTEN, IF DONALD TRUMP IS
THE NOMINEE, IT'S A DISASTER.
HILLARY WINS.
DONALD MAY BE THE ONLY CANDIDATE
ON THE FACE OF THE PLANET THAT
HILLARY CLINTON CAN BEAT IN A
GENERAL ELECTION.
AND THE STAKES ARE TOO HIGH.
IF YOU ARE FED UP WITH ILLEGAL
IMGRAGS, DONALD TRUMP FUNDED THE
GANG OF EIGHT THAT PUSHED THE
MASSIVE AMNESTY PLAN.
I LED THE OPPOSITION TO IT.
IF YOU ARE FED UP WITH WAGES
BEING DRIVEN DOWN BY ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION, DONALD TRUMP HAS
SUPPORTED OPEN BORDER DEMOCRATS
FOR 40 YEARS.
AND IF YOU ARE UNHAPPY WITH THE
ECONOMIC STAGNATION, WITH THE
JOB LOSS CAUSED BY OBAMACARE,
DONALD TRUMP FUNDED HARRY REID
AND NANCY PELOSI TAKING OVER THE
CONGRESS WHICH LED TO OBAMACARE.
>> SO FAR ABOUT HALF THE STATES
HAVE VOTED IN REPUBLICAN
PRIMARIES AND CAUCUSES.
HE HAS 2 MILLION MORE VOTES THAN
YOU HAVE.
PEOPLE HAVE SPOKEN.
>> THE PEOPLE HAVE SPOKEN.
N WHAT THEY HAVE SAID, WE
STARTED WITH 17 CANDIDATES.
IT WAS A WONDERFUL DIVERSE,
TALENTED, YOUNG DYNAMIC FIELD.
IT'S NOW NARROWED.
THIS IS EFFECTIVELY A TWO-PERSON
RACE.
ONLY TWO CANDIDATES WITH ANY
PLAUSIBLE PATH TO WINNING THE
NOMINATION AND GETTING 1,237, ME
AND DONALD TRUMP.
>> IF HE GETS CLOSE AND YOU ARE
MUCH FURTHER BEHIND AND HE HAS
MILLIONS MORE VOTES, DO YOU
THINK HE SHOULD GET THE
NOMINATION?
>> MY OBJECT SUFFICIENT TO WIN
1,237 DELEGATES.
>> LET'S SAY YOU DON'T --
>> THE HYPOTHETICAL YOU'RE
GIVING IS TOTALLY FANCIFUL NOD
NOT GOING TO HAPPEN.
ONE OF TWO SCENARIOS.
I BELIEVE WE'RE GOING TO WIN
1,237 DELEGATES BEFORE THE
CONVENTION.
THE SECOND OUTCOME FAR MORE
LIKELY IS NOBODY GETS TO 1,237
AND WE GO TO THE CONVENTION WITH
DONALD HAVING A BUNCH OF
DELEGATES AND ME HAVING A BUNCH
OF DELEGATES.
AND WE'LL BE NECK AND NECK.
THE CONVENTION IS GOING TO
DECIDE.
THEY'RE NOT GOING TO DO WHAT
PEOPLE IN WASHINGTON WANT WHICH
IS BRING IN A WHITE HORSE WHO
WASN'T ON THE BALLOT, WASN'T
RUNNING.
THAT'S NOT GOING TO HAPPEN.
THE DELEGATES ARE GOING TO
DECIDE BETWEEN DONALD AND ME.
IF WE GO IN WITH A BUNCH OF
DELEGATES EACH, I BELIEVE WE WIN
THAT AND WIN THAT BY EARNING THE
SUPPORT OF THE DELEGATES ELECTED
THROUGH THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS.
>> A POLITICO REPORT SAYING YOUR
CAMPAIGN, THE CRUZ CAMPAIGN, IS
EXPLORING THE POSSIBILITY OF
FORMING A UNITY TICKET WITH
MARCO RUBIO.
YOU ARE SMILING, LAUGHING.
THAT YOU HAD CONSIDERED THAT
POSSIBILITY.
>> LISTEN.
PEOPLE WRITE ALL SORTS OF THINGS
IN THE MEDIA.
>> IS IT TRUE?
>> I HAVEN'T HAD ANY
CONVERSATION WITH MARCO ABOUT
THAT.
THAT IS NOT ACCURATE.
OUR STAFF HASN'T HAD ANY
CONVERSATION WITH MARCO'S STAFF.
A LOT OF PEOPLE HAVE SUGGESTED
THAT MARCO AND I SHOULD JOIN
FORCES.
I THINK VERY, VERY HIGHLY OF
MARCO.
HE'S A FRIEND.
HE'S TALENTED.
INCREDIBLE COMMUNICATOR.
AND HE INSPIRED MILLIONS IN THIS
CAMPAIGN.
AND WHAT WE ARE SEEING RIGHT NOW
IS THE OVERWHELMING MAJORITY OF
THE RUBIO SUPPORTERS ARE COMING
TO SUPPORT --
>> SOUNDS LIKE YOU THINK THAT
COULD BE A GOOD IDEA.
>> WE WELCOME MARCO'S SUPPORTERS
WITH OPEN ARMS, AND I WOULD
ENTHUSIASTICALLY WELCOME MARCO'S
SUPPORT.
I THINK VERY, VERY HIGHLY OF
HIM.
BUT WHAT WE'RE SEEING, THAT IS A
MANIFESTATION AND I WOULD
ENTHUSIASTICALLY WELCOME JOHN
KASICH'S SUPPORT.
WE'RE SEEN REPUBLICANS COME
TOGETHER.
65% TO 70% OF REPUBLICANS
RECOGNIZE THAT DONALD TRUMP
WOULD BE A DISASTER.
THAT HE LOSES TO HILLARY.
IF HILLARY WINS, WE LOSE THE
SUPREME COURT FOR A GENERATION,
LOSE THE BILL OF RIGHTS AND OUR
KIDS ARE BURRREYED IN TRILLIONS
MORE DEBT.
>> IF TRUMP IS THE NOMINEE, WILL
YOU SUPPORT HIM?
>> I'VE SAID MANY TIMES, YES.
THAT'S A COMMITMENT I MADE.
AS WE STARTOD MOVING THE EMBASSY
TO JERUSALEM.
WHEN I SAY I'M GOING TO DO
SOMETHING, I DO EXACTLY WHAT I
SAID.
BUT LET ME BE CLEAR.
DONALD TRUMP IS NOT GOING TO BE
THE NOMINEE BECAUSE THAT HANDS
THE GENERAL ELECTION TO HILLARY.
OUR CAMPAIGN IS THE ONLY ONE
THAT'S BEATEN HIM NUN TIMES ALL
OVER THE COUNTRY AND WE'RE
SEEING REPUBLICANS COME TOGETHER
AND UNITE AND WE'RE GOING TO
KEEP ON WINNING PRIMARIES AND
CAUCUSES GOING IN ORDER,
INCLUDING I HOPE WE DO VERY WELL
IN UTAH AND ARIZONA COMING UP
TOMORROW.
>> SENATOR, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> THANK YOU.
GOD BLESS.
>> SENATOR TED CRUZ.
>>> COMING UP THE REPUBLICAN
FRONT-RUNNER DONALD TRUMP.
OUR CNN ELECTION SPECIAL, THE
FINAL FIVE CONTINUES IN A
MOMENT.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO OUR CNN
ELECTION SPECIAL.
THE FINAL FIVE.
JOINING US NOW, THE REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL FRONT-RUNNER,
DONALD TRUMP.
MR. TRUMP, THANKS FOR JOINING
US.
THIS IS YOUR FIRST DAY IN
WASHINGTON IN QUITE A WHILE.
THERE'S A LOT OF FOCUS TODAY ON
FOREIGN POLICY.
LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT U.S.
PARTICIPATION IN NATO.
DO YOU THINK THE UNITED STATES
NEEDS TO RETHINK U.S.
INVOLVEMENT IN NATO?
>> YES, BECAUSE IT'S COSTING US
TOO MUCH MONEY.
AND FRANKLY THEY HAVE TO PUT UP
MORE MONEY.
THEY'LL HAVE TO PUT SOME UP
ALSO.
WE'RE PLAYING
DISPROPORTIONATELY.
IT'S TOO MUCH.
AND FRACHKLY IT'S A DIFFERENT
WORLD THAN IT WAS WHEN WE
ORIGINALLY CONCEIVED OF THE
IDEA.
AND EVERYBODY GOT TOGETHER.
BUT WE'RE TAKING CARE OF AS AN
EXAMPLE THE UKRAINE.
THE COUNTRIES OVER THERE DON'T
SEEM TO BE SO INTERESTED.
WE'RE THE ONES TAKING THE BRUNT
OF IT.
WE HAVE TO RECONSIDER, KEEP
NATO, BUT MAYBE WE HAVE TO PAY A
LOT LESS TOWARD THE NATO ITSELF.
>> WHEN YOU SAY KEEP NATO, NATO
HAS BEEN AROUND SINCE RIGHT
AFTER WORLD WAR II IN 1949.
A CORNERSTONE OF U.S. NATIONAL
SECURITY AROUND THE WORLD.
NATO ALLIES HEAR YOU SAY THAT,
THEY'LL NOT BE HAPPY.
>> THEY MAY NOT BE HAPPY BUT
THEY HAVE TO HELP US ALSO.
IT HAS TO BE -- WE ARE PAYING
DISPROPORTIONATELY.
AND VERY IMPORTANTLY, IF YOU USE
UKRAINE AS AN EXAMPLE, AND
THAT'S A GREAT EXAMPLE, THE
COUNTRY SURROUNDING UKRAINE
DON'T SEEM TO CARE AS MUCH ABOUT
IT AS WE DO.
SO THERE HAS TO BE AT LEAST A
CHANGE IN PHILOSOPHY AND IN THE
CUTOUT, THE MONEY, THE SPREAD
BECAUSE IT'S TOO MUCH.
>> YOU ARE SUGGESTING THE UNITED
STATES SHOULD DECREASE ITS ROLE?
>> NOT DECREASE ITS ROLE BUT
CERTAINLY THE SPENDING.
WE'RE SPENDING A TREMENDOUS
AMOUNT IN NATO AND OTHER PEOPLE
PROPORTIONATELY LESS.
NO GOOD.
>> WHAT DO YOU SAY TO ALLIES
WATCHING AND THEY'RE NOT HAPPY
WITH WHAT YOU'RE SAYING.
>> THEY'RE NOT HAPPY?
WE'RE SPENDING A FORTUNE.
WE'RE SPENDING TREMENDOUS
AMOUNTS OF MONEY.
YOU LOOK AT COUNTRIES THAT
CIRCLE OTHER COUNTRIES.
THEY AREN'T AS BOTHERED BY IT AS
WE ARE.
YOU HAVE TO MAKE THEM HAPPY.
BUT THE KIND OF MONEY -- WE OWE
$19 TRILLION.
GOING TO BE $21 TRILLION SOON
WITH THE CRAZY OMNIBUS BUDGET
THEY JUST PASSED, WHICH IS
RIDICULOUS.
WE CAN'T AFFORD TO DO ALL OF
THIS ANYMORE TO THE SAME EXTENT.
THAT WAS A DIFFERENT TIME, A
DIFFERENT AGE.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT WHAT YOU
TOLD "THE WASHINGTON POST"
EARLIER.
YOU SUGGESTED THE U.S. SHOULD BE
NONINTERVENTIONIST.
IN OUR LAST DEBATE YOU SUGGESTED
MAYBE THE U.S. WOULD HAVE TO
DEPLOY 20,000 OR 30,000 TROOPS
IN IRAQ AND SYRIA TO DESTROY
ISIS.
>> WHAT I SAID IS THAT THEY TELL
ME, THE MILITARY TELLS ME, YOU
NEED 20 OR 30,000 TROOPS.
I WOULDN'T DEPLOY 20,000.
I'D GET PEOPLE FROM THAT PART OF
THE WORLD TO PUT UP THE TROOPS
AND CERTAINLY GIVE THEM AIR
POWER AND AIR SUPPORT AND SOME
MILITARY SUPPORT.
BUT I WOULD NEVER PUT UP 20,000
OR 30,000.
>> THE MILITARY COMMANDER SAID,
WE NEED 20,000 OR 30,000 TROOPS
TO DESTROY ISIS.
SEND THEM IN TO IRAQ AND SYRIA,
YOU WOULD SAY -- YOU SAID IN THE
DEBATE YOU'D LISTEN TO THE
GENERALS.
>> I DO LISTEN TO THE GENERALS.
I'D MUCH RATHER HAVE PEOPLE IN
THE LOCAL AREA PUT UP THE
TROOPS.
THAT'S VERY IMPORTANT.
WE'VE HAD -- LOOK.
WE'VE SPENT $2 TRILLION AT LEAST
IN IRAQ.
WE'RE SPENDING TRILLIONS OF
DOLLARS IN THE MIDDLE EAST.
YOU KNOW WHERE WE ARE NOW?
FURTHER BACK THAN 15 YEARS
POPPING THE MIDDLE EAST IS A
DISASTER FOR US.
AND IN THE MEANTIME OUR COUNTRY
IS CRUMBLING.
WE HAVE A COUNTRY THAT THE ROADS
ARE NO GOOD.
THE HOSPITALS ARE NO GOOD.
THE AIRPORTS ARE THIRD WORLD
AIRPORTS.
LOOK AT LaGUARDIA AND KENNEDY
AND L.A.X. AND ALL OF THE
AIRPORTS.
AND YOU GO TO OTHER COUNTRIES.
DUBAI AND QATAR AND THESE
COUNTRIES, IT'S LIKE
UNBELIEVABLE.
WOLF, WE HAVE TO REBUILD OUR
COUNTRY.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT THE SUBJECT
OF YOUR SPEECH TODAY AT AIPAC.
HILLARY CLINTON SPOKE THIS
MORNING AT THE AIPAC CONFERENCE.
LISTEN TO WHAT SHE SAID.
LISTEN TO THIS.
>> WE NEED STEADY HANDS, NOT A
PRESIDENT WHO SAYS HE'S NEUTRAL
ON MONDAY, PRO-ISRAEL ON TUESDAY
AND WHO KNOWS WHAT ON WEDNESDAY
BECAUSE EVERYTHING IS
NEGOTIABLE.
WELL, MY FRIENDS, ISRAEL'S
SECURITY IS NON-NEGOTIABLE.
>> SHE'S TALKING ABOUT YOU.
WHAT'S YOUR RESPONSE?
>> I AGREE ON THE LAST
STATEMENT.
IT'S NON-NEGOTIABLE.
FRANKLY, SHE IS -- JUST DOESN'T
KNOW ME.
SHE DOESN'T KNOW MY POLICY.
SHE DOESN'T KNOW WHAT I'M GOING
TO BE DOING.
>> SHE SAID YOU DON'T HAVE
STEADY HANDS.
>> I HAVE THE STEADIEST HANDS.
FAR STEADIER THAN HERS.
LOOK WHERE SHE GOT US.
LOOK AT LIBYA, THIE MIGRATION.
LOOK AT THE JOB.
PROBABLY IN HISTORY, ALTHOUGH I
THINK JOHN KERRY MAY EVEN BE
WORSE.
I'M NOT SURE AFTER THE IRAN
DEAL, BUT LOOK AT WHAT SHE'S
DONE.
>> SHE'S REFERRING TO YOUR
COMMENT THAT YOU WANTED TO BE
NEUTRAL AS A NEGOTIATOR TO TRY
TO ACHIEVE AN
ISRAELI-PALESTINIAN PEACE
AGREEMENT.
>> I WOULD LOVE TO BE NEUTRAL IF
IT'S POSSIBLE.
IT'S PROBABLY NOT POSSIBLE
BECAUSE THERE'S SO MUCH HATRED.
THERE IS SO MUCH GOING ON.
I AM VERY PRO-ISRAEL.
I'VE ALWAYS BEEN PRO-ISRAEL.
I HAVE MANY AWARDS FROM ISRAEL.
MANY, MANY AWARDS.
I'VE CONTRIBUTED A LOT OF MONEY
TO ISRAEL.
THERE'S NOBODY MORE PRO-ISRAEL
THAN I AM.
>> WHAT DO THE PALESTINIANS NEED
TO DO FOR U.S. PRESIDENT TO BE
NEUTRAL IN TRYING TO ACHIEVE A
PEACE AGREEMENT?
>> I WOULD LOVE TO ACHIEVE A
PEACE AGREEMENT.
>> WHAT DO THE PALESTINIANS NEED
TO DO?
>> THEY HAVE TO END TERROR.
THEY HAVE TO STOP WITH THE TER
OP BECAUSE WHAT THEY ARE DOING
WITH THE MISSILES AND THE
STABBINGS AND ALL OF THE OTHER
THINGS THEY DO, IT'S HORRIBLE.
AND THEY'VE GOT TO -- IT'S GOT
TO END.
NOW I HAVE MANY, MANY FRIENDS
FROM ISRAEL AND JEWISH FRIENDS.
EVERYBODY WANTS TO SEE PEACE.
IT SEEMS TO BE THE ALL-TIME
OLYMPICS IN PEACE -- IN A DEAL.
CAN YOU MAKE THAT DEAL BETWEEN
ISRAEL AND THE PALESTINIANS?
I THINK THE ANSWER IS MAYBE.
>> WHAT ELSE CAN THEY DO BESIDES
STOPPING TERROR.
>> THE PRIMARY THING IS STOPPING
TERROR.
ONE THING THEY HAVE TO DO IS
STOP THE STABBINGS, THE WEAPONS,
THE MILITARY.
WHAT THEY ARE DOING IS
INCREDIBLE.
THEY KILLED A YOUNG MAN, A YOUNG
SOLDIER LAST WEEK.
THEY STABBED HIM.
THIS IS CRAZY.
NOW FROM THE TIME THEY ARE BORN,
THEY ARE EDUCATED A CERTAIN WAY.
IT'S GOT TO CHANGE.
THERE'S A BAD MIND-SET GOING ON.
>> BACK IN DECEMBER YOU SEEMED
TO QUESTION WHETHER ISRAEL WOULD
BE WILLING TO MAKE THE
CONCESSIONS IT WOULD NEED TO
MAKE TO ACHIEVE A TWO-STATE
SOLUTION, ISRAEL AND PALESTINE.
WHAT ARE YOU EXPECTING FROM
ISRAEL?
>> I CAN SAY THIS.
I BELIEVE THAT BEBE AND ALMOST
EVERYBODY OVER THERE WANTS A
DEAL, WANTS SOME DEAL DONE.
>> WOULD YOU WANT ISRAEL TO STOP
BUILDING SETTLEMENTS IN EAST
JERUSALEM IN THE WEST BACHK?
>> THE BIGGEST THING FROM MY
STANDPOINT IS THERE HAS TO BE A
DIFFERENT WAY, A DIFFERENT
ATTITUDE BECAUSE OF ALL THE
DEALS THAT I'VE EVER SEEN, THIS
IS THE ONE THAT'S THE MOST
DIFFICULT.
NOT THE IRAN DEAL, WHICH WAS A
HORRIBLE DEAL AND WE WOULDN'T
WANT A DEAL LIKE THAT.
I DON'T LIKE THE UNITED NATIONS
GETTING INVOLVED IN THE
NEGOTIATION.
THIS HAS TO BE A DEAL BETWEEN
THE PALESTINIANS AND ISRAELIS.
THIS HAS TO BE THAT.
YOU CAN'T FORCE A DEAL DOWN THE
THROATS OF BOTH BUT YOU KNOW IT
WILL BE A BAD DEAL FOR ISRAEL IF
THEY DO THAT.
SO I WOULD VETO A DEAL WITH THE
UNITED NATIONS IF THE UNITED
NATIONS FORCES A DEAL, I WOULD
VETO THAT DEAL IMMEDIATELY.
>> YOU'D USE THE U.S. VETO AT
THE SECURITY COUNCIL?
>> ABSOLUTELY.
THAT'S NOT WHAT DEAL MAKING IS
ALL ABOUT.
THEY HAVE TO MAKE THEIR OWN
DEAL.
I'LL TRY AS PRESIDENT.
EVERYBODY HAS FAILED.
BUT I WILL TRY AS PRESIDENT TO
WORK OUT A PEACE AGREEMENT
BETWEEN ISRAEL AND THE
PALESTINIANS.
>> WILL YOU RECOGNIZE JERUSALEM
AS ISRAEL'S CAPITAL AND MOVE THE
U.S. EMBASSY FROM TEL AVIV TO
JERUSALEM IN.
>> YES, I WOULD.
>> WHEN.
HOW QUICKLY?
>> IT'S A PROCESS BUT FAIRLY
QUICKLY.
THE FACT IS I WOULD LIKE TO SEE
IT MOVED AND LIKE TO SEE IT IN
JERUSALEM.
>> HILLARY CLINTON AT THE AIPAC
MEETING TODAY ALSO SAID THIS
REFERRING TO YOU.
LISTEN.
>> ENCOURAGING VIOLENCE, PLAYING
COY WITH WHITE SUPREMACISTS,
CALLING FOR 12 MILLION
IMMIGRANTS TO BE ROUNDED UP AND
DEPORTED, DEMANDING WE TURN AWAY
REFUGEES BECAUSE OF THEIR
RELIGION AND PROPOSING A BAN ON
ALL MUSLIMS ENTERING THE UNITED
STATES.
IF YOU SEE BIGOTRY, OPPOSE IT.
IF YOU SEE VIOLENCE, CONDEMN IT.
IF YOU SEE A BULLY, STAND UP TO
HIM.
>> SHE'S TALKING ABOUT YOU.
>> I GUESS.
LOOK, WE HAVE TO BE VIGILANT.
OUR COUNTRY IS UNDER SIEGE.
WE'RE UNDER ATTACK.
WE'RE UNDER ATTACK IN VIRTUALLY
EVERY WAY.
OUR ECONOMY IS FALLING APART.
WE'RE SITTING ON A BIG, FAT
BUBBLE.
OUR TRADE DEALS ARE NO GOOD.
OUR HEALTH CARE IS NO GOOD.
OUR SECURITY IS NO GOOD.
LOOK WHAT HAPPENS IN OUR
COUNTRY.
PEOPLE ARE PORING ACROSS THE
BORDER.
PEOPLE THAT ARE CONVICTED
CRIMINALS ARE POURING ACROSS THE
BORDER.
WE HAVE TO BE SMART OR WE'RE NOT
GOING TO HAVE A COUNTRY ANY
LONGER.
>> DOZENS OF RAB EBIS AND OTHER
JEWISH RELIGIOUS LEADERS ARE
BOYCOTTING YOUR SPEECH AT AIPAC.
WE DENOUNCE THE BIGOTRY, RACISM,
XENOPHOBIA AND MISOGYNY
EXPRESSED BY MR. TRUMP.
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO THOSE RABBIS
AND OTHERS?
>> ARE THEY GOING TO LEAVE OR
WANT TO SEE WHAT I HAVE TO SAY?
BECAUSE I HAVE A VERY GOOD
CHANCE OF GETTING THE
NOMINATION.
I HAVE A VERY GOOD CHANCE --
>> ON THE SUBSTANCE, WHAT DO YOU
WANT TO SAY BECAUSE THOSE ARE
STRONG WORDS?
>> I'VE HEARD WORDS.
HILLARY'S WORDS WHICH ARE
LARGELY FALSE.
ALTHOUGH WE HAVE TO PRACTICE
VIGILANCE AND BE SMART.
WE'RE BEING VERY FOOLISH RIGHT
NOW.
WE CAN'T TAKE IN THE SYRIAN
REFUGEES.
WE DON'T KNOW WHERE THEY COME
FROM.
THERE'S NO PAPERWORK.
ARE THEY ISIS?
ISIS RELATED?
>> WHAT'S YOUR MESSAGE TO THESE
RABBIS AND OTHERS SO CONCERNED
ABOUT THE WORDS THEY'VE HEARD
FROM YOU OVER THESE MANY MONTHS?
>> MY MESSAGE TO THE RABBIS IS
THAT I'M GOING TO BE GREAT FOR
ISRAEL.
I AM VERY PRO-ISRAEL.
THE GRAND MARSHAL OF THE ISRAELI
DAY PARADE A NUMBER OF YEARS AGO
WHEN NOBODY ELSE WOULD HAVE DONE
IT BECAUSE IT WAS A BAD AND
DANGEROUS TIME FOR ISRAEL.
I WILL BE VERY GOOD FOR ISRAEL.
NOW PRESIDENT OBAMA, THE WORST
PRESIDENT THAT ISRAEL HAS
EVER -- I MEAN THERE'S BEEN
NOTHING.
PROBABLY ONE OF THE WORST THINGS
THAT'S HAPPENED TO ISRAEL IS
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S ELECTION.
IF THE RABBIS WANT TO LEAVE, IF
SOME OF THEM WANT TO LEAVE,
THAT'S OKAY.
BUT THE PEOPLE THAT REALLY
UNDERSTAND ME AND THEY
UNDERSTAND ISRAEL, THEY KNOW I'M
GOING TO BE THE BEST --
>> THEIR CONDEMNATION IS ABOUT
BIGOTRY, RACISM, XENOPHOBIA AND
MISOGYNY.
>> OR LET'S CALL IT
INTELLIGENCE.
WE HAVE TO BE CAREFUL.
WE HAVE TO BE CAREFUL WHO WE
ALLOW INTO THE COUNTRY.
WE'VE HAD TREMENDOUS PROBLEMS.
LOOK WHAT HAPPENED IN CALIFORNIA
RECENTLY WITH THE WOMAN WHO
COMES IN RADICALIZES THE GUY.
THEY WALK INTO THEIR WORKPLACE
AND KILL 14 PEOPLE.
LOOK WHAT HAPPENED IN PAURIS,
FRANCE.
>> YOU'VE DISAVOWED DAVID DUKE
AND THE KU KLUX KLAN SEVERAL
TIMES NOW.
>> I HAVE.
>> WHY DO YOU THINK THESE
VARIOUS WHITE SUPREMACISTS OUT
THERE ARE SUPPORTING YOUR
CAMPAIGN?
>> I DON'T KNOW.
I AM THE LEAST RACIST PERSON
YOU'LL EVER MEET SO I DON'T
KNOW.
I DON'T KNOW THEY REALLY ARE.
YOU ARE TELLING ME THAT'S.
>> THE ADL PUT OUT A LIST OF TEN
WHITE SUPREMACISTS, NEO-NAZIS,
ANTI-SEMITES OUT THERE WORKING,
SUPPORT YOUR CAMPAIGN.
>> YOU ARE TELLING ME THIS BUT I
DON'T KNOW WHY.
I'M CERTAINLY THE LEAST RACIST
PERSON.
>> BUT YOU CONDEMN THEM?
>> OF COURSE I CONDEMN THEM.
ALWAYS.
I'VE ALWAYS CONDEMNED THEM.
>> YOU DON'T WANT THEIR SUPPORT.
>> I DON'T WANT THEIR SUPPORT.
I DON'T NEED THEIR SUPPORT.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT CUBA RIGHT
NOW.
HISTORIC MOMENT.
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES
IS IN CUBA AS WE SPEAK RIGHT
NOW.
THE FIRST TIME IN 88 YEARS THAT
AN AMERICAN PRESIDENT HAS GONE
TO CUBA.
IF YOU ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT,
WOULD YOU CONTINUE TO NORMALIZE
ECONOMIC AND DIPLOMATIC
RELATIONS WITH CUBA?
>> PROBABLY SO BUT I'D WANT MUCH
BETTER DEALS.
I EXPECT THAT CUBA IS EXPECTING
TO BE BRING AUGUST MAJOR LAWSUIT
AGAINST US FOR ALL THE PROBLEMS
WE'VE CAUSED THEM OVER THE LAST
LONG PERIOD OF TIME.
FOR BILLIONS AND BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS.
NATURALLY BEFORE I DID ANYTHING
AS TO NORMALIZATION I'D MAKE
THEM SIGN SOMETHING THAT NO WAY
THAT SUIT IS GOING TO BE
BROUGHT.
I THOUGHT IT WAS VERY
DISRESPECTFUL WHEN THE PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES FLIES INTO
CUBA LAST NIGHT AND CASTRO
WASN'T THERE TO MEET HIM.
HE MET THE POPE.
HE MEETS OTHER LEADERS OF MUCH
SMALLER COUNTRIES.
MUCH LESS IMPORTANT COUNTRIES.
AND HE WASN'T THERE TO MEET THE
PRESIDENT GETTING OFF OF AIR
FORCE ONE.
I THOUGHT THAT WAS A VERY BIG
SLEIGHT.
I DON'T KNOW HOW OBAMA FELT
ABOUT THAT.
I THINK THAT'S WAS A VERY, VERY
BIG SLEIGHT.
>> SO YOU SAY YOU'LL CONTINUE TO
TRY TO NORMALIZE DIPLOMATIC AND
ECONOMIC RELATIONS.
WOULD YOU OPEN A TRUMP HOTEL IN
HAVANA?
>> I WOULD.
I WOULD.
AT THE RIGHT TIME, WHEN WE'RE
ALLOWED TO DO IT.
RIGHT NOW WE'RE NOT.
I WOULDN'T DO IT WITH 49%
INTEREST.
RIGHT NOW YOU GET 49% INTEREST.
NO ONE KNOWS WHAT THE ECONOMICS
ARE OR WHAT THEY'RE GOING TO DO.
MAYBE IT WON'T WORK OUT, BUT I
WILL TELL YOU, CUBA HAS CERTAIN
POTENTIAL, AND IT'S OKAY TO
BRING CUBA INTO THE FOLD BUT YOU
HAVE TO MAKE A MUCH BETTER DEAL
AND GET ALL LIABILITIES.
YOU DON'T WANT TO BE SUED IN A
YEAR FROM NOW OR TWO YEARS FROM
NOW FOR $4 TRILLION BECAUSE THEY
SAY WE DESTROYED CUBA.
IT HAS TO BE PART OF THE DEAL.
>> YOU ARE HERE IN WASHINGTON
ONCE AGAIN.
FURST TIME IN A WHILE.
YOU MET WITH MEMBERS OF CONGRESS
TODAY.
YOU ARE SEEN AS AN OUTSIDER.
IS THERE A TURNING POINT YOU SEE
RIGHT NOW HAPPENING IN YOUR RACE
FOR THE WHITE HOUSE?
AS A RESULT OF YOUR SUCCESS?
>> I THINK THE TURNING POINT HAS
ALREADY TAKEN PLACE.
I WON FLORIDA BY 20 POINTS
AGAINST A VERY POPULA SITTING
SENATOR.
I WON OTHER STATES, I'VE WON NOW
JUST ABOUT 22 --
>> ARE YOU ANXIOUS TO WORK WITH
THE SO-CALLED ESTABLISHMENT WITH
MEMBERS OF THE SENATE, MEMBERS
OF THE HOUSE AND TRY TO --
>> WOLF, MANY OF THEM WANT TO
WORK WITH ME.
THEY ARE CALLING MY OFFICE.
>> BUT NOT THE LEADERS.
THEY DIDN'T COME TO THE MEETING.
THEY WERE OTHER MEMBERS --
>> WE'LL SEE HOW THE LEADERS
REACT.
THE LEADERS HAVE CALLED ME.
I'VE SPOKEN TO MITCH McCONNELL,
PAUL RYAN.
WE'LL SEE WHAT HAPPENS.
>> DO YOU THINK YOU SHOULD HAVE
INVITED PAUL RYAN, MITCH
McCONNELL TO THE MEETING TODAY?
>> THIS WAS JUST A MEETING OF
SOME RESPECTFUL PEOPLE.
SENATOR JEFF SESSIONS IS A
TREMENDOUS MAN.
ONE OF THE MOST RESPECTED
SENATORS IN THE COUNTRY.
AND MEETING OF SOME SENATORS,
SOME CONGRESSMEN AND WOMEN.
I THINK IT WAS A VERY GOOD
MEETING.
>> JOHN KASICH, THE OHIO
GOVERNOR, REPUBLICAN
PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE, SAID
THIS ON CNN.
LISTEN.
>> EVERYBODY'S GOT TO FACE THE
FACT THAT WE'RE GOING TO AN OPEN
MULTIBALLOT CONVENTION.
I WON OHIO BECAUSE OF MY MESSAGE
AND MY RECORD.
AND GUESS WHAT, AS A RESULT OF
THAT, DONALD TRUMP IS GOING TO
GO -- NOT GOING TO GO TO THE
CONVENTION WITH ENOUGH
DELEGATES.
>> YOUR RESPONSE?
>> I DISAGREE.
50 O
FIRST OF ALL, I ALMOST BEAT HIM.
HAD I HAD ONE MORE DAY OR TWO
MORE DAYS I WOULD HAVE BEATEN
HIM.
THAT NIGHT I WON FIVE STATES
BETWEEN STATES AND ISLANDS.
I WON FIVE.
I DON'T THINK ANYONE HAS EVER
DONE THAT.
AND IT WAS A VERY, VERY CLOSE
RACE.
BUT BECAUSE I WON SO MANY
OTHERS, IT REALLY NULLIFIED IT,
NEUTRALIZED IT BECAUSE I WATCHED
YOUR REPORTS.
AND I THINK I WILL WIN AND
PERHAPS EASILY WITHOUT HAVING TO
GO THROUGH THE MACHINATIONS.
>> LET'S SAY YOU SHOW UP IN
CLEVELAND AND DON'T HAVE THE
MAGIC NUMBER OF 1,237 TO BE
GUARANTEED ON THE FIRST BALLOT.
LET'S SAY YOU ARE 20 OR 100
SHORT.
THE CHAIRMAN OF THE REPUBLICAN
PARTY REINCE PRIEBUS SAYS THAT
THAT'S NOT THE RULES.
THEY WOULD HAVE TO GO ALONG WITH
THE RULES.
WHAT WOULD HAPPEN IF YOU ARE
JUST SHORT?
>> WELL, I HEARD HIM SAY THAT.
NUMBER ONE, I DON'T THINK I'M
GOING TO BE THERE.
I KNOW THEY'LL --
>> WILL YOU GO ALONG WITH THE
RULES?
>> LET ME EXPLAIN SOMETHING.
IT'S A LITTLE UNFAIR BECAUSE I
HAVE BEEN COMPETING AGAINST, WE
STARTED OVER 17 PEOPLE.
THEN WE GO DOWN TO 15 AND 12 AND
11 AND 10 AND I HAD MANY, MANY
PEOPLE I'M COMPETING WITH.
WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT THE MAIJORIY
PLUS ONE, IT'S UNFAIR.
WE HAD SO MANY PEOPLE RUNNING.
ONE WOULD GET 2%, 4%.
I WAS ALWAYS IN THE LEAD.
JUST ABOUT FROM THE BEGINNING
I'VE BEEN LEADING.
IT'S VERY UNFAIR WHEN I HAVE ALL
OF THESE PEOPLE RUNNING.
IT'S NOT LIKE I'M RUNNING
AGAINST TWO OR THROW PEOPLE.
HILLARY IS RUNNING AGAINST ONE
PERSON.
THAT'S VERY UNFAIR.
I'M GOING TO GET THE MAJORITY
ANYWAY.
>> IF YOU DON'T, WILL YOU ABIDE
BY THE RULES?
>> I THINK THIS.
I'VE HAD MANY, MANY PEOPLE
RUNNING AGAINST ME WHICH -- YOU
UNDERSTAND WHAT I MEAN.
MATHEMATICALLY, IT'S UNFAIR.
IT'S ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE TO
BELIEVE THAT I SHOULD DO THAT.
THAT I WOULD BE ABLE TO DO THAT.
I THINK I'LL BE ABLE TO DO IT.
BUT I WILL SAY THIS.
IF I WAS AT 1,190, SO I'M A
LITTLE BIT OFF, AND I HAVE
MILLIONS OF VOTES MORE THAN
ANYBODY ELSE.
RIGHT NOW I HAVE 2 MILLION MORE
VOTES THAN ANYBODY ELSE RUNNING
FOR OFFICE BY A LOT.
NOT EVEN CLOSE.
>> ARE YOU CALLING ON THE RNC TO
CHANGE THE RULES IF YOU'RE CLOSE
YOU SHOULD STILL BE THE NOMINEE?
>> IT'S GOING TO BE VERY HARD
FOR THEM TO DO.
I HAVE MILLIONS MORE VOTES THAN
ANYBODY ELSE THAT'S RUNNING.
AGAIN THAT'S ALSO WITH A LOT OF
PEOPLE RUNNING.
SO IT'S MORE DIFFICULT.
BUT I'D SAY THE MAJORITY IS A
TOF THING WHEN YOU HAVE ALL
THESE PEOPLE.
I HAD RACES I GUESS THAT STARTED
OFF WITH -- WHEN THEY STARTED
THE PRIMARIES THERE WERE 12, 14
PEOPLE, MAYBE MORE THAN THAT'S.
I'M SUPPOSED TO GET HALF?
MATHEMATICALLY IT'S UNFAIR.
>> THOSE ARE THE RULES.
>> WELL, IT'S -- LOOK.
YOU ARE SUPPOSES TO HAVE THREE
PEOPLE, TWO PEOPLE, ONE PERSON.
CROW ARE SUPPOSED TO HAVE
PEOPLE, NOT 17 PEOPLE RUNNING.
>> I WANT TO --
>> I THINK I'LL DO IT ANYWAY.
I THINK I'LL DO IT.
I MAY DO IT EASILY BECAUSE I
THINK WE'LL HAVE A BIG NIGHT IN
ARIZONA AND I THINK WE'LL DO
WELL IN WISCONSIN.
BUT I DO SAY THIS.
IT'S MATHEMATICALLY UNFAIR.
NOW IF I HAVE MILLIONS OF VOTES
MORE AND HAVE 1,100 AND SOMEBODY
ELSE IS DOWN IN 400 OR 500, I
THINK IT'S AWFULLY TOUGH TO TAKE
ALL OF THESE PEOPLE OUT OF THE
SYSTEM.
>> I WANT TO PLAY WHAT HOUSE
SPEAKER PAUL RYAN SAID ABOUT,
YOU USED THE WORD RIOTS IF THAT
WERE TO HAPPEN.
>> NOBODY SHOULD SAY SUCH THINGS
IN MY OPINION BECAUSE TO EVEN
ADDRESS OR HINT TO VIOLENCE IS
UNACCEPTABLE.
>> YOU DON'T WANT ANY VIOLENCE
TO EMERGE, RIGHT?
>> OF COURSE I DON'T.
>> YOU USED THE WORD RIOTS
TWICE.
>> I SAYS VERY SIMPLY IF THAT
HAPPENED, I'LL HAVE NO PART IN
IT, BUT THERE COULD VERY WELL BE
RIPOPTS YOU KNOW THAT'S TRUE.
ARE WE SUPPOSED TO BE SO
POLITICALLY CORRECT THAT WE'RE
NOT ALLOWED -- I HAVE PEOPLE,
MILLIONS AND MILLIONS OF PEOPLE
THAT HAVE COME OUT.
IT'S THE BIGGEST STORY IN WORLD
POLITICS TODAY.
THE NUMBER OF PEOPLE THAT CAME
OUT.
THESE PEOPLE ARE BY THE
MILLIONS.
YOU SEE WHAT'S HAPPENING WITH
THE REPUBLICANS.
>> I WANT TO BE PRECISE.
WILL YOU UNEQUIVOCALLY SAY TOIOR
SUPPORTERS YOU DON'T WANT ANY
VIOLENCE OR RIOTS AT THE
CONVENTIONS?
>> OF COURSE I WOULD.
100%.
BUT I HAVE NO CONTROL OVER THE
PEOPLE.
>> YOU HAVE A LOT OF CONTROL
OVER THE PEOPLE.
A LOT OF YOUR SUPPORTERS LISTEN
CLOSELY TO WHAT'S YOU ARE
SAYING.
>> THESE PEOPLE HAVE BEEN
DISENFRANCHISED.
THEY LOST THEIR JOBS.
THEY MAYBE LESS MONEY NOW THAN
12 YEARS POPPING PEOPLE THAT ARE
WORKING HARD AND WORKING DOUBLE
JOBS ARE MAKING LESS MONEY IN
REAL DOLLARS THAN 12 YEARS AGO.
THEY ARE -- THEY HAVE SEEN THEIR
JOBS GOING TO JAPAN AND CHINA,
MEXICO.
FORGET IT.
IT'S THE NEW CHINA.
THEY ARE VERY -- THEY AREN'T BY
NATURE ANGRY PEOPLE BUT RIGHT
NOW, THEY'RE ANGRY PEOPLE.
>> YOU CAN CALM THEM DOWN.
>> I DON'T KNOW THAT I CAN.
>> WITH YOUR WORDS.
>> I CAN CERTAINLY TRY.
BUT THEY ARE VERY ANGRY PEOPLE.
THEY HAVE BEEN MISLED BY
POLITICIANS FOR YEARS.
AND THEY ARE TIRED OF IT.
AND THAT'S WHY I'M DOING SO WELL
AND IT'S WHY I'M LEADING.
>> DO YOU UNDERSTAND WHY THERE'S
A SENSE OF UNEASE ABOUT YOU IN
THE GENERAL PUBLIC RIGHT NOW?
>> NO, I DON'T SEE THAT.
I THINK I'LL DO VERY WELL IN THE
GENERAL AND BEAT HILLARY VERY
EASILY AND BRING IN STATES LIKE
MICHIGAN THAT WAS DEVASTATED BY
JOB LOSS.
STATES LIKE --
>> THE SENSE OF UNSEES SOME OF
THE WORDS YOU'VE SAID, THE
VIOLENCE AT THE CAMPAIGN RALLIES
THAT THEY SEE ON TELEVISION.
RIOTSS OUTSIDE --
>> WE'VE NOTED HAD ANYBODY HURT.
I HAVE 21,000 PEOPLE SHOWED UP
THE OTHER DAY TO ARIZONA.
I DIDN'T HAVE ONE PROTEST.
THEY TRIED TO BLOCK THE ROAD BUT
OUTSIDE OF THE ROAD, ONCE
SHERIFF JOE SAW THE CARS HE --
>> CANCELED THAT WHOLE EVENT IN
CHICAGO.
>> BECAUSE I DIDN'T WANT TO SEE
VIOLENCE.
I COULD HAVE GONE TO THAT EVENT
AND THERE PROBABLY WOULD HAVE
BEEN SOME PROBLEMS.
>> YOU CAN UNDERSTAND WHY SOME
PEOPLE ARE NERVOUS.
>> I DON'T REALLY.
WHEN I GO INTO THOSE ROOMS AND
HAVE BY FAR THE BIGGEST CROWDS
AND MUCH BIGGER THAN BERNIE.
HE IS SECOND, I AGREE.
MUCH BIG ARE THAN BERNIE OR
ANYBODY.
WE HAD 21,000 PEOPLE IN ARIZONA.
IT WAS LIKE A LOVEFEST.
THOSE ROOMS ARE WONDERFUL.
BUT HERE'S WHAT HAPPENS.
SOMETIMES A PROTESTER, AND I
THINK THEY ARE PROFESSIONALS,
THEY GET INTO THE ROOM AND START
RAISING THEIR VOICE AND THEY
START SCREAMING AND SOMETIMES
THEY GET PHYSICAL, VERY
PHYSICAL.
AND THEY START SCREAMING AND
MAKING NOISE AND IT'S A
DISGRACE.
SOMETIMES THEY PUT THEMSELVES IN
FRONT OF THE ENTRANCE DOORS SO
PEOPLE CAN'T GET IN.
SOMETIMES THEY TRY AND BLOCK A
CAR BY CHAINING THEMSELVES TO A
CAR IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
HIGHWAY.
THEY ARE THE PROBLEM.
MY PEOPLE AREN'T THE PROBLEM.
AND THE NEWS DOESN'T COVER IT.
YOU HAVE AGITATORS.
THESE AREN'T EVEN PROTESTERS.
THEY'LL WAIT FOR MY TO MAKE A
FINAL POINT AND JUST BEFORE
THEY'LL STOP SCREAMING AT THE
TOP OF THEIR LUNGS.
PEOPLE ARE VERY UPSET ABOUT IT.
>> THIS IS A REPUBLICAN
SUPERPAC, A VERY NEGATIVE AD
ABOUT YOU THAT YOU'VE SEEN I'M
SURE.
>> I'M SURE I'LL LOVE SEEING IT.
>> A PERSON WHO IS VERY FLAT
CHESTED IS VERY HARD TO BE A 10.
>> I'D LOOK HER RIGHT IN THAT
FAT UGLY FACE OF HERS.
>> LOOK AT THAT FACE.
WOULD ANYONE VOTE FOR THAT?
>> SHE HAD THE HEIGHT, THE
BEAUTY.
SHE WAS CRAZY.
BUT THESE ARE MINOR DETAILS.
>> I LIKE KIDS.
I MEAN, I WON'T DO ANYTHING TO
TAKE CARE OF THEM.
I'LL SUPPLY FUNDS AND SHE'LL
TAKE CARE OF THE KIDS.
>> IT REALLY DOESN'T MATTER WHAT
THEY WRITE AS LONG AS YOU HAVE A
YOUNG AND BEAUTIFUL PIECE OF
[ BLEEP ].
>> HAS YOUR LANGUAGE COME BACK
TO HAUNT YOU?
>> NO.
I THINK PEOPLE UNDERSTAND.
I THINK PEOPLE -- FIRST OF ALL,
HALF OF THAT WAS SHOW BUSINESS.
THE DROPPING TO THE KNEES WAS IN
"THE APPRENTICE."
THE ROSIE O'DONNELL STUFF.
BUT I THINK PEOPLE UNDERSTAND.
LOOK.
THESE POLITICIANS, I KNOW THEM.
THEY SAY FAR WORSE WHEN THEY ARE
IN CLOSED DOORS OR WHERE THEY
ARE WITH A GROUP OF PEOPLE THAT
THEY TRUST.
THIS -- A LOT OF THAT SHOW
BUSINESS STUFF, AND IN FLORIDA,
THE AMAZING THING.
THEY SPENT $38 MILLION IN
NEGATIVE ADS ON ME AND I WON BY
A RECORD LANDSLIDE.
PRETTY AMAZING.
>> BUT THAT'S NOT HOW YOU FEEL
ABOUT WOMEN?
>> NO.
NOBODY RESPECTS WOMEN MORE THAN
I DO.
NOBODY TAKES CARE OF WOMEN AND
THEY TAKE CARE OF ME --
>> SHOW BUSINESS?
>> I DON'T EVEN KNOW WHAT THESE
STATEMENTS ARE.
NOBODY RESPECTS WOMEN MORE THAN
I DO.
>> WHY DO YOU KEEP --
>> BY THE WAY, I'LL TAKE CARE OF
WOMEN WITH WOMEN'S HEALTH ISSUES
FAR BETTER THAN HILLARY CLINTON
WHO IS A TOTALLY PHONY, IF SHE'S
EVEN ALLOWED TO RUN.
>> WHY DO YOU KEEP ATTACKING
MEGYN KELLY OF FOX?
>> BECAUSE EVERY NIGHT ON HER
SHOW SHE DOES NEGATIVE HITS ON
ME.
EVERY SINGLE NIGHT.
FRANKLY, IF SHE DIDN'T, HER
RATINGS WOULD DROP DOWN FAR
LOWER THAN YOURS.
>> DO YOU THINK IT'S APPROPRIATE
TO GEET ABOUT HER AND CALL HER
CRAZY ON TWITTER?
>> SHE HITS ME.
SHE'S GOT A TELEVISION SHOW.
WHEN IT'S UNFAIR, I HIT HER
BACK.
SHE WAS FAIR IN THE SECOND
DEBATE.
I THOUGHT SHE WAS OKAY.
COULD HAVE DONE A LITTLE BETTER,
BUT THAT'S OKAY.
I THOUGHT SHE WAS FINE IN THE
SECOND DEBATE.
PEOPLE ASKED ME, WHAT DID YOU
THINK OF MEGYN KELLY?
I THOUGHT SHE WAS FINE.
EVERY NIGHT THE SHOW IS LIKE AN
INFOMERCIAL AND ALWAYS NEGATIVE
STUFF.
ALWAYS.
NOT FAIR.
SO I WILL FIGHT BACK WITH
TWITTER.
I WILL LET PEOPLE KNOW SHE'S A
THIRD RATE TALENT.
I'LL SAY WHAT I HAVE TO SAY.
BUT IT'S NOT FAIR THAT -- LET
HER NOT TALK ABOUT ME.
BY THE WAY, SERIOUSLY, IF SHE
DIDN'T TALK ABOUT ME, HER
RATINGS WOULD GO DOWN LIKE A
ROCK.
>> FOX NEWS ISSUED AN
EXTRAORDINARY STATEMENT.
VITRIOLIC ATTACKS AGAINST MEGYN
KELLY AND EXTREME SICK OBSESSION
WITH HER IS BENEETHS THE DIGNITY
OF A PRESIDENTIAL CANDIDATE.
>> SHE'S GOT THE OBSESSION.
SHE PUTS ME ON HER SHOW EVERY
NIGHT.
LOOK AT HER SHOW AND THE AIR
TIME I GET ON HER SHOW AND I
DON'T DO HER SHOW.
SHE WANTS ME TO DO IT SO BADLY.
ROGER AILS WANTS ME TO DO IT.
THEY WANT A PRIMETIME SPECIAL ON
FOX NETWORK WHERE MEGYN KELLY
INTERVIEWS ME.
I SAY WHAT'S IN IT FOR ME?
WHAT DO I GET OUT OF THAT?
YOU'LL GET GREAT RATINGS.
WHAT'S DO I GET OUT OF IT?
THEY WANT A PRESUMETIME SPECIAL.
I WON'T DO IT.
SHE SHOULD DO SOMEBODY ELSE.
IF SHE DIDN'T DO ME, WATCH WHAT
HAPPENS TO HER.
WATCH.
NOW IN THE MEANTIME, SHE'S
BENEFITED GREATLY.
HOTTER NOW THAN EVER BEFORE
BECAUSE OF ME.
SHE SHOULD GIVE ME AT LEAST HALF
OF HER SALARY.
>> LET'S TALK ABOUT A FEW OTHER
ISSUES BEFORE I LET YOU GO.
BEFORE YOU LOST IOWA TO TED
CRUZ, YOU HAD A GOOD
RELATIONSHIP WITH HIM.
IS IT AT ALL REALISTIC IF YOU
GET THE NOMINATION YOU COULD
CALL ON THIS MAN, YOU CALL HIM
LYING TED, TO BE YOUR VICE
PRESIDENTIAL RUNNING MATE?
>>I CRAZIER THINGS HAPPEN IN
POLITICS.
>> SO YOU AREN'T RULING THAT
OUT?
>> I DON'T WANT TO RULE OUT
ANYTHING.
I THINK IT'S PROBABLY UNLIKELY.
I HAD A RELATIONSHIP WHEN I SAID
WHEN IS IT GOING TO COME?
AT SOME POINT IT HAD TO COME.
AND WE WERE ESSENTIALLY WITH THE
LAST TWO STANDING BECAUSE JOHN
IS YOU KNOW, IS NOT DOING SO
WELL.
I MEAN HE'S 1 FOR 28.
HE WON HIS STATE AND NOT BY
MUCH.
HE WON HIS STATE SO HE'S 1 FOR
28.
HE'S IN IT BECAUSE HE'S, YOU
KNOW, A GUY THAT DOESN'T WANT TO
GET OUT.
>> YOU RECENTLY SAID HILLARY
CLINTON HAS LOW ENERGY, VERY LOW
ENERGY.
DOESN'T HAVE THE STAMINA TO BE
PRESIDENT.
YOU ARE ROUGHLY THE SAME AGE AS
HILLARY CLINTON.
WHY DO YOU SAY THAT?
>> SHE DOESN'T HAVE THE STAMINA.
YOU WATCH HER LIFE, HOW SHE'LL
GO AWAY FOR THREE, FOUR DAYS,
COME BACK.
SHE'LL GO.
I JUST DON'T THINK SHE HAS THE
STAMINA.
WE'VE GOT TO BEAT CHINA IN
TRADE, WE'VE GOT TO BEAT ISIS.
I SAY SHE DOES NOT HAVE THE
STAMINA TO BE A GOOD PRESIDENT.
PLUS SHE'S ALWAYS GOOD PROBLEMS
WHETHER IT'S WHITEWATER OR
E-MAILS OR -- IT'S ALWAYS DRAMA.
IT SHOULD END.
SHE SHOULDN'T EVEN BE RUNNING.
SHE SHOULDN'T BE ARK LOUD TO RUN
BASED ON THE E-MAILS.
SHE'S BEING PROTECTED.
BUT HILLARY CLINTON DOES NOT
HAVE THE STAMINA, DOESN'T HAVE
THE ENERGY.
DOESN'T HAVE IT.
DOESN'T HAVE THE STRENGTH TO BE
PRESIDENT IN MY OPINION.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANKS FOR JOINING
US.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
APPRECIATE IT.
>>> COMING UP, WE'LL TURN TO THE
DEMOCRATIC PRESIDENTIAL
CANDIDATES.
HILLARY CLINTON IS COMING UP.
MUCH MORE RIGHT AFTER THIS.
>>> WELCOME BACK TO OUR ELECTION
SPECIAL, THE FINAL FIVE
CANDIDATES.
JOINING ME THE DEMOCRATIC
FRONT-RUNNER HILLARY CLINTON.
THANK YOU FOR BEING WITH US.
>> GREAT TO BE HERE.
>> YOU REITERATED YOUR SUPPORT
FOR THE IRAN DEAL.
AIPAC OPPOSES IT.
NETANYAHU SAYS IT'S A MISTAKE.
EVEN CHUCK SCHUMER OPPOSES IT.
WHY ARE THEY WRONG?
>> WE HAVE PUT A LID ON THE
IRANIAN NUCLEAR WEAPONS PROGRAM.
ALMOST ALL OF THEIR ENRICHED
URANIUM SOUT OF THE COUNTRY.
THE CENTRIFUGES HAVE STOPPED
SPINNING.
WE HAVE DETECTION MEASURES THAT
WILL GIVE US FAIR WARNING.
SO I THINK ON BALANCE IT WAS THE
RIGHT STEP TO TAKE.
BUT I'VE ALSO SAID LOOK.
I GAVE A SPEECH LAST SUMMER IN
WHICH I MADE CLEAR THE SLIGHTEST
INFRACTION NEEDS TO HAVE
CONSEQUENCES.
I BELIEVE IT'S NOT TRUST AND
VERIFY.
IT'S DISTRUST AND VERIFY.
SO I THINK WE HAVE TO FOCUS NOW
ON A LOT OF IRANIAN AGGRESSIVE
BEHAVIOR WHILE WE ENFORCE THE
AGREEMENT ON THE NUCLEAR WEAPONS
PROGRAM.
I THINK THAT PUTS US IN A
STRONGER AND BETTER POSITION
GOING FORWARD.
>> YOU TOOK A SHOT AT DONALD
TRUMP DURING THE SPEECH, NOT BY
NAME.
I WANT TO PLAY FOR OUR VIEWERS
WHAT'S YOU SAID AND ASK YOU
ABOUT IT.
>> WE NEED STEADY HANDS, NOT A
PRESIDENT WHO SAYS HE'S NEUTRAL
ON MONDAY, PRO-ISRAEL ON TUESDAY
AND WHO KNOWS WHAT ON WEDNESDAY
BECAUSE EVERYTHING'S NEGOTIABLE.
SOME THINGS AREN'T NEGOTIABLE.
AND ANYONE WHO DOESN'T
UNDERSTAND THAT HAS NO BUSINESS
BEING OUR PRESIDENT.
>> DO YOU THINK HE'S NOT
QUALIFIED TO BE PRESIDENT?
>> WELL, I AM QUOTING HIM.
I THINK IT'S IMPORTANT TO LISTEN
TO WHAT HE SAYS.
YOU HAVE TO TAKE HIM AT HIS
WORD, SO TO SPEAK.
HE HAS BEEN ENGAGING IN BIGOTRY
AND BLUSTER AND BULLYING AND I
THINK WHEN IT COMES TO
UNDERSTANDING WHAT HE WOULD DO
AS PRESIDENT, THERE ARE SERIOUS
QUESTIONS THAT HAVE BEEN RAISED
IN THIS CAMPAIGN.
SHOULD HE BE THE NOMINEE, WE'LL
HAVE TO ADDRESS THEM.
>> YOU'RE SAYING HE'S A BULLY?
>> I THINK HIS BEHAVIOR
CERTAINLY QUALIFIES FOR THAT.
I THINK HIS INCITEMENT OF
VIOLENCE, HIS CONSTANT URGING ON
OF HIS SUPPORTERS IN LARGE
NUMBERS TO GO AFTER PROTESTERS.
HIS SAYING I WANT TO PUNCH
PEOPLE IN THE FACE AND TELLING
SOMEBODY WHO DID PUNCH SOMEBODY,
I WILL PAY YOUR LEGAL BILLS.
I THINK THAT RAISES VERY SERIOUS
QUESTIONS.
>> HE SAYS THAT AS PRESIDENT,
THERE WOULD BE A DIFFERENT TONE.
THAT HE'D HAVE A MORE
PRESIDENTIAL TONE.
YOU'VE KNOWN HIM FOR A LONG
TIME.
IS THERE A DIFFERENT DONALD
TRUMP IN THERE?
>> WHO KNOWS.
YOU PRESENT YOURSELF TO THE
COUNTRY THE WAY HE'S PRESENTED
HIMSELF TO THE COUNTRY OVER THE
LAST MANY MONTHS, CALLING
MEXICAN IMMIGRANTS RAPISTS AND
CRIMINALS.
SAYING JOHN McCAIN WAS NOT A WAR
HERO.
BEING RELUCTANT TO DENOUNCE THE
KU KLUX KLAN AND DAVID DUKE, AND
THE LIST GOES ON AND ON.
SO FOR ME, I THINK YOU HAVE TO
TAKE HIM AT HIS WORD AT HOW HE'S
BEHAVED AND WHAT HE HAS SAID.
IF YOU DO THAT, THEN I THINK
PEOPLE HAVE QUESTIONS THAT
DESERVE ANSWERS.
>> HE MAKES MUCH ABOUT HIS DEAL
MAKING ABILITIES, HIS
NEGOTIATING SKILLS.
ARE THE SKILLS USED IN BUSINESS
THE SAME AS THAT ARE USED IN
STATE CRAFT?
ARE THEY APPLICABLE?
>> WELL, IF YOU RUN A BUSINESS,
AND I'VE HEARD THIS FROM MANY,
MANY BUSINESS LEADERS, YOU HAVE
MUCH MORE AUTHORITY AND CONTROL
OVER YOUR EMPLOYEES THAN IF YOU
ARE THE PRESIDENT OR THE LEADER
OF A DEMOCRACY.
POLITICAL DECISION MAKING,
LISTENING TO THE FULL RANGE OF
VOICES AND OPINIONS IS SOMETHING
THAT OUR FOUNDERS HIGHLY VALUED,
AS DO I.
SO I THINK THERE IS IN GENERAL A
DIFFERENCE AND I THINK A LOT OF
THE BEHAVIOR WE'VE SEEN FROM HIM
RAISED SOME SPECIFIC QUESTIONS
ABOUT WHAT HE WOULD DO.
>> YOU HAVE SAID AT ONE POINT
THAT YOU WERE THE -- I THINK IT
WAS THE DISIGNATED YELLER IN
CHIEF IN RELATIONSHIPS WITH
PRIME MINISTER NETANYAHU.
YOU HAD A FRONT ROW SEAT AT THE
SOMETIMES CONTENTIOUS
RELATIONSHIP UNDER THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION.
HOW WOULD YOU BE BETTER?
HOW WOULD YOUR RELATIONSHIP WITH
ISRAEL BE BETTER?
>> WELL, AS I SAID IN MY SPEECH
TODAY, AND IT REALLY IS BUILT ON
MY MANY YEARS GOING BACK TO THE
FIRST TIME I WENT TO ISRAEL 35
YEARS AGO AND THE WORK THAT I'VE
DONE, THE PEOPLE THAT I'VE KNOWN
AND ADMIRED, I AM STAUNCHLY IN
FAVOR OF ISRAEL'S SECURITY.
AND ALTHOUGH WE MAY HAVE
DIFFERENCES, WHICH WE DO, I
BELIEVE IN TREATING THOSE IN A
RESPECTFUL MANNER, CANDID BUT
RESPECTFUL, WHICH IS WHAT I HAVE
DONE IN THE PAST.
AND I THINK MY FIRM COMMITMENT
TO ISRAEL'S SECURITY PUTS ME ON
A VERY STRONG FOUNDATION TO DEAL
WITH WHATEVER THE QUESTIONS
MIGHT BE IN THE RELATIONSHIP.
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY, WE HAVE TO
STAND AGAINST WHAT'S HAPPENING
IN THE BROADER REGION, WHICH I
THINK IS NOT JUST A THREAT TO
ISRAEL BUT A THREAT TO OUR OTHER
PARTNERS IN THE REGION AND EVEN
TO THE UNITED STATES.
>> WHAT WAS THE DISCONNECT UNDER
THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION?
>> I'M NOT GOING TO GO INTO
THAT.
I THINK THE PRESIDENT HAS MADE
VERY CLEAR THAT UNDER THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION, ISRAEL HAS BEEN
GIVEN AN ENORMOUS AMOUNT OF
DEFENSIVE CAPABILITIES.
I MENTIONED THE IRON DOME
MISSILE DEFENSE SYSTEM WHICH HAS
WORKED VERY WELL AGAINST THE
ROCKETS COMING FROM GAZA BY
HAMAS, AND THERE HAVE BEEN
DIFFERENCES.
BUT I THINK IN GENERAL, THE
RELATIONSHIP REMAINS VERY STRONG
AND CENTRAL TO AMERICAN FOREIGN
POLICY.
>> YOU SAID TODAY YOU'D INVITE
THE PRIME MINISTER WITHIN THE
FIRST COUPLE OF DAYS OF TAKING
OFFICE.
>> I'VE KNOWN HIM A LONG TIME.
THAT'S ONE OF MY ADVANTAGES.
>> IS IT TRUE YOU YELL AT EACH
OTHER?
>> I'D SAY WE ENGAGE IN VIGOROUS
DISCUSSION.
AND I LIKE THAT.
LOOK, WE HAVE A RAUCOUS
DEMOCRACY.
ISRAEL HAS A RAUCOUS DEMOCRACY.
I THINK THOSE OF US WHO ARE IN
THE MIDST OF THE POLITICAL
ACTIVITIES IN BOTH OF OUR
COUNTRIES UNDERSTAND THAT A GIVE
AND TAKE BETWEEN FRIENDS IS THE
BEST AND MOST HONEST WAY TO COME
TO ANY RESOLUTION.
SO, YES, I HAVE HAD MY
DISAGREEMENTS, BUT I'VE ALSO
NEVER STRAYED FROM MY STRONG
COMMITMENT TO ISRAEL'S SECURITY.
>> WOULD YOU MOVE THE U.S.
EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM?
>> THAT'S SOMETHING THAT REALLY
HAS TO BE LOOKED AT IN THE
CONTEXT OF A TWO-STATE SOLUTION.
AND I'VE ALWAYS SAID THAT.
I'VE ALWAYS SUPPORTED THAT AS A
FIRST LADY, AS A SENATOR, AS
SECRETARY OF STATE.
>> WOULD YOU COMMIT TO USING THE
U.S. VETO POWER OVER THE
SECURITY COUNCIL TO PROTECT
ISRAEL?
>> YES, I WOULD.
>> NO MATTER WHAT?
>> WELL, LOOK.
THE TALK NOW, YOU KNOW, I CAN'T
PREDICT EVERYTHING IN THE FUTURE
BUT IN GENERAL THE ANSWER IS
YES.
BUT THE TALK NOW IS TO SOMEHOW
TRY TO USE THE U.N. THROUGH THE
SECURITY COUNCIL TO IMPOSE
PARAMETERS ON A SETTLEMENT
BETWEEN ISRAEL AND THE
PALESTINIANS.
NUMBER ONE, I DON'T THINK IT
WORKS.
AND I DON'T THINK THAT'S THE
PLACE FOR IT TO BE HASHED OUT.
IT HAS TO BE BETWEEN THE TWO
PARTIES.
AND, REMEMBER, I WAS THE LAST
PERSON WHO BROUGHT PRIME
MINISTER NETANYAHU AND PRESIDENT
ABBAS TOGETHER FOR THREE
FACE-TO-FACE MEETINGS IN 2010.
THE FACT THAT I SAT THERE AND IT
WAS JUST GEORGE MITCHELL AND ME
AND PRESIDENT ABBAS AND PRIME
MINISTER NETANYAHU AND I WATCHED
THE INTERACTION AND LISTENED TO
THE ISSUES THAT THEY WERE
DEBATING ACTUALLY GAVE ME MORE
ENCOURAGEMENT AND COMMITMENT TO
KEEP PURSUING A TWO-STATE
SOLUTION.
>> TED CRUZ IS TALKING ABOUT ON
DAY ONE OF TAKING THE OFFICE IF
HE BECOMES PRESIDENT OF
AUTHORIZING THE MOVEMENT OF THE
EMBASSY TO JERUSALEM.
WHAT'S YOUR -- WHAT'S -- WHY
WOULDN'T YOU DO THAT?
>> BECAUSE I THINK THAT WOULD
END ANY CHANCE FOR A TWO-STATE
SOLUTION.
AND I THINK IT WOULD, IN THE
MIDST OF A VERY DANGEROUS REGION
RIGHT NOW WITH MANY THREATS, NOT
JUST AIMED AT ISRAEL BUT AIMED
AT JORDAN, FOR EXAMPLE, THAT
TURKEY AND LEBANON AND EGYPT AND
OTHERS ARE COPING WITH.
IT WOULD LIGHT A FIRE THAT WOULD
ADD FUEL TO THE FLAME OF WHAT'S
ALREADY SO THREATENING IN THE
REGION.
I DON'T THINK IT ACCOMPLISHES
ANY PURPOSE THAT WOULD LEAD US
TO A TWO-STATE SOLUTION BUT
INSTEAD IT COULD MAKE IT EVEN
MORE DANGEROUS FOR ISRAEL.
I'M NOT ABOUT TO SIGN OFF ON
THAT.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA IS IN CUBA
RIGHT NOW.
THEY'VE BEEN CRACKING DOWN ON
DISSENT IN ADVANCE OF HIS
ARRIVAL.
THEY ARE STILL PROTECTING THIS
WOMAN WHO IS THE AUNT OF TUPAC
SHAKUR CONVICTED OF MURDERING A
NEW JERSEY POLICE OFFICER.
THE STATE DEPARTMENT CLAIMS IT'S
IN TALKS WITH CUBA TO NEGOTIATE
HER RETURN BUT HER ATTORNEY IS
SAYING SKUBAN OFFICIALS HAVE
ASSURED HIM HER POLITICAL ASYLUM
WILL NOT BE REVOKED.
SHOULD PRESIDENT OBAMA HAVE MADE
HER RETURN PART OF THE DEAL?
>> I THINK WHAT HE DID WAS TO
GET AN INTELLIGENCE OFFICIAL, AS
WELL AS WE GOT THE RETURN, NOT
PART OF THE DEAL, BUT IN
ADDITION, ALAN GROSS.
AND HAVING BEEN INVOLVED IN SOME
OF THOSE NEGOTIATIONS WHILE I
WAS STILL SECRETARY OF STATE,
YOU PUSH AS HARD AS YOU CAN TO
GET AS MUCH AS YOU CAN.
AND I SUPPORT THE PRESIDENT'S
EFFORTS TO MOVE THE RELATIONSHIP
FORWARD.
I THINK IT'S GOOD FOR THE CUBAN
PEOPLE.
I WANT THEM TO HAVE DEMOCRACY
AND FREEDOM.
AND I ALSO WANT HUMAN RIGHTS
RESPECTED.
AND I KNOW THAT THE PRESIDENT
WILL BE MEETING WITH SOME
DISSIDENTS, AND I HIGHLY APPROVE
OF THAT.
AND I THINK WE HAVE TO
CONTINUALLY RAISE THE ISSUES OF
ALL OF THE DISSIDENTS.
AND THAT'S WHAT I HOPE HE DOES,
AND I WILL CERTAINLY CONTINUE TO
DO THAT.
>> I WANT TO TALK ABOUT ISIS.
ACCORDING TO A POLICE REPORT
OBTAINED BY "THE NEW YORK
TIMES," AUTHORITIES IN EUROPE
SAY THE PARIS ATTACKERS USED
ENCRYPTED COMMUNICATIONS DEVICES
DURING THE MASSACRE THERE.
IF THAT IS ACCURATE, DO YOU
BELIEVE IT PROVES THAT MAJOR
TECH COMPANIES, MOST NOTABLY
APPLE, SHOULD COOPERATE WITH THE
U.S. AND OTHER GOVERNMENTS ON
UNLOCKING TERRORIST PHONES?
>> I REALLY WANT TO SEE A
RESOLUTION TO THIS.
NOW IT'S CAUGHT UP IN THE LEGAL
PROCESS, AS YOU KNOW.
AND I'VE SAID FOR MANY MONTHS,
THERE HAS TO BE SOME WAY TO
PROTECT OUR REAL PHYSICAL
SECURITY, TO PREVENT TERRORIST
ATTACKS, TO TRACK DOWN
PERPETRATORS WHILE WE PROTECT
ONLINE SECURITY.
I THINK WE'VE GOT A LOT OF
REALLY SMART PEOPLE IN OUR TECH
COMMUNITY, IN OUR GOVERNMENT WHO
SOMEHOW HAVE TO COME TO TERMS
WITH THIS.
BECAUSE IT IS A SERIOUS PROBLEM
FOR LAW ENFORCEMENT.
AND IT'S ALSO A PROBLEM FOR THE
TECH COMPANIES.
>> YOUR CRITICS SAY YOU'RE
TRYING TO HAVE IT BOTH WAYS.
YOU AREN'T TAKING A SIDE BETWEEN
THE GOVERNMENT OR PRIVATE
SECTOR.
>> TRY TO SOLVE HARDER DECISIONS
LIKE THE ONES I'VE SOLVED.
YOU HAVE TO KEEP WORKING A
PROBLEM UNTIL YOU GET SOME BREAK
IN THAT.
>> YOU DON'T THINK IT IS AN
EITHER/OR?
>> I HOPE IT'S NOT AN EITHER/OR.
I THINK IT'S STILL TOO SOON TO
SAY WHETHER IT'S AN EITHER/OR
BECAUSE IT'S STILL IN THE LEGAL
PROCESS.
THE FEDERAL COURTS CAN MAKE ALL
KINDS OF ORDERS.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT THEY WILL
DECIDE BUT AT THE SAME TIME,
PEOPLE WORKING IN THE TECH
COMMUNITY ALSO HAVE A STAKE IN
PREVENTING TERRORIST ATTACKS ON
OUR SHORES.
AND IN KEEPING PEOPLE SAFE.
HOW DO WE DO THAT?
AND, YOU KNOW, I THINK IT'S
IMPORTANT TO KEEP TRYING TO WORK
THE PROBLEM AND TRYING TO FIND
SOME COMMON GROUND FOR PEOPLE TO
WORK ON.
>> REGARDING THE SUPREME COURT,
SENATOR SANDERS SAID LAST WEEK
IF ELECTED HE'D ASK PRESIDENT
OBAMA TO WITHDRAW THE NOMINATION
OF MERRICK GARLAND SO HE COULD
NOMINATE A MORE, IN HIS WORDS,
PROGRESSIVE CAND DAUT.
IS THAT SOMETHING YOU'D ASK
PRESIDENT OBAMA TO DO?
>> I WANT TO ASK THE SENATE TO
DO THEIR CONSTITUTIONAL DUTY.
IT'S TIME FOR THEM TO QUIT THE
PARTISAN POSTURING AND RECEIVE
THE NOMINEE.
HAVE THE APPROPRIATE PROCESS GO
FORWARD, INCLUDING HEARINGS, AS
TO WHETHER OR NOT TO VOTE TO
CONFIRM HIM.
>> IF HE'S STILL FACING
NOMINATION WHEN YOU ARE -- AND
YOU GET THE NOMINATION, WOULD
YOU ASK PRESIDENT OBAMA -- WOULD
YOU CONTINUE TO PUSH FOR GARLAND
OR IF ELECTED, WOULD YOU TRY TO
APPOINT SOMEONE OF YOUR OWN?
>> I THINK THAT IS GETTING WAY
AHEAD OF OURSELVES.
OTHERS CAN SAY WHAT THEY WANT TO
SAY.
I'M GOING TO KEEP THE PRESSURE
ON THE SENATE.
WHY WOULD WE LIFT THE PRESSURE
OFF?
>> WOULD HE HAVE BEEN YOUR PICK?
>> WE HAVE ONE PRESIDENT AT A
TIME.
THAT'S SOMETHING I WANT THE
SENATE TO REMEMBER.
THERE IS ONE PRESIDENT AT A
TIME.
BARACK OBAMA IS OUR PRESIDENT.
HE HAS A CONSTITUTIONAL
RESPONSIBILITY TO FILL THAT
VACANCY.
HE HAS EXERCISED IT BY
APPOINTING SOMEONE NOMINATING
SOMEONE THAT HE BELIEVES WOULD
BE A VERY GOOD, QUALIFIED
CHOICE.
>> DO YOU THINK HE WOULD BE A
GOOD JUSTICE?
>> I THINK HE HAS A TREMENDOUS
REPUTATION.
LET'S FOCUS ON WE HAVE ONE
PRESIDENT AT THE TIME.
HE'S MADE HIS NOMINATION.
WE HAVE A SENATE THAT REFUSES TO
FULFILL ITS CONSTITUTIONAL
OBLIGATION.
AND I BELIEVE AND HOPE PERHAPS,
AS MORE TO THE ACCURACY, I HOPE
THAT AS THIS ELECTION GOES
FORWARD AND A LOT OF THOSE
REPUBLICAN SENATORS WHO ARE UP
FOR RE-ELECTION WHO ARE RUNNING
IN STATES WHERE THEY ARE GOING
TO FACE INCREASING PRESSURE TO
DO THE RIGHT THING, TO STAND UP
AND TELL THEIR LEADER, HEY, GIVE
HIM A HEARING, AND LET US VOTE.
YOU DON'T HAVE TO VOTE FOR HIM.
YOU CAN VOTE HIM DOWN BUT GO
THROUGH THE PROCESS.
THAT'S WHAT'S REQUIRED.
>> LAST WEEK YOUR DAUGHTER WAS
ON THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL IN SALT
LAKE CITY AND IMPLIED THAT YOU
WOULD WANT TO EXTEND OBAMACARE
TO UNDOCUMENTED IMMIGRANTS.
I WANT TO PLAY WHAT SHE SAID SO
YOU CAN RESPOND.
>> SHE THINKS IT'S SO IMPORTANT
TO EXTEND THE AFFORDABLE CARE
ACT TO PEOPLE WHO ARE LIVING AND
WORKING HERE, REGARDLESS OF
IMMIGRATION STATUS, REGARDLESS
OF CITIZENSHIP STATUS.
>> DONALD TRUMP TOOK TO TWITTER
ATTACKING YOU SAYING THAT NOW
YOU WANT OBAMACARE FOR ILLEGAL
IMMIGRANTS.
ARE YOU IN FAVOR OF EXTENDING
OBAMACARE TO UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS?
>> THERE ARE TWO STEPS HERE.
IF SOMEONE CAN AFFORD TO PAY FOR
AN INSURANCE POLICY OFF THE
EXCHANGES THAT WERE SET UP UNDER
THE AFFORDABLE CARE ACT, I
SUPPORT THAT.
>> EVEN IF THEY ARE
UNDOCUMENTED?
>> IF THEY CAN AFFORD IT, THEY
SHOULD BE ABLE TO GO INTO THE
MARKETPLACE AND BUY IT.
BUT IT IS NOT GOING TO APPLY TO
PEOPLE WHO ARE IN NEED OF
SUBSIDIES IN ORDER TO AFFORD
THAT BECAUSE THE SUBSIDIES
QUESTIONS HAS TO BE WORKED OUT
IN COMPREHENSIVE IMMIGRATION
REFORM.
AND WHAT I DO WANT TO SEE IS
THAT WE HAVE MORE OPTIONS FOR
UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE TO BE ABLE
TO GET THE HEALTH CARE THEY
NEED.
IT'S NOT ONLY THE RIGHT AND
MORAL THING TO DO FOR THEM.
IT'S ALSO IMPORTANT THAT WE KEEP
OURSELVES HEALTHY AND PUBLIC
HEALTH REQUIRES THAT.
SO I SEE THIS AS A TWO-STEP
PROCESS.
>> AT THE DEBATE IN MIAMI
RECENTLY, YOU WERE PUSHED ON
WHAT YOU WOULD DO WITH THE 11
MILLION OR SO UNDOCUMENTED
IMMIGRANTS CURRENTLY HERE.
YOU SAID NO MORE DEPORTATIONS OF
CHILDREN.
YOU DON'T WANT TO DEPORT FAMILY
MEMBERS.
YOU WANT TO FOCUS ON THOSE WHO
HAVE BROKEN THE LAW.
ARE YOU SAYING NO MORE
DEPORTATIONS OF ANYBODY WHO
HASN'T BROKEN -- WHO IS NOT A
VIOLENT CRIMINAL?
WON'T THAT JUST ENCOURAGE MORE
PEOPLE TO COME, IF PEOPLE KNOW
THERE'S NOT ANY CHANCE THEY'LL
BE DEPORTED AS LONG AS THEY OBEY
THE LAW?
>> PEOPLE ARE ALREADY HERE HAVE
TO BE PUT IN A SEPARATE
CATEGORY.
PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN HERE.
SOME OF THEM DECADES.
I WANT TO STOP THE RAIDS AND
ROUND-UPS.
I DON'T BELIEVE WE SHOULD BE
BREAKING UP FAMILIES AND
DEPORTING MOTHERS AND FATHERS.
I THINK THAT IS, YOU KNOW,
REALLY UNNECESSARY.
I WANT TO GO AFTER PEOPLE WHO
HAVE COMMITTED VIOLENT CRIMES.
POSE A THREAT TO OUR COUNTRY'S
SECURITY, ABSOLUTELY.
BUT I WANT TO GET COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM, AND I WANT
TO START TRYING TO GET IT AS
SOON AS I AM ELECTED PRESIDENT,
IF I'M SO FORTUNATE.
>> IT'S OBVIOUSLY A VERY
DIFFICULT SITUATION, BUT DOESN'T
ALLOWING THOSE WHO ALREADY BROKE
THE LAW IN CROSSING THE BORDER
ILLEGALLY TO COME HERE, DOESN'T
THAT REWARD THEM FOR BREAKING
THE IMMIGRATION LAW?
>> THERE HAS TO BE A SEVERAL
STEP PROCESS UNDER COMPREHENSIVE
IMMIGRATION REFORM.
I DO THINK PEOPLE HAVE TO PAY A
FINE BECAUSE, YES, THEY CAME
HERE WITHOUT LEGAL
AUTHORIZATION.
THEY HAVE TO PAY A FINE.
THEY HAVE TO LEARN ENGLISH.
THEY HAVE TO BE AT THE END OF
THE LINE IN TERMS OF OTHERS WHO
CAME HERE LEGALLY AND ARE
WAITING TO BE PROCESSED.
BUT THEY SHOULD BE IN THE
PIPELINE.
AND THEY SHOULD BE GIVEN LEGAL
AUTHORITY TO WORK, WHICH I THINK
ACTUALLY HELPS THE WHOLE ECONOMY
BECAUSE YOU CAN NO LONGER
EXPLOIT UNDOCUMENTED WORKERS,
PAY THEM LESS AND ENDANGER JOBS
OF OTHERS.
SO I HAVE A WHOLE THEORY ABOUT
HOW WE CAN DO THIS, AND I DON'T
SEE THE PURPOSE IN BREAKING UP
FAMILIES.
I'VE MET A LOT OF THESE
FAMILIES, ANDERSON.
I'VE MET, YOU KNOW, PEOPLE WHO
HAVE BEEN HERE FOR ONE OR TWO
DECADES WHO HAVE WORKED WHO HAVE
SUPPORTED THEIR FAMILIES, WHO
SOME KIDS WERE BORN BEFORE.
A LOT OF KIDS WERE BORN AFTER.
AND THEY ARE CITIZENS.
AND, YOU KNOW, THERE'S A KNOCK
ON THE DOOR AND ALL OF A SUDDEN,
A FATHER OR MOTHER IS DEPORTED.
I THINK WE CAN SEND A STRONG
MESSAGE THAT WE ARE LITERALLY
DRAWING A LINE BETWEEN THOSE WHO
HAVE BEEN HERE SO THAT THOSE WHO
MIGHT THINK, HEY, I COULD FIT IN
UNDER THAT LINE ARE TOLD, NO,
THEY CAN'T.
AND WE HAVE INCREASED DEFENSES
ALONG THE BORDER.
RIGHT NOW THERE IS NO NET
MIGRATION FROM MEXICO.
MEXICANS HAVE GONE BACK TO THEIR
HOME VILLAGES AND AREAS.
SO WE KNOW WE CAN DO A BETTER
JOB ON BORDER SECURITY.
AND THEN FOR PEOPLE WHO DO COME,
ESPECIALLY FROM CENTRAL AMERICA,
THEY NEED TO BE TREATED HUMANELY
AND FAIRLY.
THEY NEED TO BE GIVEN FULL DUE
PROCESS TO SEE WHETHER THEY
QUALIFY UNDER OUR LAWS TO BE
GIVEN ASYLUM STATUS.
>> A COUPLE OF POLITICS
QUESTIONS.
YOU WERE NOT DOING WELL WITH
WHITE MALE VOTERS.
YOU DID WELL IN 2008 WITH THEM.
THIS TIME EXIT POLLS SHOWED YOU
LOST THEM IN ALL FIVE PRIMARIES
LAST WEEK.
WHY DO YOU THINK
>> WELL, I'M DOING REALLY WELL.
YOU KNOW, RIGHT NOW I HAVE MORE
VOTES THAN ANYBODY RUNNING.
I'VE GOT MORE THAN 8.5 MILLION
VOTES, I THINK, AND THAT'S A
MILLION MORE THAN DONALD TRUMP
AND IT'S 2.5 MILLION MORE THAN
BERNIE SANDERS.
SO WE'RE GOING TO BUILD ON THE
BROAD, INCLUSIVE COALITION THAT
WE HAVE AND WE'RE GOING TO KEEP
ADDING TO IT.
>> WHY DO YOU THINK AMONG WHITE
MALE VOTERS YOU HAVE AN ISSUE?
>> WELL, I DON'T KNOW.
BECAUSE I HAVEN'T ANALYZED ALL
OF THAT DATA.
IN SOME PLACES I HAVE CARRIED
WHITE VOTERS AND OTHER PLACES I
HAVE NOT CARRIED WHITE VOTERS.
NOBODY, IS IN MY VIEW, TO BE
LEFT OUT.
I THINK I HAVE A MESSAGE THAT
WILL RESONATE WITH VOTERS OF ALL
KINDS.
>> BERNIE SANDERS HAS A NEW LINE
OF ATTACK.
I WANT TO PLAY THAT.
>> LET ME SAY A WORD OR TWO
ABOUT MY GOOD FRIEND DONALD
TRUMP.
[ BOOING ]
JUST KIDDING.
HE'S NOT MY GOOD FRIEND.
IN FACT, I NEVER EVEN WENT TO
ONE OF HIS WEDDINGS, YOU KNOW.
I JUST NEVER DID.
>> YOU PROBABLY HEARD THAT ONE
BEFORE.
>> YEAH, I HAVE.
>> IN A NEW CNN POLL, SANDERS
DOES BETTER AGAINST REPUBLICANS
THAN YOU.
DO YOU BUY THAT?
>> NO, I DON'T BUY THAT AT ALL.
I THINK ANY HORSE RACE POLL THIS
FAR OUT IS MEANINGLESS.
I ALSO THINK -- AND I'M PROUD OF
THIS.
SENATOR SANDERS AND I HAVE RUN A
CAMPAIGN BASED ON ISSUES AND WE
HAVEN'T BEEN PERSONALLY
ATTACKING EACH OTHER AND RUNNING
NEGATIVE ADS.
WE'VE HAD DIFFERENCES ON ISSUES
AND WE HAVE TRIED TO DRAW THE
CONTRAST WHICH I THINK IS FULLY
APPROPRIATE COMPARED TO WHAT THE
REPUBLICANS HAVE DONE.
I'M PRETTY WELL VETTED.
I THINK PEOPLE HAVE A GOOD IDEA
ABOUT, YOU KNOW, WHAT I'VE BEEN
THROUGH, WHO I AM AND I THINK
THAT ACTUALLY MAKES ME THE
STRONGER CANDIDATE TO GO INTO A
GENERAL ELECTION.
>> ONE OF THE THINGS YOU SAID
ACTUALLY TO ME AT A TOWN HALL, I
THINK IT WAS NEW HAMPSHIRE.
IT'S BEEN A WHILE.
WE'VE DONE A LOT OF THEM.
IT WAS REALLY PERSONAL AND I HAD
NEVER HEARD YOU SAY IT BEFORE
AND I'VE HEARD YOU SAY IT ONCE
OR TWICE, THIS DOESN'T COME
NATURALLY TO YOU.
THAT YOUR HUSBAND IS -- IT'S
PART OF HIS DNA.
IT'S NOT FOR YOU.
>> RIGHT.
RIGHT.
>> IS THAT -- CAN YOU EXPLAIN
THAT A LITTLE MORE?
CAN YOU TALK ABOUT THAT?
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, IT'S FUNNY,
BECAUSE EVERY TIME I HAVE A JOB,
I GET REALLY, REALLY HIGH
RATINGS.
YOU KNOW, GO BACK AND LOOK AT MY
FAVORABILITY RATINGS WHEN I WAS
SECRETARY OF STATE AND HOW HIGH
REGARDED I WAS IN THE SENATE AND
AS FIRST LADY WHEN I STARTED
ACTUALLY GETTING INTO POLITICS.
SO WHENEVER I HAVE A JOB, I
REALLY WORK HARD TO DO IT TO THE
BEST OF MY CAPACITY.
AND I GET GOOD RESULTS AND I
WORK ACROSS THE AISLE AND PEOPLE
WHO NEVER HAVE A GOOD THING TO
SAY ABOUT ME WHEN I'M RUNNING
FOR SOMETHING ACTUALLY SAY
REALLY NICE THINGS ABOUT ME WHEN
WE'RE WORKING TOGETHER.
SO DOING THE JOB, GETTING
RESULTS FOR PEOPLE, MAKING A
DIFFERENCE FOR OUR COUNTRY,
THAT'S WHAT I FEEL BEST AT AND
WHAT I AM COMMITTED TO DOING.
AND I THINK THAT THE KIND OF
RESULTS THAT I GET WHEN I'M
ACTUALLY HOLDING A POSITION
SPEAK TO THAT.
BUT ACTUALLY GOING OUT AND
CAMPAIGNING, IT IS HARDER.
IT IS HARDER FOR ME.
AND IT MAY BE PARTLY THAT IT
SEEMS HARDER FOR WOMEN.
AND I RECOGNIZE THAT.
AND ALSO AS SOMEONE WHO HAS
SUPPORTED MY HUSBAND AND OTHER
DEMOCRATS FOR SO MANY YEARS, YOU
KNOW, MOVING FROM HE OR SHE TO I
OR ME IS NOT EASY FOR ME EITHER.
>> DO YOU THINK YOU'RE HELD TO A
DIFFERENT STANDARD?
I'VE SEEN PEOPLE ON TELEVISION
SAYING, OH, YOU SHOULD SMILE
MORE, THAT WHEN YOU'RE YELLING
IT SOUNDS -- THAT WHEN YOU'RE
SPEAKING IT SOUNDS LIKE YOU'RE
YELLING.
>> YEAH.
>> DO YOU THINK THAT'S A -- IS
THAT SEXIST?
>> WELL, LET ME SAY I DON'T HEAR
ANYBODY SAY THAT ABOUT MEN.
AND I'VE SEEN A LOT OF MALE
CANDIDATE WHO IS DON'T SMILE
VERY MUCH AND WHO TALK PRETTY
LOUD.
SO I GUESS I'LL JUST LEAVE IT AT
THAT.
>> OR MALE CANDIDATES THAT EVEN
YELL.
>> THERE HAVE BEEN ONE OR TWO
THAT DO THAT.
>> THEY RELISH THE IDEA OF YOU
TAKING ON DONALD TRUMP THIS
FALL.
PRESIDENT OBAMA IS CLEARLY
GEARED UP TO CAMPAIGN.
DO YOU HAVE ANY CONCERNS THAT BY
HAVING PRESIDENT OBAMA OUT THERE
CAMPAIGNING, TALKING AGAINST
DONALD TRUMP, HE'S GOING TO TALK
INTO DONALD TRUMP'S HANDS, HE'S
GOING TO ELEVATE DONALD TRUMP?
>> I DON'T THINK SO.
LOOK, I'M NOT YET THE NOMINEE.
I HOPE TO BE THE NOMINEE AND I
INTEND TO RUN A CAMPAIGN ABOUT
THE REAL ISSUES FACING OUR
COUNTRY AND TO KNOCK DOWN THE
BARRIERS THAT ARE STANDING IN
THE WAY OF PEOPLE GETTING AHEAD
AND STAYING AHEAD.
THAT IS REALLY MY CORE
COMMITMENT.
AND I WANT EVERYBODY OUT THERE
CAMPAIGNING ON WHAT WE CAN DO
TOGETHER AND I'D BE HONORED TO
HAVE THE PRESIDENT.
I'D BE DELIGHTED TO HAVE OTHERS
WHO ARE WITH ME IN MAKING THAT
CASE, WHOEVER THE REPUBLICANS
END UP NOMINATING.
>> DO YOU FEEL LIKE YOU KNOW HOW
TO RUN AGAINST DONALD TRUMP?
>> I KNOW HOW TO RUN A CAMPAIGN
THAT IS ABOUT THE REAL ISSUES
AFFECTING THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
AND I BELIEVE, AT THE END,
AMERICANS ARE GOING TO VOTE ON
WHO THEY THINK CAN DO ALL
ASPECTS OF THE JOB.
THIS IS LIKE A BIG, GIANT JOB
INTERVIEW.
AND AT THE END OF THE PROCESS, I
REALLY BELIEVE AMERICANS ARE
GOING TO SAY WHO'S STEADY, WHO'S
PREDICTABLE, THE TEMPERAMENT TO
DO ALL ASPECTS OF THE JOB IN
JANUARY 2017.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON, THANK YOU
FOR COMING TO THE ELECTION
CENTER.
>> GOOD TO TALK TO YOU.
>> WHEN WE COME BACK, SENATOR
BERNIE SANDERS WILL JOIN US
>>> WELCOME BACK TO THE CNN
ELECTION CENTER.
JOINING ME NOW IS SENATOR BERNIE
SANDERS WHO IS IN SALT LAKE
CITY, UTAH, CAMPAIGNING TONIGHT.
THANK YOU FOR BEING WITH US.
YOU SKIPPED THE AIPAC MEETING
TODAY BECAUSE OF CAMPAIGNING OUT
WEST.
IS THERE ANY MESSAGE PEOPLE
SHOULD READ INTO THAT?
ARE YOU SENDING A MESSAGE IN ANY
WAY?
>> NO.
IN FACT, WE JUST DID A PRESS
CONFERENCE AND GAVE A SPEECH
RIGHT HERE IN SALT LAKE CITY ON
THE MIDDLE EAST AND ON ISRAEL,
PRETTY MUCH THE SPEECH THAT I
WOULD HAVE GIVEN TO AIPAC HAD I
BEEN ABLE TO ATTEND THEIR
CONFERENCE.
I WANTED TO BE THERE.
IT WAS SIMPLY A QUESTION OF
SCHEDULING.
>> YOU SAID THAT THE U.S. SHOULD
BE EVEN-HANDED WHEN IT COMES TO
DEALING WITH THE ISRAELIS AND
PALESTINIANS.
DOES THAT MEAN THAT THE U.S.
SHOULD REMAIN NEUTRAL TO ACHIEVE
MIDDLE EAST PEACE?
>> NO.
IF WE WANT LASTING PEACE IN THE
MIDDLE EAST, WE'VE GOT TO
OBVIOUSLY MAKE SURE THAT THE
SECURITY AND THE INDEPENDENCE OF
ISRAEL REMAINS IN TACT.
THAT IS NOT A DEBATE.
ISRAEL MUST CONTINUE TO EXIST AS
AN INDEPENDENT FREE STATE.
BUT IF WE ARE GOING TO HAVE
LASTING PEACE, WE HAVE ALSO GOT
TO WORK WITH THE PALESTINIANS.
AND WHAT THAT MEANS, WE HAVE GOT
TO RECOGNIZE, FOR EXAMPLE, IN
GAZA, AN UNEMPLOYMENT RATE OF
44%, YOU HAVE PEOPLE LIVING IN
HORRIFIC POVERTY.
YOU HAVE A COMMUNITY THAT WAS
DESTROYED.
SO IF WE ARE GOING TO GO
FORWARD, IT CANNOT BE THAT THE
UNITED STATES JUST TAKES THE
SIDE OF ISRAEL.
WE'VE GOT TO WORK WITH BOTH
COMMUNITIES TO TRY TO DO WHAT IS
VERY, VERY DIFFICULT.
AND THAT IS CREATE A LASTING
PEACE IN THE REGION.
>> DO YOU THINK THE U.S. HAS NOT
BEEN EVEN-HANDED UP TILL NOW?
>> RIGHT.
I DO NOT THINK SO.
I THINK THAT OVERWHELMINGLY THE
UNITED STATES TIME AND TIME
AGAIN HAS LOOKED ASIDE WHEN
ISRAEL HAS DONE SOME BAD THINGS.
I THINK, FOR EXAMPLE, THAT THE
GROWTH OF SETTLEMENTS IN
PALESTINIAN TERRITORY IS NOT
ACCEPTABLE TO ME, NOT CONDUCIVE
TO THE PEACE PROCESS.
I THINK THAT THE KIND OF
DESTRUCTION THAT WAS RACKED ON
GAZA DURING THAT WAR WAS WAY
ABOVE WHAT NEEDED TO BE DONE FOR
MILITARY PURPOSES.
A LOT OF CIVILIANS WERE KILLED.
A LOT OF HOSPITALS AND SCHOOLS
AND APARTMENTS, ABOVE AND BEYOND
WHAT HAD TO BE DONE.
SO LOOK, I THINK THERE IS NO
QUESTION THAT THERE'S ENOUGH
BLAME TO GO AROUND ON BOTH
SIDES.
ISRAEL HAS THE RIGHT TO DEFEND
ITSELF AGAINST TERRORIST
ATTACKS, AGAINST HEZBOLLAH,
AGAINST HAMAS.
BUT I THINK THE UNITED STATES IS
STRONGER WHEN WE WORK WITH BOTH
SIDES.
>> SECRETARY CLINTON SAID THAT
SHE'S PRESIDED OVER FACE-TO-FACE
MEETINGS BETWEEN PRIME MINISTER
NETANYAHU, FOR INSTANCE, AND
PRESIDENT ABBAS, THREE SEPARATE
SESSIONS.
SHE SAYS SHE'S HAD A LOT OF
EXPERIENCE IN THIS REGION.
WHY DO YOU THINK YOU WOULD DO A
BETTER JOB THAN A PRESIDENT
CLINTON?
>> WELL, I'LL TELL YOU WHY.
BECAUSE I THINK I HAVE SHOWN A
LOT BETTER JUDGMENT THAN SHE HAS
ON FOREIGN POLICY.
LOOK, SHE WAS SECRETARY OF STATE
FOR FOUR YEARS.
AND IN THAT CAPACITY, YOU GAIN A
LOT OF EXPERIENCE.
BUT, IN FACT, WHEN SHE WAS IN
THE SENATE, SHE HEARD THE SAME
EVIDENCE THAT I DID FROM GEORGE
BUSH AND DICK CHENEY ABOUT GOING
INTO IRAQ.
I NOT ONLY VOTED AGAINST THAT
WAR, I HELPED LEAD THE
OPPOSITION TO THAT WAR AND IF
YOU GO TO MY WEBSITE,
BERNIESANDERS.COM, READ WHAT I
SAID BACK THEN IN 2002.
MUCH OF WHAT I PREDICTED WOULD
HAPPEN IN THAT VACUUM WITH
SADDAM HUSSEIN GONE HAS
HAPPENED.
SECRETARY CLINTON VOTED FOR THE
WAR.
AS SECRETARY OF STATE, SHE
WORKED VERY HARD AS "THE NEW
YORK TIMES" DOCUMENTED TO
OVERTHROW GADHAFI IN LIBYA.
ONCE AGAIN, REGIME CHANGE.
WITHOUT THINKING ABOUT IT A
WHOLE LOT CREATED A POLITICAL
VACUUM.
ISIS CAME IN.
SECRETARY CLINTON IN A DEBATE I
HAD WITH HER A MONTH OR SO AGO,
SHE TALKED ABOUT HENRY KISSINGER
PRAISING HER ACHIEVEMENTS.
IN MY VIEW, HENRY KISSINGER WAS
ONE OF THE WORST SECRETARY OF
STATES IN THE HISTORY OF THE
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
VERY DESTRUCTIVE POLICIES.
SO I THINK SECRETARY CLINTON AND
I LOOK AT FOREIGN POLICY IN VERY
DIFFERENT WAYS.
I AM CONFIDENT THAT I HAVE THE
JUDGMENT TO BRING TOGETHER
PEOPLE, TO CREATE A FOREIGN
POLICY THAT WORKS FOR ISRAEL,
THAT WORKS FOR THE PALESTINIANS,
THAT WORKS FOR THE PEOPLE
THROUGHOUT THIS WORLD.
>> ONE OF THE THINGS THAT
SECRETARY CLINTON TALKED ABOUT
IN HER AIPAC SPEECH IS
CONTINUING MILITARY AID TO
ISRAEL WITH THE MOST ADVANCED
WEAPON SYSTEMS AVAILABLE.
YOU IN THE PAST HAVE SAID YOUR
LONG-TERM HOPE THAT U.S. POLICY
SHIFTS FROM MORE MILITARY AID TO
ISRAEL TO MORE ECONOMIC AID.
THE U.S. GAVE ABOUT $3 BILLION A
YEAR IN MILITARY AID.
WOULD YOU CONTINUE THAT MUCH
MILITARY AID?
>> WELL, I THINK WE'VE GOT TO DO
BOTH.
I THINK ISRAEL NEEDS MILITARY
AID.
I CAN'T GIVE YOU THE EXACT
NUMBER.
BUT THIS IS WHAT I WILL ALSO
TELL YOU.
I WANT TO SEE THE UNITED STATES
PROVIDING ECONOMIC ASSISTANCE TO
THE REGION.
I WANT TO SEE THE UNITED STATES
WORKING ON WATER ISSUES IN THE
REGION WHICH ARE MAJOR, MAJOR
PROBLEM IN MANY OF THE ARAB
COUNTRIES.
I WANT TO SEE THE INTERNATIONAL
COMMUNITY WITH THE HELP OF
ISRAEL, WITH THE HELP OF THE
UNITED STATES REBUILDING THE
DEVASTATION IN GAZA.
AT THE END OF THE DAY, LONG
TERM, NOT GOING TO HAPPEN
TOMORROW, I WOULD MUCH PREFER TO
SEE MONEY GOING INTO THAT REGION
FOR ECONOMIC DEVELOPMENT,
SCHOOLS, HEALTH CARE,
INFRASTRUCTURE RATHER THAN JUST
WEAPONS OF DESTRUCTION.
>> BUT FOR NOW, WOULD YOU
CONTINUE THE SAME AMOUNT OF AID
THAT ISRAEL HAS BEEN GETTING IN
TERMS OF MILITARY ASSISTANCE?
>> I CAN'T GIVE YOU THAT.
I JUST DON'T KNOW THE ANSWER.
IT'S A LOT OF MONEY AND MAYBE
BUT I'VE GOT TO TAKE A HARD LOOK
AT IT AND TALK TO A NUMBER OF
PEOPLE.
BUT ISRAEL -- LET ME BE CLEAR --
LET ME BE CLEAR.
ISRAEL HAS THE RIGHT TO DEFEND
ITSELF, PERIOD.
>> WOULD YOU RECOGNIZE JERUSALEM
AS THE CAPITAL OF ISRAEL AND
MOVE THE U.S. EMBASSY TO
JERUSALEM?
>> I DON'T KNOW THE ANSWER TO
THAT ONE AS WELL.
I THINK THE STATUS QUO, IN
GENERAL, I AM SYMPATHETIC TO
WHAT PRESIDENT OBAMA HAS DONE IN
THAT AREA AND I AM NOT HAPPY,
FOR EXAMPLE, WITH SOME OF THE
BEHAVIOR OF PRIME MINISTER
NETANYAHU.
ESPECIALLY WHEN HE WENT TO A
JOINT SESSION OF CONGRESS
WITHOUT EVEN NOTIFYING PRESIDENT
OBAMA THAT HE WAS COMING.
SO, IN GENERAL, I THINK THAT,
YOU KNOW, PRESIDENT OBAMA -- I
KNOW HE HAS BEEN CRITICIZED A
LOT, BUT I AM SUPPORTIVE OF MANY
OF HIS EFFORTS IN THE MIDDLE
EAST.
>> HILLARY CLINTON HAILED HER
DEAL IN THE IRAN NUCLEAR DEAL.
YOU SAY IT DOESN'T ACHIEVE
EVERYTHING YOU WOULD LIKE.
WHAT DO YOU THINK SHE AND THE
OBAMA ADMINISTRATION LEFT OUT,
DID NOT GET IN THE DEAL?
>> WELL, THIS IS WHAT I THINK.
I VERY STRONGLY SUPPORTED THE
AGREEMENT TO MAKE SURE THAT IRAN
DID NOT GET A NUCLEAR WEAPON.
AND WE HAVE TO DO EVERYTHING WE
CAN.
AND IF IRAN BREAKS THAT TREATY,
WE'VE GOT TO GO BACK TO
SANCTIONS REMAINS ON THE TABLE.
BUT IN A GENERAL SENSE, WHEN WE
LOOK AT THE ENTIRE REGION, I
THINK WE HAVE GOT TO UNDERSTAND
THAT IT'S NOT JUST IRAN THAT HAS
BEEN A BAD PLAYER AND THEY HAVE
BEEN A BAD PLAYER.
THEY HAVE SUPPORTED TERRORIST
ACTIVITY BUT, YOU KNOW WHAT,
WE'VE GOT TO LOOK AT THE OTHER
MAJOR COUNTRY IN THAT REGION,
SAUDI ARABIA.
AND IF ANYONE THINKS THAT SAUDI
ARABIA IS A MODEL OF
JEFFERSONIAN DEMOCRACY, YOU HAVE
ANOTHER THING COMING.
THEY HAVE ALSO IN THAT COUNTRY
PUT MONEY INTO TERRORIST
ORGANIZATIONS.
THEY ARE THE FOURTH LARGEST
MILITARY IN THE WORLD -- DEFENSE
DEPARTMENT IN THE WORD.
I WOULD RATHER THEM PLAY A
CONSTRUCTIVE ROLE IN THE FIGHT
AGAINST ISIS ALONG, BY THE WAY,
WITH QATAR, WHICH IS NOW
SPENDING $200 BILLION FOR THE
WORLD CUP IN 2022.
I WANT TO SEE THOSE COUNTRIES
BECOMING ENGAGED IN THE WAR
AGAINST ISIS RATHER THAN SAUDI
ARABIA BEING IN YEMEN AND QATAR
PREPARING FOR THE WORLD CUP.
>> RIGHT.
YOU'VE TALKED IN THE PAST ABOUT
SAUDI ARABIA AND IRAN TEAMING UP
AGAINST ISIS.
HILLARY CLINTON HAS SAID, LOOK,
THAT'S A NONSTARTER.
I MEAN, THAT A LOT OF THESE
COUNTRIES DON'T EVEN VIEW ISIS
AS THEIR PRIMARY ENEMY.
CERTAINLY SAUDI ARABIA VIEWS
IRAN AS A MAJOR FOE.
>> BUT ANDERSON, THAT IS EXACTLY
MY POINT.
YOU KNOW, WE ARE ALLIES WITH
SAUDI ARABIA.
AND IT IS TIME THAT THEY WORK
WITH US.
IN FACT, IN MY VIEW, ISIS IS A
REAL THREAT TO SAUDI ARABIA.
BUT SAUDI ARABIA IN SOME WAYS
HAS PAID OFF AND BOUGHT OFF SOME
OF THESE TERRORIST ORGANIZATIONS
TO PROTECT THEMSELVES.
>> HOW DO YOU FORCE THEM TO GET
INVOLVED AGAINST ISIS?
>> WELL, IT CANNOT JUST BE
ATTACKS ON IRAN.
YOU KNOW, IT'S NOT THAT IRAN IS
WONDERFUL.
THEY ARE INVOLVED IN TERRORIST
ACTIVITIES.
SAUDI ARABIA IS A MONARCHY, DOES
NOT RESPECT WOMEN'S RIGHTS, DOES
NOT HAVE TREE ELECTIONS.
THERE ARE PEOPLE IN SAUDI ARABIA
WHO ARE FUNDED TERRORIST
ORGANIZATIONS.
THAT'S WHAT OUR JOB IS, TO TRY
TO BRING THESE ORGANIZATIONS,
THESE COUNTRIES TOGETHER AND TO
SAY, YOU KNOW WHAT, THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA CAN'T DO IT
ALL FOR YOU.
WE ARE NOT THE POLICEMEN OF THE
WORLD.
OUR MEN AND WOMEN ARE NOT GOING
TO BE INVOLVED IN PERPETUAL
WARFARE.
YOU HAVE THE FOURTH LARGEST
MILITARY IN THE WORLD IN SAUDI
ARABIA.
START USING THAT MILITARY IN A
CONSTRUCTIVE WAY.
WORK WITH OTHER COUNTRIES.
LISTEN TO KING ABDULLAH OF
JORDAN ABOUT THE NEED FOR THE
MUSLIM COUNTRIES TO BE ON THE
GROUND TO DEFEAT ISIS.
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT CUBA.
PRESIDENT OBAMA IS OBVIOUSLY IN
CUBA RIGHT NOW, HISTORIC VISIT.
AS PRESIDENT, WOULD YOU ALSO
MAKE HISTORY?
WOULD YOU INVITE RAUL CASTRO, IF
HE'S STILL THE LEADER OF CUBA,
TO THE WHITE HOUSE?
>> I HAVE LONG BELIEVED THAT WE
SHOULD NORMALIZE RELATIONS WITH
CUBA IN EVERY RESPECT, INCLUDING
DOING AWAY WITH THE ECONOMIC
EMBARGO.
I THINK NORMALIZED RELATIONS
WOULD BE GOOD FOR AMERICANS.
RIGHT NOW, YOU CAN GO TO SAUDI
ARABIA, IT'S A MONARCHY, YOU CAN
GO TO CHINA, IT'S A
DICTATORSHIP.
BUT FOR SOME REASON YOU CAN'T GO
TO CUBA.
WHICH, OF COURSE, IS AN
AUTHORITARIAN COUNTRY.
I THINK AMERICANS SHOULD HAVE
THE RIGHT TO GO WHERE THEY WANT.
SECOND OF ALL, I THINK FOR
AMERICAN BUSINESSES AND JOBS IN
THIS COUNTRY, THERE ARE
INVESTMENT OPPORTUNITIES IN CUBA
WHICH ARE NOW BEING TAKEN
ADVANTAGE OF BY CANADA AND
EUROPE.
WE SHOULD TAKE ADVANTAGE AS
WELL.
SO TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION, YES,
I WANT TO SEE US MOVE AS FORWARD
AS QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE TO
NORMALIZE RELATIONS WITH CUBA.
I APPLAUD PRESIDENT OBAMA FOR
HIS INITIATIVE.
>> NORMALIZE RELATIONS FOR YOU
WOULD MEAN INVITING A LEADER
LIKE RAUL CASTRO TO THE WHITE
HOUSE?
>> WELL, LAST I HEARD, WE'VE
INVITED THE LEADERS OF SAUDI
ARABIA, WE'VE INVITED THE
LEADERS OF CHINA.
WE'VE INVITED THE LEADERS OF A
WHOLE LOT OF AUTHORITARIAN
COUNTRIES TO COME TO THE UNITED
STATES.
I THINK CUBA SHOULD BE TREATED
SIMILARLY.
>> I WANT TO FOLLOW UP TO A
QUESTION YOU WERE ASKED IN MIAMI
RECENTLY.
THE MODERATORS PLAYED A VIDEO OF
YOU BACK IN 1985 IN WHICH YOU
PRA
PRAISED FIDEL CASTRO.
DO YOU THINK THE CUBAN
REVOLUTION WAS GOOD FOR THE
PEOPLE OF CUBA?
>> LOOK, YOU KNOW, THE CUBAN
REVOLUTION TOOK PLACE -- WHEN
WAS IT?
1959?
IT WAS A LONG TIME AGO.
WHAT I SAID, THE MAIN POINT THAT
I MADE, ANDERSON, IS THAT I
DON'T THINK THAT THE UNITED
STATES OF AMERICA SHOULD GO
AROUND OVERTHROWING GOVERNMENTS.
I THINK THE BAY OF PIGS WAS A
DISASTER.
I THINK THE OVERTHROW OF THE
DEMOCRATICALLY ELECTED PRESIDENT
IN GUATEMALA WAS A DISASTER.
I THINK THE OVERTHROW OF THE
DEMOCRATIC ELECTED PRIME
MINISTER IN IRAN WAS A DISASTER.
SO I DON'T THINK THE UNITED
STATES HAS THE LEGAL OR MORAL
RIGHT TO GO AROUND OVERTHROWING
GOVERNMENTS AND I THINK VERY
OFTEN THOSE EFFORTS HAVE
BACKFIRED BRINGING ABOUT A WHOLE
LOT OF INSTABILITY IN REGIONS
THROUGHOUT THIS COUNTRY.
>> BUT AS YOU KNOW, EVEN AT THAT
DEBATE, HILLARY CLINTON WENT
AFTER YOU FOR, IN HER WORDS,
ESSENTIALLY PRAISING THE REGIME
OF FIDEL CASTRO WHICH IN A
GENERAL ELECTION WOULD NO DOUBT
BE USED AGAINST YOU.
>> ANDERSON, LET'S NOT GET
INTO -- LET'S NOT GET INTO RED
BAITING HERE.
HERE IS THE TRUTH.
EVERYBODY KNOWS IT.
CUBA IS A VERY POOR COUNTRY.
ITS ECONOMY IS IN VERY BAD
SHAPE.
IT IS AN AUTHORITARIAN COUNTRY.
DO I SUPPORT THEIR POLITICAL
POLICIES?
OF COURSE I DON'T.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT ELSE?
CUBA PRODUCES A LOT OF
PHYSICIANS IN THIS COUNTRY.
AND YOU KNOW WHERE THEY GO?
THEY GO TO POOR COUNTRIES AROUND
THE WORLD DOING A LOT OF GOOD.
I WISH WE HAD PHYSICIANS IN THIS
COUNTRY, THE NUMBER OF
PHYSICIANS THAT WE NEED TO GO TO
POOR COUNTRIES AROUND THE WORLD.
BY AND LARGE, CUBA'S EDUCATIONAL
SYSTEM FOR A POOR COUNTRY IS
PRETTY GOOD.
WHEN CASTRO CAME TO POWER, THEY
DID A LOT TO ELIMINATE
ILLITERACY IN THAT COUNTRY.
SO, YES, YOU DON'T HAVE TO
PRAISE EVERYTHING ABOUT FIDEL
CASTRO.
IT'S A DICTATORSHIP.
IT'S A POOR ECONOMY.
WE WANT CHANGES.
BUT HAVE SOME GOOD THINGS BEEN
DONE IN CUBA?
YES.
SHOULD THE UNITED STATES GO
AROUND OVERTHROWING GOVERNMENTS
WE DON'T LIKE?
I DON'T T THINK SO.
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT THE
SUPREME COURT.
YOU'RE SUPPORTING PRESIDENT
OBAMA'S PICK JUDGE MERRICK
GARLAND AND YOU SAID YOU WANTED
TO NOMINATE SOMEONE MORE
PROGRESSIVE IF YOU'RE PRESIDENT.
IN WHAT WAY DOES MERRICK GARLAND
FAIL THAT TEST?
>> WELL, I THINK GARLAND IS A
WIDELY RESPECTED AND CLEARLY
INTELLIGENT MAN.
BUT WHAT I HAVE SAID, ANDERSON,
AND YOU'VE HEARD ME SAY IT ON
NUMEROUS OCCASIONS, I BELIEVE
THAT THE SUPREME COURT DECISION
SIX YEARS AGO ON CITIZENS UNITED
WAS ONE OF THE WORST SUPREME
COURT DECISIONS IN THE HISTORY
OF OUR COUNTRY AND, IN FACT, IT
IS PAVING THE WAY TO UNDERMINING
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY AND CREATING
A VERY CORRUPT CAMPAIGN FINANCE
SYSTEM.
I DO HAVE A LITMUS TEST FOR A
SUPREME COURT NOMINEE.
AND THAT IS THAT I WANT THAT
NOMINEE TO BE LOUD AND CLEAR IN
TELLING THE AMERICAN PEOPLE THAT
HE OR SHE WILL VOTE TO OVERTURN
CITIZENS UNITED.
>> PRESIDENT OBAMA SAID RECENTLY
AT A FUND-RAISER THE DEMOCRAT
SUCCESS IN NOVEMBER REQUIRES THE
PARTY TO COME TOGETHER BEHIND A
NOMINEE.
YOU PLEDGE TO STAY IN THE RACE
THROUGH JUNE TO THE CONVENTION.
IF HILLARY CLINTON CLINCHES THE
NOMINATION BEFORE JUNE, ARE YOU
HURTING DEMOCRAT CHANCES OF
STAYING IN THE RAY -- BY STAYING
IN THE RACE?
>> NO.
QUITE THE CONTRARY.
NUMBER ONE, AS YOU KNOW, MANY OF
THE EARLY STATES WERE IN THE
DEEP SOUTH.
SECRETARY CLINTON PICKED UP A
LOT OF DELEGATES.
SHE DID WELL THERE.
NOW WE'RE MOVING TO ANOTHER PART
OF THE COUNTRY.
JUST TOMORROW -- I'M HERE IN
UTAH.
THERE IS GOING TO BE A CAUCUS
HERE.
WE THINK WE'RE GOING TO DO WELL.
WE THINK WE'RE GOING TO DO WELL
IN IDAHO.
WE THINK WE HAVE A CHANCE.
IT'S GOING TO BE TOUGH IN
ARIZONA.
WE HAVE WASHINGTON STATE.
I SPOKE YESTERDAY TO 35,000
PEOPLE IN WASHINGTON STATE IN
THREE SEPARATE LOCATIONS.
WE THINK WE HAVE AN EXCELLENT
CHANCE TO WIN THERE.
WE THINK WE'RE GOING TO DO WELL
IN ALASKA.
IN HAWAII.
WE THINK THAT ONCE WE'RE ON THE
WEST COAST, WE THINK WE'RE GOING
TO DO WELL IN OREGON.
WE THINK WE'RE GOING TO DO WELL
IN CALIFORNIA.
SO TO ANSWER YOUR QUESTION,
NUMBER ONE, I THINK WE HAVE A
ROAD -- A NARROW ROAD BUT A ROAD
TO VICTORY.
NUMBER TWO, IT IS ABSURD.
IT IS COMPLETELY ANTI-DEMOCRATIC
TO TELL SOME OF THE LARGEST
STATES IN THIS COUNTRY,
CALIFORNIA, NEW YORK STATE, YOU
SHOULD NOT HAVE A VOICE IN
HELPING TO SELECT THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINEE.
NUMBER THREE, DEMOCRATS WIN WHEN
THE VOTER TURNOUT IS HIGH.
REPUBLICANS WIN WHEN IT'S LOW.
BY CONTESTING AND HAVING SERIOUS
DEBATES ABOUT THE IMPORTANT
ISSUES FACING THIS COUNTRY,
GETTING PEOPLE INVOLVED IN THE
PROCESS, WE'RE GOING TO DRIVE UP
THE VOTER TURNOUT IN NOVEMBER NO
MATTER WHO THE NOMINEE IS.
NUMBER FOUR, VIRTUALLY EVERY
POLL THAT HAS COME OUT HAS
BERNIE SANDERS DEFEATING DONALD
TRUMP BY VERY LARGE NUMBERS.
LAST NBC POLL HAD ME 19 POINTS
AHEAD OF HIM.
FAR MORE THAN SECRETARY CLINTON.
HERE IN UTAH, OF ALL PLACES, I
WAS 11 POINTS AHEAD OF TRUMP.
SHE WAS TWO POINTS AHEAD OF
TRUMP.
A CBS POLL CAME OUT TODAY HAVING
HER ALL OF FIVE POINTS AHEAD OF
ME NATIONALLY.
WHEN WE STARTED OFF, WE WERE 70
POINTS BEHIND.
I AM NOT A QUITTER.
WE'RE GOING TO FIGHT THIS TO THE
LAST VOTE.
WE'RE GOING TO GIVE EVERY
AMERICAN THE CHANCE TO DECIDE
WHICH CANDIDATE THEY WANT TO BE
THE DEMOCRATIC NOMINEE IN
NOVEMBER.
>> YOU SAVED ME THE PROBLEM OF
BRINGING UP DONALD TRUMP.
SINCE YOU'VE BROUGHT HIM UP, YOU
RECENTLY REFERRED TO HIM AS A
PATHOLOGICAL LIAR.
THAT'S PRETTY TOUGH WORDS.
>> YES.
>> PATHOLOGICAL IS ACTUALLY A
WORD HE HAD USED AGAINST BEN
CARSON WHO IS NOW ENDORSING HIM.
DO YOU THINK HE HAS SOME SORT OF
COMPULSION TOWARDS LYING?
>> LOOK, THIS IS NOT BERNIE
SANDERS, AS I'M SURE YOU ARE
AWARE, THERE HAVE BEEN A NUMBER
OF PUBLICATIONS, POLITICO DID AN
ARTICLE CHECKING WHAT HE SAYS.
POLITO FACT WHICH CHECKS ON WHAT
POLITICIANS SAY, OVERWHELMINGLY,
ALMOST EVERYTHING THAT HE SAYS
IS NOT TRUE.
HE JUST SAYS THINGS OFF THE TOP
OF HIS HEAD.
HE SAW MUSLIMS IN NEW JERSEY,
THOUSANDS CELEBRATING THE
DESTRUCTION OF THE TWIN TOWERS
ON 9/11.
IT NEVER HAPPENED.
TIME AFTER TIME, HE SAYS THINGS
THAT ARE JUST NOT TRUE.
AND I THINK MORE AND MORE PEOPLE
UNDERSTAND THAT.
THAT IS ABOVE AND BEYOND THE
FACT THAT ALMOST EVERY DAY HE IS
INSULTING LATINOS AND MEXICANS,
MUSLIMS, WOMEN,
AFRICAN-AMERICANS.
I MEAN, THERE IS A REASON WHY
THIS GUY WILL NOT BE ELECTED
PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED STATES.
THAT TYPE OF TEMPERAMENT, THAT
KIND OF DIVISIVENESS WHICH HE IS
INGENDERING, THE KIND OF
VIOLENCE WHICH HE IS ALMOST
ENCOURAGING IS NOT WHAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE WANT.
IN UTAH, WHEN I AM BEATING
DONALD TRUMP BY 11 POINTS IN
WHAT IS ONE OF THE MOST
CONSERVATIVE STATES IN THIS
COUNTRY, IT IS CLEAR TO ME THAT
DONALD TRUMP IS NOT GOING TO BE
ELECTED PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
>> YOUR FELLOW SENATOR ELIZABETH
WARREN ON TWITTER SAID SOME
TOUGH WORDS AGAINST DONALD
TRUMP.
AMONG OTHER THINGS, SHE CALLED
HIM A WANNABE TYRANT.
DO YOU AGREE WITH THAT?
>> OH, THERE'S NO QUESTION THAT
HE HAS AUTHORITARIAN TENDENCIES.
YOU KNOW, WHAT REALLY BOGGLED MY
MIND -- AND BY THE WAY,
ANDERSON, IT'S NOT JUST ME.
YOU'VE GOT A LOT OF REPUBLICANS
OUT THERE, CONSERVATIVE
REPUBLICANS WHO ARE LOOKING AT
THIS GUY AND SAYING, WHAT IS
GOING ON?
IT'S WHAT MITT ROMNEY AND PEOPLE
LIKE THAT ARE SAYING.
WHEN HE SUGGESTS AFTER ONE OF
HIS SUPPORTERS PUNCHES OUT A
PROTESTER, KNOCKS HIM DOWN,
SUCKER PUNCHES HIM, TRUMP SAYS,
I'VE GIVEN THOUGHT TO PAYING FOR
THE LEGAL DEFENSE FOR THAT GUY.
WHEN DO YOU THAT, YOU ARE GIVING
A SIGNAL TO YOUR SUPPORTERS TO
SAY, VIOLENCE IS OKAY.
YOU GO AROUND BEATING UP PEOPLE,
WE'LL BE THERE TO SUPPORT YOU
WITH LEGAL COSTS.
SO I THINK THAT DOES HE HAVE A
TENDENCY TOWARDS AUTHORITARIAN,
I THINK THE EVIDENCE IS CLEAR
THAT HE DOES.
>> YOU'RE URGING SUPERDELEGATES
TO BACK YOU, SAYING THAT YOU'LL
FAIR BETTER AGAINST DONALD
TRUMP.
YOU TALKED ABOUT THAT TONIGHT
RATHER THAN HILLARY CLINTON.
THE CLINTON CAMP SAYS IN PRIVATE
THAT YOU POLL BETTER ESSENTIALLY
BECAUSE YOU HAVEN'T BEEN
TARGETED YET BY REPUBLICANS AS A
SOCIALIST WHO WILL RAISE TAXES
ON THE MIDDLE CLASS.
IS THAT WHY YOU'RE POLLING
BETTER?
>> WELL, NO.
THAT'S NONSENSE.
FIRST OF ALL, I WASN'T BORN
YESTERDAY.
AND THIS IS NOT MY FIRST
CAMPAIGN.
CERTAINLY IT'S MY FIRST CAMPAIGN
FOR PRESIDENT.
I'VE RUN A NUMBER OF TIMES IN
VERMONT AGAINST VERY WEALTHY
PEOPLE WHO HAVE OPPOSITION
RESEARCH AND THEY THROW A LOT OF
GARBAGE AT ME.
MY LAST ELECTION IN VERMONT I
WON BY 71%.
IN THIS PRIMARY PROCESS I HAVE
VERMONTERS WHO HAVE SEEN ALL OF
THE CRAP THAT PEOPLE CAN THROW
AT YOU.
BUT I THINK WHEN YOU LOOK AT A
RACE AGAINST TRUMP, THERE IS NO
QUESTION THAT WE ARE A MUCH
STRONGER CAMPAIGN THAN IS
HILLARY CLINTON.
WE WILL GET ALL OR VIRTUALLY ALL
OF THE DEMOCRATIC SUPPORT.
NOT MANY DEMOCRATS WILL BE
VOTING FOR DONALD TRUMP.
BUT WE WILL DO MUCH BETTER THAN
HILLARY CLINTON WITH THE
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE WHO ARE
INDEPENDENTS.
THE MILLIONS OF PEOPLE, FOR
WHATEVER REASON, FEEL
UNCOMFORTABLE WITH HILLARY
CLINTON.
SO THE POLLS SHOW AND WHAT I
THINK THE EVIDENCE IS PRETTY
CLEAR, WE ARE THE CANDIDATE TO
BEAT DONALD TRUMP AND I THINK
MORE AND MORE DEMOCRATS ARE
SEEING THAT.
>> ONE OF THE IMPACTS YOU'VE HAD
ON THIS RACE IS HILLARY CLINTON
HAS MOVED TO A NUMBER OF YOUR
POSITIONS TO THE KEYSTONE
PIPELINE AND ASIAN TRADE AND
CALLING ON THE GOVERNOR OF
MICHIGAN TO RESIGN.
SHE SEEMED TO DO THAT RIGHT
BEFORE THE DEBATE IN FLINT.
IF YOU COULD MOVE HER ON ONE
MORE POLICY, WHAT WOULD IT BE?
>> LOOK, ANDERSON, YOU KNOW, I
THINK THE AMERICAN PEOPLE KNOW
IT IS NOT WHAT A CANDIDATE SAYS
DURING A CAMPAIGN.
WHAT THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, THE
IDEAS THAT THEY STEAL FROM OTHER
PEOPLE, WHAT IS IMPORTANT IS
WHAT YOUR RECORD IS AND WHAT
YOUR HISTORY IS.
RIGHT NOW, HILLARY CLINTON HAS
SUPER PACS RAISING HUGE AMOUNTS
OF MONEY FROM THE FOSSIL FUEL
INDUSTRY AND DRUG COMPANIES.
I THINK MOST AMERICANS
UNDERSTAND THAT SOMEBODY CANNOT
BE A SERIOUS AGENT FOR CHANGE
WHEN THEY ARE SO CLOSE TO SOME
OF THE MOST POWERFUL INTERESTS
IN THIS COUNTRY.
WE HAVE RAISED MONEY THROUGH 5
MILLION INDIVIDUAL CONTRIBUTIONS
AVERAGE 27 BUCKS A PIECE.
I HAVE SPENT MY ENTIRE POLITICAL
LIFE TAKING ON WALL STREET,
TAKING ON THE DRUG COMPANIES,
TAKING ON THE FOSSIL FUEL
INDUSTRY.
THAT IS THE KIND OF RECORD THAT
I THINK THE AMERICAN PEOPLE AND
DEMOCRATS WILL LOOK AT AND
THAT'S WHY I AM CONFIDENT WE ARE
GOING TO DO BETTER AND BETTER AS
THIS CAMPAIGN PROCEEDS.
>> I SAW YOU ON THE CAMPAIGN
TRAIL THE OTHER DAY.
YOU SAID YOU NEVER WENT TO ONE
OF DONALD TRUMP'S WEDDING,
CLEARLY REFERRING TO SECRETARY
CLINTON WHO DID ATTEND DONALD
TRUMP'S WEDDING.
SHOULD VOTERS TAKE THAT INTO
CONSIDERATION THAT SHE WAS ONCE
FRIENDLY WITH DONALD TRUMP, THAT
SHE RECEIVED FUNDS FROM DONALD
TRUMP?
>> I THINK, YOU KNOW, PEOPLE
HAVE GOT TO TAKE EVERYTHING INTO
CONSIDERATION.
LOOK, THIS IS NO SECRET.
HILLARY CLINTON IS THE CANDIDATE
OF THE ESTABLISHMENT.
SHE IS THE CANDIDATE -- THE
DEMOCRATIC CANDIDATE OF THE BIG
MONEY INTERESTS.
SHE HAS THE SUPPORT OF PUBLIC
OFFICIALS ALL OVER AMERICA.
WHAT IT IS ALSO CLEAR, WE ARE
RUNNING AN INSURGENT CAMPAIGN.
WE ARE THE ANTI-ESTABLISHMENT
CAMPAIGN.
WE ARE THE CAMPAIGN THAT IS
CALLING FOR A POLITICAL
REVOLUTION, THAT HAS TAKEN ON
THE BILLIONAIRE CLASS AND WALL
STREET.
AND I THINK AS PEOPLE LOOK AT
OUR RECORDS, HOW WE RAISE MONEY,
WHAT OUR VIEWS ARE ON INCOME AND
WEALTH INEQUALITY, WHO WAS THERE
FIRST, WHO WAS HELPING TO LEAD
THAT FIGHT, THE WAR IN IRAQ,
FRACKING, ON ALL PUBLIC COLLEGES
AND UNIVERSITIES BEING
TUITION-FREE, DEMANDING THAT THE
WEALTHY AND LARGE CORPORATIONS
START PAYING THEIR FAIR SHARE OF
TAXES, WHO IS CALLING FOR THE
UNITED STATES TO JOIN THE REST
OF THE INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD FOR
A MEDICARE FOR ALL HEALTH CARE
SYSTEM GUARANTEEING HEALTH CARE
TO ALL PEOPLE?
THAT IS BERNIE SANDERS.
AND THAT IS WHY WE ARE CREATING
SO MUCH EXCITEMENT AT THE
GRASSROOTS LEVEL.
>> SENATOR SANDERS, THANK YOU
VERY MUCH.
GOOD TO TALK TO YOU TONIGHT.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>>> HOW HAVE WHAT WE HEARD
IMPACT TOMORROW'S CONTEST?
MUCH MORE FROM THE CNN ELECTION
CENTER AHEAD.