>>> ANOTHER PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
>> I DON'T THINK ONE WILL BE
VERY GOOD.
>> WHY IS THAT?
>> BECAUSE WE'RE NOT IN IT.
>> LINDSEY GRAHAM AND JOHN
McCAIN GAVE IT THEIR BEST.
NOW IT'S TIME FOR THE SEVEN
CANDIDATES ON THE STAGE.
LET'S SEND IT TO MARTHA RADDATZ
AND DAVID MUIR.
TAKE IT AWAY, GUYS.
>> THANK YOU, GEORGE.
AND WELCOME TO YOU AT HOME AND
OUR AUDIENCE OF MORE THAN 1,000.
MO
MARTHA AND I, ALONG WITH WMRT
ARE HONORED TO BE HERE.
THE CANDIDATES ARE ALL HERE AND
THE NEW HAMPSHIRE REPUBLICAN
DEBATE STARTS NOW.
>> THE TIME IS HERE.
IT'S MAKE OR BREAK.
STARTING NOW.
THE REPUBLICANS DEBATE.
LIVE FROM ST. ANSELM COLLEGE IN
MANCHESTER, NEW HAMPSHIRE.
DAVID MUIR AND MARTHA RADDATZ.
>> GOOD EVENING, AGAIN.
EVERYONE.
THIS IS THE FIRST TIME SINCE
IOWA AND THE ONLY TIME BEFORE
THE NEW HAMPSHIRE PRIMARY THAT
THE REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES WILL
HAVE THE OPPORTUNITY TO FACE
EACH OTHER.
THE PEOPLE OF IOWA HAVE BEEN
HEARD.
NOW IT'S NEW HAMPSHIRE'S TURN.
IN JUST THREE DAYS, VOTERS HERE
WILL DECIDE WHO THEY THINK
SHOULD BE THE REPUBLICAN NOMINEE
FOR PRESIDENT.
>> QUESTIONS OF LEADERSHIP AND
CHARACTER HAVE DOMINATED THE
NEWS EVER SINCE THE IOWA
CAUCUSES A FEW DAYS AGO.
HERE WITH US TO QUESTION THE
CANDIDATES THIS EVENING, JOSH
McKELVIN FROM WMUR HERE IN
MANCHESTER, AND AUTHOR AND
COMMENTATOR MARY KATHERINE HAMM.
>> LET'S WELCOME THE CANDIDATES
FOR THE REPUBLICAN NOMINATION
FOR PRESIDENT.
NEW JERSEY GOVERNOR CHRIS
CHRISTIE.
>> DR. BEN CARSON.
>>
TEXAS SENATOR TED CRUZ.
>> BUSINESSMAN DONALD TRUMP.
>> FLORIDA SENATOR MARCO RUBIO.
>> FORMER FLORIDA GOVERNOR, JEB
BUSH.
>> AND OHIO GOVERNOR JOHN
KASICH.
>> LADIES AND GENTLEMEN, THE
REPUBLICAN CANDIDATES.
>> AND DR. BEN CARSON, PLEASE
COME OUT ON THE STAGE.
HE'S STANDING THERE, AS WELL.
DR. CARSON.
>> AND DONALD TRUMP.
>> AND LASTLY, WE WELCOME BACK
TO THE DEBATE STAGE, DONALD
TRUMP.
>> I CAN SINTRODUCE KASICH?
>> YES, YES, WE'RE GOING TO
INTRODUCE OHIO GOVERNOR JOHN
KASICH.
>> THE APPLAUSE SO LOUD HERE IN
THE HALL.
>> THE APPLAUSE YOU COULDN'T
HEAR, WE COULDN'T HEAR, EITHER.
THAT'S A GOOD SIGN FOR THE
EXCITEMENT THIS EVENING.
GENTLEMEN, THANK YOU FOR BEING
HERE TONIGHT, JUST DAYS BEFORE
VOTERS HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE
MAKE THEIR DECISIONS.
THE RULES ARE SIMPLE.
AND HAVE BEEN AGREED TO BY ALL
THE CAMPAIGNS.
THERE WILL BE 60 SECONDS TO
ANSWER AND IF ANOTHER CANDIDATE
IS MENTIONED IN THAT ANSWER,
THAT CANDIDATE WILL HAVE 30
SECONDS TO RESPOND.
THERE ARE GREEN, YELLOW AND RED
LIGHTS THAT EACH CANDIDATE WILL
SEE TO SIGNAL WHEN TIME IS UP
AND THEY WILL ALSO HEAR THIS
SOUND.
>> SO, LET'S GET STARTED.
WE WELCOME YOU ALL TO THE DEBATE
STAGE HERE TONIGHT.
WE'RE GOING TO TACKLE THE ISSUES
AMERICANS ARE MOST CONCERNED
ABOUT, THE ECONOMY, ISIS,
HOMELAND SECURITY.
AND HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, SOME
OF THE MOST HEATED RHETORIC YET
OVER WHO IS BEST SUITED TO STEP
IN ON DAY ONE, WHO HAS THE
EXPERIENCE, WHO HAS THE
TEMPERAMENT TO BE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF.
MR. TRUMP, SENATOR CRUZ HAS SAID
ABOUT YOU RIGHT HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE THIS WEEK, QUOTE, I
DON'T KNOW ANYONE WHO WOULD BE
COMFORTABLE WITH SOMEONE WHO
BEHAVES THIS WAY, HAVING HIS
FINGER ON THE BUTTON.
WE'RE LIABLE TO WAKE UP ONE
MORNING, AND IF HE WERE
PRESIDENT, HE WOULD NUKE
DENMARK.
SAYING THAT'S
TEMPERAMENT TO KEEP THIS COUNTRY
SAFE.
>> I THINK I HAVE THE BEST
TEMPERAMENT.
I BUILT A MASSIVE CORPORATION.
I EMPLOY THOUSANDS AND THOUSANDS
OF PEOPLE.
I'VE GOTTEN ALONG WITH PEOPLE
FOR YEARS AND YEARS, HAVE
TREMENDOUS RELATIONSHIPS WITH
MANY PEOPLE, INCLUDING
POLITICIANS ON BOTH SIDES.
AND NO MATTER HOW YOU CUT IT,
WHEN I CAME OUT, I HIT
IMMIGRATION, I HIT IT VERY HARD.
EVERYBODY SAYS, OH, THE
TEMPERAMENT, BECAUSE I TALKED
ABOUT ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION.
NOW, EVERYBODY'S COMING TO ME,
THEY'RE ALL TRYING TO SAY, WELL,
HE'S RIGHT, WE HAVE TO COME TO
HIM.
I HIT OTHER THINGS.
I TALKED ABOUT MUSLIMS.
WE HAVE A PROBLEM.
NOBODY ELSE WANTED TO MENTION
THE PROBLEM.
I BROUGHT IT UP.
I TOOK A LOT OF HEAT.
WE HAVE TO HAVE A TEMPORARY
SOMETHING, BECAUSE THERE'S
SOMETHING GOING ON THAT'S NOT
GOOD.
AND REMEMBER THIS, I'M THE ONLY
ONE UP HERE, WHEN THE WAR IN
IRAQ -- I WAS THE ONE THAT SAID,
DON'T GO, DON'T DO IT, YOU'RE
GOING TO DESTABILIZE THE MIDDLE
EAST.
I'M NOT ONE WITH THE TRIGGER.
OTHER PEOPLE UP HERE, BELIEVE
ME, WOULD BE A LOT FASTER.
BUT I'LL BUILD THE MILL
ARBITRARY STRONGER, BIGGER,
BETTER, AND NOBODY IS GOING TO
MESS WITH US.
THAT, I CAN TELL YOU.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BRING THIS TO SENATOR
CRUZ THEN.
YOU DID SAID OF TRUMP'S
BEHAVIOR, THAT'S NOT THE TEMPT
PROGRAM OF A LEADER TO KEEP THIS
COUNTRY SAFE.
WHY NOT?
>> WELL, THE ASSESSMENT THE
VOTERS ARE MAKING HERE, THEY ARE
EVALUATING EACH AND EVERY ONE OF
US.
THEY ARE LOOKING TO OUR
EXPERIENCE.
KNOWLEDGE.
THEY ARE LOOKING TO OUR
TEMPERAMENT AND JUDGMENT.
THEY ARE LOOKING TO OUR CLARITY
OF VISION AND OUR STRENGTH OF
RESOLVE.
THE WORLD IS GETTING MUCH MORE
DANGEROUS.
WE'VE HAD SEVEN YEARS WITH
BARACK OBAMA IN THE OVAL OFFICE,
A COMMANDER IN CHIEF THAT IS
UNWILLING EVEN TO ACKNOWLEDGE
THE ENEMY WE'RE FACING.
THIS IS A PRESIDENT WHO, IN THE
WAKE OF PARIS, IN THE WAKE OF
SAN BERNARDINO, WILL NOT EVEN
USE THE WORD RADICAL ISLAMIC
TERRORISM, MUCH LESS FOCUS ON
DEFEATING THE ENEMY.
I AM CONVINCED, EVERY INDIVIDUAL
STANDING ON THIS STAGE, WOULD
MAKE A MUCH BETTER COMMANDER IN
CHIEF THAN BARACK OBAMA OR
HILLARY CLINTON OR BERNIE
SANDERS.
AND THE PRIMARY VOTERS ARE
MAKING THE ASSESSMENT FOR EACH
OF US, WHO IS BEST PREPARED TO
KEEP THIS COUNTRY SAFE, TO
REBUILD THE MILITARY, TO REBUILD
OUR NAVY, OUR AIR FORCE, OUR
ARMY, OUR MARINES, AND TO ENSURE
THAT WE KEEP AMERICA SAFE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, I DID ASK ABOUT
MR. TRUM.
YOU SAID HE DOESN'T HAVE THE
TEMPERAMENT.
DO YOU STAND BY THOSE WORDS?
>> I THINK THAT IS AN ASSESSMENT
THE VOTERS ARE GOING TO MAKE.
THEY ARE GOING TO ASSESS WHO IS
LEVEL-HEADED.
WHO HAS CLEAR VISION.
WHO HAS JUDGMENT.
WHO CAN CONFRONT OUR ENEMIES,
WHO CAN CONFRONT THE THREATS WE
FACE IN THIS COUNTRY.
AND WHO CAN HAVE THE JUDGMENT
WHEN TO ENGAGE AND WHEN NOT TO
ENGAGE, BOTH ARE INCREDIBLY
IMPORTANT FOR A COMMANDER IN
CHIEF, KNOWING HOW TO GO AFTER
OUR ENEMIES.
IN THE CASE OF IRAN, FOR
EXAMPLE, WHO HAS THE CLARITY OF
VISION TO UNDERSTAND THAT THE
AYATOLLAH, WHEN HE CHANTS DEATH
TO AMERICA, HE MEANS IT.
WE NEED A PRESIDENT WITH THE
JUDGMENT AND RESOLVE TO KEEP
THIS COUNTRY SAFE.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE ON THIS
NOTION OF READINESS --
>> AM I ALLOWED TO RESPOND?
I HAVE TO RESPOND.
>> IF YOU WOULD LIKE TO.
>> I RESPECT WHAT TED JUST SAID,
BUT IF YOU NOTICED, HE DIDN'T
ANSWER YOUR QUESTION.
AND THAT'S WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN -- IT'S OKAY.
THAT'S WHAT'S GOING TO HAPPEN
WITH OUR ENEMIES AND THE PEOPLE
WE COMPETE AGAINST.
WE'RE GOING TO WIN WITH TRUMP.
WE'RE GOING TO WIN.
WE DON'T WIN ANYMORE.
OUR COUNTRY DOESN'T WIN ANYMORE.
WE'RE GOING TO WIN WITH TRUMP.
AND PEOPLE BACK DOWN WITH TRUMP.
AND THAT'S WHAT I LIKE AND
THAT'S WHAT THE COUNTRY IS GOING
TO LIKE.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
AND WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE ON
THIS NOTION OF READINESS AND ON
EXPERIENCE, BUT I WANT TO ASK
ABOUT A HEADLINE THAT WAS BACK
IN THE PAPERS AGAIN THIS
MORNING.
DR. CARSON, ON THE DAY OF THE
IOWA CAUCUSES, THE CRUZ CAMPAIGN
SENTOUS MESSAGES SAYING DR. BEN
CARSON WILL BE PLANNING TO
SUSPEND HIS CAMPAIGN FOLLOWING
TONIGHT'S CAUCUSES.
PLEASE INFORM ANY CARSON
CAUCUS-GOERS OF THIS NEWS.
AS WE CAN ALL SEE, YOU ARE STILL
STANDING HERE TONIGHT.
LATE THIS WEEK, YOUR CAMPAIGN
SENT THIS E-MAIL, QUOTE, THIS
KIND OF DECEITFUL BEHAVIOR IS
WHY THE AMERICAN PEOPLE DON'T
TRUST POLITICIANS.
IF SENATOR CRUZ DOES NOT ACT,
THEN HE CLEARLY REPRESENTS D.C.
VALUES.
WHAT KIND OF ACTION DO YOU THINK
SENATOR CRUZ SHOULD TAKE?
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, WHEN I WASN'T
INTRODUCED NUMBER TWO, AS WAS
THE PLAN, I THOUGHT MAYBE HE
THOUGHT I ALREADY HAD DROPPED
OUT, BUT -- BUT YOU KNOW, TODAY
IS THE 105th ANNIVERSARY, OR --
105th BIRTHDAY OF RONALD REAGAN.
HIS 11th COMMANDMENT WAS NOT TO
SPEAK ILL OF ANOTHER REPUBLICAN,
SO, I'M NOT GOING TO USE THIS
OPPORTUNITY TO SAVAGE THE
REPUTATION OF SENATOR CRUZ.
BUT I WILL SAY -- I WILL SAY --
I WILL SAY THAT I WAS VERY
DISAPPOINTED THAT MEMBERS OF HIS
TEAM THOUGHT SO LITTLE OF ME
THAT THEY THOUGHT THAT AFTER
HAVING HUNDREDS, IF NOT
THOUSANDS OF VOLUNTEERS AND
COLLEGE STUDENTS WHO SACRIFICED
THEIR TIME AND WERE DEDICATED TO
THE CAUSE, ONE EVEN DIED, TO
THINK THAT I WOULD JUST WALK
AWAY TEN MINUTES BEFORE THE
CAUCUS AND SAY, FORGET ABOUT YOU
GUYS -- I MEAN, WHO WOULD DO
SOMETHING LIKE THAT?
I DON'T THINK ANYONE ON THIS
STAGE WOULD DO SOMETHING LIKE
THAT.
AND TO ASSUME THAT SOMEONE WO
WOULD, WHAT DOES THAT TELL YOU?
SO, UNFORTUNATELY, IT DID
HAPPEN.
IT GIVES US A VERY GOOD EXAMPLE
OF CERTAIN TYPES OF WASHINGTON
ETHICS.
WASHINGTON ETHICS, BASICALLY
SAYS, IF IT'S LEGAL, YOU DO WHAT
YOU NEED TO DO IN ORDER TO WIN.
THAT'S NOT MY ETHICS.
MY ETHICS IS, YOU DO WHAT'S
RIGHT.
>> SENATOR CRUZ -- DR. CARSON,
THANK YOU.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU HAVE SAID THAT
DR. CARSON AND HIS WIFE HAVE
BECOME FRIENDS OF YOURS.
I'M CURIOUS WHY YOU DIDN'T CALL
AHEAD OF TIME TO EITHER THE
DOCTOR OR HIS WIFE OR HAD YOUR
CAMPAIGN CHECK IN BEFORE SENDING
OUT THOSE MESSAGES.
>> BEN IS A GOOD AND HONORABLE
MAN AND BEN AND CANDY HAVE
BECOME FRIENDS.
HE HAS AN AMAZING LIFE STORY
THAT HAS INSPIRED MILLIONS
INCLUDING ME.
WHEN THIS TRANSPIRED, I
APOLOGIZED TO HIM THEN AND I DO
SO NOW, BEN, I'M SORRY.
LET ME TELL YOU THE FACTS OF
WHAT OCCURRED FOR THOSE WHO ARE
INTERESTED IN KNOWING.
ON MONDAY NIGHT, ABOUT 6:30
P.M., CNN REPORTED THAT BEN WAS
NOT GOING FROM IOWA TO NEW
HAMPSHIRE OR SOUTH CAROLINA,
RATHER, HE WAS, QUOTE, TAKING A
BREAK FROM CAMPAIGNING.
THEY REPORTED THAT ON TELEVI
TELEVISION, CNN'S POLITICAL
ANCHORS, JAKE TAPPER AND DANA
BASH AND WOLF BLITZER SAID IT
WAS HIGHLY UNUSUAL AND HIGHLY
SIGNIFICANT.
MY POLITICAL TEAM SAW CNN'S
REPORT BREAKING NEWS AND THEY
FORWARDED THAT NEWS TO OUR
VOLUNTEERS, IT WAS BEING COVERED
ON LIVE TELEVISION.
NOW, AT THE TIME, I WAS AT THE
CAUCUSES, I WAS GETTING READY TO
SPEAK AT THE CAUCUSES JUST LIKE
BEN WAS, JUST LIKE EVERYONE ELSE
WAS.
I KNEW NOTHING ABOUT THIS.
A COUPLE HOURS LATER, I WAS TOLD
THAT BEN WAS UNHAPPY.
I CALLED HIM THAT EVENING
BECAUSE I RESPECT HIM VERY, VERY
HIGHLY.
I DIDN'T REACH HIM THAT EVENING.
I REACHED HIM THE NEXT DAY AND
APOLOGIZED.
HE ASKED ME THEN, HE SAID, TED,
WOULD YOU MAKE THIS APOLOGIZE IN
PUBLIC.
I SAID, YES, I WILL.
AND I DID SO.
I REGRET THAT SUBSEQUENTLY, CNN
REPORTED ON THAT, THEY DIDN'T
CORRECT THAT STORY UNTIL 9:15
THAT NIGHT, SO, FROM 6:30 P.M.
TO 9:15, THAT'S WHAT CNN WAS
REPORTING.
SUBSEQUENT TO THAT INITIAL
REPORT, BEN'S CAMPAIGN PUT OUT A
STATEMENT SAYING THAT HE WAS NOT
SUSPENDING HIS CAMPAIGN, I WISH
THAT OUR CAMPAIGN STAFF HAD
FORWARDED THAT STATEMENT, THEY
WERE UNAWARE OF IT, I WISH THAT
THEY HAD, THAT'S WHY I
APOLOGIZED.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON HERE.
BACK TO THE ISSUES --
>> SINCE I WAS MENTIONED --
>> DR. CARSON --
>> THIS IS GREAT.
I WANT YOU ALL TO MENTION ME
WHEN YOU SAY SOMETHING.
IN FACT THE TIMELINE INDICATES
THAT INITIAL
FOLLOWED BY ANOTHER ONE WITHIN
ONE MINUTE THAT CLARIFIED THAT I
WAS NOT DROPPING OUT, SO, WHAT
HAPPENED TO THAT ONE, IT IS
UNCLEAR.
BUT THE BOTTOM LINE IS, WE CAN
SEE WHAT HAPPENED, EVERYBODY CAN
SEE WHAT HAPPENED AND YOU CAN
MAKE YOUR OWN JUDGMENT.
>> DR. CARSON, THANK YOU.
THANK YOU, DOCTOR.
SENATOR RUBIO.
I WANT TO STAY ON THE ISSUE OF
READINESS TO BE PRESIDENT AND
EXPERIENCE AND QUESTIONS ABOUT
YOU BEING A FIRST-TERM SENATOR.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE WARNING VOTERS
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE AGAINST
VOTING FOR ANOTHER FIRST-TERM
SENATOR AS AMERICA DID WITH
BARACK OBAMA IN 2008.
ARGUING THAT YOU ARE, QUOTE, NOT
READY TO BE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
AND SENATOR SANTORUM, WHO WE ALL
KNOW, DROPPED OUT OF THE RACE
AND ENDORSED YOU, HAD A HARD
TIME WHEN ASKED ON NATIONAL
TELEVISION, LISTING YOUR
ACCOMPLISHMENTS AS SENATOR.
TONIGHT, WHAT ARE YOUR
ACCOMPLISHMENTS IN THE SENATE
THAT DEMONSTRATE YOU ARE READY
TO BE PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES?
>> FROM PROTECTING THE PEOPLE OF
FLORIDA, TO BRINGING
ACCOUNTABILITY TO THE V.A., TO
THE GIRL'S COUNT ACT, TO
SANCTIONING GROUPS, I'M PROUD OF
MY WORK.
I WILL SAY, IF POLITICS BECOMES
AND THE PRESIDENCY BECOMES ABOUT
ELECTING PEOPLE THAT HAVE BEEN
IN THE SENATE THE LONGEST, WE
SHOULD ALL RALLY AROUND JOE
BIDEN.
HE'S BEEN AROUND 1,000 YEARS.
I DON'T THINK ANY OF US BELIEVE
JOE BIDEN SHOULD BE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES.
AND LET'S DISPEL ONCE AND FOR
ALL WITH THIS FICTION THAT
BARACK OBAMA DOESN'T KNOW WHAT
HE'S DOING.
HE KNOWS EXACTLY WHAT HE'S
DOING.
BARACK OBAMA IS UNDERTAKING AN
EFFORT TO CHANGE THIS COUNTRY,
TO MAKE AMERICA MORE LIKE THE
REST OF THE WORLD.
THAT'S WHY HE PASSED OBAMA CARE
AND THE STIMULUS AND THE DEAL
WITH IRAN.
IT IS AN EFFORT TO CHANGE
AMERICA.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES, WE ARE GOING TO
RE-EMBRACE ALL THE THINGS THAT
MADE AMERICA THE GREATEST NATION
IN THE WORLD, AND WE ARE GOING
TO LEAVE OUR CHILDREN WITH WHAT
THEY DESERVE, THE SINGLE
GREATEST NATION IN THE HISTORY
OF THE WORLD.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
I DO WANT TO ASK GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE, YOU SAID, FOOL ME
ONCE, SHAME ON YOU, FOOL ME
TWICE, SHAME ON ME.
YOU HEARD SENATOR RUBIO MAKE THE
CASE THAT HE HAS THE EXPERIENCE.
YOUR RESPONSE?
>> SURE.
FIRST, LET'S REMEMBER SOMETHING.
EVERY MORNING WHEN A UNITED
STATES SENATOR WAKES UP, THEY
THINK ABOUT WHAT KIND OF SPEECH
CAN I GIVE, OR WHAT KIND OF BILL
CAN I DROP?
EVERY MORNING, WHEN I WAKE UP, I
THINK ABOUT, WHAT KIND OF
PROBLEM DO I NEED TO SOLVE FOR
THE PEOPLE WHO ACTUALLY ELECTED
ME?
IT'S A DIFFERENT EXPERIENCE.
IT'S A MUCH DIFFERENT
EXPERIENCE.
AND THE FACT IS, MARCO, YOU
SHOULDN'T COMPARE YOURSELF TO
JOE BIDEN.
AND YOU SHOULDN'T SAY THAT'S
WHAT WE'RE DOING.
HERE IS EXACTLY WHAT WE'RE
DOING.
YOU HAVE NOT BE INVOLVED IN A
CONSEQUENTIAL DECISION WHERE YOU
HAD TO BE HELD ACCOUNTABLE.
YOU JUST SIMPLY HAVEN'T.
AND THE FACT IS --
WHEN YOU TALK ABOUT HEZBOLLAH
SANCTIONS ACT THAT YOU LIST AS
ONE OF YOUR ACCOMPLISHMENTS, YOU
WEREN'T EVEN THERE TO VOTE FOR
IT.
THAT'S NOT LEADERSHIP.
THAT'S TRUANCY.
THE FACT IS THAT WHAT WE NEED TO
DO, WHAT WE NEED TO DO IN THIS
COUNTRY IS NOT TO MAKE THE SAME
MISTAKE WE MADE EIGHT YEARS AGO.
IT DOES MATTER WHEN THE
CHALLENGES DON'T COME ON A LIST
OF A PIECE OF PAPER OF WHAT TO
VOTE YES OR NO EVERY DAY.
WHEN THE PROBLEMS COME IN FROM
THE PEOPLE THAT YOU SERVE, I
LIKE MARCO RUBIO AND HE'S A
SMART PERSON AND A GOOD GUY, BUT
HE SIMPLY DOES NOT HAVE THE
EXPERIENCE TO BE PRESIDENT OF
THE UNITED STATES AND MAKE THESE
DECISIONS.
WE'VE WATCHED IT HAPPEN,
EVERYBODY.
FOR THE LAST SEVEN YEARS, THE
PEOPLE OF NEW HAMPSHIRE ARE
SMART.
DO NOT MAKE THE SAME MISTAKE
AGAIN.
>> THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> I THINK THE EXPERIENCE IS NOT
JUST WHAT YOU DID, BUT HOW IT
WORKED OUT.
UNDER CHRIS CHRISTIE'S
GOVERNORSHIP OF NEW JERSEY, THEY
HAVE BEEN DOWNGRADED NINE TIMES
IN THEIR CREDIT RATING.
THIS COUNTRY ALREADY HAS A DEBT
PROBLEM.
WE DON'T NEED TO ADD TO IT.
BUT I WOULD ADD THIS.
LET'S DISPEL WITH THIS FICTION
THAT BARACK OBAMA DOESN'T KNOW
WHAT HE'S DOING.
HE KNOWS EXACTLY WHAT HE'S
DOING.
HE IS TRYING TO CHANGE THIS
COUNTRY.
HE WANTS AMERICA TO BECOME MORE
LIKE THE REST OF THE WORLD.
WE DON'T WANT TO BE LIKE THE
REST OF THE WORLD.
WE WANT TO BE THE UNITED STATES
OF AMERICA.
AND WHEN I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT,
THIS WILL BECOME ONCE AGAIN, THE
SINGLE GREATEST NATION IN THE
HISTORY OF THE WORLD, NOT THE
DISASTER BARACK OBAMA HAS
IMPOSED UPON US.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BRING IN GOVERNOR BUSH
ON THIS.
>> EXCUSE ME --
>> IF YOU WOULD --
>> HE MENTIONED MY RECORD IN
THERE.
I GET A CHANCE TO RESPOND.
YOU SEE, EVERYBODY, I WANT THE
PEOPLE AT HOME TO THINK ABOUT
THIS.
THIS IS WHAT WASHINGTON, D.C.
DOES.
THE DRIVE-BY SHOT AT THE
BEGINNING WITH INCORRECT AND
INCOMPLETE INFORMATION AND THEN
THE MEMORIZED 25-SECOND SPEECH
THAT IS EXACTLY WHAT HIS
ADVISERS GAVE HIM.
SEE MARCO -- MARCO, THE THING IS
THIS.
WHEN YOU'RE PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, WHEN YOU ARE A
GOVERNOR OF A STATE, THAT
MEMORIZED SPEECH DOESN'T SOLVE
ONE PROBLEM FOR ONE PERSON.
THEY EXPECT YOU TO PLOW THE
SNOW.
THEY EXPECT YOU TO GET THE
SCHOOLS OPEN.
AND WHEN THE WORST NATURAL
DISASTER IN YOUR STATE'S HISTORY
HITS YOU, THEY EXPECT YOU TO
REBUILD THEIR STATE, WHICH IS
WHAT I'VE DONE.
NONE OF THAT STUFF HAPPENS ON
THE FLOOR OF THE UNITED STATES
SENATE.
IT'S A FINE JOB, I'M GLAD YOU
RAN FOR IT, BUT IT DOES NOT
PREPARE YOU FOR PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> CHRIS -- CHRIS, YOUR STATE
GOT HIT BY A MASSIVE SNOWSTORM
TWO WEEKS AGO.
YOU DIDN'T EVEN WANT TO GO BACK.
THEY HAD TO SHAKE YOU INTO GOING
BACK.
YOU STAYED THERE FOR 36 HOURS
AND THEN HE LEFT AND CAME BACK
TO CAMPAIGN.
HERE'S THE BOTTOM LINE.
THIS NOTION THAT BARACK OBAMA
DOESN'T KNOW WHAT HE'S DOING --
>> THERE IT IS.
THERE IT IS.
THE MEMORIZED 25-SECOND SPEECH.
>> THAT'S THE REASON WHY THIS
CAMPAIGN IS SO IMPORTANT.
BECAUSE I THINK THIS NOTION -- I
THINK THIS IS AN IMPORTANT
POINT.
WE HAVE TO UNDERSTAND WHAT WE'RE
GOING THROUGH HERE.
WE ARE NOT FACING A PRESIDENT
THAT DOESN'T KNOW WHAT HE'S
DOING.
HE KNOWS WHAT HE IS DOING.
THAT'S WHY HE'S DONE THE THINGS
HE'S DONE.
THAT'S WHY WE HAVE A PRESIDENT
THAT PASSED OBAMA CARE AND THE
STIMULUS, ALL THIS DAMAGE THAT
HE'S DONE TO AMERICA IS
DELIBERATE.
THIS IS A PRESIDENT THAT'S
TRYING TO REDEFINE THIS COUNTRY.
THAT'S WHY THIS ELECTION IS
TRULY A REFERENDUM ON OUR
IDENTITY AS A NATION, AS A
PEOPLE.
OUR FUTURE IS AT STAKE.
THIS ELECTION IS NOT ABOUT THE
PAST.
IT IS ABOUT WHAT KIND OF COUNTRY
THIS IS GOING TO BE IN THE 21st
CENTURY AND IF WE EXELELECT SOM
LIKE BARACK OBAMA, BERNIE
SANDERS, HILLARY CLINTON, OUR
CHILDRENS ARE GOING TO BE THE
FIRST TO INHERIT A DIMINISHES
COUNTRY --
>> YOU KNOW WHAT THE SHAME IS,
MAR
MARCO?
THE SHAME IS THAT YOU WOULD
ACTUALLY CRITICIZE SOMEBODY FOR
SHOWING UP TO WORK, PLOWING THE
STREETS, GETTING THE TRAINS
RUNNING BACK ON TIME WHEN YOU
ARE NEVER BEEN RESPONSIBLE FOR
THAT IN YOUR ENTIRE LIFE.
>> HE DIDN'T WANT TO GO BACK.
>> AND THE FACT IS, I WENT BACK,
IT GOT DONE AND HERE'S --
>> YOU DIDN'T WANT TO GO BACK,
CHRIS.
>> OH, SO -- WAIT A SECOND.
ONE OF THE SKILLS YOU GET AS A
UNITED STATES SENATOR ESP ALSO?
I DON'T THINK IT IS.
>> YOU SAID YOU WEREN'T GOING TO
GO BACK.
HE TOLD EVERYONE HE WASN'T GOING
TO GO BACK.
THEY HAD TO SHAME HIM INTO GOING
BACK.
AND WHEN HE DECIDED TO GO BACK,
HE CRITICIZED THE YOUNG LADY,
S
SAYING, WHAT AM I SUPPOSED TO
DO, CLEAN IT UP WITH A MOP?
>> IT GETS VERY UNRULY WHEN HE
GETS OFF HIS TALKING POINTS.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
>> IT'S YOUR RECORD.
IT'S NOT A TALKING POINT.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, I'LL MENTION
YOUR NAME SO YOU CAN COME IN ON
THIS.
>> I REALLY DO APPRECIATE IT.
>> I WANT TO BRING YOU IN ON
THIS, BECAUSE YOU MADE THIS
CENTRAL TO YOUR CAMPAIGN RIGHT
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE IN THE
LAST COUPLE OF DAYS, BUT FOUR
YEARS AGO, YOU SAID OF SENATOR
RUBIO, HE WAS READY TO BE VICE
PRESIDENT, YOU SPOKE OF HIS
EXPERIENCE, AS WELL.
YOU SAID HE HAS THE FORTITUDE TO
BE A GOOD PRESIDENT.
BUT JUST THIS WEEK, YOU SAID
SENATOR RUBIO ACCOMPLISHED,
QUOTE, NOTHING IN THE SENATE.
HOW DO YOU SQUARE THE TWO?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, HE SAID
THE EXACT SAME THING ABOUT ME,
THAT I WOULD MAKE A GREAT VICE
PRESIDENTIAL NOMINEE WHEN MYITT
ROMNEY WAS CONSIDERING.
I THINK WE WERE BOTH RIGHT AT
THE TIME AND MITT PICKED
SOMEBODY ELSE.
SO, LET'S MOVE ONTO THE 2016
RACE.
WHO HAS THE LEADERSHIP SKILLS --
WHO HAS THE LEADERSHIP SKILLS TO
LEAD?
AND I'M PROUD OF THE FACT THAT I
HAVE 12 MEDAL OF HONOR RESIMILAR
YENTS, 30
WHO BELIEVE IN ME.
WE CUT TAXES IN THE STATE OF
FLORIDA AND REDUCED GOVERNMENT.
I TOOK ON VERY POWERFUL
INTERESTS, FOUGHT FOR MY
BELIEFS, IMPLEMENTED THEM.
WE HAD EIGHT HURRICANES AND FOUR
TROPICAL STORMS IN 16 MONTHS.
THE WHOLE STATE WAS TURNED
UPSIDE DOWN.
IT REQUIRED A STEADY HAND.
LEADERSHIP.
YOU LEARN THIS.
YOU LEARN IT BY DOING IT.
IT'S NOT SOMETHING THAT YOU JUST
SHOW UP ON THE JOB DOING.
IT'S NOT TO SAME -- LET'S BE
CLEAR.
MARCO RUBIO IS A GIFTED, GIFTED
POLITICIAN.
AND HE MAY HAVE THE SKILLS TO BE
A PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES.
BUT WE'VE TRIED IT THE OLD WAY
WITH BARACK OBAMA, WITH SOARING
ELEGANCE AND WE GOT SOMEONE WHO
WANTS TO DIVIDE THE COUNTRY UP.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT IS GOING TO
HAVE TO FORGE CONSENSUS TO BRING
ABOUT A SET OF COMMON PURPOSES
SO WE CAN MOVE FORWARD AGAIN.
>> WE'RE GOING TO CONTINUE WITH
LEADERSHIP NOW, AND --
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU ARE A
FIRST-TERM SENATOR, AS WELL.
YOUR OPPONENTS SAY YOU, LIKE
SENATOR RUBIO, ARE NOT PREPARED
TO BE COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
YOU HAVE TALKED TOUGH ABOUT
THREATS WE FACE IN THE MIDDLE
EAST.
IT WAS REPORTED JUST MOMENTS AGO
THAT THE NORTH KOREANS TEST
LAUNCHED AN INTERCONTINENTAL
BALLISTIC MISSILE.
NORTH KOREA HAS NUCLEAR WEAPONS
AND CONDUCTED ANOTHER NUCLEAR
TEST JUST LAST MONTH.
THE MISSILE THAT WAS LAUNCHED IS
THE KIND THE NORTH KOREANS HOPE
COULD SOME DAY CARRY A NUCLEAR
WEAPON CAPABLE OF REACHING THE
UNITED STATES.
HOW WOULD YOU RESPOND IF
COMMANDER IN CHIEF TO THAT
LAUNCH?
>> WELL, I WOULD NOTE INITIALLY
THE FACT THAT WE'RE SEEING THE
LAUNCH AND WE'RE SEEING THE
LAUNCH FROM A NUCLEAR NORTH
KOREA IS THE DIRECT RESULT OF
THE FAILURES OF THE FIRST
CLINTON ADMINISTRATION.
THE CLINTON ADMINISTRATION LED
THE WORLD IN RELAXING SANCTIONS
AGAINST NORTH KOREA, BILLIONS OF
DOLLARS FLOWED INTO NORTH KOREA,
IN EXCHANGE FOR PROMISES NOT TO
BUILD NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
THEY TOOK THOSE BILLIONS AND
BUILT NUCLEAR WEAPONS.
AND I WOULD NOTE, ALSO, THE LEAD
NEGOTIATOR IN THAT FAILED NORTH
KOREA SANCTIONS DEAL WAS A WOMAN
NAMED WENDY SHERMAN, WHO BARACK
OBAMA AND HILLARY CLINTON
RECRUITED TO COME BACK TO BE THE
LEAD NEGOTIATOR WITH IRAN, SO,
WHAT WE ARE SEEING WITH NORTH
KOREA IS FORESHADOWING OF WHERE
WE WILL BE WITH IRAN.
WITH RESPECT TO NORTH KOREA AND
WHAT WE SHOULD DO NOW, ONE OF
THE FIRST THINGS WE SHOULD DO IS
EXPAND OUR MISSILE DEFENSE
CAPACITY.
WE OUGHT TO PUT MISSILE DEFENSE
IN SOUTH KOREA.
ONE OF THE REAL RISKS OF THIS
LAUNCH, NORTH KOREA WANTS TO
LAUNCH A SATELLITE.
ONE OF THE GREATEST RISKS OF THE
SATELLITE, THEY WOULD PLACE A
NUCLEAR DEVICE IN THE SATELLITE
AS IT WOULD ORBIT AROUND THE
EARTH.
AS IT GOT OVER THE UNITED
STATES, IT WOULD SET OFF WHAT IS
CALLED AN EMP, AN ELECTRON
MAGNETIC PULSE.
THAT WOULD TAKE DOWN THE ENTIRE
ELECTRICAL GRID OF THE EASTERN
SEABOARD.
WE NEED TO HARDEN THE GRID TO
DEFEND OURSELVES AND WE NEED
MISSILE DEFENSE TO PROTECT
OURSELVES AGAINST NORTH KOREA.
>> WELL, LET ME ASK YOU THIS.
IF YOU WERE COMMANDER IN CHIEF,
TONIGHT, WOULD YOU HAVE ORDERED
THE U.S. MILITARY TO DESTROY
THAT MISSILE PREEMPTIVELY, ON
THE LAUNCH PAD, TO PREVENT NORTH
KOREA FROM BECOMING AN EVEN
GRAVER THREAT?
>> AT THIS POINT, I'M NOT GOING
TO SPECULATE ON THAT WITHOUT THE
INTELLIGENCE BRIEFING THAT ANY
COMMANDER IN CHIEF WOULD HAVE,
KNOWING EXACTLY WHAT IS THERE.
ONE OF THE REAL PROBLEMS --
>> LET ME TELL YOU THIS.
YOU HAVE TALKED TOUGH ABOUT
MIDEAST.
YOU HAVEN'T GOTTEN THE
INTELLIGENCE BRIEFINGS ABOUT
THAT.
WHY WOULDN'T YOU PREEMPTIVELY
STREAK A MISSILE ON AN LAUNCH
PAD --
>> I HAVE GOTTEN THE
INTELLIGENCE BRIEFINGS ON THE
MIDEAST.
THOSE HAVE BEEN GOING ON FOR
MANY YEARS.
I HAVEN'T GOTTEN THE BRIEFING
TONIGHT ON WHAT NORTH COREY IS
DOING BECAUSE I'M HERE IN NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
AND WHEN YOU ARE RESPONDING TO
AN IMMEDIATE INCIDENT, YOU NEED
TO KNOW THE UNTELL JENSINTELLIGT
IS OCCURRING.
IT IS DIFFERENT, DEALING WITH A
COUNTRY, ONCE THEY HAVE NUCLEAR
WEAPONS.
IT IS WHY YOU PREVENT THEM FROM
GETTING THEM IN THE FIRST PLACE.
BECAUSE YOUR HANDS ARE SOMEWHAT
TIED ONCE THEY HAVE NUKES.
IT'S WHY THIS IRANIAN NUCLEAR
DEAL IS SO CATASTROPHIC AND IT'S
WHY I PLEDGED ON THE VERY FIRST
DAY IN OFFICE TO RIP TO SHREDS
THIS IRANIAN NUCLEAR DEAL, SO
WE'RE NOT SITTING HERE IN FIVE
YEARS, WONDERING WHAT TO DO
ABOUT AN IRANIAN MISSILE LAUNCH
WHEN THEY HAVE NUCLEAR WEAPONS,
THE STAKES ARE TOO HIGH FOR
THAT.
>> OKAY.
SENATOR CRUZ, I WILL SAY THAT
MISSILE HAS BEEN SITTING THERE
FOR QUITE SOME TIME AND THEY
HAVE HAD EYES ON IT.
>> JUST TO CLARIFY ON THAT
POINT, BECAUSE HE'S RIGHT.
IT IS STANDARD PROCEDURE OF THE
UNITED STATES TO SHOOT DOWN
THOSE MISSILES ONCE LAUNCHED IF
THEY --
>> SENATOR RUBIO, I'M TALKING
ABOUT A PRESEMIIVE STRIKE ON THE
LAUNCH PAD.
>> I UNDERSTAND.
BUT IT IS IMPORTANT TO NOTE THAT
IT IS, AND SENATOR CRUZ, I
THINK, WAS ALLUDING TO THIS, AS
WELL, IT IS THE STANDARD
PROCEDURE OF THE UNITED STATES,
IF THOSE MISSILES POSE A THREAT
TO LAND, CIVILIANS, ALLIES OR
ANY OF OUR ASSETS TO SHOOT DOWN
THAT MISSILE.
I UNDERSTAND YOUR QUESTION WAS
ABOUT A PREEMPTIVE STRIKE, BUT
MY POINT IS, THERE IS IN PLACE
NOW A CONTINGENCY TO AVOID THAT
STRIKE FROM GOING ERRANT AND
DESTROYING ANY ASSETS OF THE
UNITED STATES OR IMPLICATING OR
HURTING ANY OF OUR ALLIES OR ANY
OF OUR ASSETS IN THE REGION.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR RUBIO.
GOVERNOR KASICH, HOW WOULD YOU
RESPOND TO TONIGHT'S LAUNCH?
>> WELL, WE HAVE TO STEP UP THE
PRESSURE.
AND I HAVE TO SAY, AFTER BEING
HERE, EVERY ONE OF MY 100 TOWN
HALL MEETINGS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE
WERE A LOT MORE FUN THAN WHAT I
SAW HERE TODAY, WERE SO MUCH
MORE POSITIVE.
LOOK, IN TERMS OF NORTH KOREA,
MARTHA, WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE
THAT WE INTERCEPT BOTH THE SHIPS
AND THEIR AIRCRAFT, BECAUSE WHAT
THEY'RE TRYING TO DO IS TO
PROLIFERATE THIS VERY DANGEROUS
MATERIAL, ALONG WITH THE
TECHNOLOGY, THE INSTRUMENTS THAT
CAN BE USED FOR MASS
DESTRUCTION.
THAT'S WHAT I WORRY ABOUT THE
MOST, FRANKLY, IS NONSTATE
ACTORS, PEOPLE WHO DON'T HAVE A
UNIFORM, PEOPLE DON'T HAVE A
COUNTRY, WHO CAN SPREAD THIS,
WHO ARE NOT SUBJECT TO THE -- TO
THE MUTUAL ASSURED DEFENSE.
IN OTHER WORDS, YOU STRIKE US,
WE STRIKE YOU.
SOME OF THESE RADICALS, THEY
DON'T CARE ABOUT THAT.
PTH
MY CHILDREN, AND FOR THEIR
CHILDREN, GOING FORWARD.
SO, WE HAVE TO BE VERY TOUGH AND
WE SHOULD TELL THE CHINESE,
LOOK, IF YOU ARE NOT GOING TO DO
THIS, BALLISTIC MISSILE DEFENSE
TO THE KOREANS, TO JAPAN, AND WE
SHOULD IMPOSE THE SANCTIONS ON
NORTH KOREA THAT WE IMPOSED ON
IRAN.
THEY ARE ABLE TO SEND AND
RECEIVE MONEY.
WE HAVE TO BE TOUGH ON THIS.
AND I THINK WE COULD HAVE -- I
THINK WE COULD HAVE LET THE
JAPANESE KNOW THAT IF YOU WANT
TO TAKE ACTION ON THAT MISSILE
THAT IS RISING, YOU WANT TO TAKE
ACTION -- YOU WILL HAVE OUR
SUPPORT, IF THAT'S WHAT YOU
THINK IS THE BEST THING TO DO.
WE CANNOT CONTINUE TO BE WEAK IN
THE FACE OF THE NORTH
THE REST OF THE WORLD.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR.
I WILL GET TO NEW A MOMENT.
>> THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION
COMES UP WITH THE GREAT
MARKETING TERMS.
WHAT THEY DO IS PULL BACK.
AND VOIDS ARE FILLED.
THEY ARE FILLED WITH NATION
STATES ON THE RUN.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES IS GOING HAVE TO GET THE
UNITED STATES BACK IN THE GAME
AND IF A PREEMPTIVE STRIKE IS
NECESSARY TO KEEP US SAFE, THEN
WE SHOULD DO IT.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR BUSH.
MR. TRUMP.
DO YOU HAVE A RED LINE WITH
NORTH KOREA?
WOULD YOU CONSIDER MILITARY
ACTION AND HOW FAR WOULD YOU LET
THEM GO?
>> WELL, LET ME SAY A COUPLE OF
THINGS.
FIRST OF ALL, MARCO SAID EARLIER
ON THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA KNOWS
EXACTLY WHAT HE'S DOING, LIKE WE
HAVE THIS PRESIDENT THAT REALLY
KNOWS -- I DISAGREE,
RESPECTFULLY, WITH MARCO.
I THINK WE HAVE A PRESIDENT WHO,
AS A PRESIDENT, IS TOTALLY
INCOMPETENT AND HE DOESN'T KNOW
WHAT HE'S DOING.
I THINK HE HAS NO IDEA WHAT HE'S
DOING.
AND OUR COUNTRY IS GOING TO
HELL.
SO, I JUST WANTED TO SAY, WE
DISAGREE ON THAT.
IS THAT OKAY?
>> YEAH, I HAVE -- I GOT
MENTIONED, CAN I RESPOND?
>> I'D LIKE YOU TO FINISH THE
QUESTION, PLEASE.
SPECIFICS AS TO NORTH KOREA.
>> WE HAVE -- TREMENDOUS HAS
BEEN JUST SUCKED OUT OF OUR
COUNTRY BY CHINA.
CHINA SAYS THEY DON'T HAVE THAT
GOOD OF CONTROL OVER NORTH
KOREA.
THEY HAVE TREMENDOUS CONTROL.
I DEAL WITH THE CHINESE ALL OF
THE TIME.
I DO -- LARGEST BANK IN THE
WORLD IS IN ONE OF MY BUILDINGS
IN MANHATTAN.
THEY TELL ME.
THEY HAVE TOTAL, ABSOLUTE
CONTROL, PRACTICALLY, OF NORTH
KOREA.
THEY HAVE SUCKING TRILLIONS OF
DOLLARS OUT OF OUR COUNTRY.
THEY ARE REBUILDING CHINA WITH
THE MONEY THEY TAKE OUT OF OUR
COUNTRY.
I WOULD GET ON WITH CHINA, LET
CHINA SOLVE THAT PROBLEM, THEY
CAN DO IT QUICKLY AND
SURGICALLY.
THAT'S WHAT WE SHOULD DO WITH
NORTH KOREA.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
YOU WERE MENTIONED.
>> HERE'S THE BROADER POINT, AS
WELL, AND I THINK IT TOUCHES ON
WHAT DONALD JUST MENTIONED.
THIS IS A PRESIDENT THAT VIEWS
THIS COUNTRY AS A COUNTRY THAT'S
BEEN TOO POWERFUL IN THE WORLD
AND WE CREATE PROBLEMS AROUND
THE WORLD.
FOR EXAMPLE, IT IS ONE OF THE
REASONS WHY HE HAS BETRAYED
ISRAEL.
BECAUSE HE BELIEVES IF WE CREATE
SEPARATION FROM ISRAEL, IT WILL
HELP OUR RELATIONS IN THE
ISLAMIC WORLD.
THE SAME IS HAPPENING IN THE
ASIA PACIFIC REGION, WITH
ACCOMMODATIONS TO NORTH KOREA.
NORTH KOREANS SHOULD BE BACK ON
THE LIST OF TERRORIST NATIONS,
AS AN EXAMPLE.
AND DONALD IS RIGHT.
CHINA DOES HAVE A LOT OF
INFLUENCE OVER NORTH KOREA AND
HE SHOULD BE LEVERAGING OUR
RELATIONSHIP WITH THE CHINESE TO
ENSURE THAT NORTH KOREA NO
LONGER HAS ACCESS TO THE
RESOURCES THAT HAVE ALLOWED A
COUNTRY WITH NO ECONOMY TO
DEVELOP LONG RANGE MISSILES
ALREADY CAPABLE OF REACHING THE
WEST COAST OF THE UNITED STATES
POTENTIALLY.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR RUBIO.
GOVERNOR BUSH, ANOTHER PROBLEM
FACING THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF
RIGHT NOW IS THAT NORTH KOREA IS
CURRENTLY DETAINING AN AMERICAN
COLLEGE STUDENT.
WHAT WOULD YOU DO TO GET THAT
COLLEGE STUDENT BACK HOME?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, IT IS
INTERESTING THAT HAPPENED
LITERALLY DAYS WHEN THIS HOSTAGE
RELEASE TOOK PLACE IN IRAN.
A DAY OR TWO DAYS AFTERWARDS,
NORTH KOREA TOOK A -- HELD AN
AMERICAN STUDENT HOSTAGE.
I THINK IT'S WHEN WE SEND A
SIGNAL OF WEAKNESS, WHEN WE ARE
NEGOTIATING TO RELEASE PEOPLE
THAT COMMITTED CRIMES IN OUR
COUNTRY FOR PEOPLE THAT DIDN'T
COMMIT CRIMES THAT ARE HELD
HOSTAGE IN IRAN.
WE'VE SAW THE SHAMEFUL TREATMENT
OF OUR SAILORS, THAT THIS SENDS
A SIGNAL OF WEAKNESS AROUND THE
WORLD.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT OF THE UNITED
STATES IS GOING TO HAVE TO GET
BACK IN THE GAME.
WHERE THE UNITED STATES' WORD
MATTERS.
WE DON'T SEND SIGNALS OF
WEAKNESS.
WE NEED TO USE EVERY INFLUENCE
POSSIBLE TO GET THIS STUDENT
BACK.
AND I THINK JOHN IS RIGHT ABOUT
THIS, THERE ARE CRIPPLING
SANCTIONS THAT ARE AVAILABLE, AS
IT RELATES TO THE TWO OR THREE
BANKS THAT NORTH KOREA USES TO
ILLICIT TRADE.
WE OUGHT TO RE-ESTABLISH
SANCTIONS, NOT JUST BECAUSE OF
THE STUDENT, BUT BECAUSE OF THE
ACTIONS THEY ARE TAKING RIGHT
NOW, AS IT RELATES TO BUILDING
THIS MISSILE CAPABILITY.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, I WANT TO
GO TO YOU ON THE SAME QUESTION.
WOULD YOU NEGOTIATE WITH NORTH
KOREA --
>> LET'S MAKE SOMETHING VERY
CLEAR.
I LEARNED SEVEN YEARS AS A
FEDERAL POROSECUTOR IN DEALING
WITH SITUATIONS LIKE WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT IN NORTH KOREA,
WHERE CRIMINALS TAKE PEOPLE
HOSTAGE.
YOU NEVER PAY RANSOM TO THE
CRIMINALS.
EVER.
YOU NEVER PAY RANSOM TO THE
CRIMINALS.
EVERYONE OUT AT HOME WATCHING
TONIGHT UNDERSTANDS THAT
PRINCIPLE.
AND SO, WHAT YOU NEED TO DO IS
TO ENGAGE IN A MUCH DIFFERENT
WAY WITH THESE FOLKS.
THEY DO NOT UNDERSTAND ANYTHING
BUT TOUGHNESS AND STRENGTH.
AND WE NEED TO ENGAGE THE
CHINESE TO DEAL WITH THE NORTH
KOREANS, BUT WE NEED TO MAKE
SURE THEY UNDERSTAND, THERE'S A
COMMANDER IN CHIEF WHO WILL NOT
PAY RANSOM FOR ANY HOSTAGE.
THIS PRESIDENT AND HIS FORMER
SECRETARY OF STATE ARE FOR
PAYING RANSOM FOR HOSTAGES.
WHEN DO THAT, YOU ENDANGER EVEN
MORE AMERICANS AROUND THE WORLD
TO BE THE SUBJECT OF THIS TYPE
OF HOSTAGE TAKING AND ILLEGAL
DETENTION.
YOU NEED A STRONG COMMANDER IN
CHIEF WHO WILL SAY, WE WILL NOT
PUT UP WITH THIS AND WE WILL
TAKE THE ACTIONS WE NEED TO
TAKE, NOT ONLY TO GET OUR PEOPLE
HOME SAFELY, BUT TO PUNISH THOSE
WHO BELIEVE THEY CAN VIOLATE THE
LAW AND VIOLATE AMERICAN'S
SOVEREIGN RIGHTS TO TRAVEL THE
WORLD.
THIS IS UNACCEPTABLE.
AND THIS IS WHY THIS PRESIDENT
IS SO WEAK AND WHY THE SECRETARY
OF STATE, WHO IS EMBRACING A
THIRD BARACK OBAMA TERM WOULD BE
EVEN WEAKER.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE.
DAVID?
>> MARTHA, WE'RE GOING TO TURN
TO IMMIGRATION NOW.
AND I WANT TO BRING IN GOVERNOR
KASICH.
YOU TOLD US IN AN ABC INTERVIEW,
QUOTE, IT IS COMPLETELY
RIDICULOUS TO THINK WE ARE GOING
TO GRAB PEOPLE OUT OF THEIR
HOMES AND SHIP PEOPLE BACK TO
MEXICO.
ADDING, QUOTE, THAT'S NOT WHERE
THE PARTY IS.
THE PARTY IS NOT FOR DEPARTING
11.5 MILLION PEOPLE.
BUT MR. TRUMP AND SENATOR CRUZ,
WHO HAVE MADE DEPORTATION
CENTRAL TO THEIR CAMPAIGNS, TOP
THE NATIONAL POLLS.
SO, MY QUESTION FOR YOU, ARE YOU
NOT WHERE THE VOTERS ARE?
>> WELL, YOU KNOW, DAVID, I
SPENT A LOT OF TIME HERE IN THIS
STATE, AS I MENTIONED EARLIER,
AND WE HAVE TO HAVE PRACTICAL
SOLUTIONS, JUST LIKE WE WERE
JUST TALKING ABOUT A FEW MINUTES
AGO ON NORTH KOREA.
LOOK, THE SITUATION IS, WE NEED
TO FINISH THE BORDER.
IT HAS TO BE COMPLETED, JUST
LIKE WE LOCK OUR DOORS AT NIGHT,
THE COUNTRY HAS TO BE ABLE TO
LOCK ITS DOORS.
AND WE CAN HAVE A GUEST WORKER
PROGRAM, WHERE PEOPLE CAN COME
IN AND OUT IN AND ORDERLY WAY.
FOR THE 11.5 MILLION THAT ARE
HERE, IF THEY HAVE NOT COMMITTED
A CRIME SINCE THEY'VE BEEN HERE,
I BELIEVE THEY OUGHT TO PAY SOME
TAXES, PAY A FINE.
NEVER GET ON THE PATH TO
CITIZENSHIP, BUT GET
LEGALIZATION.
IT IS -- I COULDN'T EVEN IMAGINE
HOW WE WOULD EVEN BEGIN TO THINK
ABOUT TAKING A MOM OR A DAD OUT
OF A HOUSE WHEN THEY HAVE NOT
COMMITTED A CRIME SINCE THEY'VE
BEEN HERE, LEAVING THEIR
CHILDREN IN THE HOUSE?
I MEAN, THAT IS NOT, IN MY
OPINION, THE KIND OF VALUES THAT
WE BELIEVE IN.
AND SECONDLY, I THINK AT THE END
OF THE DAY, THAT AMERICANS WOULD
SUPPORT A PLAN LIKE THIS.
I THINK CONGRESS WOULD PASS A
PLAN, TO FINISH THE BORDER,
GUEST WORKER, PAY A FINE, A PATH
TO LEGALIZATION, AND NOT
CITIZENSHIP.
AND WE'VE GOT TO GET THIS DONE.
AND I WILL TELL YOU THIS, WITHIN
THE FIRST 100 DAYS THAT I AM
PRESIDENT, I WILL PUT THAT
PROPOSAL TO THE CONGRESS AND I
WILL TELL YOU, AS A FORMER
CONGRESSMAN, AND AN EXECUTIVE,
IN OHIO, I CAN PROMISE YOU THAT
I BELIEVE YOU'LL GET THE VOTES
TO PASS THAT AND WE CAN MOVE ON
WITH THAT ISSUE AND PROTECT OUR
BORDER.
THAT'S WHAT I THINK.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BRING THIS NEXT TO
SENATOR CRUZ.
YOU HEARD WHAT THE GOVERNOR
SAID.
HE SAID WE NEED PRACTICAL
SOLUTIONS.
AND YOU'VE SAW, I DON'T INTEND
TO SEND JACK BOOTS TO KNOCK ON
DOORS.
THAT'S NOT HOW WE ENFORCE THE
LAW FOR ANY CRIME.
SO, WHAT IS YOUR PLAN?
HOW WILL YOU DEPORT 11.5 MILLION
UNDOCUMENTED PEOPLE AND BE
SPECIFIC.
HOW WOULD YOU DO IT?
>> IN TERMS OF PRACTICAL
SOLUTION, I'VE LAID OUT THE MOST
DETAILED PLAN FOR SOLVING
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION.
IT'S 11 PAGES, SINGLE SPACED,
CHAPTER AND VERSE.
IT'S ON TEDCRUZ.ORG.
IN SHORT, WE'RE GOING TO BUILD A
WALL.
WE'RE GOING TO TRIPLE THE BORDER
PATROL.
WE'RE GOING TO INCREASE -- AND
ACTUALLY, SINCE DONALD ENJOYED
THAT, I WILL SIMPLY SAY, I'VE
GOT SOMEBODY IN MIND TO BUILD
IT.
WE'RE GOING TO INCREASE
FOUR-FOLD, THE FIXED WING AND
ROTARY WING AIRCRAFT SO THAT YOU
HAVE TECHNOLOGY MONITORING AN
ATTEMPTED INCURSION TO DIRECT
THE BOOTS ON THE GROUND, WHERE
THEY'RE OCCURRING.
WE'RE GOING TO PUT IN PLACE A
STRONG E-VERIFY SYSTEM IN THE
WORKPLACE, SO YOU CAN'T GET A
JOB WITHOUT PROVING YOU ARE HERE
LEGALLY.
WE'LL PUT IN PLACE A
SYSTEM ON VISAS.
40% COME IN ON VISAS AND
OVERSTAY.
WE WILL END SANCTUARY CITIES BY
CUTTING OFF TAXPAYER DOLLARS TO
ANY JURISDICTION THAT DEFIES
FEDERAL IMMIGRATION LAW AND WE
WILL END WELFARE BENEFITS FOR
THOSE HERE ILLEGALLY.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH WAS TALKING
ABOUT THE FAMILIES AND WHAT YOU
DO WITH THE FAMILIES THAT YOU
HAVE TO SEND HOME.
CAN YOU TELL THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
TONIGHT HOW YOU WOULD DO THAT?
>> WHAT YOU DO IS, YOU ENFORCE
THE LAW.
UNDER THE CONSTITUTION, THE
PRESIDENT HAS AN OBLIGATION TO,
QUOTE, TAKE CARE THAT THE LAWS
BE FAITHFULLY EXECUTED.
FEDERAL IMMIGRATION LAW PROVIDES
IF SOMEONE IS HERE ILLEGALLY,
THEY ARE TO BE DEPORTED.
WE SAW JUST THIS PAST WEEK THE
HEAD OF THE BORDER PATROL UNION
TESTIFY BEFORE CONGRESS THAT
PRESIDENT OBAMA HAD GIVEN THE
ORDER TO THE BORDER PATROL TO
STAND DOWN, NOT TO ENFORCE THE
LAW.
THAT IS WRONG.
I WILL ENFORCE THE LAW AND FOR
EVERYONE WHO SAYS, YOU CAN'T
POSSIBLY DO THAT -- I WOULD NOTE
THAT IN EIGHT YEARS, BILL
CLINTON DEPORTED 12 MILLION
PEOPLE.
IN EIGHT YEARS, GEORGE W. BUSH
DEPORTED 10 MILLION PEOPLE.
ENFORCING THE LAW, WE CAN DO IT.
WHAT IS MISSING IS THE POLITICAL
WILL.
AND WHEN THEY WERE DEPORTING THE
PEOPLE, THE BORDER WASN'T
SECURE, SO, THEY'D COME RIGHT
BACK.
ONCE YOU SECURE THE BORDER,
ENFORCING THE LAW WILL SOLVE
THIS PROBLEM AND THAT WILL
BENEFIT AMERICAN WORKERS.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BRING IN SENATOR
RUBIO.
THIS QUESTION IS ABOUT
IMMIGRATION, IT IS ALSO ABOUT
LEADERSHIP.
YOU'RE AWARE OF THE CRITICISM
FROM MANY CANDIDATES ON THIS
STAGE TONIGHT, THAT YOU
COAUTHORED THE SO-CALLED GANG OF
EIGHT BILL THAT WOULD HAVE
CREATED A PATH TO CITIZENSHIP.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE SAID, AS SOON
AS YOU FELT THE HEAT, YOU TURNED
TAIL AND RUN.
GOVERNOR BUSH HAS SAID, I DON'T
THINK WE NEED PEOPLE CUTTING AND
RUNNING ANYMORE.
DID YOU FIGHT FOR YOUR OWN
LEGISLATION, SENATOR, OR DID YOU
RUN FROM IT?
>> HERE'S THE BOTTOM LINE.
WE CAN'T GET THAT LEGISLATION
PASSED.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE WILL NOT
SUPPORT DOING ANYTHING ABOUT
PEOPLE THAT ARE IN THIS COUNTRY
ILLEGALLY UNTIL THE LAW IS
ENFORCED FIRST, AND YOU PROVE IT
TO THEM.
THIS HAS BEEN CLEAR.
EVERY EFFORT OVER THE LAST TEN
YEARS TO DO THOSE HAS FAILED.
AND IT HAS FAILED BECAUSE THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE HAVE ZERO TRUST
THAT THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT WILL
ENFORCE OUR LAWS.
THAT'S WHY SINCE THEN I HAVE
SAID, IF YOU ARE SERIOUS ABOUT
IMMIGRATION REFORM, THEN THE KEY
THAT UNLOCKS THE DOOR TO BEING
ABLE TO DO THAT IS NOT JUST TO
PASS A LAW THAT SAYS IT IS GOING
TO ENFORCE THE LAW, BUT TO
ACTUALLY DO IT.
TO HIRE THE 20,000 NEW BORDER
AGENTS, TO FINISH THE FENCING
AND WALLS, TO PUT IN PLACE
MANDATORY E-VERIFY.
AN ENTRY/EXIT SYSTEM.
AND ONCE THAT IS IN PLACE AND
THAT'S WORKING, I BELIEVE THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE WILL SUPPORT A
VERY REASONABLE, BUT RESPONSIBLE
APPROACH TO PEOPLE WHO HAVE BEEN
HERE A LONG TIME, WHO ARE NOT
DANGEROUS CRIMINALS, WHO PAY
TAXES AND PAY FINES FOR WHAT
THEY DID.
BUT UNTIL THEN, NONE OF THAT IS
GOING TO BE POSSIBLE.
>> DID YOU FIGHT FOR THE
LEGISLATION AT THE TIME OR DID
YOU RUN FROM IT --
>> WELL, THE LEGISLATION PASSED,
BUT IT HAS NO SUPPORT.
IT COULDN'T PASS IN THE HOUSE,
IT WILL NEVER PASS IN THE UNITED
STATES UNTIL WE SECURE THE
BORDER AND IT IS NOT THE WAY
WE'RE GOING TO DO WHEN I'M
PRESIDENT.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE ARE GOING
TO ENFORCE THE LAW FIRST, PROVE
TO PEOPLE THAT ILLEGAL
IMMIGRATION IS UNDER CONTROL AND
THEN WE'LL SEE WHAT THE AMERICAN
PEOPLE ARE WILLING TO SUPPORT
WHEN IT COMES TO PEOPLE THAT ARE
NOT CRIMINALS WHO HAVE BEEN IN
THE THIS COUNTRY FOR A LONG TIME
AND WHO WOULD LIKE TO SAY.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE?
>> DAVID, JUST LISTEN, AGAIN,
EVERYBODY.
THIS IS THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
BEING A GOVERNOR WHO HAS TO BE
RESPONSIBLE FOR PROBLEMS AND NOT
ANSWERING A QUESTION.
THE QUESTION WAS, DID HE FIGHT
FOR HIS LEGISLATION.
IT'S ABUNDANTLY CLEAR THAT HE
DIDN'T.
DIDN'T FIGHT FOR THE
LEGISLATION.
WHEN THE TEACHERS UNIONS
ATTACKED ME WITH $20 MILLION OF
ADS BECAUSE I WANTED TO REFORM
TEACHER TENURE, I FOUGHT THEM
AND FOUGHT THEM AND FOUGHT THEM
AND I WON.
WHEN THEY DIDN'T WANT -- WHEN
PEOPLE WANTED TO RAISE TAXES IN
MY STATE AT DEMOCRATIC
LEGISLATURE AND THREATENED TO
CLOSE DOWN THE GOVERNMENT, I
SAID, FINE.
CLOSE DOWN THE GOVERNMENT.
I'LL ORDER A PIZZA, OPEN A BEER
AND WATCH THE METS.
YOU CAN CALL ME WHEN THE
GOVERNMENT REOPENS.
AND GUESS WHAT THEY DIDN'T DO?
THEY DIDN'T PASS A TAX INCREASE,
BECAUSE I VETOED IT THEY NEVER
CLOSED THE GOVERNMENT BECAUSE
THEY KNEW I WOULD FIGHT FOR WHAT
I BELIEVED IN.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, A
LEADER MUST FIGHT FOR WHAT THEY
BELIEVE IN.
NOT HANDICAP IT, SAY, MAYBE
BECAUSE I CAN'T WIN THIS ONE,
I'LL RUN.
THAT'S NOT WHAT LEADERSHIP IS.
THAT'S WHAT CONGRESS IS.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> LEADERSHIP -- LEADERSHIP IS
ULTIMATELY ABOUT SOLVING THE
PROBLEM.
AND THE APPROACH THAT WAS TRIED
AND HAS BEEN TRIED NOW
REPEATEDLY OVER TEN YEARS TO DO
THIS ALL AT ONCE IN A MASSIVE
PIECE OF LEGISLATION HAS NO
CHANCE OF PASSAGE.
IT IS NOT LEADERSHIP TO CONTINUE
TO TRY SOMETHING THAT HAS NO
CHANCE OF HAPPENING.
I WANT TO MAKE PROGRESS ON THIS
ISSUE.
IT HAS BEEN DISCUSSED NOW FOR 30
YEARS AND NOTHING EVER HAPPENS.
AND I AM TELLING YOU THAT THE
ONLY WAY FORWARD ON THIS ISSUE
THAT HAS ANY CHANCE OF
HAPPENING, MEANING GAINING THE
SUPPORT OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE,
YOU CANNOT DO THIS WITHOUT THE
SUPPORT OF THE AMERICAN PEOPLE.
IS AN APPROACH THAT BEGINS BY
PROVING THAT ONCE AND FOR ALL,
ILLEGAL IMMIGRATION IS UNDER
CONTROL.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
WE WANT TO TURN TO HEALTH CARE
IN THIS COUNTRY, AND MARY
KATHERINE.
>> THANKS, DAVID.
GOOD EVENING, GUYS.
>> GOOD EVENING.
>> MR. TRUMP.
>> YES.
>> IN THE DEMOCRATIC PRIMARY,
HILLARY CLINTON HAS CRITICIZED
BERNIE SANDERS' PLAN FOR SINGLE
PAYER GOVERNMENT HEALTH CARE,
NOTING IT WOULD REQUIRE BIG
ACROSS THE BOARD TAX INCREASES
FOR AMERICANS.
IN DOING SO, SHE'S DOUBLING DOWN
ON OBAMA CARE, DESPITE ITS
PERSISTENT UNPOPULARITY.
YOU HAVE SAID YOU WANT TO APPEAL
OBAMA CARE.
YOU HAVE SAID, QUOTE,
EVERYBODY'S GOT TO BE COVERED,
ADDING, QUOTE, THE GOVERNMENT'S
GOING TO PAY FOR IT.
ARE YOU CLOSER TO BERNIE
SANDERS' VISION FOR HEALTH CARE
THAN --
>> I DON'T THINK I AM.
I THINK I'M CLOSER TO COMMON
SENSE.
WE ARE GOING TO REPEAL OBAMA
CARE.
WE'RE GOING TO REPEAL OBAMA
WE ARE GOING TO REPLACE OBAMA
CARE WITH SOMETHING SO MUCH
BETTER.
AND THERE ARE SO MANY EXAMPLES
OF IT.
AND I WILL TELL YOU, PART OF THE
REASON WE HAVE SOME PEOPLE
LAUGHING, BECAUSE YOU HAVE
INSURANCE PEOPLE THAT TAKE CARE
OF EVERYBODY UP HERE.
THE ONLY ONE THEY'RE NOT TAKING
CARE OF IS ME.
WE HAVE LINES AROUND EACH STATE.
THE INSURANCE COMPANIES ARE
GETTING RICH ON OBAMA CARE.
GETTING RICH ON HEALTH CARE AND
HEALTH SERVICES AND EVERYTHING
HAVING TO DO WITH HEALTH.
WE ARE GOING TO END THAT.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE OUT THE
ARTIFICIAL BOUNDARIES, THE
ARTIFICIAL LINES.
WE'RE GOING TO GET A PLAN WHERE
PEOPLE COMPETE, FREE ENTERPRISE.
THEY COMPETE.
SO MUCH BETTER.
IN ADDITION -- IN ADDITION TO
THAT, IN ADDITION TO THAT, YOU
HAVE THE HEALTH CARE SAVINGS
PLANS, WHICH ARE EXCELLENT.
WHAT I DO SAY IS, THERE WILL BE
A CERTAIN NUMBER OF PEOPLE THAT
WILL BE ON THE STREET DYING AND
AS A REPUBLICAN, I DON'T WANT
THAT TO HAPPEN.
WE'RE GOING TO TAKE CARE OF
PEOPLE THAT ARE DYING ON THE
STREET BECAUSE THERE WILL BE A
GROUP OF PEOPLE THAT ARE NOT
GOING TO BE ABLE TO EVEN THINK
IN TERMS OF PRIVATE OR ANYTHING
ELSE AND WE'RE GOING TO TAKE
CARE OF THOSE PEOPLE.
AND I THINK EVERYBODY ON THIS
STAGE WOULD HAVE TO AGREE,
YOU'RE NOT GOING TO LET PEOPLE
DIE, SITTING IN THE MIDDLE OF A
STREET IN ANY CITY IN THIS
COUNTRY.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, TO THAT POINT,
MR. TRUMP HAS SAID THAT YOUR
POSITION ON HEALTH CARE MEANS
THAT MAYBE YOU'VE GOT, QUOTE, NO
HEART.
THERE IS A QUESTION HERE,
THOUGH, ABOUT UNCOVERED FOLKS.
YOU SUGGESTED REPLACING OBAMA
CARE.
ANY MAJOR CHANGE IN HEALTH CARE
POLICY CARRIES WITH IT THE RISK
THAT SOME PEOPLE WILL LOSE THEIR
INSURANCE COVERAGE OR HAVE TO
CHANGE IT.
HOW DO YOU REASSURE THOSE PEOPLE
THAT REPEALING AND REPLACING
OBAMA CARE IS STILL IN THEIR
BEST INTEREST?
>> LET ME TAKE TWO DIFFERENT
PARTS OF THAT.
LET ME START WITH SOCIALIZED
MEDICINE.
SOCIALIZED MEDICINE IS A
DISASTER.
IT DOES NOT WORK.
IF YOU LOOK AT THE COUNTRIES
THAT HAVE IMPOSED SOCIALIZED
MEDICINE, THAT HAVE PUT THE
GOVERNMENT IN CHARGE OF
PROVIDING MEDICINE, WHAT
INEVITABLY HAPPENS IS RATIONING.
YOU HAVE A SCARCITY OF DOCTORS.
YOU HAVE RATIONING.
AND THAT MEANS THE ELDERLY ARE
TOLD, WE'RE GOING TO RATION A
HIP REPLACEMENT, WE'RE GOING TO
RATION A KNEE REPLACEMENT.
WE'RE GOING TO RATION END OF
LIFE CARE.
WE'RE RIGHT NOW HEADING INTO A
MEDICAL SYSTEM WITH ABOUT A
90,000-DOCTOR SHORTAGE IN
AMERICA AND SOCIALIZED MEDICINE,
WHETHER PROPOSED BY THE
DEMOCRATS OR PROPOSED BY A
REPUBLICAN WOULD HURT THE PEOPLE
OF THIS COUNTRY.
WHAT SHOULD WE DO ON HEALTH
CARE?
IF I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT, WE
WILL REPEAL EVERY WORD OF OBAMA
CARE.
AND ONCE WE DO THAT, WE WILL
ADOPT COMMON SENSE REFORMS,
NUMBER ONE, WE'LL ALLOW PEOPLE
TO PURCHASE HEALTH INSURANCE
ACROSS STATE LINES, THAT WILL
DRIVE DOWN PRICES AND EXPAND THE
AVAILABILITY OF LOW COST
CATASTROPHIC INSURANCE.
WE'LL EXPAND HEALTH SAVINGS
ACCOUNTS.
AND WE WILL DELINK HEALTH
INSURANCE FROM EMPLOYMENT SO
THAT YOU DON'T LOSE YOUR HEALTH
INSURANCE WHEN YOU LOSE YOUR JOB
AND THAT WAY, HEALTH INSURANCE
CAN BE PERSONAL, PORTABLE AND
AFFORDABLE AND WE KEEP
GOVERNMENT FROM GETTING IN
BETWEEN US AND OUR DOCTORS.
>> DR. CARSON, YOU HAVE SOME
EXPERIENCE WITH THIS MATTER.
IN THE PAST, YOU HAVE SAID THAT
OBAMA CARE SHOULD BE REPLACED,
BEFORE IT IS REPEALED.
HOW AND WHY?
>> WELL, THANK YOU.
YOU KNOW, I WAS HOPING TO GET A
CHANCE TO TALK ABOUT NORTH
KOREA.
I WAS THE ONLY ONE WHO DIDN'T
GET TO DO THAT AND I HAVE SOME
TOUGH TO SAY ABOUT IT, LET ME
TELL YOU.
BUT AT IN RATE, YOU HAVE TO
REPLACE IT WITH SOMETHING THAT
MAKES SENSE.
IT DOESN'T MAKE SENSE.
AND THE REASON THAT I DISLIKE
OBAMA CARE IS BECAUSE THE
GOVERNMENT COMES IN AND TELLS
THE PEOPLE, WHICH, THE NATION IS
SUPPOSED TO BE CENTERED ON, WE
DON'T CARE WHAT YOU THINK, IF
YOU DON'T LIKE IT, TOO BAD.
THAT'S A PROBLEM.
AND WE CAN'T AFFORD TO DO THAT,
BECAUSE THAT WILL CHANGE
AMERICA.
I HAVE PROPOSED A HEALTH
EMPOWERMENT ACCOUNT SYSTEM.
EVERYBODY GETS AN ACCOUNT THE
DAY THEY ARE BORN, THEY KEEP IT
UNTIL THEY DIE.
THEY CAN PASS IT ON.
WE PAY FOR IT WITH THE SAME
DOCTORS THAT WE PAY FOR
TRADITIONAL HEALTH CARE WITH,
RECOGNIZING THAT WE SPEND TWICE
AS MUCH AS MANY COUNTRIES AND
HEALTH CARE AND DON'T HAVE AS
SUCH ACCESS.
WE GIVE PEOPLE THE ABILITY TO
SHIFT MONEY WITHIN THEIR HEALTH
EMPOWERMENT ACCOUNT, SO THAT
EACH FAMILY BASICALLY BECOMES
ITS OWN INSURANCE COMPANY
WITHOUT A MIDDLEMAN THAT SAVES
YOU A LOT OF MONEY.
AND THAT WILL LOWER THE COST OF
YOUR CATASTROPHIC INSURANCE
TREMENDOUSLY, BECAUSE THE ONLY
THING COMING OUT OF THAT IS
CATASTROPHIC HEALTH CARE.
AND IN TERMS OF TAKING CARE OF
THE INDIGENT, WE HAVE ANOTHER
WHOLE SYSTEM AND I CAN GO AHEAD
AND EXPLAIN IT, BUT I DON'T HAVE
THE TIME, BUT I'D BE HAPPY TO.
BUT GO TO BENCARSON.COM, READ
ABOUT IT.
YOU CAN READ ABOUT EVERYTHING
THAT'S BEEN DISCUSSED HERE IN
GREAT DETAIL.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
DAVID, MARTHA, BACK TO YOU.
>> MARY KATHERINE, THANK YOU.
WE WANT TO TURN NOW TO THE ISSUE
OF EMINENT DOMAIN.
AND JOSH, GO AHEAD.
>> THANK YOU, DAVID.
AND GOOD EVENING, CANDIDATES.
MR. TRUMP, YOU HAVE SAID, QUOTE,
I LOVE EMINENT DOM MAIN
THE SEIZURE OF PRIVATE PROPERTY
FOR THE GREATER GOOD.
YOU TRIED TO USE THE MEASURE IN
PRISON.
YOU SUPPORTED IT FOR THE
KEYSTONE PIPELINE.
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, THE
NORTHERN PASS WOULD BRING
HYDRO-ELECTRIC POWER FROM
CANADA.
DO YOU SEE EMINENT DOMAIN AS AN
APPROPRIATE TOOL TO GET THAT
DONE?
>> LET ME JUST TELL YOU ABOUT
EMINENT DOMAIN.
SO MANY PEOPLE HAVE HIT ME WITH
COMMERCIALS AND OTHER THINGS
ABOUT EMINENT DOMAIN.
EMINENT DOMAIN IS AN ABSOLUTE
NECESSITY FOR A COUNTRY, FOR OUR
COUNTRY.
WITHOUT IT, YOU WOULDN'T HAVE
ROADS.
YOU WOULDN'T HAVE HOSPITALS.
YOU WOULDN'T HAVE ANYTHING.
YOU WOULDN'T HAVE SCHOOLS.
YOU WOULDN'T HAVE BRUJS.
YOU NEED EMINENT DOMAIN.
AND A LOT OF THE BIG
CONSERVATIVES THAT TELL ME HOW
CONSERVATIVE THEY ARE, THIEY AL
WANT THE KEYSTONE PIPELINE.
THE KEYSTONE PIPELINE, WITHOUT
EMINENT DOMAIN, IT WOULDN'T GO
TEN FEET, OKAY?
YOU NEED IT.
IT A GOOD THING, NOT A BAD
THING.
WHAT A LOT OF PEOPLE DON'T KNOW,
OH, YOU'RE GOING TO TAKE THEIR
PROPERTY -- WHEN SOMEBODY --
WHEN EMINENT DOMAIN IS USED ON
SOMEBODY'S PROPERTY, THAT PERSON
GETS A FORTUNE.
THEY GET AT LEAST FAIR MARKET
VALUE AND IF THEY ARE SMART,
THEY'LL GET TWO OR THREE TIMES
THE VALUE OF THEIR PROPERTY.
BUT WITHOUT EMINENT DOMAIN, YOU
DON'T HAVE ROADS, HIGHWAYS,
SCHOOLS, BRIDGES OR ANYTHING.
SO, EMINENT DOMAIN, NOT THAT I
LOVE IT, BUT EMINENT DOMAIN IS
ABSOLUTELY -- IT'S A NECESSITY
FOR A COUNTRY.
AND CERTAINLY IT'S A NECESSITY
FOR OUR COUNTRY.
>> SO, THAT IS YES ON THE
NORTHERN PASS PROJECT?
>> YES.
>> THE DUCIFFERENCE BETWEEN
EMINENT DOMAIN FOR PUBLIC
PURPOSE, ROADS AND PIPELINES,
THAT'S FOR PUBLIC PURPOSE.
WHAT DONALD TRUMP DID WAS USE
EMINENT DOMAIN TO TRY TO TAKE
THE PROPERTY OF AN ELDERLY WOMAN
ON THE STRIP IN ATLANTIC CITY.
THAT IS NOT PUBLIC PURPOSE.
THAT IS DOWN RIGHT WRONG.
HERE'S THE PROBLEM WITH THAT.
THE PROBLEM WAS, IT WAS TO TEAR
DOWN --
>> JEB WANTS TO BE A TOUGH GUY
TONIGHT.
I DIDN'T TAKE THE PROPERTY.
>> THE NET RESULT WAS --
>> YOU TRIED.
>> THE WOMAN ULTIMATELY DIDN'T
WANT TO DO THAT.
I WALKED AWAY.
>> THAT'S NOT TRUE.
TO TURN THIS INTO A LIMOUSINE
PARKING LOT FOR HIS CASINOS IS
NOT PUBLIC USE.
AND IN FLORIDA, BASED ON WHAT WE
DID, WE MADE THAT IMPOSSIBLE.
IT IS PART OF OUR CONSTITUTION.
THAT'S THE BETTER APPROACH.
THAT IS THE CONSERVATIVE
APPROACH.
>> MR. TRUMP?
30 SECONDS.
>> HE WANTS TO BE A TOUGH GUY.
A LOT OF TIMES YOU'LL HAVE --
YOU'LL HAVE -- AND IT DIDN'T
WORK VERY WELL.
>> HOW TOUGH IT IS TO TAKE
PROPERTY FROM AN ELDERLY WOMAN.
>> LET ME TALK.
QUIET.
A LOT OF TIMES -- A LOT OF
TIMES -- THAT'S ALL OF HIS
DONORS AND SPECIAL INTERESTS OUT
THERE.
SO -- IT'S WHAT IT IS.
THAT'S WHAT IT IS.
AND BY THE WAY, LET ME JUST TELL
YOU, WE NEEDED TICKETS.
YOU CAN'T GET THEM.
YOU KNOW WHO HAS THE TICKETS --
TO THE TELEVISION AUDIENCE?
DONORS, SPECIAL INTERESTS, THE
PEOPLE THAT ARE PUTTING UP THE
MONEY.
THAT'S WHO IT IS.
THE RNC TOLD US.
WE HAVE ALL DONORS IN THE
AUDIENCE.
AND THE REASON THEY'RE NOT
LOVING ME -- THE REASON THEY'RE
NOT -- EXCUSE ME.
THE REASON THEY'RE NOT LOVING ME
IS, I DON'T WANT THEIR MONEY.
I'M GOING TO DO THE RIGHT THING
FOR THE AMERICAN PUBLIC.
I DON'T WANT THEIR MONEY.
I DON'T NEED THEIR MONEY.
AND I'M THE ONLY ONE UP HERE
THAT CAN SAY THAT.
EMINENT DOMAIN, THE KEYSTONE
PIPELINE.
YOU CONSIDER THAT A PRIVATE JOB?
>> I CONSIDER IT A PUBLIC USE.
>> LET ME ASK YOU, JEB.
DO YOU CONSIDER IT PRIVATE?
>> IT'S A PUBLIC USE.
>> PUBLIC USE?
NO, IT'S A PRIVATE JOB.
>> IT'S A PUBLIC USE.
THAT WAS BY THE COURTS, FEDERAL,
STATE COURTS.
>> YOU WOULDN'T HAVE THE
KEYSTONE PIPELINE THAT YOU WANT
SO BADLY WITHOUT EMINENT DOMAIN.
>> GENTLEMEN --
>> YOU WOULDN'T HAVE MASSIVE
FACTORIES WITHOUT EMINENT
DOMAIN.
>> GENTLEMEN?
WE DO HAVE TO MOVE FORWARD.
DAVID, MARTHA?
>> WHEN WE COME BACK HERE, JOBS,
ISIS, AND WHAT IT MEANS TO BE A
CONSERVATIVE.
THE REPUBLICAN DEBATE CONTINUES
RIGHT HERE FROM NEW HAMPSHIRE ON
ABC.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> ABC NEWS LIVE COVERAGE OF
THE NEW HAMPSHIRE REPUBLICAN
DEBATE IS CONNECTED BY
>>> LIVE FROM MANCHESTER, NEW
HAMPSHIRE, HERE AGAIN IS GEORGE
STEPHANOPOULOS.
>> CANDIDATES TAKING A QUICK
BREAK.
I'M HERE WITH JON KARL RIGHT
NOW.
AND BOY, JON, MARCO RUBIO CAME
INTO THIS DEBATE WITH A HEAD OF
STEAM.
RAN RIGHT INTO CHRIS CHRISTIE.
>> I HAVE NEVER SEEN MARCO RUBIO
MORE RATTLED.
HE REPEATED HIMSELF THREE TIMES,
PRECISELY WHEN CHRIS CHRISTIE'S
CRITICISM BECAUSE, YOU ALWAYS
REPEAT YOURSELF.
THIS WAS A TOUGH MOMENT FOR
RUBIO.
>> DONALD TRUMP STARTED OUT MORE
SUBDUED.
GOT A PASS FOR MOST OF THE
DEBATE, RIGHT UP UNTIL THAT
FIRST SECTION AND JEB BUSH WAS
READY.
>> MAKES YOU WONDER WHERE WOULD
WE BE IF JEB BUSH HAD BEEN THAT
FORCEFUL IN GOING AFTER TRUMP
FROM THE START?
>> HE HAS BEEN HITTING DONALD
TRUMP.
>> NOT AS EFFECTIVELY.
>> HE SEEMED TO DRAW SOME BLOOD
AND SEEMED TO HAVE THE CROWD ON
HIS SIDE, AT LEAST FOR PART OF
THAT ANSWER TONIGHT.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
THE CANDIDATES ON THE STAGE IN
JUST A MINUTE.
>>> LIVE FROM ST. ANSELM COLLEGE
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, HERE AGAIN ARE
DAVID MUIR AND MARTHA RADDATZ.
>> AND WE WELCOME YOU BACK TO
THE REPUBLICAN DEBATE FROM NEW
HAMPSHIRE TONIGHT HERE ON ABC.
WE'RE GOING TO TURN NOW TO WHAT
IT MEANS TO BE A CONSERVATIVE.
I WANT TO TURN TO GOVERNOR
KASICH.
GOVERNOR, WHILE CAMPAIGNING HERE
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, YOU WERE ASKED
BY ABC ABOUT GROANS FROM SOME
CONSERVATIVES AFTER YOUR
ENDORSEMENTS FROM "THE NEW YORK
SOMETI
TIMES" AND "THE BOSTON GLOBE."
YOU SAID, CONSERVATIVES HAVE TO
SAY, ISN'T IT NICE TO HAVE A
CONSERVATIVE LIKE ME LIKED?
IF I GET ELECTED PRESIDENT, THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY AND THE
DEFINITION OF CONSERVATISM IS
GOING TO CHANGE.
HOW COULD YOU CHANGE
CONSERVATISM?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, LOOK.
HE'S CERTAINLY NOT A MODERATE,
BUT HE CAN BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER
TO SOLVE PROBLEMS.
AND THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS,
I'VE CUT TAXES MORE THAN ANYBODY
IN THE COUNTRY.
THIS YEAR.
I HAVE -- I HAVE BALANCED
BUDGETS, THE FEDERAL BUDGET, THE
STATE OF OHIO BUDGET.
WE'RE RUNNING A $2 BILLION
SURPL
SURPLUS.
AND IN WASHINGTON, WE WERE ABLE
TO HAVE SIGNIFICANT JOB GROWTH.
WHEN WE BALANCED THE BUDGET, OF
WHICH I WAS THE ARCHITECT.
IT'S NOT JUST BALANCING THE
BUDGET.
IT'S ABOUT JOBS.
WHEN I WAS A KID GROWING UP IN A
NEIGHBORHOOD WHERE DAD WENT HOME
AT NIGHT AND SAID, I LOST MY JOB
TODAY, IT JUST KILLED THE
FAMILY, IT JUST -- IT JUST WAS A
DEVASTATING AFFECT.
SO, WE HAVE TO HAVE ECONOMIC
GROWTH.
BUT ONCE WE HAVE ECONOMIC
GROWTH, I BELIEVE WE HAVE TO
REACH OUT TO PEOPLE WHO LIVE IN
THE SHADOWS.
I BELIEVE WE NEED TO HELP THE
MENTALLY ILL, THE WORKING POOR.
WE NEED TO HELP THE
DEVELOPMENTAL DISABLED TO RISE
AND WE NEED TO HELP OUR FRIENDS
IN THE MINORITY COMMUNITY
DEVELOP ENTREPRENEURSHIP.
IN AMERICA, CONSERVATISM SHOULD
MEAN NOT ONLY THAT SOME RISE
WITH CONSERVATIVE PRINCIPLES,
BUT EVERYBODY HAS A CHANCE TO
RISE, REGARDLESS OF WHO THEY ARE
SO THEY CAN LIVE THEIR GOD-GIVEN
PURPOSE.
THAT'S WHAT CONSERVATISM SHOULD
BE.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, THANK YOU.
MR. TRUMP, YOU'VE HEARD THE
ARGUMENT THAT YOU ARE NOT A TRUE
CONSERVATIVE.
TELL THE VOTERS WATCHING TONIGHT
WHY YOU ARE.
>> WELL, I THINK I AM.
AND I VIEW THE WORD CONSERVATIVE
AS A DERIVATIVE OF THE WORD
CONSERVE.
WE WANT TO CONSERVE OUR MONEY.
WE WANT TO CONSERVE OUR WEALTH.
WE WANT TO CONSERVE, WE WANT TO
BE SMART.
WE WANT TO BE SMART, WHERE WE
GO, WHERE WE SPEND, HOW WE
SPEND.
WE WANT TO CONSERVE OUR COUNTRY.
WE WANT TO SAVE OUR COUNTRY.
AND WE HAVE PEOPLE THAT HAVE NO
IDEA HOW TO DO THAT AND THEY ARE
NOT DOING IT.
IT'S SOMETHING I BELIEVE IN
VERY, VERY STRONGLY.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
SENATOR RUBIO, YOU HAVE SAID
YOURSELF THAT YOU DON'T THINK
DONALD TRUMP IS RUNNING AS A
CONSERVATIVE.
DID HE CONVINCE YOU?
>> WELL, I THINK CONSERVATISM IS
ABOUT THREE THINGS.
THE FIRST IS CONSERVATISM IS
ABOUT LIMITED GOVERNMENT.
ESPECIALLY AT THE FEDERAL LEVEL.
THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT IS
LIMITED BY THE CONSTITUTION,
WHICH DELINEATES ITS POWERS.
IF IT IS NOT IN THE
CONSTITUTION, IT DOES NOT BELONG
TO THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT.
IT BELONGS TO STATES,
COMMUNITIES.
IT IS ABOUT FREE ENTERPRISE.
IT ALLOWS EVERYONE TO SURVIVE
WITHOUT PULLING ANYONE DOWN.
THE REASON WHY FREE ENTERPRISE
IS THE GREATEST ECONOMIC MODEL
IN THE HISTORY OF THE WORLD IS
BECAUSE IT IS THE ONLY ECONOMIC
MODEL WHERE YOU CAN MAKE POOR
PEOPLE RICHER WITHOUT MAKING
RICH PEOPLE POOR.
IT'S ABOUT A STRONG NATIONAL
DEFENSE.
IT'S BELIEVING THAT THE WORLD IS
A SAFER AND BETTER PLACE WHEN
AMERICA IS THE STRONGEST
MILITARY AND THE STRONGEST
NATION ON THIS PLANET.
THAT'S CONSERVATISM.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO GO TO THE ECONOMY NOW.
MR. TRUMP, GOVERNOR CHRISTIE HAS
SAID, IF YOU GET TO ASK A
QUESTION, JUST ASK HIM HOW.
CHRISTIE SAID, I DON'T CARE WHAT
HE TALKS ABOUT, JUST ASK HIM
HOW.
YOU HAVE SAID THAT YOU'D BE THE
GREATEST JOBS PRESIDENT GOD EVER
CREATED.
TELL AMERICANS WATCHING TONIGHT
HOW MANY JOBS YOU WOULD CREATE
IN THE FIRST TERM AND HOW.
>> WELL, BEFORE I GO THERE, I
WILL TELL YOU, I WILL BRING JOBS
BACK FROM CHINA.
I WILL BRING JOBS BACK FROM
JAPAN.
MEXICO, WHERE NEW HAMPSHIRE, BY
THE WAY, HAS BEEN VIRTUALLY
WIPED OUT, THEY LOST SO MANY
BUSINESSES, GOING TO MEXICO
BECAUSE OF HORRIBLE TRADE DEALS
AND NOW WE ARE ABOUT TO SIGN
ANOTHER TRADE DEAL, TPP, WHICH
IS GOING TO BE A DISASTER FOR
THIS COUNTRY, BECAUSE THEY DON'T
TALK ABOUT MONETARY MANIPULA
MANIPULATION.
IT IS GOING TO BE A DISASTER.
I'M GOING TO BRING JOBS BACK AND
I'LL START BRINGING THEM BACK
VERY FAST.
UNDER MY TAX PLAN, RIGHT NOW,
WE'RE THE HIGHEST TAXED COUNTRY
IN THE WORLD.
UNDER MY PLAN, WE CUT NOT ONLY
TAXES FOR THE MIDDLE CLASS, BUT
WE CUT TAXES FOR CORPORATIONS.
WE WILL BRING BACK TRILLIONS OF
DOLLARS, THAT'S OFFSHORE, RIGHT
NOW, $2.5 TRILLION AND IN MY
OPINION, IT'S MUCH MORE THAN
THAT, THAT'S WHAT THE GOVERNMENT
SAYS.
ALL OF THAT MONEY IS GOING TO
COME BACK.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO LOSE PFIZER
WHICH IS NOW LEAVING, AND OTHER
GREAT COMPANIES, AND THEY ARE
ALL LEAVING.
WE HAVE MANY, MANY COMPANIES
THAT ARE LEAVING THIS COUNTRY.
WE'RE NOT GOING TO LOSE THEM.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE A TAX
STRUCTURE THAT IS GOING TO KEEP
THEM IN OUR COUNTRY.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
THERE ARE A LOT OF GOVERNORS ON
THIS STAGE TONIGHT AND GOVERNOR
CHRISTIE, GOVERNOR KASICH SAID
OF YOU, QUOTE, IN OHIO, WE
BALANCED A BUDGET.
THEY DON'T HAVE ONE IN NEW
JERSEY.
WE'VE GOT MORE JOBS.
HOW IMPORTANT ARE THOSE MET
ICKES IN CHOOSING THE NEXT
PRESIDENT AND IS HIS JOB -- IS
HIS RECORD ON JORDS, I SHOULD
SAY, ACTUALLY STRONGER THAN
YOURS?
>> WELL, HE DESERVES CREDIT.
HE'S DONE A VERY GOOD JOB AS
GOVERNOR OF OHIO.
NEVER SAID JOHN HASN'T.
HE'S DONE A GREAT JOB.
BUT UNFORTUNATELY, JOHN'S BEEN
SO BUSY DOING OVER STUFF, HE'S
USING OLD STATISTICS.
THAT'S OKAY.
NEW JER
NEW JERSEY HAS CUT SPENDING OVER
$2.3 BILLION AND WE HAVE 10,000
FEWER EMPLOYEES THAN WE HAD WHEN
I WALKED IN THE DOOR.
JOHN HAS A BIGGER GOVERNMENT
NOW, AND MORE EMPLOYEES THAN HE
HAD WHEN HE WALKED IN THE DOOR.
ALL THAT DOESN'T MATTER.
WHAT REALLY MATTERS IS THIS.
THAT EXECUTIVE EXPERIENCE
MATTERS.
WE HEARD IT SAID ON THE STAGE
THAT PRESIDENT OBAMA KNOWS WHAT
HE IS DOING.
I WOULD LIKE TO ASK THE VETERANS
OUT THERE TONIGHT, WHO ARE
WAITING IN LINE FOR HEALTH CARE
WHO ARE LITERALLY DYING BECAUSE
THE VETERANS ADMINISTRATION
DOESN'T WORK, DO YOU THINK
BARACK OBAMA KNOWS WHAT HE'S
DOING?
I DON'T.
AND I'LL TELL YOU SOMETHING.
ANYBODY WHO EVALUATING HIM AS
KNOWING WHAT HE'S DOING DOESN'T
KNOW HOW TO MANAGE A GOVERNMENT
THEMSELVES.
AND ONE LAST THING, DAVID, WHICH
I THINK IS REALLY IMPORTANT.
I LISTEN TO SENATOR RUBIO'S
ANSWER ON HIS BILL.
HE SAID HIS BILL COULDN'T PASS
ON THE GANG OF EIGHT.
HE ACTED AS IF HE WAS SOMEHOW
DISEMBODIED FROM THE BILL.
IT WAS HIS BILL.
HE SAID THAT DIDN'T WORK.
IT WAS HIS IDEA.
SEE, WHEN YOU ARE A GOVERNOR,
YOU HAVE TO TAKE RESPONSIBILITY
FOR THESE THINGS.
YOU CAN'T JUST ACT AS IF IT
HAPPENED OUT OF NOWHERE.
WE HAVE TO TAKE RESPONSIBILITY
AS EXECUTIVES.
I TAKE RESPONSIBILITY FOR MY
RECORD IN NEW JERSEY.
WE REBUILT THE ECONOMY AND
REBUILT AFTER THE SECOND-WORST
NATURAL DISASTER IN AMERICAN
HISTORY.
I'M PROUD OF MY RECORD.
AND I LIKE KASICH'S RECORD, TOO.
HE'S A GOOD GOVERNOR.
>> DAVID?
>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> LOOK, I'M NOT HERE -- I LIK
CHRIS.
LET ME JUST TELL YOU, FIRST OF
ALL, WE HAVE THE LOWEST NUMBER
OF STATE EMPLOYEES IN 30 YEARS.
SECONDLY, WE HAVE GROWN
GOVERNMENT AT THE RATE OF
INFLATION.
AND I WENT FROM AN $8 BILLION
HOLE TO A $2 BILLION SURPLUS.
AND WE'VE GROWN JOBS BY 400,000,
THAT'S ONE OF THE FASTEST
GROWING STATES IN THE COUNTRY.
OUR PENSIONS ARE SECURE.
AND OUR CREDIT IS ROCK SOLID.
NOW, I'VE LEARNED THAT, WHAT
MAKES THINGS WORK, WHAT GETS THE
ECONOMY GOING, NOT JUST IN OHIO,
BUT IN WASHINGTON?
AND IT'S THREE THINGS.
COMMON SENSE REGULATIONS, WHICH
WE HAVE, LOWER TAXES, WHICH WE
HAVE, THE LOWEST TAXES, TAX CUTS
IN THE COUNTRY, AND THIRDLY, A
FISCAL PLAN TO BALANCE THE
BUDGET.
WHEN YOU GO FROM $8 BILLION IN
THE HOLE TO $2 BILLION IN THE
BLAX WHEN YOU CUT TAXES BY $5
BILLION AND YOU GROW OVER
400,000 JOBS, THAT IS A RECORD
THAT I CAN TAKE TO WASHINGTON,
USING THE SAME FORMULA THAT I
USED IN WASHINGTON WHEN I WAS
PART OF THE EFFORT TO BALANCE
THE BUDGET TO GIVE US A SURPLUS
AND TO CREATE JOBS.
THAT'S WHAT I DID AND I'LL DO IT
AGAIN.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH --
>> I WAS MENTIONED --
>> I'M GOING TO COME TO YOU NEXT
WITH A QUESTION, ANYWAY.
GOING FROM JOBS TO TAXES, AND
HERE'S --
>> LET ME RESPOND TO THAT
QUESTION.
>> TO THE GANG OF EIGHT BILL
FIRST?
>> HERE'S THE RESPONSE.
I THINK ANYONE WHO BELIEVES THAT
BARACK OBAMA ISN'T DOING WHAT
HE'S DOING ON PURPOSE DOESN'T
UNDERSTAND WHAT WE'RE DEALING
WITH HERE, OKAY?
THIS IS A PRESIDENT -- THIS IS A
PRESIDENT THAT IS TRYING TO
CHANGE THIS COUNTRY.
WHEN HE TALKED ABOUT CHANGE, HE
WASN'T TALKING ABOUT DEALING
WITH OUR PROBLEMS.
OBAMA CARE WAS NOT AN ACCIDENT.
THE UNDERMINING OF THE SECOND
AMENDMENT IS NOT AN ACCIDENT.
THE GUTTING OF OUR MILITARY IS
NOT AN ACCIDENT.
THE UNDERMINING OF AMERICA ON
THE GLOBAL STAGE IS NOT AN
ACCIDENT.
BARACK OBAMA IS, INDEED, TRYING
TO REDEFINE THIS COUNTRY.
WE BETTER UNDERSTAND WHAT WE'RE
DEALING WITH HERE, BECAUSE
THAT'S WHAT HILLARY CLINTON AND
BERNIE SANDERS WANT TO DOUBLE
DOWN ON.
>> THE GOVERNOR WASN'T TALKING
ABOUT THE PRESIDENT --
>> HE TALKED ABOUT BARACK OBAMA.
>> LET ME ASK YOU ABOUT TAXES,
SENATOR RUBIO.
A RECENT POLL, 68% OF AMERICANS
FAVOR RAISING TAXES ON PEOPLE
MAKING MORE THAN $1 MILLION A
YEAR.
ARE THEY WRONG?
>> I DON'T KNOW OF ANY PROBLEM
IN AMERICA THAT'S GOING TO BE
FIXED WITH A TAX INCREASE.
WE HAVE AN ECONOMY TODAY, AN
ECONOMY TODAY THAT IS NOT
CREATING JOBS THAT PAY ENOUGH.
AND ONE OF THE REASONS WHY IS
BECAUSE WE HAVE ONE OF THE MOST
EXPENSIVE BUSINESS TAX RATES ON
THE PLANET.
OUR COMBINED RATE PUTS US AMONG
THE HIGHEST IN THE
INDUSTRIALIZED WORLD.
AND WE ARE THE ONLY ONE THAT HAS
A WORLDWIDE SYSTEM OF TAXATION.
AN AMERICAN COMPANY WHO MAKES
MONEY ABROAD HAS TO PAY TAXES
WHERE THEY MADE THE MONEY AND A
SECOND TIME WHEN THEY BRING IT
BACK.
THE COMBINATION OF THESE TWO
THINGS HAS STRANDED OVER $2
TRILLION, THE EQUIVALENT OF THE
SIZE OF THE RUSSIAN ECONOMY, $2
TRILLION OF AMERICAN CORPORATE
MONEY, STRANDED OVERSEAS,
COMBINED WITH ALL OF THESE
INVERSIONS OF COMPANIES LEAVING
US.
THE SOLUTION TO THE PROBLEMS WE
HAVE TODAY ARE NOT A TAX
INCREASE.
IT IS TO LOWER OUR TAXES ON BOTH
PEOPLE AND ON COMPANIES SO WE
CAN MAKE AMERICA GLOBALLY
COMPETITIVE AGAIN.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO BRING IN GOVERNOR
BUSH.
68% OF AMERICANS FAVOR RAISING
TAXES ON PEOPLE MAKING MORE THAN
$1 MILLION.
WHAT DO YOU SAY TO THOSE PEOPLE
TONIGHT?
>> I WOULD LIKE TO SEE MORE
MILLIONA
MILLIONAIRES.
WE NEED TO CREATE A PROSPERITY
SOCIETY WHERE PEOPLE CAN RISE
UP.
THIS NOTION THAT SOMEHOW WE'RE
UNDERTAXED AS A NATION IS JUST
FOOL HEARTY, WHEN WE HAVE
ENTITLEMENTS GROWING FASTER THAN
OUR ABILITY TO PAY FOR IT.
A CONSERVATIVE, BECAUSE THAT'S
THE POINT OF THIS, BELIEVES IN
LIMITED GOVERNMENT, BELIEVES IN
A STRONG NATIONAL DEFENSE.
BUT WE NEED TO REFORM THINGS.
IN MY TOWN HALL MEETINGS, I WENT
TO A PLACE WHERE A WOMAN
DESCRIBED HER NEIGHBOR WHO HAS A
BETTER ECONOMIC DEAL BY NOT
WORKING THAN HER STRUGGLING TO
MAUCK E
MAKE ENDS MEET.
WE NEED TO BE ON THE SIDE OF
WORKING PEOPLE.
THE PROBLEM WITH THE LEFT IS,
ANOTHER TAX, ANOTHER REGULATION,
ANOTHER MANDATE MAKES IT HARDER
FOR THEM TO RISE UP.
EVERYTHING THAT WE SHOULD DO
SHOULD BE FOCUSED ON HIGH
SUSTAINED ECONOMIC GROWTH, WHERE
THE MIDDLE CLASS GETS A RAISE
FOR THE FIRST TIME AND WHERE
PEOPLE ARE REWARDED FOR WORK,
RATHER THAN NONWORK.
AND I KNOW HOW TO DO THIS.
IF PEOPLE ARE INTERESTED IN THE
SPECIFICS, GO TO JEB2016.COM.
>> KNEW THAT WAS COMING.
>> DAVID?
DAVID?
I ACTUALLY HAVE EXPERIENCE WITH
RAISING TAXES ON MILLIONAIRES IN
MY STATE, IT WAS DONE.
IT WAS DONE BY MY PREDECESSOR.
I WANT PEOPLE TO KNOW THE TRUTH.
YOU'RE WRONG.
HERE IS WHY YOU'RE WRONG.
AFTER NEW JERSEY RAISED TAXES ON
MILLIONAIRES, WE LOST, IN THE
NEXT FOUR YEARS, $70 BILLION IN
WEALTH, IT LEFT OUR STATE, TO GO
WHERE IT WOULD BE TREATED MORE
KINDLY.
IF THE UNITED STATES RAISES
TAXES ANY FURTHER, THAT MONEY
WILL LEAVE THE UNITED STATES, AS
WELL.
WE WON'T HAVE BETTER JOBS.
LET NEW JERSEY BE THE CANARY IN
THE COAL MINE.
IT IS A FAILED IDEA AND A FAILED
POLICY, IT'S CLASS WARFARE.
IT HAPPENED IN MY STATE.
I'VE STOPPED IT FROM HAPPENING
AGAIN.
T WE CANNOT DO IT.
THE 68% OF THE PEOPLE ARE WRONG
ABOUT THAT, IT WILL HURT THE
AMERICAN ECONOMY.
WE TRIED IT IN HJ HNEW JERSEY.
IT DID NOT WORK.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, THANK YOU.
MARTHA?
>> SENATOR CRUZ, YOU ADVOCATE
WHAT YOU CALL CARPET BOMBING, OR
SATURATION BOMBING, TO DEFEAT
ISIS, CITING THE MORE THAN 1,100
AIR ATTACKS A DAY, THE U.S.
CARRIED OUT DURING THE FIRST
GULF WAR IN 1991.
EXPLAIN HOW A STRATEGY TO DEFEAT
A STANDING ARMY WOULD WORK
AGAINST AN UNCONVENTIONAL
TERRORIST GROUP THAT IS NOW
HIDING AMONGST THE POPULATION.
>> WELL, SURE.
IT STARTS WITH A COMMANDER IN
CHIEF THAT SETS THE OBJECTIVE.
AND THE OBJECTIVE HAS TO BE
UTTERLY AND COMPLETELY
DESTROYING ISIS.
OBAMA HASN'T STARTED WITH THAT
OBJECTIVE AND EVERYTHING ELSE
FLOWS FROM THERE.
ONCE YOU SET THAT OBJECTIVE, WE
HAVE THE TOOLS TO CARRY THAT
OUT.
THE FIRST TOOL IS OVERWHELMING
AIR POWER.
IT IS ONE OF THE BLESSINGS OF
THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA,
HAVING THE GREATEST MILITARY ON
THE FACE OF THE EARTH, IS, WE
HAVE THE ABILITY TO USE THAT AIR
POWER, AS YOU KNOW, THE FIRST
PERSIAN GULF WAR, 1,100 AIR
ATTACKS A DAY.
OBAMA IS LAUNCHING BETWEEN 15
AND 30.
NOW, WHEN I SAY SATURATION
CARPET BOMBING, THAT IS TARGETED
AT OIL FACILITIES, TARGETED AT
THE OIL TANKERS, COMMAND AND
CONTROL LOCATIONS, TARGETED AT
INF
INFRASTRUCTURE, COMMUNICATIONS,
IT'S TARGETED AT BOMBING ALL OF
THE ROADS AND BRIDGES.
IT'S USING OVERWHELMING AIR
POWER.
YOU KNOW, COUPLE OF WEEKS AGO,
IT WAS REPORTED THAT A FACILITY
IS OPEN CALLED JIHADIST
UNIVERSITY.
NOW, THE QUESTION I WONDER, WHY
IS THAT BUILDING STILL STANDING?
IT SHOULD BE RUBBLE.
AND IF YOU HAD A PRESIDENT,
THOUGH, I WILL SAY THIS -- I
WOULD BE WILLING TO WAIT UNTIL
FRESHMAN ORIENTATION BEFORE
LAUNCHING THOSE BOMBS.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, WOULD YOU LIKE
TO EXPAND OR LOOSEN THE RULES OF
EXGAUGEMENT?
I WAS JUST IN A COMMAND CENTER,
AND THEY SAID THEY THOUGHT THE
RULES OF ENGAGEMENT WORKED.
BECAUSE YOU HAVE SO MANY
CIVILIANS IN THOSE POPULATED
AREAS, THEY DON'T WANT TO HIT
CIVILIANS.
>> MARTHA, I'LL TELL YOU, I HAVE
VISITED WITH ACTIVE DUTY
MILITARY, WITH VETERANS OVER AND
OVER AND OVER AGAIN IN TOWN
HALLS ALL OVER THE STATE OF NEW
HAMPSHIRE.
WHAT WE ARE DOING TO OUR SONS
AND DAUGHTERS, IT IS IMMORAL.
WE ARE SENDING THEM IN TO FIGHT
WITH THEIR ARMS TIED BEHIND
THEIR BACK.
THEY CANNOT DEFEND THEMSELVES.
AND IT IS WRONG.
AND I WILL TELL YOU THIS.
LOOK.
AMERICA HAS ALWAYS BEEN
RELUCTANT TO USE MILITARY FORCE.
IT'S THE LAST STEP WE TAKE.
BUT IF AND WHEN WE USE IT, AND
WHEN IT COMES TO DEFEATING ISIS,
WE SHOULD USE IT.
WE SHOULD USE OVERWHELMING
FORCE, KILL THE ENEMY, AND THEN
GET THE HECK OUT.
DON'T ENGAGE IN NATION-BUILDING,
BUT INSTEAD, ALLOW OUR SOLDIERS
TO DO THEIR JOBS INSTEAD OF
RISKING THEIR LIVES WITH
POLITICIANS, MAKING IT
IMPOSSIBLE TO ACCOMPLISH THE
OBJECTIVE.
>> SO, LOOSEN THE RULES OF
ENGAGEMENT?
>> ABSOLUTELY, YES.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, YOU SAID IN
THE LAST DEBATE THAT ISIS IS THE
MOST DANGEROUS JIHADIST GROUP IN
THE HISTORY OF MANKIND.
AND THAT WILL IT TAKE
OVERWHELMING U.S. FORCE TO
DEFEAT THEM.
CAN YOU SPECIFICALLY TELL US
WHAT YOU MEAN BY OVERWHELMING
FORCE?
>> WELL, FIRST, WE NEED TO
UNDERSTAND WHO THEY ARE.
ISIS IS NOT JUST A JIHADIST
GROUP, THEY'RE AN APOCALYPTIC
GROUP.
THEY WANT TO TRIGGER A SHOWDOWN
BETWEEN THE WEST AND THEMSELVES,
WHICH THEY BELIEVE WILL TRIGGER
THE ARRIVAL OF THEIR FIGURE.
I'M NOT SAYING WHAT'S GOING TO
HAPPEN.
THE REASON WHY IT'S IMPORTANT TO
UNDERSTAND THAT IS BECAUSE THESE
ARE NOT GROUPS THAT ARE JUST
GOING TO GO AWAY ON THEIR OWN.
THEY ARE GOING TO HAVE TO THE
DEFEATED.
AND I BELIEVE THEY NEED TO BE
DEFEATED AND THE GROUND, BY A
GROUND FORCE, MADE UP OF SUNNI
ARABS.
IT WILL TAKE SUNNI ARABS TO
REJECT THEM AND DEFEAT THEM
MILITARILY.
THAT WILL REQUIRE COALITION OF
IRAQIS AND SYRIANS THAT ARE ALSO
SUNNIS, BUT THE COOPERATION OF
JORDANIANS, EGYPTIANS, THAT WILL
NEED TO BE BACKED UP WITH U.S.
SPECIAL OPERATION FORCES
ALONGSIDE THEM AND IT WILL HAVE
TO BE BACKED UP WITH INCREASED
AIR STRIKES.
WE ARE GOING TO HAVE TO STRIKE
THEM IN IRAQ AND SYRIA AND EVERY
OTHER PART OF THE WORLD WHERE
THEY HAVE HUBS OF OPERATION.
THEY HAVE AFFILIATES IN A DOZEN
COUNTRIES ON THIS PLANET.
IT ALL BEGINS BY TAKING AWAY
THEIR THEY OPERATING SPACES.
>> AGAIN, SENATOR RUBIO, YOU'VE
ALREADY SAID ISIS IS THE MOST
DANGEROUS JIHADIST GROUP IN THE
HISTORY OF MANKIND.
SO, THAT WOULD MAKE IT MORE
DAUNG RO
DANGEROUS THAN AL QAEDA, THE
INSURGENTS IN IRAQ.
WE COMMITTED HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF U.S. TROOPS TO
FIGHT THOSE GROUPS.
SO, IF ISIS IS THE MOST
DANGEROUS GROUP IN HISTORY, WHY
NOT COMMIT A LARGE U.S. GROUND
FORCE?
>> BECAUSE THEY CURRENTLY OCCUPY
SUNNI CITIES AND VILLAGES.
SUNNI CITIES AND VILLAGES CAN
ONLY TRULY BE LIBERATED AND HELD
BY SUNNIS THEMSELVES.
IF THEY ARE HELD BY SHIAS,
WILL START SECTARIAN VIOLENCE.
KURDS DO NOT WANT TO LIBERATE
AND HOLD SUNNI VILLAGES AND
TOWNS.
IT WILL TAKE SUNNI FIGHTERS TOE
TAKE THOSE VILLAGES AND CITIES
AND TO AVOID THE SECTARIAN
VIOLENCE THAT FOLLOWS IN THE
PAST.
AND WHY THAT IS IMPORTANT IS
BECAUSE IF SUNNIS ARE NOT ABLE
TO GOVERN THEMSELVES IN THESE
AREAS, YOU ARE GOING TO HAVE A
SUCCESSOR GROUP TO ISIS.
ISIS IS A SUCCESSOR GROUP OF AL
QAEDA.
IN FACT, THEY BROKE AWAY FROM AL
QAEDA, AS HORRIBLE AS AL QAEDA
IS, ISIS THOUGHT AL QAEDA WAS
NOT RADICAL ENOUGH.
THIS IS WHO WE'RE DEALING WITH
AND THEY HAVE MORE MONEY THAN AL
QAEDA EVER HAD.
>> WHAT WOULD YOU DO DIFFERENTLY
TO TRY TO GET THE SUNNI FORCES?
THEY HAVE NOT BEEN COMING
FORWARD.
>> WELL, THE PROBLEM WITH THE
SUNNI FORCES IN THE REGION IS
THEY DON'T TRUST THIS
ADMINISTRATION.
THIS ADMINISTRATION CUT A DEAL
WITH THEIR MORTAL ENEMIES, THE
SHIA, IN IRAN.
IT POISONED THE WELL WITH THESE
COUNTRIES.
IT MAKES IT VERY DIFFICULT TO
COOPERATE WITH THEM.
THEY UNDERSTAND WHAT REAL U.S.
AIR POWER LOOKS LIKE.
THEY SAW THE IRAQ WAR.
THEY SAW AFGHANISTAN.
NA
THEY KNOW WHAT AIR POWER LOOKS
LIKE WHEN THE UNITED STATES IS
COMMITTED TO THE CAUSE.
THEY SEE THE AIR STRIKES
CONDUCTED NOW AND THEY SAY TO
THEMSELVES, THAT'S NOT REAL
COMMITMENT.
WE KNOW WHAT REAL COMMITMENT
LOOKS LIKE.
THE JORDANIAN KING WAS IN
WASHINGTON THREE WEEKS AGO.
HE TOLD EVERYONE WHO WOULD
LISTEN THAT THEY HAVE BEGGED FOR
PERMISSION FROM THE COALITION TO
TARGET CAR HAVE ACARAVANS.
THEY WILL NOT ALLOWED TO
PROCEED.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU VERY
MUCH, SENATOR RUBIO, MR. TRUMP.
YOU HAVE SAID YOU WILL
VIGOROUSLY BOMB ISIS.
YOU'VE SAID, WE'VE GOT TO GET
RID OF ISIS, QUICKLY, QUICKLY.
HOW WOULD YOU GET RID OF THEM SO
QUICKLY AND PLEASE GIVE US
SPECIFICS.
>> WELL, FOUR YEARS AGO, I SAID,
BOMB THE OIL AND TAKE THE OIL.
AND IF WE DID THAT, THEY
WOULDN'T HAVE THE WEALTH THEY
HAVE RIGHT NOW.
NOW, I STILL SAY THE SAME THING.
BECAUSE WE'RE DOING LITTLE
PINPRICKS, WE'RE NOT EVEN BOMB,
IF SOMEBODY IS DRIVING A TRUCK,
THEY GIVE NOTICE, WE'RE GOING TO
BOMB.
IF THEY DON'T GET OUT OF THE
TRUCK, THE TRUCK SAILS AWAY WITH
THE OIL.
WE DON'T WANT TO BOMB THE OIL,
BECAUSE WE DON'T WANT TO HURT --
POLLUTE THE ATMOSPHERE.
CAN YOU IMAGINE, GENERAL PATTON
SAYING, WE CAN'T BOMB BECAUSE
WE'RE GOING TO HURT THE
ATMOSPHERE.
YOU HAVE TO KNOCK THE HELL OUT
OF THE OIL.
YOU HAVE TO TAKE THE OIL.
AND YOU HAVE ALSO BACK CHANNELS
OF BANKING.
YOU HAVE PEOPLE WHO THINK ARE
OUR FRIENDS, IN THE MIDDLE EAST,
THAT ARE PAYING TREMENDOUS
NUMBERS OF -- TREMENDOUS AMOUNTS
OF MONEY TO ISIS, SO, WE HAVE TO
STOP THOSE CIRCUITS.
NOBODY KNOWS BANKING BETTER THAN
I DO.
THEY HAVE BACK CHANNELS.
TREMENDOUS AMOUNTS OF MONEY IS
COMING IN THROUGH THE BANKING
SYSTEM.
SO, BETWEEN THE OIL AND THE
BANKING, YOU WILL DRY THEM UP.
BUT IT SHOULD HAVE BEEN DONE
FOUR YEARS AGO, NOT NOW.
>> AND WHAT WOULD YOU DO IN
THOSE CITY WHERE THERE ARE
PEOPLE WHO WE ARE TRYING TO HELP
WHO ISIS IS ESSENTIALLY HOLDING
HOSTAGE?
>> YOU HAVE TO GO IN -- FIRST OF
ALL, WHEN YOU TAKE AWAY THEIR
MONEY AND WEALTH, THAT WILL
WEAK
WEAKEN.
IT WILL LAST FOR A YEAR.
BUT WHEN YOU STOP THE BANKING
CHANNELS AND WHEN YOU STOP THE
OIL AND TAKE THE OIL, NOT JUST
BOMB IT, TAKE IT, WHEN YOU DO
THAT, IT'S GOING TO DRY UP VERY
QUICKLY.
THEY'RE GOING TO BECOME A VERY
WEAKENED POWER QUICKLY.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, MR.
TRUMP.
LET'S TURN TO LIBYA.
GOVERNOR BUSH, IT IS A COUNTRY
IN CHAOS, THERE IS NO
GOVERNMENT.
THIS WEEK, DEFENSE OFFICIALS
SAID THERE ARE NOW 5,000 ISIS
FIGHTERS THERE, ROUGHLY DOUBLING
PREVIOUS ESTIMATES.
WE KNOW YOU AND OTHERS HAVE BEEN
CRITICAL OF THE ADMINISTRATION'S
HANDLING OF LIBYA AFTER THE
INITIAL AIR STRIKES THAT YOU
SUPPORTED.
BUT THIS IS A PROBLEM YOU WOULD
STAND TO INHERIT IF YOU'RE THE
NEXT PRESIDENT.
REPORTS THIS WEEK SAID THE
ADMINISTRATION IS CONSIDERING
NEW AIR STRIKES, POSSIBLE
SPECIAL OPERATIONS RAIDS.
WOULD YOU SUPPORT RENEWED AIR
STRIKES OR ANY U.S. INVOLVEMENT
ON THE GROUND?
>> I WOULD.
AND I WOULD DO IT IN CONCERT,
AGAIN, WITH OUR ARAB ALLIES AND
WITH EUROPE, MOST PARTICULARLY,
IN THIS CASE.
THIS IS THE LESSON LEARNED, IN
HISTORY, IF YOU BOMB SOMETHING
AND NOT DO ANYTHING AS IT
RELATES TO DEAL WITH THE
AFTERMATH OF THIS, IF YOU DON'T
HAVE A STABLE GOVERNMENT, YOU
GET WHAT WE HAVE IN LIBYA.
AND THIS IS NOT LEADING FROM
BEHIND.
IT'S NOT AN EFFECTIVE POLICY.
WE HAVE TO LEAD.
WITHOUT THE UNITED STATES,
NOTHING SEEMS TO WORK.
EUROPE DOESN'T HAVE THE ABILITY
TO LEAD FORWARDLY IN THIS
REGARD.
AND SO, DEALING WITH THE
CALIPHATE IS IMPORTANT, BECAUSE
IT NOW HAS SPAWNED OTHER AREAS.
THERE HAVE BEEN 70-PLUS ATTACKS
IN 17 COUNTRIES, EITHER INSPIRED
BY ISIS OR ORGANIZED BY ISIS.
LIBYA BEING THE MOST IMPORTANT
ONE NOW.
WE HAVE TO DEAL WITH THE
CALIPHATE WITH BUILDING A SUNNI
ARMY THERE, BUT WE HAVE TO DEAL
WITH IT IN LIBYA.
I THINK THE UNITED STATES,
ULTIMATELY, IS GOING TO PLAY A
SIGNIFICANT ROLE IN THIS.
THE PROBLEM WITH THE OBAMA
ADMINISTRATION IS THAT THEY SEE
THIS INCREMENTALLY.
THEY'RE RELUCTANT.
THEY DON'T LEAD.
NO ONE KNOWS IF WE'RE SERIOUS
AND WHEN WE DO IT, WE DO IT IN
INCREMENTS YOU CAN BARELY SEE.
THE UNITED STATES HAS TO LEAD IN
A MUCH MORE AGGRESSIVE WAY THAN
WE'RE DOING RIGHT NOW.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, GOVERNOR
BUSH.
DR. CARSON.
>> I WANT TO SAY SOMETHING ABOUT
THIS, BECAUSE I'M NOT HERE JUST
TO ADD BEAUTY TO THE STAGE.
YOU KNOW, I'VE BEEN TALKING
ABOUT LIBYA FOR QUITE A LONG
TIME.
I THINK I WAS THE FIRST ONE TO
START TALKING ABOUT IT.
I SAY, WE HAVE TO HAVE A PRO
ACTIVE FOREIGN POLICY STRATEGY.
AND, OF COURSE, THE NEXT PLACE
THAT ISIS IS GOING TO ATTACK TO
IS LIBYA.
IF YOU WANT TO EXPAND YOUR
CALIPHATE AND INCREASE YOUR
INFLUENCE, THEN, YOU'RE GOING TO
GO TO A PLACE THAT'S TRA
TEEJICILY LOCATED.
YOU GO NORTH, ACROSS THE
MEDITERRANEAN.
YOU'RE INTO SOUTHERN EUROPE.
YOU GO SOUTH, YOU ARE INTO CHAD
AND SUDAN AND NIGER.
NOT TO MENTION THE FACT THAT YOU
HAVE MUCH MORE OIL THAN YOU DO
IN IRAQ.
THAT'S THE KIND OF PLACE THAT
THEY'RE GOING TO GO TO.
THEREFORE, WE NEED TO BE
THINKING ABOUT HOW DO WE PREVENT
THEM FROM ATTACKING OVER THERE.
THEY ARE ALREADY SENDING THEIR
FIGHTERS THERE.
WE NEED TO BE CONSULTING WITH
OUR MILITARY EXPERTS AND ASKING
THEM, WHAT DO THEY NEED IN ORDER
TO PREVENT ISIS FROM BEING ABLE
TO TAKE OVER LIBYA.
THAT'S GOING TO HAVE ENORMOUS
CONSEQUENCES.
>> WOULD YOU SUPPORT RENEWED AIR
STRIKES?
>> I WOULD SUPPORT THE
POSSIBILITY OF RENEWED AIR
STRIKES IF IN CONJUNCTION WITH
OUR JOINT CHIEFS AND OUR
MILITARY PEOPLE, THEY FELT THAT
THAT WAS AN APPROPRIATE
STRATEGY.
THE FACT OF THE MATTER IS, NONE
OF US UP HERE IS A MILITARY
EXPERT.
AND WE SOMETIMES ACT LIKE WE
ARE, BUT WE'RE NOT.
IF WE ACTUALLY SIT DOWN AND TALK
WITH THEM AND GET THEM TO
UNDERSTAND OUR PLAN AND GET
THEIR IMPRESSION OF WHAT NEEDS
TO BE DONE, I THINK WE'RE GOING
TO MAKE A LOT MORE --
>> WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON.
>> MARTHA, THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO STAY ON ISIS HERE
AND THE WAR ON TERROR, BECAUSE
THERE'S BEEN A DEBATE IN THIS
COUNTRY ABOUT HOW TO DEAL WITH
THE ENEMY AND ENHANCED
INTERROGATION ATTEMPTS.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU HAVE SAID,
TORTURE IS WRONG, PERIOD.
CIVILIZED NATION DO NOT ENGAGE
IN TORTURE.
SOME OF THE OTHER CANDIDATES SAY
THEY DON'T THINK WATERBOARDING
IS TORTURE.
MR. TRUMP HAS SAID, I WOULD
BRING IT BACK.
SENATOR CRUZ, IS WATERBOARDING
TORTURE?
>> WELL, UNDER THE DEFINITION OF
TORTURE, NO, IT'S NOT.
UNDER THE LAW, TORTURE IS
EXCRUCIATING PAIN THAT IS
EQUIVALENT TO LOSING ORGANS AND
SYSTEMS, SO, UNDER THE
DEFINITION OF TORTURE, IT IS
NOT.
IT IS ENHANCED INTERROGATION, IT
IS VIGOROUS INTERROGATION, BUT
IT DOES NOT MEET THE GENERALLY
RECOGNIZED DEFINITION OF TORT
TORTURE.
>> IF ELECTED PRESIDENT, WOULD
YOU BRING IT BACK?
>> I WOULD NOT BRING IT BACK IN
ANY SORT OF WIDESPREAD USE.
AND INDEED -- I
SENATOR McCAIN IN LEGISLATION
THAT WOULD PROHIBIT LINE
OFFICERS FROM EMPLOYING IT,
BECAUSE I THINK BAD THINGS
HAPPEN WHEN ENHANCED
INTERROGATION IS EMPLOYED AT
LOWER LEVELS, BUT WHEN IT COMES
TO KEEPING THIS COUNTRY SAFE,
THE COMMANDER IN CHIEF HAS
INHERENT CONSTITUTIONAL
AUTHORITY TO KEEP THIS COUNTRY
SAFE.
AND SO, IF IT WERE NECESSARY TO,
SAY, PREVENT A CITY FROM FACING
AN IMMINENT TERRORIST ATTACK,
YOU CAN REST ASSURED THAT AS
COMMANDER IN CHEECH,IEF, I WOUL
WHATEVER METHODS WE COULD TO
KEEP THIS COUNTRY SAFE.
>> NOR CRUZ, THANK YOU.
MR. TRUMP, YOU SAID NOT ONLY
DOES IT WORK, BUT YOU WOULD
BRING IT BACK.
>> WELL, I'LL TELL YOU WHAT.
IN THE MIDDLE EAST, WE HAVE
PEOPLE CHOPPING THE HEADS OFF
CHRISTIANS.
WE HAVE PEOPLE CHOPPING THE
HEADS OFF MANY OTHER PEOPLE.
WE HAVE THINGS THAT WE HAVE
NEVER SEEN BEFORE, AS A GROUP,
WE HAVE NEVER SEEN BEFORE,
WHAT'S HAPPENING RIGHT NOW.
THE MEDIEVAL TIMES, I MEAN, WE
STUDIED MEDIEVAL TIMES, NOT
SINCE MEDIEVAL TIMES HAVE PEOPLE
SEEN WHAT'S GOING ON.
I WOULD BRING BACK WATERBOARDING
AND I WOULD BRING BACK A HELL OF
A LOT WORSE THAN WATERBOARDING.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
GOVERNOR BUSH, YOU SAID YOU
WON'T RULE IT OUT.
CONGRESS HAS PASSED LAWS BANNING
THE USE OF WATERBOARDING BY THE
MILITARY AND THE CIA, AS YOU
KNOW.
WOULD YOU WANT CONGRESS TO
CHANGE THAT?
>> NO, NO, I WOULDN'T.
IT WAS USED SPARINGLY, CONGRESS
HAS CHANGED THE LAWS AND I THINK
WHERE WE STAND IS THE
APPROPRIATE PLACE.
BUT WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS TO
MAKE SURE THAT WE EXPAND OUR
INTELLIGENCE CAPABILITIES.
THE IDEA THAT WE'RE GOING TO
SOLVE THIS FIGHT WITH PREDATOR
DRONES, KILLING PEOPLE SOMEHOW
IS MORE ACCEPTABLE THAN
CAPTURING THEM, SECURING THE
INFORMATION.
THIS IS WHY, CLOSING GUANTANAMO
IS A COMPLETE DISASTER.
WHAT WE NEED TO DO IS MAKE SURE
WE ARE KEPT SAFE BY HAVING
INTELLIGENCE CAPABILITIES, BOTH
HUMAN AND TECHNOLOGICAL.
THAT'S HOW YOU GET A MORE SAFE
PLACE, IS BY MAKING SURE THAT
WE'RE FULLY ENGAGED.
RIGHT NOW, THIS ADMINISTRATION
DOESN'T DO THAT.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH, THANK YOU.
SENATOR RUBIO, I DO WANT TO ASK
YOU, YOU HAVE SAID THAT YOU DO
NOT WANT THE TELEGRAPH TO THE
ENEMY WHAT YOU WOULD DO AS
COMMANDER IN CHIEF.
BUT FOR THE AMERICAN PEOPLE, DO
YOU BELIEVE WATERBOARDING IS
TORTURE?
>> WELL, WHEN PEOPLE TALK ABOUT
INTERROGATING TERRORISTS, THEY
ARE ACTING LIKE THIS IS SOME
SORT OF LAW ENFORCEMENT
FUNCTION.
LAW ENFORCEMENT IS ABOUT
GATHERING EVIDENCE.
ANTI-TERRORISM IS ABOUT FINDING
OUT INFORMATION TO PREVENT A
FUTURE ATTACK.
SO, THE SAME TACTICS DO NOT
APPLY.
AND IT IS TRUE, WE SHOULD NOT BE
DISCUSSING IN A WIDESPREAD WAY
THE EXACT TACTICS THAT WE'RE
GOING TO USE, BECAUSE IT ALLOWS
TERRORISTS AND OTHERS TO
PRACTICE HOW TO EVADE US.
BUT HERE'S THE BIGGER PROBLEM
WITH ALL OF THIS.
WE'RE NOT INTERROGATING ANYBODY
RIGHT NOW.
BEGAN TONE
BEGAN ON THE MOW IS BEING
EMPTIED.
WE SHOULDN'T BE RELEASING THESE
KILLERS WHO ARE REJOINING THE
BATTLEFIELD.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
WE WANT TO TURN NOW TO EXECUTIVE
ORDERS.
AND LET'S GO BACK TO MARY
KATHERINE.
>> DAVID, THANK YOU.
SENATOR CRUZ, ON THE CAMPAIGN
TRAIL, YOU'VE PROMISED VOTERS A
LOT, AND FAST.
IF YOU ARE ELECTED PRESIDENT,
YOU SAID YOU'D END COMMON CORE,
ABOLISH THE IRS AND DO AWAY WITH
SANCTUARY CITIES.
YOU'VE BEEN A CRITIC OF
PRESIDENT OBAMA'S EXECUTIVE
OVERREACH.
HOW DO YOU INTEND TO IMPLEMENT
THIS AGGRESSIVE AGENDA WITHIN
YOUR CONSTITUTIONAL AUTHORITY,
ESPECIALLY GIVEN THAT IT WOULD
REQUIRE WORKING WITH CONGRESS
AND WASHINGTON PLAYERS WITH WHOM
YOU ARE HAPPY TO SAY YOU HAVE A
STRAINED RELATIONSHIP.
>> WELL, THANK YOU FOR THAT
QUESTION, YOU KNOW, THERE ARE
THREE AVENUES OF PRESIDENTIAL
AUTHORITY TO CHANGE THE
DIRECTION OF THIS COUNTRY.
THE FIRST IS EXECUTIVE POWER.
THE SECOND IS FOREIGN POLICY.
AND THE THIRD IS LEGISLATION.
EXECUTIVE POWER, AS WE ALL KNOW,
HAS BEEN THE PREFERRED VEHICLE
OF PRESIDENT OBAMA, ABUSING HIS
AUTHORITY, ABUSING HIS
CONSTITUTIONAL AUTHORITY.
NOW, THE SILVER LINING OF THAT
IS, EVERYTHING DONE WITH
EXECUTIVE POWER CAN BE UNDONE
WITH EXECUTIVE POWER.
SO, I HAVE PLEDGED, ON DAY ONE,
I WILL RESCIND EVERY SINGLE
ILLEGAL AND UNCONSTITUTIONAL
EXECUTIVE ACTION BARACK OBAMA
HAS DONE.
THAT MEANS ON DAY ONE, HIS
EFFORTS TO RESTRICT THE SECOND
AMENDMENT GO AWAY.
THAT MEANS ON DAY ONE, HIS
ILLEGAL EXECUTIVE AMNESTY GOES
AWAY.
THE REASON I CAN END COMMON CORE
AT THE FEDERAL LEVEL IS BECAUSE
OBAMA IS ABUSING EXECUTIVE POWER
USING RACE TO THE TOP FUNDS TO
FORCE IT ON THE STATES.
THAT'S ONE AVENUE.
THE SECOND AVENUE OF CHANGE IS
FOREIGN POLICY.
AND FOREIGN POLICY CAN CHANGE
THE FASTEST.
IT'S WORTH REMEMBERING THAT IRAN
RELEASED OUR HOSTAGES THE DAY
REAGAN WAS SWORN IN.
AND THE THIRD IS LEGISLATION,
AND THAT CAN ONLY BE DONE WITH
THE PEOPLE BEHIND YOU, WHICH IS
WHY THE TWO BIG LEGISLATIVE
INITIATIVES I'M CAMPAIGNING ON
ARE REPEALING OBAMA CARE AND
ADOPTING A SIMPLE FLAT TAX TO
ABOLISH THE IRS.
>> MR. TRUMP.
IF SENATOR CRUZ IS KNOWN FOR
OPPOSING DEALS, YOU LITERALLY
WROTE THE BOOK ON MAKING THEM.
SENATOR CRUZ HAS MENTIONED THAT
ON THE TRAIL.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO THOSE
CONSERVATIVES WHO ARE CONCERNED
THAT A DEALMAKER WILL JUST
PERPETUATE THE SAME DEEMS IN
WASHINGTON, THE WAY THAT THINGS
RUN NOW.
>> NO, A GOOD DEALMAKER WILL
MAKE GREAT DEALS.
BUT WILL DO IT THE WAY OUR
FOUNDERS THOUGHT IT SHOULD BE
DONE.
PEOPLE GET TOGETHER, THEY MAKE
DEALS.
RONALD REAGAN DID IT WITH TIP
O'NEILL.
YOU DIDN'T HEAR SO MUCH ABOUT
EXECUTIVE ORDERS, IF YOU HEARD
ABOUT IT AT ALL.
YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO GET A
CONSENSUS.
NOW, THE REAL PERSON, LIKE IT
WAS MENTIONED ABOUT THE DEAL
WITH IRAN, HOW BAD A DEAL IS
THAT?
IT DOESN'T GET ANY MORE
AMATEURISH THAN THAT.
WITH CONGRESS, YOU HAVE TO GET
EVERYBODY IN A ROOM, AND YOU
HAVE TO GET THEM TO AGREE.
BUT YOU HAVE TO GET THEM TO
AGREE WITH WHAT YOU WANT.
AND THAT'S PART OF BEING A
DEALMAKER.
YOU CAN'T LEAVE THE WHITE HOUSE,
GO TO HAWAII AND PLAY GOLF FOR
THREE WEEKS AND BE A REAL
DEALMAKER.
IT DOESN'T WORK THAT WAY.
YOU HAVE TO GET PEOPLE IN, GRAB
THEM, HUG THEM, KISS THEM AND
GET THE DEAL DONE.
BUT IT'S GOT TO BE THE DEAL THAT
YOU WANT.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH.
IS THE PROBLEM WITH WASHINGTON
THAT THERE ARE TOO MANY DEALS OR
TOO FEW?
>> WELL, RIGHT NOW, THE DEALS --
THERE'S NO LEADERSHIP.
A LOT OF THE THINGS THAT WE'RE
TALKING ABOUT HERE TONIGHT, YOU
KNOW, ON THE BORDER AND SO MANY
OF THE THINGS, YOU KNOW, WHAT WE
SHOULD BE DOING ON FOREIGN
POLICY, THE PROBLEM IS, MARY
KATHERINE, THERE'S NOT A LEADER
THAT GETS SOMEBODY TO RISE UP.
YOU HAVE TO HAVE A LEADER THAT
CAN INSPIRE.
I MEAN, ACTUALLY, SOME OF WHAT
DONALD IS SAYING IS TRUE.
LOOK, YOU KNOW HOW HARD IT WAS
TO --
>> SOME?
>> TO GET THE FEDERAL BUDGET
BALANCED?
YOU HAVE TO PLEAD WITH PEOPLE.
TO DO WHAT WE'VE DONE IN OHIO,
THEN, YOU GO BACK DOWN TO
WASHINGTON AND DO THE SAME
THING.
WE HAVE TO REMIND PEOPLE, WE'RE
AMERICANS BEFORE WE'RE
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS.
AND WHEN WE WAIT AND WHEN WE
DELAY, WHAT WE END UP DOING,
MARY KATHERINE, IS, WE MAKE THE
UNITED STATES WEAKER.
IN FACT, IT'S A FOREIGN POLICY
ISSUE, BECAUSE PEOPLE LOOK AT
AMERICAN, NOT SOLVING PROBLEMS
AND THEY SAY, WHAT ARE THEY
DOING OVER THERE?
SO, THE POINT IS, YOU HAVE TO
WORK WITH PEOPLE.
THE PROBLEM WITH EXECUTIVE
AUTHORITY FOR THE PRESIDENT,
IT'S REALLY BAD NEWS FOR THIS
REASON.
SINCE HE'S GIVEN UP ON WORKING
WITH CONGRESS, HE THINKS HE CAN
IMPOSE ANYTHING HE WANTS.
HE'S NOT A KING.
HE'S A PRESIDENT.
AND EXECUTIVE ORDERS SHOULD BE
USED, FRANKLY, IN CONSOLIDATION
AND CONSULTING WITH THE
LEADERSHIP IN THE CONGRESS.
I'VE DONE IT IN OHIO, I CONSULT,
I CAN USE EXECUTIVE ORDERS, BUT
I DON'T TRUMP THE LEGISLATURE.
BECAUSE IF YOU DO, YOU AGGRAVATE
THEM, YOU ANGER THEM AND THEN
THE LONG-TERM PROSPECTS GET
BLEAK.
WE HAVE TO SOLVE PROBLEMS IN
AMERICA BY COMING TOGETHER,
REPUBLICANS AND DEMOCRATS,
AMERICANS FIRST, PARTY AND
IDEOLOGY SECOND, IN THE SECOND
BACK SEAT OF THIS COUNTRY.
THAT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO.
AND WE CAN DO IT.
>> THIS IS A -- THIS IS AN
IMPORTANT SUBJECT.
I AGREE WITH EVERYTHING THAT'S
BEEN SAID HERE ABOUT REPEALING
UNCONSTITUTIONAL RULES AND RULES
THAT ARE CREATING REAL BURDENS
FOR INVESTING THAT CREATING
JOBS.
BUT WE ALSO OUGHT TO GET BACK TO
BEING A TENTH AMENDMENT COUNTRY,
AS WELL.
A COUNTRY THAT RESPECTS THE
STATES TO BE ABLE TO MAKE MORE
DECISIONS.
AND IN THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION,
WE WOULD SHIFT TRANSPORTATION
DOLLARS BACK TO THE STATES.
I TRUST KASICH AND CHRISTIE TO
BUILD THE ROADS AND THE INF
INFRASTRUCTURE OF THEIR STATES
THAN WASHINGTON, D.C.
EPA DELEGATED AUTHORITY, BACK TO
THE STATES.
EDUCATION DOLLARS, BACK TO THE
STATES.
I WOULD LIKE TO SEE REFORM TAKE
PLACE ALL ACROSS THE COUNTRY,
WHERE THERE'S MORE VOUCHERS,
MORE FREEDOM.
IF WE DID THAT, WE WOULD SHRINK
GOVERNMENT'S POWER IN
WASHINGTON, D.C., AND WE WOULD
HAVE A MUCH MORE EFFECTIVE
GOVERNMENT, WHERE PEOPLE WOULD
BEGIN TO TRUST OUR GOVERNMENT
AGAIN, BECAUSE NOW, NO ONE
BELIEVES IT WORKS.
>> MARY KATHERINE, LET ME JUST
SAY THIS TO YOU.
YOU MUST HAVE AN AGENDA THAT YOU
ARE READY TO MOVE ON IN THE
FIRST 100 DAYS.
JEB IS RIGHT.
IF YOU DELAY AND YOU WAIT, THE
WASHINGTON OPERATORS WILL TAKE
YOU DOWN.
I CAN TELL YOU THIS, IN THE
FIRST 100 DAYS, I WILL HAVE
LEGISLATION TO FREEZE FEDERAL
REGULATIONS, HAVE THEM REVIEWED
BY THE VICE PRESIDENT, REDUCE
STATE TAXES ON INDIVIDUALS,
REDUCE TAXES ON CORPORATIONS,
HAVE A FISCAL PLAN TO BALANCE
THE BUDGET, GET THE BORDER
PROTECTED AND BEGIN TO FIX
SOCIAL SECURITY IN THE FIRST 100
DAYS, SO, ANYBODY WHO IS HERE
TONIGHT, IF I GET ELECTED
PRESIDENT, HEAD OUT TOMORROW AND
BUY A SEAT BELT, BECAUSE THERE'S
GOING TO BE SO MUCH HAPPENING IN
THE FIRST 100 DAYS, IT'S GOING
TO MAKE YOUR HEAD SPIN.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE AMERICA
FORWARD.
I PROMISE YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE US FORWARD.
>> YOU MENTIONED ME.
>> HE MENTIONED ME.
ALONG WITH REPEALING OBAMA CARE,
WE NEED TO SHIFT ALL OF THIS
POWER OF HEALTH CARE, WHICH IS
THE MOST EGREGIOUS, ALLOW
GOVERNORS TO HAVE THE MEDICAID
PLANS SO THEY CAN CREATE 21st
CENTURY MEDICAID INSURANCE FOR
PEOPLE WHO ARE STUCK IN POVERTY.
THERE ARE SO MUCH THAT CAN BE
DONE, BUT I DON'T TRUST
WASHINGTON TO DO IT.
I TRUST THE STATES TO BE THE
SOURCE OF INNOVATION AND REFORM
IN THIS COUNTRY.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNORS.
MARTHA AND DAVID, BACK TO YOU.
>> MARY KATHERINE, THANK YOU.
WE WANT TO TURN TO SOMETHING THE
GOVERNOR OF NEW HAMPSHIRE
SAID --
>> JEB MENTIONED ME.
TIME FOR ME TO GO AGAIN!
>> I DIDN'T MENTION HIM THE
SECOND TIME.
>> HE SAYS HE DIDN'T MENTION ME
THE SECOND TIME.
I THOUGHT I HEARD IT, JEB.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH FOR
LISTENING AND BEING PATIENT WITH
ALL OF US TONIGHT.
THANK YOU.
>> CONNECTION HERE ON THE STAGE.
WE'RE GOING TO MOVE ON TO WHAT
THE GOVERNOR OF NEW HAMPSHIRE
SAID JUST THIS WEEK, AND THAT IS
SECOND-LEADING CAUSE OF DEATH IN
THIS STATE.
48% OF THE PEOPLE HERE IN THIS
STATE KNOWS SOMEONE WHO ABUSES
HEROIN.
JOSH?
>> THIS IS A VERY DEADLY PROBLEM
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
LAST MONTH, NEW HAMPSHIRE
SENAT
SENATORS WENT DOWN TO
WASHINGTON, ALONG WITH THE
POLICE CHIEF OF THE STATE'S
LARGEST CITY TO TESTIFY BEFORE
THE JUDICIARY COMMITTEE IN D.C.
SENATOR CRUZ, YOU DID NOT ATTEND
THIS.
EVEN SO, THE POLICE CHIEF CALLED
YOUR ABSENCE NOW RAY JOUTRAGEOU
THE PROBLEM.
YOU TALKED ABOUT A FAMILY
MEMBERS PROBLEM WITH ADDICTION.
WHAT CAN YOU SAY NOW THAT YOU
UNDERSTAND THE SEVERITY OF THE
PROBLEM AND YOU ARE NOT JUST
SAYING WHAT YOU THINK PEOPLE
WANT TO HEAR?
>> WELL, JOSH, AS YOU NOTED,
THIS IS A PROBLEM THAT, FOR ME,
I UNDERSTAND FIRST-HAND.
MY OLDER SISTER, MYRIAM, WHO IS
MY HALF-SISTER, STRUGGLED HER
WHOLE LIFE WITH DRUG AND ALCOHOL
ADDICTION.
MY FATHER AND HER MOM DIVORCED
WHEN SHE WAS A LITTLE GIRL AND
SHE WAS ANGRY HER WHOLE LIFE.
AND SHE ENDED UP MARRYING A MAN
WHO HAD BEEN IN AND OUT OF JAIL.
SHE THEN BECAME A SINGLE MOM AND
SHE HERSELF WENT TO JAIL SEVERAL
TIMES AND SHE ENDED UP SPENDING
SOME TIME IN A CRACK HOUSE.
I STILL REMEMBER MY FATHER AND
ME DRIVING UP TO GET MYRIAM OUT
OF THAT CRACK HOUSE TO TRY TO
CONVINCE HER, SHE NEEDED TO BE A
MOM TO MY NEPHEW, JOEY.
SHE WASN'T WILLING TO LISTEN.
SHE WAS NOT WILLING TO CHANGE
THE PATH SHE WAS ON.
SHE WAS ANGRY.
I WAS -- HAD JUST GOTTEN MY
FIRST JOB COMING OUT OF LAW
SCHOOL.
I TOOK A $20,000 LOAN ON A
CREDIT CARD TO PUT MY NEPHEW,
JOEY, IN VALLEY FORGE MILITARY
ACADE
ACADEMY.
HE WAS IN SIXTH GRADE AT THE
TIME, TO PAY HIS WAY THROUGH
THAT.
AND ABOUT FIVE, SIX YEARS AGO,
MYRIAM DIED OF AN OVERDOSE.
IT WAS THE -- SHE WENT TO
ONE NIGHT, HAD TAKEN TOO MANY
PILLS, AND JOEY WALKED IN, FOUND
HER DEAD.
THIS IS AN EPIDEMIC.
WE NEED LEADERSHIP TO SOLVE IT.
SOLVING IT HAS TO OCCUR AT THE
STATE AND LOCAL LEVEL WITH
PROGRAMS LIKE AA AND COUNCILING
AND CHURCHES AND CHARITIES.
BUT IT HAS TO BE SECURING THE
BORDERS.
MEXICAN CARTELS ARE STRUGGLING
HEROIN INTO THIS COUNTRY.
WE KNOW HOW TO SECURE THE
BORDERS.
WHAT IS MISSING IS THE POLITICAL
WILL TO DO IT.
AND AS PRESIDENT, I WILL SECURE
THE BORDER, WE WILL END THIS
DELUGE OF DRUGS THAT IS FLOWING
OVER OUR SOUTHERN BORDER AND
THAT IS KILLING AMERICANS ACROSS
THIS COUNTRY.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, YOU TALKED
A LOT ABOUT THIS ISSUE HERE IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE, STATE REFORMS,
CRIMINAL JUSTICE REFORMS, ACCESS
TO TREATMENT.
TO SENATOR CRUZ'S POINT, LET'S
TAKE IT A STEP FURTHER.
WOULD YOU BE WILLING TO ENGAGE
INTO ENFORCEMENT INTO MEXICO, A
PLACE WHERE LAW ENFORCEMENT IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE HAS TRACED THE
SUPPLY BACK TO, WOULD YOU ENGAGE
IN CROSS-BORDER ENFORCEMENT
WITHOUT THE COOPERATION WITHOUT
THE MEXICAN GOVERNMENT?
>> OF COURSE I WOULD.
AS A FORMER UNITED STATES
ATTORNEY THAT SPENT SEVEN YEARS
OF MY LIFE FIGHTING THIS, I
WOULD DO THAT.
WE NEED TO DO MORE.
LET ME TELL YOU WHAT WE'VE DONE
IN NEW JERSEY.
WE ARE WORKING WITH THE FOLKS IN
NEW HAMPSHIRE RIGHT NOW TO SHOW
THEM HOW WE'RE HELPING TO SOLVE
THIS PROBLEM IN HJ HNEW JERSEY.
THREE YEARS AGO, I PROPOSED A
LAW THAT WE SIGN INTO EFFECT,
WHICH SAID ANYONE WHO WAS A
NONVIOLENT, NONDEALING
FIRST-TIME DRUG OFFENDER NO
LONGER GOES TO PRISON IN NEW
JERSEY.
THEY GO TO MANDATORY IN-PATIENT
DRUG TREATMENT.
WHAT'S HAPPENED IS, CRIME HAS
GONE DOWN 20% IN THERE'S YEARS.
THE PRISON POPULATION HAS GONE
DOWN 10%.
WE'RE NOW CLOSED THE STATE
PRISON, CLOSED A STATE PRISON
AND TURNING IT INTO A DRUG
REHABILITATION CENTER.
LISTEN, EVERYONE OUT THERE KNOWS
THIS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
THIS IS A DISEASE.
IT'S NOT A MORAL FAILING.
IT'S A DISEASE.
AND WEAPON NEED TO GET PEOPLE
THE TREATMENT THEY NEED.
AND LET ME TELL YOU WHY.
BECAUSE I'M PRO-LIFE.
AND I'M PRO LIFE, NOT JUST FOR
THE NINE MONTHS IN THE WOMB,
WHEN THEY GET OUT AND IT'S A LOT
MORE COMPLICATED.
16-YEAR-OLD HEROIN-ADDICTED DRUG
GIRL ON THE FLOOR OF A COUNTY
LOCKUP, THE 42-YEAR-OLD WHO
HIS OWN FAMILY.
AND THE LAST THING IS THIS.
THESE EFFORTS TAKEN OVER THE
LAST THREE YEARS, 2015 IN NEW
JERSEY, FOR THE FIRST TIME IN
FOUR YEARS, DRUG OVERDOSE DEPTHS
HAVE GONE DOWN, NOT UP, I'LL
BRING THE SAME SOLUTIONS TO THE
COUNTRY.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, THANK YOU
VERY MUCH.
DAVID, MARTHA, BACK TO YOU.
>> THANK YOU, GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
THANK YOU, JOSH.
OUR PARTNER IN THIS DEBATE, THE
INDEPENDENT JOURNAL REVIEW, HAS
COLLECT ED QUESTIONS FROM SOME
PROMINENT CONSERVATIVES AROUND
THE COUNTRY.
HERE'S A VIDEOTAPED QUESTION
FROM RADIO HOST LARRY O'CONNOR.
>> IN 2008, WE SAW HOW MOTIVATED
AND ELECTORATE CAN BE WHEN THEY
THINK THEIR VOTE IS MAKING
HISTORY.
YOU'LL BE RUNNING AGAINST THE
PROSPECT OF THE FIRST WOMAN
PRESIDENT.
HOW WILL YOU CHANGE THAT
NARRATIVE AND MOTIVATE THE
ELECTORATE BEHIND YOUR CONDITION
SI?
>> MR. TRUMP, I'M GOING TO GIVE
THAT QUESTION TO YOU.
YOU TOOK IT AWAY ANYWAY.
>> IT LOOKED LIKE HE WAS LOOKING
RIGHT AT ME RIGHT THERE.
I THINK THAT -- I LOOK AT WHAT'S
GOING ON, I LOOK AT ALL OF THE
POLLS, I DO VERY, VERY WELL
AGAINST HILLARY CLINTON.
I CAN TELL YOU, I'M THE LAST
PERSON THAT SHE WANTS TO RUN
AGAINST.
AND I THINK YOU CAN SEE WHAT
WE'VE DONE IN TERMS OF
GALVANIZING.
I'VE BEEN ALL OVER THE COUNTRY.
WE'RE -- LAST NIGHT, I WAS IN
SOUTH CAROLINA, WE HAD 12,000
PEOPLE.
IT SET UP IN ABOUT FOUR DAYS.
WE HAVE GALVANIZED AND CREATED A
MOVEMENT.
A LOT OF IT HAS TO DO WITH --
JOSH'S QUESTION ON DRUGS, I'M
THE FIRST PERSON THAT SAID,
BUILD A WALL.
NOT A TOY WALL THAT THEY HAVE
RIGHT NOW.
A REAL WARM.
YOU'LL SOLVE LOTS OF PROBLEMS.
BUT WE WILL GALVANIZE THE PEOPLE
OF THIS COUNTRY AND WE WILL BEAT
HILLARY CLINTON.
ASSUMING THAT SHE RUNS, BY THE
WAY, HOW SHE GETS AWAY WITH THE
E-MAIL STUFF, BUT ON THE ASSU
ASSUMPTION THAT SHE RUNS, AND IF
SHE RUNS, SHE'S RUNNING FOR ONE
REASON.
HE'S GOING TO BE ABLE TO RUN FOR
ONE REASON, AND THAT'S BECAUSE
THE DEMOCRATS ARE PROTECTING
HER.
BECAUSE SO MANY PEOPLE HAVE DONE
SO MUCH LESS THAN HER AND THEY
WERE ABSOLUTELY, THEIR LIVES
HAVE BEEN DESTROYED.
BUT ON THE ASSUMPTION THEY
PROTECT HER, I WILL WIN THE
ELECTION AND WE WILL WIN IT BY A
LOT.
WE WILL WIN IT.
WE CANNOT HAVE ANOTHER FOUR
YEARS OF ESSENTIALLY BARACK
OBAMA.
>> THANK YOU, MR. TRUMP.
I'M GOING TO GO TO SENATOR
RUBIO.
HOW WOULD YOU CHANGE THAT
NARRATIVE?
>> I THINK IT'S ALREADY
HAPPENING.
LOOK AT THE TURNOUT IN IOWA.
HISTORIC NUMBERS.
LOOK AT THE RALLIES THAT PEOPLE
ON THIS STAGE ARE HAVING.
MUCH HIGHER NUMBERS THAN YOU
USED TO SEE IN THE PAST.
HERE IS WHY.
PEOPLE ARE STARTING TO
UNDERSTAND, VERY CLEARLY, THAT
THIS ELECTION IS GOING TO BE A
TURNING POINT.
THAT 2016 IS NOT JUST A VOICE
BETWEEN REPUBLICAN OR DEMOCRAT.
IT IS A REFERENDUM ON OUR
IDENTITY AS A NATION AND AS A
PEOPLE.
HERE IS WHAT HILLARY CLINTON
NEEDS TO UNDERSTAND.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE OUR PREE
MARE, OUR DEBATES, TWICE AS MANY
AS THE DEMOCRATS HAVE BEEN
HAVING TO HAVE THEMSELVES.
WE'RE GOING TO BRING THIS PARTY
TOGETHER.
AND WE ARE GOING TO DEFEAT
HILLARY CLINTON, BECAUSE SHE IS
UNQUALIFIED TO BE THE PRESIDENT
OF THE UNITED STATES.
SHE PUT CLASSIFIED INFORMATION
ON HER COMPUTER BECAUSE SHE
THINKS SHE'S ABOVE THE LAW AND
ANYONE WHO LIES TO THE FAMILIES
OF PEOPLE WHO HAVE LOST THEIR
LOVED ONES IN THE SERVICE OF OUR
COUNTRY LIKE SHE DID IN BENGHAZI
CAN NEVER BE THE COMMANDER IN
CHIEF OF THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR RUBIO.
DR. CARSON, I WANT TO GO TO YOU.
WOULD YOU CHANGE THE NARRATIVE?
>> SAME QUESTION?
>> YES.
WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I THINK IT
WOULD BE PRETTY EASY CONTRAST,
QUITE FRANKLY, BETWEEN MYSELF
AND HILLARY CLINTON.
IN ONE CASE, YOU HAVE SOMEONE
WHO IS KNOWN AS A DECEITFUL
INDIVIDUAL.
AN INDIVIDUAL WHO AT BENGHAZI,
WHICH I WILL NEVER LET GO, QUITE
FRANKLY, BECAUSE I THINK OF
THOSE TWO MEN WHO WENT UP THERE
ON THE TOP OF THAT COMPOUND WITH
MACHINE GUNS, FIRING AWAY,
ALLOWING THEIR COLLEAGUES TO
ESCAPE, AND I'M SURE, IN THE
BACK OF THEIR MIND, THEY WERE
JUST SAYING, IF WE CAN JUST HOLD
ON, HELP IS ON THE WAY, BUT HELP
WAS NOT ON THE WAY.
WHEN DID WE IN THE UNITED STATES
NOT SEND PEOPLE TO HELP OUR OWN
PEOPLE?
YOU KNOW, THIS IS NOT WHO WE
ARE.
AND -- I WOULD SIMPLY MAKE IT A
REFERENDUM ON HONESTY AND
INTEGRITY VERSUS DECEIT AND THE
WASHINGTON WAY.
MARTHA?
>> I'M GOING TO GO BACK TO
DAVID.
>> WHEN WE COME BACK, QUESTIONS
ABOUT RACE, OUR VETERANS, AND
WHAT YOUNGER CONSERVATIVE
VOTERS, AS WE CONTINUE WITH NEW
HAMPSHIRE WITH THE REPUBLICAN
DEBATE, RIGHT HERE ON ABC.
>>> ABC NEWS LIVE COVERAGE OF
THE NEW HAMPSHIRE REPUBLICAN
DEBATE WILL CONTINUE IN A
MOMENT.
>>> LIVE FROM MANCHESTER, NEW
HAMPSHIRE, HERE AGAIN IS GEORGE
STEPHANOPOULOS.
>> TWO-THIRDS OF THE WAY THROUGH
THIS DEBATE.
CANDIDATES MAKING THEIR WAY BACK
TO THE STAGE.
HERE WITH JON KARL AGAIN.
AND JON, IN THAT SECOND SECTION,
YOU REALLY SAW ALL THE GOVERNORS
RISE TO THE TOP THERE ON ISSUES
OF JOBS, EXECUTIVE POWER,
ADDICTION.
>> THIS IS SOMETHING ELSE.
THIS IS THE REVENGE OF THE
GOVERNORS IN THIS DEBATE.
YOU LOOK AT WHAT HAPPENED WITH
JEB BUSH, JOHN KASICH AND CHRIS
CHRISTIE, THEY CAME IN SIXTH,
EIGHTH AND TENTH IN IOWA.
THEY WERE THE ALSO-RANS.
IN THIS DEBATE, I THINK ALL
THREE OF THEM HAVE PUT IN THEIR
BEST DEBATE PERFORMANCES OF THE
CAMPAIGN.
>> AND JOHN KASICH, WHO IS DOING
THE BEST IN MOST OF THE POLLS
RIGHT NOW, REALLY TRYING TO
STRIKE HIMSELF OUT AS THE MOST
POSITIVE CANDIDATE UP THERE ON
THE STAGE.
>> HE'S THE ONE TRYING TO GET
THE INDEPENDENTS THAT CAN BE SO
IMPORTANT HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE.
AND HE IS PRESENTING THE
OPTIMISTIC VISION OF, WE'RE
ANGRY, BUT WE'RE ANGRY ABOUT THE
ANGER.
WE WANT TO GET BEYOND THAT.
>> AND THE BETTER THEY DO, MAYBE
THE BETTER DONALD TRUMP DOES.
>> YEAH, AND TRUMP HAS HAD --
THIS HAS BEEN A GREAT DEBATE FOR
TRUMP.
NOBODY'S GONE AFTER HIM.
JEB BUSH WENT AFTER HIM A LITTLE
BIT OF IMMINENT DOMAIN.
>> OKAY, ONE MORE SECTION TO GO.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> LIVE FROM ST. ANSELM COLLEGE
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, HERE AGAIN ARE
DAVID MUIR AND MARTHA RADDATZ.
>> WELCOME BACK TO NEW
HAMPSHIRE, ABC NEWS COVERAGE OF
THE REPUBLICAN DEBATE AND IT IS
GREAT TO HAVE YOU BACK AT THE
PODIUMS AND WE WANT TO TURN TO
RACE IN AMERICA.
AND MR. TRUMP.
THERE ARE MANY WHO ARGUE CELL
PHONES AND SMARTPHONES ARE JUST
NOW EXPOSING WHAT'S BEEN
HAPPENING IN THIS COUNTRY FOR
YEARS.
CASES OF EXCESSIVE FORCE AGAINST
MINORITIES.
AS YOU KNOW, MR. TRUMP, ON THE
OTHER SIDE, THE FBI DIRECTOR
RECENTLY SAID THERE'S A CHILL
WIND BLOWING THROUGH LAW
PHONE,MENT, BECAUSPHON
ENFORCEMENT.
YOU HAVE SAID POLICE ARE THE
MOST MISTREATED PEOPLE IN
AMERICA.
HOW DO YOU BRIDGE THE DIVIDE?
>> WELL, THERE IS A DIVIDE, BUT
I HAVE TO SAY THAT THE POLICE
ARE ABSOLUTELY MISTREATED AND
MISUNDERSTOOD AND IF THERE IS AN
INCIDENT, WHETHER IT'S AN
INCIDENT DONE PURPOSELY, WHICH
IS A HORROR, AND YOU SHOULD TAKE
VERY STRONG ACTION, OR IF IT IS
A MISTAKE, IT'S ON YOUR NEWS
CASTS ALL NIGHT, ALL WEEK, ALL
MONTH, AND IT NEVER ENDS.
THE POLICE IN THIS COUNTRY HAVE
DONE AN UNBELIEVABLE JOB OF
KEEPING LAW AND ORDER.
AND THEY'RE AFRAID FOR THEIR
JOBS.
THEY'RE AFRAID OF THE
MISTREATMENT THEY GET AND I'M
TELLING YOU THAT NOT ONLY, ME
SPEAKING, MINORITIES ALL OVER
THE COUNTRY, THEY RESPECT THE
POLICE OF THIS COUNTRY AND WE
HAVE TO GIVE THEM MORE RESPECT.
THEY CAN'T ACT.
THEY'RE AFRAID FOR LOSING THEIR
PENSION, THEIR JOB.
THEY DON'T KNOW WHAT TO DO.
AND I DEAL WITH THEM ALL THE
TIME.
WE HAVE TO GIVE CREATE RESPECT,
FAR GREATER THAN WE ARE RIGHT
NOW, TO OUR REALLY FANTASTIC
POLICE.
>> MR. RUMP, I DID ASK ABOUT
BRIDGING THE DIVIDE, THOUGH, AS
PRESIDENT.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO THE
AMERICAN FAMILIES WHO SAY, WE
HAVE SEEN EXCESSIVE FORCE?
>> WELL, THEY DO.
AND THEY SUE.
EVERYBODYSUES, RIGHT?
WE HAVE SO MUCH LITIGATION.
I SEE THE COURTS, I SEE WHAT
THEY'RE DOING.
THEY SUE, AND, YOU KNOW WHAT?
WE DON'T WANT EXCESSIVE FORCE,
BUT AT WHAT POINT?
YOU KNOW, EITHER YOU ARE GOING
TO HAVE A POLICE FORCE THAT CAN
DO ITS JOB -- I WAS JUST UP IN
MANCHESTER, I MET WITH THE
POLICE OFFICERS YESTERDAY,
TREMENDOUS PEOPLE.
THEY LOVE THE AREA.
THEY LOVE THE PEOPLE.
THEY LOVE ALL THE PEOPLE.
THEY WANT TO DO THEIR JOB.
AND YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE ABUSE
AND YOU'RE GOING TO HAVE
PROBLEMS AND YOU HAVE TO SOLVE
THE PROBLEMS AND YOU HAVE TO
WEED OUT THE PROBLEMS.
BUT THE POLICE IN THIS COUNTRY
ARE ABSOLUTELY AMAZING PEOPLE.
>> I WANT TO ASK --
>> GOVERNOR KASICH?
>> I WANTED TO SAY, THERE CAN BE
A WIN-ONE HERE.
I HAVE FORMED A COLLABORATIVE
BETWEEN POLICE AND COMMUNITY
LEADERS.
BECAUSE PEOPLE HAVE TO RESPECT
LAW ENFORCEMENT.
THE FAMILY DIDN'T WANT DAD OR
MOM GOING HOME IN A BOX.
AND FOR OUR COMMUNITY LEADERS,
MANY OF THEM THINK THE SYSTEM
NOT ONLY WORKS -- NOT ONLY
DOESN'T WORK FOR THEM, BUT IT
WORKS AGAINST THEM.
AND I CREATED A BIG
COLLABORATIVE IN OHIO, MADE UP
OF LAW ENFORCEMENT, COMMUNITY
LEADERS, THE HEAD OF MY PUBLIC
SAFETY AND A FORMER DEMOCRAT,
LIBERAL SENATE SENATOR RUN IT.
THEY GOT TOGETHER, THEY MADE
RECOMMENDATIONS ON RECRUITING,
HIRING, THE USE OF DEADLY FORCE
AND WHAT WE'RE ABOUT TO DO IS TO
BRING COMMUNITY AND POLICE
TOGETHER SO WE CAN HAVE A
WIN-WIN.
WE NEED MORE WIN-WINS IN AMERICA
AND WE DON'T HAVE TO PICK ONE
OVER ANOTHER.
WE LOVE THE POLICE, BUT WE'VE
GOT TO BE RESPONSIBLE TO THE
PEOPLE IN THE COMMUNITY.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, I WANT TO ASK
YOU NEXT, PRESIDENT OBAMA
VISITED A MOSQUE THIS WEEK IN
AMERICA FOR THE FIRST TIME IN
HIS PRESIDENCY.
PRESIDENT GEORGE W. BUSH VISITED
A MOSQUE AFTER SEPTEMBER 11th.
YOU SAID OF PRESIDENT OBAMA,
QUOTE, HE IS ALWAYS PITTING
PEOPLE AGAINST EACH OTHER.
SO, I'M CURIOUS, HOW ARE THE TWO
VISITS DIFFERENT AND WOULD YOU
VISIT A MOSQUE AS PRESIDENT?
>> I WOULD.
BUT THAT'S NOT -- THE ISSUE --
MY PROBLEM WITH WHAT HE DID IS,
HE CONTINUES TO PUT OUT THIS
FICTION THAT THERE'S WIDESPREAD
DISCRIMINATION AGAINST MUSLIM
AMERICANS.
FIRST OF ALL, LET'S RECOGNIZE
THIS.
IF YOU GO TO A NATIONAL CEMETERY
IN THIS COUNTRY, YOU WILL SEE
STARS OF DAVIDS AND CROSSES, BUT
YOU SEE CRESCENT MOONS.
THERE ARE BRAVE MEN AND WOMEN
WHO HAPPEN TO BE MUSLIM
AMERICANS WHO ARE SERVING THIS
COUNTRY IN UNIFORM AND WHO HAVE
DIED IN THE SERVICE OF THIS
COUNTRY.
AND WE RECOGNIZE THAT AND WE
HONOR THAT.
BUT BY THE SAME TOKEN, WE FACE A
VERY SIGNIFICANT THREAT OF HOME
GROWN VIOLENT EXTREMISM.
WE NEED TO HAVE STRONG, POSITIVE
RELATIONSHIPS IN THE ISLAMIC
COMMUNITIES IN THIS COUNTRY SO
THEY CAN IDENTIFY AND REPORT
THIS ACTIVITY.
ESPECIALLY MOSQUES, FOR EXAMPLE,
THAT ARE PARTICIPATING NOT JUST
IN HATE SPEECH, BUT INCITING
VIOLENCE AND TAKING ACTS AGAINST
US.
I DO BELIEVE IT IS IMPORTANT TO
RECOGNIZE, YOU WANT TO TALK
ABOUT RELIGIOUS DISCRIMINATION
IN AMERICA.
I DON'T THINK BARACK OBAMA'S
BEING SUED BY ANY ISLAMIC
GROUPS, BUT HE IS BEING SUED BY
THE LITTLE SISTERS OF THE POOR.
WE HAVE FACING CHRISTIAN GROUPS,
TRADITIONAL VALUES WHO FEEL AND
IN FACT ARE BEING DISCRIMINATED
AGAINST THAT TRY TO FORCE THEM
TO VIE TO VIOLATE THEIR
CONSCIENCE.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU.
MARTHA?
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, EARLIER
THIS WEEK, THE WORLD HEALTH
ORGANIZATION DECLARED THE ZIKA
VIRUS A GLOBAL EMERGENCY.
THE SAME KIND OF MOSQUITOS THAT
CARRY THE ZIKA VIRUS IN LATIN
AMERICA ARE FOUND HERE IN THE
UNITED STATES.
AND THE VIRUS HAS BEEN LINKED TO
SEVERE BIRTH DEFECTS.
GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, AT THE PEAK
OF THE EBOLA OUTBREAK IN WEST
AFRICA, YOU ORDERED AN AMERICAN
NURSE WHO LANDED AT NEWARK
AIRPORT BE DETAINED AND
QUARANT
QUARANTINED.
AS FEAR SPREADS NOULT OF THE
ZIKA VIRUS AND THE RIO OLYMPICS
JUST MONTHS AWAY, IS THERE A
SCENARIO WHERE YOU WOULD
QUARANTINE PEOPLE TRAVELING BACK
FROM BRAZIL TO PREVENT THE
SPREAD IN THE UNITED STATES?
>> YOU BELT I WOULD.
AND THE FACT IS THAT BECAUSE I
TOOK STRONG ACTION TO MAKE SURE
THAT ANYONE WHO WAS SHOWING
SYMPTOMS -- REMEMBER WHAT
HAPPENED WITH THAT NURSE.
SHE WAS SHOWING SYMPTOMS AND
COMING BACK FROM A PLACE THAT
HAD THE EBOLA VIRUS ACTIVE AND
SHE HAD BEEN TREATING PATIENTS.
THIS WAS NOT JUST SOMEONE, WE
PICKED HER UP JUST FOR THE HECK
OF IT.
WE DID IT BECAUSE SHE WAS
SHOWING SYMPTOMS.
AND THE FACT IS, THAT'S HOW WE
SHOULD MAKE THESE DECISIONS.
YOU MAKE THE DECISIONS BASED
UPON THE SYMPTOMS, THE MEDICINE
AND THE LAW.
SHE TURNED OUT TO TEST NEGATIVE
AFTER 48 HOURS AND WE RELEASED
HER BACK TO THE STATE OF MAINE.
BUT I WANT TO ADD SOMETHING ON
THE ISSUE OF MOSQUES.
NOW, I'M THE ONLY ONE UP HERE
WHO HAS A LAW ENFORCEMENT
BACKGROUND AND WAS THE U.S.
ATTORNEY AFTER SEPTEMBER 11th.
I WENT TO MOSQUES TO BUILD
BRIDGES BETWEEN OUR COMMUNITY
AND LAW ENFORCEMENT TO GET
INTELLIGENCE AND INFORMATION
FROM THESE FOLKS.
I HAD THE EXPERIENCE OF WORKING
WITH THEM AS GOVERNOR OF NEW
JERSEY, AS WELL.
WE CANNOT MIX THE RADICAL
ISLAMIC JIHADIST WITH EVERY DAY
MUSLIM AMERICANS.
NEW JERSEY HAS THE
SECOND-LARGEST MUSLIM AMERICAN
POPULATION IN AMERICA, OF ANY
STATE.
THESE ARE GOOD, LAW-ABIDING,
HARD-WORKING PEOPLE.
WHAT THEY NEED IS OUR
COOPERATION AND OUR
UNDERSTANDING.
THEY DO NOT NEED JUST BROADSIDES
AGAINST THEM BECAUSE OF THEIR
RELIGIOUS FAITH.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, THANK YOU.
I'M GOING TO MOVE TO DR. CARSON
AND GO BACK TO THE ZIKA VIRUS.
IS THAT GOING TOO FAR,
QUARANTINING?
YOU ARE A DOCTOR.
WHAT WOULD YOU DO?
>> IT'S NOT A SIMPLE ISSUE.
AND NOW, YOU KNOW, WE'VE GOT
EVIDENCE THAT THERE CAN BE
ACTIVE VIRUSES IN OTHER BODILY
FLUIDS, LIKE IS A LSALIVA AND U.
THIS IS GOING TO BE A BIG DEAL,
OBVIOUSLY.
DO WE QUARANTINE PEOPLE, IF WE
HAVE EVIDENCE THAT THEY ARE
INFECTED AND THAT THERE IS
EVIDENCE THAT THAT INFECTION CAN
SPREAD BY SOMETHING THAT THEY'RE
DOING, YES.
BUT YOU KNOW, JUST WILLY NILLY
GOING OUT AND QUARANTINING
PEOPLE BECAUSE THEY WENT TO
BRAZIL, I DON'T BELIEVE THAT'S
GOING TO WORK.
WE REALLY NEED TO TALK ABOUT,
HOW DO WE GET THIS DISEASE UNDER
CONTROL?
AND THIS IS WHERE WE NEED RAPID
RESPONSE.
WE NEEDLED RAPID RESPED RAPID RR
EBOLA.
WE NEED IT FOR ZIKA.
OTHER THINGS WILL COME UP.
AND THESE ARE THE KINDS OF
THINGS THAT THE NIH, THE CDC,
CAN BE VERY EFFECTIVE AT.
WE NEED TO GIVE THEM THE
APPROPRIATE SUPPORT FOR THOSE
KINDS OF THINGS.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH, DR.
CARSON.
I WANT TO MOVE ONTO THE
MILITARY.
SENATOR RUBIO, ALL RESTRICTIONS
ON WOMEN IN COMBAT HAVE BEEN
LIFTED, AS LONG AS THEY QUALIFY,
TO SIX
POE S
POSITIONS LIKE NAVY S.E.A.L.s.
THE MILITARY LEADERS OF THE ARMY
AND MARINE CORPS SAID THEY
BELIEVE YOUNG WOMEN, JUST AS
YOUNG MEN ARE REQUIRED TO DO,
SHOULD SIGN UP FOR SELECTIVE
SERVICE IN CASE THE DRAFT IS
REINSTATED.
MANY OF YOU HAVE YOUNG
DAUGHTERS.
SENATOR RUBIO, SHOULD YOUNG
WOMEN BE REQUIRED TO SIGN UP FOR
SELECTIVE SERVICE IN CASE OF A
NATIONAL EMERGENCY?
>> WELL, FIRST, LET ME SAY,
THERE ARE WOMEN TODAY SERVING IN
ROLES THAT ARE LIKE COMBAT,
THAT, WHOSE LIVES ARE IN VERY
SERIOUS DANGER.
SO, I HAVE NO PROBLEM WHATSOEVER
WITH PEOPLE OF EITHER GENDER
SERVING IN COMBAT, SO LONG AS
THE MINIMUM REQUIREMENTS ARE NOT
COMPROMISED.
BUT I SUPPORT THAT.
AND NOW THAT THAT IS THE CASE, I
DO BELIEVE THAT SELECTIVE
SERVICE SHOULD BE OPENED UP FOR
BOTH MEN AND WOMEN IN CASE A
DRAFT IS EVER INSTITUTED.
I THINK THE MORE FUNDAMENTAL
CHALLENGE IS WHAT'S HAPPENING TO
THE U.S. MILITARY.
IT'S IMPORTANT TO START PAYING
ATTENTION TO THIS.
OUR AIR FORCE IS ABOUT TO BE THE
SMALLEST IT'S BEEN IN OUR
HISTORY.
THE ARMY IS SET TO BE SMALLER
THAN IT'S BEEN SINCE THE SECOND
WORLD WAR.
AND OUR NAVY IS ABOUT TO BE THE
SMALLEST THAT IT'S BEEN IN 100
YEARS.
WE NEED TO BEGIN TO REFOCUS ON
REBUILDING OUR MILITARY.
EVERY TIME WE HAVE CUT OUR
MILITARY, WE HAVE HAD TO COME
BACK LATER AND REBUILD IT, IT
COSTS MORE, IT'S A LOT MORE
CHAOTIC AND DANGEROUS.
WHEN I'M PRESIDENT, WE ARE
REBUILDING THE U.S. MILITARY.
>> THANK YOU, SENATOR RUBIO.
GOVERNOR BUSH, DO YOU BELIEVE
YOUNG WOMEN SHOULD SIGN UP FOR
SELECTIVE SERVICE, BE REQUIRED
TO DO SO --
>> I DO, I DO.
AND WE SHOULD NOT IMPOSE ANY
KIND OF POLITICAL AGENDA ON THE
MILITARY.
THERE SHOULD BE, IF WOMEN CAN
MEET THE REQUIREMENTS, THE
MINIMUM REQUIREMENTS FOR COMBAT
SERVICE, THEY OUGHT TO HAVE THE
RIGHT TO DO IT, FOR SURE.
IT OUGHT TO BE FOCUSED ON THE
MORALE, AS WELL.
WE HAVE TO MAKE SURE WE HAVE
READINESS.
WE NEED TO ELIMINATE THE
SEQUESTER, WHICH IS DEVASTATING
OUR MILITARY.
WE CAN'T BE FOCUSING ON THE
POLITICAL SIDE OF THIS.
WE NEED TO REALIZE THE MILITARY
FORCE IS HOW WE PROJECT OUR WORD
IN THE WORLD.
WHEN WE ARE WEAK, MILITARILY,
DOESN'T MATTER WHAT WE SAY.
WE CAN TALK ABOUT RED LINES AND
ISIS BEING THE JV TEAM AND RESET
BUTTONS AND ALL THIS.
IF WE DON'T HAVE A STRONG
MILITARY, THEN NO ONE FEARS US
AND THEY TAKE ACTIONS THAT ARE
AGAINST OUR NATIONAL INTERESTS.
>> TELL ME WHAT YOU'D SAY TO
AMERICAN PEOPLE OUT THERE WHO
ARE SITTING AT HOME, WHO HAVE
DAUGHTERS, WHO MIGHT WORRY ABOUT
THOSE ANSWERS AND MIGHT --
>> WHY WOULD THEY WORRY?
>> THE DRAFT IS REINSTITUTED.
>> IT'S NOT GOING TO BE, BUT IF
WOMEN --
>> DO YOU JUST DO AWAY WITH
THAT?
>> NO.
YOU ASKED THE QUESTION, NOT
ABOUT THE DRAFT.
YOU ASKED ABOUT REGISTERING.
IF WOMEN --
>> YOU REGISTER FOR THE DRAFT.
IF IT'S --
>> I'M NOT SUGGESTING WE HAVE A
DRAFT.
WHAT I'M SUGGESTING IS THAT WE
OUGHT TO HAVE READINESS BEING
THE FIRST PRIORITY OF OUR
MILITARY, AND SECONDLY, THAT WE
MAKE SURE THAT THE MORALE IS
HIGH.
AND RIGHT NOW, NEITHER ONE OF
THOSE ARE ACCEPTABLE, BECAUSE
WE'VE BEEN GUTTING THE MILITARY
BUDGET.
WE ALSO NEED TO REFORM OUR
PROCUREMENT PROCESS.
WE NEED TO MAKE SURE THERE ARE
MORE MEN AND WOMEN IN UNIFORM
THAN CIVILIANS IN OUR DEFENSE
DEPARTMENT.
THERE ARE A LOT OF THINGS WE
NEED TO REFORM TO BRING OUR
DEFENSE CAPABILITIES INTO THE
21st CENTURY.
I CAN DO THAT.
THAT'S WHY I HAVE THE SUPPORT OF
GENERALS, OF ADMIRALS, OF 12
MEDAL OF HONOR RECIPIENTS AND
PEOPLE KNOW THAT I WOULD BE A
STEADY COMMANDER IN CHIEF AND
REBUILD OUR MILITARY.
>> MARTHA?
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> CAN I BE REALLY CLEAR ON
THIS, BECAUSE I AM THE FATHER OF
TWO DAUGHTERS.
ONE OF THEM IS HERE TONIGHT.
WHAT MY WIFE AND I HAVE TAUGHT
OUR DAUGHTERS RIGHT FROM THE
BEGINNING, THAT THEIR SENSE OF
SELF-WORTH, THEIR SENSE OF
VALUE, THEIR SENSE OF WHAT THEY
WANT TO DO FROM LIFE COMES NOT
FROM THE OUTSIDE, BUT COMES FROM
WITHIN.
AND IF A YOUNG WOMAN IN THIS
COUNTRY WANTS TO GO AND FIGHT TO
DEFEND THEIR COUNTRY, SHE SHOULD
BE PERMITTED TO DO SO.
PART OF THAT NEEDS TO BE PART OF
A GREATER EFFORT IN THIS COUNTRY
NO REASON WHY WOMEN SHOULD BE
DISCRIMINATED AGAINST FOR
REGISTERING FOR THE SELECTIVE
SERVICE.
THE FACT IS, WE NEED TO BE A
PARTY AND A PEOPLE THAT MAKES
SURE THAT OUR WOMEN IN THIS
COUNTRY UNDERSTAND ANYTHING THEY
CAN DREAM, ANYTHING THAT THEY
WANT TO ASPIRE TO, THEY CAN DO.
THAT'S THE WAY WE RAISE OUR
DAUGHTERS.
THAT'S WHAT WE SHOULD ASPIRE TO.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE -- ONE
SECOND, DR. CARSON.
>> SOMETHING ABOUT THE DRAFT.
VERY QUICKLY.
>> VERY QUICKLY.
>> YOU KNOW, 14% DECREASE IN THE
NUMBER OF PEOPLE APPLYING FOR
VOLUNTARY MILITARY SERVICE, AND
I THINK PART OF IT IS BECAUSE OF
THE WAY WE TREAT OUR VETERANS.
YOU KNOW, WE WOULDN'T BE A FREE
COUNTRY IF IT WASN'T FOR THEM.
AND WE HAVE 22 VETERANS PER DAY
COMMITTING SUICIDE.
SO, I THINK WHAT WE SHOULD DO IS
HAVE AN EXTERNAL SUPPORT SYSTEM
FOR PEOPLE ONCE THEY VOLUNTEER
AND IT SHOULD FOLLOW THEM
THROUGHOUT THEIR CAREER.
SHOULD FOLLOW THEM FOR THREE
YEARS, FIVE YEARS AFTERWARDS, A
YEAR BEFORE THEY GET OUT, SHOULD
BE WORKING ON INTEGRATING THEM
BACK INTO SOCIETY, SO THAT THEY
QUIT ON FRIDAY AND THEY START
THEIR NEW JOB, THEY SHOULD HAVE
HEALTH EMPOWERMENT ACCOUNTS THAT
ARE SUBSIDIZED SO THEY CAN GO TO
ANY MEDICAL FACILITY AND BE
TAKEN CARE OF.
THEY CAN GO TO A V.A. IF THEY
WANT TO.
IF WE TAKE CAROL OF OUR VETERANS
THE RIGHT WAY, WE WON'T HAVE TO
EVER WORRY ABOUT A DRAFT AGAIN.
>> THANK YOU VERY MUCH FOR
BRINGING UP THAT SUBJECT, DR.
CARSON, OF OUR VETERANS AND FOR
ANOTHER QUESTION ABOUT OUR
VETERANS, WE GO BACK TO JOSH
FROM WMUR.
JOSH?
>> THANK YOU, MARTHA.
NONE OF YOU ON STAGE TONIGHT
HAVE EVER WORN A UNIFORM AS A
MEMBER OF THE ARMED SERVICES,
THAT'S THE REALITY OF IT.
AS COMMANDER IN CHEECIEF, YOU A
CHARGED WITH THE CARE OF
VETERANS IN THIS COUNTRY.
SOME HAVE SUGGESTED PRIVATIZING
THE V.A. IS A WAY TO ENHANCE
CARE AND INCREASE THE QUALITY OF
THE CARE.
AND ACCESS.
OTHERS SAY THAT VETERANS SHOULD
CARRY I.D. CARDS, ALLOW THEM
ACCESS TO ANY HOSPITAL OF HEALTH
CARE PROVIDER.
GOVERNOR BUSH, WHAT SPECIFICALLY
WOULD YOU DO TO ENSURE THOSE WHO
HAVE SACRIFICED FOR US ARE CARED
FOR?
>> I TOTALLY AGREE THAT WE NEED
TO GIVE VETERANS MORE CHOICES.
VETERANS CARD TO BE ABLE TO GO
TO A PRIVATE PROVIDER WILL
ENHANCE THE QUALITY OF THE
SERVICE INSIDE THE DEPARTMENT OF
VETERANS AFFAIRS.
WE NEED CAREER SEVERAL SERVICE
REFORM.
ONLY THREE PEOPLE WERE FIRED
AFTER A WAITING LIST WERE
DROPPED WHERE VETERANS DIDN'T
GET CARE AND PEOPLE DIED.
IT IS OUTRAGEOUS.
AND HILLARY CLINTON SAYS THAT
THAT'S ACCEPTABLE?
BECAUSE SHE IS CAPTIVE OF THE
PUBLIC SERVICE UNIFORMS.
THE NEXT PRESIDENT COULD FIRE
PEOPLE THAT ARE SHOWING SHEER
INCOMPETE
INCOMPETENCE.
SOMEONE TOLD THE STORY OF THEIR
FATHER WHO LOOKED LIKE HE WAS
85, HE GOT A BILL EIGHT YEARS
LATER FROM AN OPERATION HE HAD,
EIGHT YEARS, IT TOOK, THEY
COULDN'T RESOLVE THE DISPUTE AND
THEN HE WAS TOLD THAT HE DIED.
LITERALLY, THE VETERANS
ADMINISTRATION SENT A DEATH
CERTIFICATE TO THIS GUY.
AND IT TOOK NINE MONTHS TO
CLARIFY THE GUY -- I MET HIM.
HE'S VOTING FOR ME.
AND HE IS -- LIKELY TO BE ALIVE.
THIS IS -- THIS IS OUTRAGEOUS.
IT IS COMPLETELY OUTRAGEOUS.
SO, GIVING VETERANS MORE
CHOICES.
CREATING CENTERS OF
FOCUSES ON THE TRUE PROBLEMS
THAT EXIST.
DR. CARSON IS RIGHT.
WE NEED TO FOCUS ON THIS
EARLIER, BEFORE THEY BECOME
VETERANS SO THERE'S A CUSTOMIZED
PLAN SO PEOPLE DON'T FALL F
THROUGH THE CRACKS.
WE CAN DO THIS.
>> GOVERNOR KASICH, DO YOU HAVE
A FAVORED APPROACH?
>> JOSH, I MEAN, CLEARLY, WHEN A
VETERAN COMES HOME, THEY SHOULD
GET HEALTH CARE ANYWHERE THEY
WANT TO GO.
IN OUR STATE, WHICH IS WHAT WE
SHOULD DO IN THE COUNTRY, YOU
KNOW, IF THEY DRIVE A TRUCK FROM
KABUL TO KANDAHAR IN
AFGHANISTAN, WE SAY, YOU CAN
DRIVE A TRUCK FROM COLUMBUS TO
CLEVELAND AND WE DON'T HAVE TO
GO GET A LICENSE.
WE'RE GOING TO HAND YOU ONE.
AND IF YOU GOT EXPERTISE IN THE
MILITARY, WE'RE GOING TO GIVE
YOU COLLEGE CREDIT OR COMMUNITY
COLLEGE CREDIT FOR THE THINGS
THAT YOU DID FOR OUR COUNTRY.
AND IN ADDITION TO THAT, I'LL
TELL YOU, ONE OF THE BIGGEST
THINGS I THINK HAS TO BE DONE
AND I WOULD DO IT AS PRESIDENT,
THE PENTAGON HAS GOT TO WORK
WITH THE RETURNING SOLDIER,
SAILOR, ALONG WITH THE FAMILY,
AND THEY'RE THE MOST VALUABLE
EMPLOYEES IN THE COUNTRY.
I CALL THEM GOLDEN EMPLOYEES.
EVERYBODY WANTS TO HIRE A
VETERAN.
BUT THERE IS A DISCONNECT
BETWEEN THE JOB OPENINGS AND THE
VETERAN WHEN THE VETERAN COMES
BACK.
THE VETERAN IS A LEADER.
THE VETERAN IS STRONG.
THE VETERAN IS DRUG FREE.
THERE SHOULD BE NO UNEMPLOYMENT
AMONG VETERANS.
IF THE PENTAGON WILL WORK WITH
THE VETERAN SERVICES AGENCIES
ACROSS THIS COUNTRY, JOSH, WE
CAN GET PEOPLE JOBS AND WE CAN
GET THEM JOBS QUICKLY, GET
HEALTH CARE, COLLEGE EDUCATION.
LET'S LIFT THEM.
THEY'RE THE GREATEST PEOPLE
DEFENDING THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA AND WE NEED TO TAKE CARE
OF THEM AND WE WILL.
WE WILL.
>> SENATOR RUBIO?
>> WELL, MY BROTHER'S A VETERAN.
WE'RE VERY PROUD OF HIM IN OUR
FAMILY.
HE SERVED AS A GREEN BERET FROM
1968 THROUGH 1971.
AND AS PART OF HIS TRAINING HE
JUMPED OUT OF AN AIRPLANE AND HE
LOST HIS TWO FRONT TEETH.
FOR YEARS HE HAS DENTAL CLAIMS.
WHEN HE GOES TO GET ONE FILLED,
THE V.A. SAYS, HOW DO WE KNOW
YOU LOST YOUR TEETH IN THE ARMY?
HE SAID, WELL, IT'S THE ONLY
TIME I'VE JUMPED OUT OF A PLANE.
I WORKED IN A BIPARTISAN WAY, WE
PASSED A V.A. ACCOUNTABILITY
BILL THAT FOR THE FIRST TIME
ALLOWS US TO FIRE, ALLOWS THE
V.A. SECRETARY TO FIRE SOMEONE
WHO IS NOT DOING A GOOD JOB, WHO
IS A SENIOR EXECUTIVE.
AND THE GOVERNOR'S RIGHT.
THEY HAVE ONLY FIRED THREE
PEOPLE UP UNTIL NOW.
MORE PEOPLE WILL BE FIRED IF I'M
PRESIDENT.
BUT THE PORTABILITY PART OF IT
IS INCREDIBLY IMPORTANT.
VETERANS SHOULD BE ABLE TO TAKE
THEIR BENEFITS TO ANY HOSPITAL
OR DOCTOR THEY WANT TO GO TO.
WHEN I AM PRESIDENT OF THE
UNITED STATES, VETERANS WILL BE
ABLE TO TAKE THEIR BENEFITS TO
ANY HOSPITAL OR DOCTOR THAT THEY
CHOOSE.
>> SENATOR RUBIO, THANK YOU VERY
MUCH.
GOT TO MOVE FORWARD NOW.
DAVID, MARTHA, BACK TO YOU.
>> JOSH, THANK YOU.
I WANT TO TURN TO A FAMILY THAT
NEW HAMPSHIRE VOTERS KNOW QUITE
WELL, AND SENATOR CRUZ, THE
ISSUE OF HOSTAGES HAS BEEN A
VERY REAL AND PAINFUL ONE HERE
IN THIS STATE.
AS WE ALL KNOW, JAMES FOLEY WAS
KILLED, HIS MOTHER SAID OUR
GOVERNMENT SHOULD BE WILLING TO
NEGOTIATE.
ARGUING THAT FAMILIES SHOULD BE
ALLOWED TO RAISE MONEY FOR
RANSOM.
WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO DIANE
FOLEY TONIGHT?
SHOULD FAMILIES BE ALLOWED TO
RAISE MONEY FOR RANSOM FOR THEIR
LOVED ONES?
>> WELL, I RECOGNIZE IT IS AN
AGONIZING EXPERIENCE WHEN ANYONE
IS FACING A LOVED MEMBER WHO HAS
BEEN KIDNAPPED, BUT AT THE SAME
TIME, PUTTING IN PLACE LEGAL
REGIMES THAT ENCOURAGE THE
PAYMENT OF RANSOM HAS THE AFFECT
OF PUTTING A BOUNTY ON OTHER
AMERICANS.
THERE IS A REASON IT HAS BEEN
LONG-STANDING U.S. POLICY THAT
WE DON'T NEGOTIATE WITH
TERRORISTS, WE DON'T PAY
RANSOMS.
IF YOU LOOK AT WHAT PRESIDENT
OBAMA HAS DONE OVER AND OVER
AGAIN, WHETHER IT WAS THE JAMES
BERGDAHL DEAL THAT WAS
ABSOLUTELY SHAMEFUL, RELEASING
FIVE SENIOR TALIBAN TERRORISTS
TO BRING BERGDAHL BACK.
OR IF IT WAS THIS RECENT DEAL
WITH IRAN, WHERE, AGAIN, UP TO
21 TERRORISTS OR POTENTIAL
TERRORISTS WERE RELEASED OR NOT
PROSECUTED IN ORDER TO BRING
BACK FOUR AMERICANS, WHAT THAT
DOES IS, IT EFFECTIVELY PUTS A
BOUNTY ON AMERICAN SERVICEMEN
AND WOMEN SERVING ABOARD, ON
AMERICAN TOURISTS TRAVELING
ABOARD, AND THE PROPER APPROACH
IS A PRESIDENT AND COMMANDER IN
CHIEF THAT DEFENDS THIS COUNTRY
AND THAT GOES AFTER -- GOES
AFTER THE TERRORISTS RATHER THAN
SHOWING THEM WEAKNESS AND
ENCOURAGING THEM TO TARGET MORE
AMERICANS.
>> SENATOR CRUZ, THANK YOU.
MR. TRUMP, WHAT WOULD YOU SAY TO
DIANE FOLEY?
SHOULD FAMILIES BE ALLOWED TO
RAISE MONEY FOR RANSOM?
>> WELL, I KNOW DIANE VERY WELL.
HER HUSBAND AND -- THESE ARE
TREMENDOUS PEOPLE.
I SPOKE FOR THEM, I RAISED A LOT
OF MONEY FOR THE FOUNDATION.
I FULLY UNDERSTAND JAMES, ONE
OF -- THAT WAS REALLY THE FIRST
THAT WE SAW, REALLY VISUALLY
SAW, IT WAS SO HORRIBLE, AND I
WILL TELL YOU, WITH ALL OF THAT
BEING SAID, YOU CAN NOT
NEGOTIATE THIS WAY WITH
TERRORISTS.
IF YOU DO, YOU ARE GOING TO HAVE
MANY, MANY MORE JAMES FOLEYS.
JAMES WAS A GREAT YOUNG MAN.
HIS PARENTS ARE INCREDIBLE
PEOPLE.
THEY'VE DONE SUCH A GOOD JOB,
SINCE HIS DEATH, BUT YOU JUST
CANNOT NEGOTIATE THAT WAY WITH
TERRORISTS, OR YOU ARE GOING TO
HAVE SO MANY OTHER JAMES FOLEYS.
AND ONE THING ON THE VETS,
DURING THE LAST DEBATE, I RAISED
$6 MILLION FOR THE VETS AND I
WILL TELL YOU SOMETHING -- I
WILL TELL YOU THAT I THINK
NOBODY HERE, NOBODY ON THIS
STAGE, GETS ALONG WITH THE
VETERANS GROUPS IN NEW HAMPSHIRE
BETTER THAN I DO, WITH ALL OF
THE PEOPLE THAT I DEAL WITH, AND
THESE ARE GREAT PEOPLE.
THE ONE THING THAT WE'RE NOT
MENTIONING, THERE'S TREMENDOUS
FRAUD, WASTE AND ABUSE IN THE
VETERANS ADMINISTRATION AND IF
I'M RUNNING THINGS, THAT'S GOING
TO DISAPPEAR AND IT'S GOING TO
DISAPPEAR QUICKLY.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
WE WANT TO TURN NOW TO SOCIAL
ISSUES, AND YOUNG VOTERS AND FOR
THE QUESTION FROM MARY
KATHERINE.
>> THANK YOU, DAVID.
SENATOR RUBIO.
ONE OF THE LAZIER PIECES OF
POLITICAL CONVENTIONAL WISDOM IS
THAT SO-CALLED SOCIAL ISSUES ARE
HURTING REPUBLICANS WITH YOUNG
PEOPLE.
BUT ON THE TWO-MOST PROMINENT
SOCIAL ISSUES, POLLING WITH
MILLENNIALS MOVES IN DIFFERENT
DIRECTIONS.
ON ONE HAND, IT IS CLEAR, YOUNG
PEOPLE ACROSS THE POLITICAL
SPECTRUM FAVOR SAME SEX
MARRIAGE.
YOUNG VOTERS HAVE NOT MOVED TO
THE LEFT ON ABORTION.
IN FACT, LARGE NUMBERS OF THEM
FAVOR AT LEAST SOME MODEST
RESTRICTIONS THAT CONSERVATIVES
HAVE SUPPORTED.
HOW DO YOU SPEAK TO MILLENNIALS
ON BOTH THESE ISSUES WHILE
DEMOCRATS WILL CHARGE
INTOLERANCE AND EXTREMISM?
>> WELL, FIRST OF ALL, I DON'T
BELIEVE THAT BELIEVING IN
TRADITIONAL MARRIAGE THE WAY I
DO MAKES YOU A BIG GOT ON A
HATER.
IT MEANS THAT YOU BELIEVE THAT
THIS INSTITUTION THAT'S BEEN
AROUND FOR MILL LEN YA IS AN
IMPORTANT CORNERSTONE OF
SOCIETY.
I BELIEVE, DEEPLY, THAT MARRIAGE
SHOULD BE BETWEEN ONE MAN AND
ONE WOMAN.
ON THE ISSUE OF LIFE, TO ME, THE
ISSUE OF LIFE IS NOT A POLITICAL
ISSUE.
IT'S A HUMAN RIGHTS ISSUE.
IT PUTS IN CONFLICT TWO
COMPETING RIGHTS.
ON THE ONE HAND IS THE RIGHT OF
A WOMAN TO CHOOSE WHAT TO DO
WITH HER BODY, WHICH IS A REAL
RIGHT.
AND ON THE OTHER HAND IS THE
RIGHT OF AN UNBORN HUMAN CHILD
TO LIVE.
AND THEY'RE IN CONFLICT.
AS A POLLY MIPOLICYMAKER, I MUS.
I HAVE CHOOSEN TO ERR ON THE
SIDE OF LIFE.
HERE'S WHAT I FIND OUTRAGEOUS.
FIVE DEMOCRATIC DEBATES.
THE MEDIA HAS NOT ASKED THEM A
SINGLE QUESTION ON ABORTION AND
THE DEMOCRATS ARE EXTREMISTS.
WHY DOESN'T THE MEDIA ASK
HILLARY CLINTON WHY SHE BELIEVES
ALL ABORTION SHOULD BE ILLEGAL
WHY DOES SHE BELIEVE THAT
PARTIAL BIRTH ABORTION, WHICH
HAS BEEN OUTLAWED IN THIS
COUNTRY, SHE THINKS THAT'S A
RIGHT.
THEY ARE THE EXTREMISTS WHEN IT
COMES TO THE ISSUE OF ABORTION
AND I CAN'T WAIT TO EXPOSE THEM
IN A GENERAL ELECTION.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH?
I WANT TO COME TO YOU.
YOUR ALLIES HAVE ATTACKED
SENATOR RUBIO FOR BEING TOO PRO
LIFE TO BE ELECTED IN NOVEMBER.
YOU MADE A SIMILAR CHARGE IN AN
INTERVIEW.
THIS IS A PRO LIFE PARTY.
DO YOU STAND BEHIND THAT
CRITICISM?
>> I'M PRO LIFE.
ON THIS STAGE, I'M THE MOST PRO
LIFE PERSON BECAUSE I ACTED ON
IT FOR EIGHT YEARS IN THE STATE
OF FLORIDA.
WHERE WE ABOLISHED PARTIAL BIRTH
ABORTION, WHERE PARENTS HAVE THE
RIGHT TO BE NOTIFIED WHEN THEIR
TEENAGE CHILD IS HAVING AN
ABORTION.
WE WERE THE FIRST STATE TO DO A
CHOOSE LIFE LICENSE PLATE.
WE WERE THE FIRST STATE TO HAVE
STATE MONEYS GO TO CRISIS
PREGNANCY CENTERS, WHICH
RECENTLY WAS JUST INCREASED TO
$4 MILLION A YEAR.
WE CREATED GREATER REGULATION ON
ABORTION CLINICS, WHERE THERE
WERE HORRIFIC PROCEDURES.
I'M PRO LIFE.
BUT I BELIEVE THERE SHOULD BE
EXCEPTIONS.
RAPE, INCEST AND WHEN THE LIFE
OF THE MOTHER IS IN DANGER.
AND SO, THAT -- THAT BELIEF, AND
MY CONSISTENCY ON THIS, MAKES
ME, I THINK, POISED TO BE IN THE
RIGHT PLACE, THE SWEET SPOT FOR
REPUBLICAN NOMINEE.
AND OTHERS MAY HAVE A DIFFERENT
VIEW AND I RESPECT IT.
BUT I THINK WE HAVE TO BE
COGNIZANT OF THE FACT, THERE'S A
LOT OF PEOPLE THAT ARE CONCERNED
ABOUT HAVING A PRO LIFE POSITION
WITHOUT ANY EXCEPTIONS.
>> I DO SUPPORT -- I JUST
BELIEVE DEEPLY THAT ALL HUMAN
LIFE IS WORTHY OF PROTECTION.
IF I'M PRESIDENT, THERE'S A BILL
THAT'S PASSED THAT SAVES LIVES
BUT THERE'S EXCEPTION, I'LL SIGN
IT.
I BELIEVE THAT ALL HUMAN LIFE IS
WORTHY OF PROTECTION.
THE ISSUE OF LIFE IS NOT A
POLITICAL ISSUE.
I WANT TO BE FRANK.
I WOULD RATHER LOSE AN ELECTION
THAN BE WRONG ON THE ISSUE OF
LIFE.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
YOU, TOO, HAVE TALKED ABOUT
SENATOR RUBIO'S POSITION ON THE
LIFE ISSUE.
SOME CONSERVATIVE ACTIVISTS HAVE
CALLED THIS LINE OF ATTACK
HARMFUL TO THE PRO LIFE CAUSE.
>> I'VE BEEN PRETTY HELPFUL TO
THE PRO LIFE CAUSE IN ONE OF THE
MOST PRO-CHOICE STATES IN THE
U
UNION.
WE DEFENDED PLANNED PARENTHOOD.
FOR SIX YEARS AS GOVERNOR,
PLANNED PARENTHOOD DOES NOT
RECEIVE THE MONEY.
$50 MILLION IS NOT GOING TO DO
EXACTLY WHAT HILLARY CLINTON
WANTS TO HAVE DONE, HAS
ADVOCATED FOR.
SHE BELIEVES THAT ORGANIZATION,
WHICH ENGAGES IN THE MURDER OF
CHILDREN IN THE WOMB, IN ORDER
TO MAXIMIZE THE VALUE OF THEIR
BODY PARTS FOR SALE ON THE OPEN
MARKET, IS AN ACCEPTABLE
POSITION.
I DON'T CARE IF YOU ARE A
MILLENNIAL OR IN YOUR 90s, NO
ONE IS FOR THAT TYPE OF
ACTIVITY, UNLESS YOU ARE THE
MOST RADICAL TYPE OF EXTREMIST
ON THIS ISSUE, LIKE SENATOR
CLINTON AND HER PARTY IS ON THIS
ISSUE.
I'LL SAY ONE OTHER THING.
FACT IS, THAT I BELIEVE THAT IF
A WOMAN HAS BEEN RAPED, THAT IS
A PREGNANCY THAT SHE SHOULD BE
ABLE TO TERMINATE.
IF SHE IS THE VICTIM OF UNZESIN
THIS IS NOT A WOMAN'S CHOICE.
THIS IS A WOMAN BEING VIOLATED.
THE FACT IS, WE HAVE ALWAYS HAS
BELIEVED, AS HAS RONALD REAGAN,
THAT WE HAVE SELF-DEFENSE FOR
WOMEN WHO HAVE BEEN RAPED AND
IMPREGNATED BECAUSE OF IT OR THE
SUBJECT OF INCEST AND BEEN
IMPREGNATED FOR IT.
THAT WOMAN SHOULD NOT HAVE TO
DELIVER THAT CHILD IF THEY
BELIEVE THAT VIOLATION IS NOW AN
ACT OF SELF-DEFENSE BY TERM
NAFTING THAT PREGNANCY.
>> THANK YOU, ALL.
BACK TO YOU, DAVID AND MARTHA.
>> MARY KATHERINE, THANK YOU.
WE'RE GOING TO HAVE CLOSING
STATEMENTS IN A MOMENT, BUT A
QUICK LIGHTNING ROUND.
COME NOVEMBER, TWO BATTLEGROUND
STATES, BUT FACE OFF TOMORROW IN
THE SUPER BOWL.
GOVERNOR KASICH, WHO WINS?
>> OH.
CAROLINA'S GOING TO WIN THAT
ONE.
I HATE TO SAY IT.
THEY'RE GOING TO WIN THAT ONE.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH?
>> PEYTON MANNING IS SUPPORTING
ME.
I'M FOR DENVER.
>> NOR RUBIO?
>> WELL, I WAS GOING FOR PEYTON
MANNING, BUT NOW I'M ROOTING FOR
CAROLINA.
>> MR. TRUMP?
>> CAROLINA.
>> WITH AN EYE TO FEBRUARY 20th,
CAROLINA.
>> ALL RIGHT, DR. CARSON?
>> WITH 100% CERTAINLY, I WILL
PREDICT THE WINNER, IT WILL
EITHER BE DENVER OR CAROLINA.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE, THE LAST
WORD?
>> DENVER.
THANK YOU SO MUCH, GENTLEMEN.
CLOSING STATEMENTS IN JUST A
MOMENT, RIGHT HERE, AS THE ABC
NEWS REPUBLICAN DEBATE CONTINUES
FROM NEW HAMPSHIRE RIGHT AFTER
THIS.
>>> THERE YOU SEE, THE TOP
ISSUES OF FACEBOOK TONIGHT.
IMMIGRATION, ISIS, THE ECONOMY,
HEALTH CARE, SIZE OF GOVERNMENT.
HERE WITH JON KARL.
WE SAW THE CANDIDATES TALKED
ABOUT MOST, DONALD TRUMP, MARCO
RUBIO.
NOT SURPRISING WHEN YOU LOOK AT
THE ISSUES.
THOSE ARE THE ISSUES THAT HAVE
BEEN ANIMATING THEM ALL THE WAY
THROUGH.
>> RIGHT THERE ON THE TOP, THE
NUMBER ONE ISSUE DISCUSSED ON
SOCIAL MEDIA, IMMIGRATION.
WE'VE SEEN DEBATES WHERE
IMMIGRATION DOMINATED MORE THAN
IT HAS HERE, BUT EVEN SO, THAT
IS THE ISSUE THAT IS RESONATING
WITH THIS REPUBLICAN ELECTORATE.
>> THE FIRST ISSUE THAT DONALD
TRUMP TALKED ABOUT RIGHT OUT OF
THE BOX TONIGHT, AS WELL.
HE IS THE MOST SEARCHED
CANDIDATE TONIGHT.
IN EVERY STATE EXPECT NEW
HAMPSHIRE, WHERE MORE PEOPLE ARE
SEARCHING FOR MARCO RUBIO.
>> IT IS INTERESTING THAT NONE
OF THE ISSUES PERTAIN TO WHAT
WAS RUBIO'S TOUGH START IN THIS,
THE QUESTION OF BARACK OBAMA AND
BARACK OBAMA KNOW WHAT HE'S
DOING.
THAT DIDN'T SEEM TO BE --
>> AND THE QUESTION IS, THE
VOTERS LOVE TO SEE HIM
BASHING -- REPUBLICAN VOTERS
LOVE TO SEE HIM BUASHING THE
UNITED STATES.
>> HE DID THAT OVER AND OVER AND
OVER AGAIN.
>> HE DID.
CLOSING STATEMENTS COMING UP.
WE'LL BE RIGHT BACK.
>>> ABC NEWS COVERAGE OF THE NEW
HAMPSHIRE REPUBLICAN DEBATE WILL
CONTINUE IN A MOMENT.
>>> LIVE FROM ST. ANSELM COLLEGE
IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, HERE AGAIN ARE
DAVID MUIR AND MARTHA RADDATZ.
>> WE WELCOME YOU BACK TO NEW
HAMPSHIRE PRIMARY, OF COURSE, IS
TUESDAY.
BUT TIME NOW FOR CLOSING
STATEMENTS.
AND WE BEGIN TONIGHT WITH
GOVERNOR KASICH.
>> WELL, FOLK, I'VE DONE NOW
OVER 100 TOWN HALL MEETINGS AND
I'VE LOVED EVERY SECOND OF IT.
IT'S BEEN THE GREATEST THING IN
THE WORLD.
AND I WANT YOU TO KNOW THAT
YOU'VE CHANGED ME.
BECAUSE I'VE LISTENED TO YOUR
STORIES AND I'VE HAD YOUR HUGS
AND I'VE SEEN YOUR TEARS.
AND I'VE SEEN YOU WALK AWAY AND
SAY, I NOW HAVE HOPE.
YOU KNOW, I'VE HAD A
CONSERVATIVE MESSAGE, BUT A
POSITIVE MESSAGE, NOT JUST A
POSITIVE MESSAGE ABOUT HOW WE
CAN BRING PEOPLE TOGETHER.
HOW WE CAN RESTORE AMERICA'S
STRENGTH, LIFT EVERYONE.
NEW HAMPSHIRE, PLEASE GIVE ME A
CHANCE TO CARRY THIS MESSAGE
FORWARD TO THE UNITED STATES OF
AMERICA.
AND THEN, I WILL COME BACK.
THANK YOU, LOVED IT.
AND GOD BLESS YOU.
>> GOVERNOR CHRISTIE.
>> THANK YOU.
I SPENT THE LAST 13 YEARS OF MY
LIFE FOCUSED ON ONE THING.
SERVING THE PEOPLE WHO HAVE
GIVEN ME THE OPPORTUNITY TO
SERVE THEM.
NOT ABOUT POLITICS.
NOT ABOUT PARTISANSHIP.
BUT PUTTING THE PEOPLE OF MY
STATE AND OUR COUNTRY FIRST.
I'M PROUD TO HAVE STOOD ON THE
FRONT LINES OF FIGHTING THE WAR
ON TERRORISM AFTER SEPTEMBER
11th.
I'M PROUD TO HAVE REBUILT MY
STATE AFTER HURRICANE SANDY.
AND I'M INCREDIBLY PROUD TO BE
ON THIS STAGE TONIGHT WITH THESE
MEN, ASKING FOR YOUR VOTE.
NEW HAMPSHIRE, I SPENT 70 DAYS
HERE WITH YOU.
YOU'VE GOTTEN TO KNOW MY HEART.
MY HEART IS TO HELP YOU SOLVE
THE PROBLEMS OF YOUR STATE AND
THE PROBLEMS OF OUR NATION.
IF YOU GIVE ME YOUR VOTE ON
TUESDAY, I WILL DO JUST THAT.
>> GOVERNOR BUSH?
>> I WANT TO THANK THE PEOPLE OF
NEW HAMPSHIRE AND I WANT TO
CELEBRATE THE BIRTHDAY OF A
GREAT PRESIDENT, RONALD REAGAN,
WOULD HAVE BEEN 105 TODAY.
AND PRESIDENT REAGAN BELIEVED IN
THE FUTURE OF OUR COUNTRY.
HAD A HOPEFUL MESSAGE.
DREW PEOPLE TOWARDS OUR CAUSE.
WE NEED SOMEONE WHO HAS A PROVEN
RECORD TO TAKE OUR CASE TO THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE.
BECAUSE OUR PHILOSOPHY IS, BY
FAR, THE BEST ONE, OF LIMITED
GOVERNMENT, OF ENTRPEACE THROUG
STRENGTH.
I BELIEVE I HAVE THE SKILLS TO
TAKE OUR PARTY TO VICTORY IN
NOVEMBER.
I ASK FOR YOUR SUPPORT ON
TUESDAY TO KEEP AMERICA AND MAKE
AMERICA, SAFER, STRONGER AND
FREER.
THANK YOU ALL VERY MUCH.
>> DR. CARSON?
>> FOR MANY MONTHS, THE
POLITICAL CLASS, PUNDITS, THE
MEDIA HAVE TRIED TO IGNORE OR
BURY ME.
THEY SAY THAT POLITICS IS TOO
COMPLEX AND TOO SLEAZY.
YOU CAN'T SURVIVE.
WELL, GUESS WHAT?
I'M STILL HERE.
AND I'M NOT GOING ANY PLACE,
EITHER.
AND I BELIEVE THERE IS STILL A
PLACE IN OUR COUNTRY FOR FAITH,
INTEGRITY AND COMMON SENSE.
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF YOU
DRAFTED ME TO RUN FOR PRESIDENT
AND I AM GOING TO, WITH THE HELP
OF GOD AND YOU, ONCE AGAIN PLACE
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE AT THE
PINNACLE WITH THE GOVERNMENT
THERE TO SERVE IT.
>> THANK YOU, DR. CARSON.
SENATOR RUBIO?
>> THANK YOU.
YOU KNOW, THIS WEEK, I HAD THE
GREAT PLEASURE OF HAVING MY KIDS
JOIN ME ON THE CAMPAIGN TRAIL.
I HADN'T SEEN THEM IN AWHILE.
IT WAS GREAT TO HAVE THEM.
BUT THE MOST IMPORTANT PART, IT
REMINDED ME OF WHAT'S AT STAKE
HERE IN NEW HAMPSHIRE, IN LESS
THAN 72 HOURS.
WE ARE LITERALLY DECIDING WHAT
KIND OF COUNTRY WE WILL BE LIKE
WHEN THEY'RE MY AGE.
WHAT COUNTRY THEY WILL RAISE
THEIR FAMILIES IN.
THAT'S WHY I'M ASKING YOU FOR
YOUR VOTE.
YOU VOTE FOR ME AND WE WILL
UNITE THIS PARTY.
WE WILL GROW THE CONSERVATIVE
MOMENT.
WE WILL DEFEAT HILLARY CLINTON
AND WE WILL LEAVE OUR CHILDREN
WHAT OUR PARENTS LEFT US.
THE SINGLE GREATEST NATION IN
THE HISTORY OF ALL MANKIND.
THANK YOU.
>> SENATOR CRUZ?
>> YOU KNOW, EVERY CANDIDATE
RUNNING FOR PRESIDENT SAYS THEY
WILL STAND UP TO WASHINGTON.
THE NATURAL FOLLOWUP QUESTION
IS, WHEN HAVE YOU EVER STOOD UP
TO WASHINGTON?
LAST WEEK, WE SAW A POWERFUL
ILLUSTRATION OF THAT.
I CAMPAIGNED IN THE STATE OF
IOWA FOUR SQUARE AGAINST THE
ETHANOL MANDATE.
SOMETHING ELSE SAID WAS
POLITICAL SUICIDE.
MY TWO LEADING COMPETITORS BOTH
ATTACKED ME FOR IT.
THE GOVERNOR OF THE STATE SAID,
VOTE FOR ANYONE BUT CRUZ, AND
LOBBYISTS SPENT MILLIONS OF
DOLLARS IN ATTACK ADS, BUT I
SAID, WE SHOULD HAVE NO
MANDATES, A LEVEL PLAYING FIELD,
AND THE PEOPLE OF IOWA PUT
COUNTRY AND OUR CHILDREN ABOVE
THE CORPORATE WELFARE.
WE CAN TURN THIS COUNTRY AROUND
IF WE GET BACK TO THE
CONSTITUTION AND I WILL ALWAYS
STAND WITH THE AMERICAN PEOPLE
AGAINST THE BIPARTISAN
CORRUPTION OF WASHINGTON.
>> THANK YOU.
MR. TRUMP.
>> THAT'S BECAUSE HE GOT BEN
CARSON'S VOTES, BY THE WAY, BUT
WE WON'T SAY THAT.
OUR COUNTRY THAT WE LOVE SO MUCH
DOESN'T WIN ANYMORE.
WE DON'T WIN WITH THE MILITARY,
WE DON'T WIN ON THE BORDER.
YOU LOOK AT NEW HAMPSHIRE, WITH
THE TREMENDOUS PROBLEM WE HAVE
WE HEROIN.
NUMBER ONE THING I HEAR FROM THE
PEOPLE OF NEW HAMPSHIRE, WHO I
LOVE AND DEVELOPED SUCH
RELATIONSHIPS, WE DON'T WIN WITH
HEALTH CARE, WE DON'T WIN WITH
TRADE.
YOU LOOK AT WHAT OTHER COUNTRIES
ARE DOING TO US, CHINA,
EVERYONE.
THEY'RE KILLING US ON TRADE.
IF I'M ELECTED PRESIDENT, WE
WILL WIN AND WE WILL WIN AND WE
WILL WIN.
THANK YOU.
THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
>> MR. TRUMP, THANK YOU.
THANKS TO ALL THE CANDIDATES ON
THE STAGE HERE TONIGHT.
THANKS TO THE PEOPLE OF NEW
HAMPSHIRE FOR HAVING US FOR THIS
DEBATE AND TO EVERYONE AT HOME,
THE NEW HAMPSHIRE PRIMARY IS